So, in this video, I'm going to talk about
wireless media access control and why it
is that the media access control
algorithms we see in wired systems, like
CSMA, Carrier Sense Multiple Access, CD,
Collision Detection, don't work in
wireless.
So, recall the basic goals of the
media access control protocol.
There are essentially three:
you want to arbitrarily control the
channel, who gets to transmit when while
simultaneously trying to achieve three
things.
And generally, you can't achieve all of
them simultaneously, so you trade off
between them.
So, the first is that if there's only one
node that wants to transmit, it should be
able to get 100% of the medium.
The second goal is that if you have
multiple nodes trying to transmit, they
should each get a fair share of the
medium, so, say, one nth.
Finally,
If there's lots of nodes contending, you'd
like it that the medium is being used
heavily.
So, if that one nth is only one thousandth
of the medium, that's not very useful.
So, these are the three goals that we have
in a media access control protocol.
So, recall that Ethernet, CSMA/CD, Carrier
Sense Multiple Access Collision Detection
has a simple approach on transmission.
You set a counter n if the channel is
idle, you just sense the voltages on the
wire and you transmit.
If it's busy you wait until it's idle for
96 bit times.
It's this timing thing in Ethernet, and
then, you transmit.
During a transmission, you can detect a
collision.  That is you hear, that you're
transmitting some zeros and ones, but
what you hear is different than
that,
That you hear some other ones, but you
thought you were transmitting zeros.
So, if you detect a collision, the voltage
is different than what you'd expect.
You wait 96 bit times and then if there's,
sorry, if there's no collision, you just
wait 96 bit times, it transmitted fine and
you will then transmit again.
If you do detect a collision, then
you send a jam signal so everyone knows
there is a collision just to be sure.
And then, you backoff, and this backoff is
exponentially increasing.
And you check the channel again.
So, there's this idea that you start
transmitting.
If the channel is idle, if the channel,
you hear a collision then you transfer it
into the jam signal and you back off and
you wait.
So, in carrier sense multiple access
collision detection
you can detect a collision.
So, it turns out this approach does not
work on wireless.
And the basic reason is this.
This step here, "if collision detected."
The problem is that the transmitter is
transmitting a signal which is being
received at the receiver.
The transmitter is going to hear its own
signal at a really, really high signal
strength,
You know, it's right next to itself.
But it can't necessarily hear what's
happening at the receiver.  In a wired
network,
Because there's so little attenuation over
distance, the receiver and transmitter
share their observation of the
environment.
You know,  if the receiver is
hearing a signal, then the transmitter is
going to hear that signal as well, because
it's going to propagate along the wire
with very little attenuation.
But that's not true in wireless.
In wireless, it could be that the
interfering transmitting signal is too
weak for the transmitter to hear.
So, let me show you an example
of this.
So here, we have A, B, and C.
And so, A is our transmitter, and it's
transmitting a packet to B.
B is receiving this packet just fine.
Then simultaneously, C starts transmitting
to B.
Now, B is able to hear C's signal,
B is able to hear A's signal.
When they both arrive, it just hears
garbage.
There's interference.
But it turns out that C's signal, because
it's decaying with at least the
square of the distance, is too weak for A
to hear.
In particular, because A's own signal is
so powerful (it's shouting) and C is
coming from far away,
even if C's signal was strong enough for A
to hear, A can't hear C's signal over its
own because its signal is, say, way up
here, you know, it's something like say,
-20 dBm, whereas C's signal's arriving
at, say, -80 dBm.
A can't hear it.
It's trying to hear a whisper, while it's
shouting.
It can't do it.
This is different in contrast to a wire
where C's signal will arrive, you know,
at, say, -21 dBm, it wouldn't attenuate
very much at all, and so A would still be
able to hear it.
And so, the problem here is that A can't
detect the collision at B.
So, CSMA/CD doesn't work.
So, what this means in practice is that
wireless networks, in order to be able to
respond to collisions, in order to get
good utilization of the channel, use
different algorithms.