Phil: In this unit, we’re going to dig into
the transport layer. Recall that the transport
layer provides the service for data communication
between applications. This data communication
can, in the case of UDP be simple, unreliable
datagrams, or in the case of TCP a reliable,
bidirectional byte stream. You’ll learn
about how these transport layers work, their
abstractions, and their algorithms. You’ll
also learn a new network principle, called
the “end-to-end argument” or the “end-to-end
principle,” which governs how and where
you can implement a feature correctly.
Nick: In this unit, we’ll ask and answer
questions such as “how exactly does TCP
set up a connection?” “What do TCP segments
look like?” “How can two computers reliably
transfer data with high performance?” To
transfer data reliably, TCP needs to know
when data has been corrupted – you’ll
learn how to detect errors in data using three
algorithms: checksums, cyclic redundancy checks,
and message authentication codes. You’ll
also learn about a basic tools and approach
to network protocol design, finite state machines,
and walk through all of the details of the
state machine TCP uses.
Phil: At the end of this unit, you’ll fully
understand how TCP transfers data reliably
and sets up connections to do so. We won’t
yet cover how TCP can be designed to run really
fast – that’s not until Unit 4, but we
will cover how it can run reasonably well
and, most importantly, correctly. You’ll
also know all of the details of UDP as well
as ICMP, the internet control message protocol,
used to carry control information like error
notifications in the Internet.