Let’s walk through the answers.
The answer to the first row is no. They are
in different networks. The two addresses differ
in their second octet -- 34 versus 35. If
we take a bitwise AND of the two addresses
with the netmask, we get 128.34.0.0 and 128.35.0.0,
which are not the same.
The answer to the second row is yes. They
are in the same network. If we take a bitwise
AND of the two addresses with the netmask,
we get 10.0.1.0 in both cases.
The answer to the third row is no. They are
not in the same network, because they differ
in their third octet. The source is in network
10.0.1.0, while the destination is in network
10.0.2.0.
The answer to the fourth row is no. They are
on in the same network. Just think of the
last byte. The address on the left, with 33,
is 0x21. The address on the right is 0x05.
224 is 0xE0, which is three bits. Since the
source has this bit set but the destination
doesn’t, they don’t match. ANDed with
the netmask, the source address is 171.64.15.32,while
the destination is 171.64.15.0.
The answer to the final row is yes. They match
in the first byte: both are 171.0.0.0 when
ANDed with the netmask.