You will have heard people say many times
that the Internet has transformed society
in profound ways, not seen since the invention
of the printing press.
In this video, I will give you a brief background
on the history of networking leading up to
the invention of the Internet in the 1960s.
Let’s start with a brief history of how
messages were communicated over long distances.
While today we think nothing of sending an
email to the other side of the world, 3,000
years ago it was very hard to communicate
over long distances.
The first recorded long distance communications
are from about 1,000 BC and were mostly put
in place for military offense and defensive
purposes.
Fire beacons were used to signal the arrival
of an enemy, or to synchronize an attack.
This is an example of a fire beacon in the
south of England.
Fire beacons carry information fast, work
particularly well at night when danger is
greatest, but they carry very little information.
Generally, they are on or off, signaling danger.
Carrier pigeons, human messengers and horse
relays have been used around the world for
thousands of year because they can carry more
information. But the information travels more
slowly than a fire beacon, and messengers
are prone to interception along the way. The
message could be read, tampered with or blocked
completely.
The earliest recorded relay systems were horses
in Egypt and China 2-3 thousand years ago.
They were common throughout history. In 13th
C, Marco Polo described how the great Mongol
ruler Kublai Khan used horse relays. His army
had relay stations every 40km, with 400 horses
waiting for relay riders. Horse relays were
used all the way up to 19th century for mail
delivery in the famous Pony Express across
the USA. These early systems were limited
in the information they could carry (fires)
or by the speed of delivery (horses, humans,
pigeons).
Around 2,000 years ago, optical methods started
to be used, such as FLAGS, and HELIOGRAPHS,
which encoded digital information such as
letters, words and numbers.
These systems transmit data at the speed of
light, over limited distances, with limited
information --- they are basically simple
encodings.
Perhaps the biggest advances in optical communications
happened in France around the time of the
French Revolution in 1793 when Claude Chappe
invented and starting building a semaphore
telegraph network.
Claude Chappe built towers with a large HORIZONTAL
beam (the REGULATOR), with two smaller arms
called INDICATORS.
It looked like a human being giving different
signals with their arms. The location of the
arms indicated a SYMBOL.
In 1793, the French government built 15 stations
to cover 190km, or 13km per station. By 1804,
a 370km network stretched from Paris to Dijon.
The system was used to send a variety of messages,
including military information and fast-breaking
news. Most went towards Paris to report information
from the provinces.
The operators became quite skilled: The fastest
messages could be signaled by one station
every 10-20seconds, and could cross France
in less than 30 minutes! They could send about
3,000 signs per day, corresponding to a few
hundred messages.
To make the network function properly, the
optical telegraph systems in France and Sweden
developed a number of concepts that are used
in networks to this day:
They needed to develop five concepts in particular:
The first were CODES. These are symbols to
indicate characters, and control signals like:
START OF TX, END OF TX, “WAIT” or “CONFLICT
(When two signals arrived at the same time!)”,
ERROR (cancel last code), PRIORITY (between
conflicting messages), FAILURE of TOWER, Acknowledgment
(of ciphered text from far end), RAIN/FOG
to say “we can’t see you!”.
The second was FLOW CONTROL, to stop the sender
overwhelming the receiver. Basically, the
receiver tells the sender to slow down because
it can’t keep up
Third was SYNCHRONIZATION, to tell when one
symbol ended and the next one started. This
helps delineate words made up of several symbols.
The forth concept was ERROR CORRECTION AND
RETRANSMISSION to tell the sender when symbols
were misunderstood. This allows the sender
to try sending the symbols again.
Finally, they used ENCRYPTION so that messages
could not be intercepted. They were particularly
worried about news of the stock market beating
the newspapers.
By 1830 the Chappe optical telegraph network
was very extensive, covering most of France.
We can characterize four main steps of invention
in communication networks up until the 1700s.
First, from about 2,000 BC, humans used systems
to signal a small set of pre-defined messages,
for example using fire beacons.
Second, starting in the 1600s, people developed
systems to transmit arbitrary messages, by
encoding the entire alphabet.
By the early 1700s, numeric codes started
to be used for common words and phrases. This
was the earliest form of compression, because
it required less information to be sent over
the link.
During the 1700s, codes were developed for
control signals. They could communicate when
to start and stop sending, when to slow down,
how to retransmit and so on. This was the
birth of what we call today “Protocols”
– the agreed upon rules governing how two
or more parties communicate.
By 1800 there were a number of different optical
telegraph systems deployed across Europe,
using a variety of different protocol signals,
such as these.
Clearly there was an enormous step forward
in communications when the telephone was invented
at the end of the 19th century.
For some time, there had been many attempts
to increase the capacity of the electrical
telegraph network that now connected many
towns across the United States.
Alexander Graeme Bell – a Scottish born
inventor – transmitted the first voice call
in 1876 in the very celebrated phone call
to his colleague, Thomas Watson.
While his patent was challenged many times,
most notably by fellow inventor Elisha Gray,
the patent stood up to the legal challenges
and we generally attribute the invention to
Bell.
Within 10 years over 150,000 people owned
telephones, and by 1915 the first transcontinental
phone call was made from New York to San Francisco.
The series of events and inventions that eventually
led to the internet started in 1960.
In 1962, J.C.R. Licklider at MIT started to
write memos and give talks about his concepts
of an Intergalactic Network, in which everyone
on the globe is interconnected and can access
programs and data at any site from anywhere.
He talked of being able to communicate with
his own ‘Intergalactic Network’ of researchers
across the country. This is widely thought
to be the first recorded description of the
social interactions that could be enabled
by a large communication network - very much
like the Internet of today. Licklider became
the first head of the computer research program
at DARPA - the Defense Advanced Research Projects
Agency - from 1962. While at DARPA he convinced
Ivan Sutherland, Bob Taylor, and MIT researcher
Lawrence G. Roberts, of the importance of
his new networking concept, and they took
up the mantle when they succeeded him at DARPA.
In 1964 researcher Paul Baran wrote what is
now considered the first academic paper about
large scale communication networks. The paper
is titled: “On Data Communication networks”.
At about the same time, Leonard Kleinrock’s
thesiswas published on queueing theory. Donald
Davies was working on very similar ideas at
the National Physical Laboratory in the UK.
in 1965 working with Thomas Merrill, Larry
Roberts connected the TX-2 computer in Mass.
to the Q-32 in California with a low speed
dial-up telephone line creating the first
wide-area computer network ever built.
Larry Roberts joined DARPA in 1966 to help
develop the first ARPANET plans, which were
published in 1967.
In 1969 the first four nodes were installed
at UCLA, SRI, UCSB and University of Utah
and the very first messages sent.
This is what the Internet looked like in 1969
– it was called the ARPANET and was a single
CLOSED, PROPRIETARY network.
By the early 1970s a number of different packet-switched
data networks started to appear.
In 1971, the first packet radio network was
built between the Hawaii Islands, called AlohaNet.
The mechanisms developed for the ALOHA protocol
have influenced pretty much every wireless
network since.
Also in 1971 the Cyclades research network
was built in France. It was the first to give
the end hosts the responsibility for reliable
communications, and heavily influenced the
design of the Internet.
In 1974 IBM introduced an entire data network
stack called SNA, which stands for Systems
Network Architecture. Its goal was to reduce
the cost of building large time-shared computers
with many teletype terminals, rather than
batch processing with punch cards.
DARPA sponsored work on “Internetting”
to create the first “networks of networks”
to connect together networks around the world.
The protocols needed for Internetting were
first described by Vint Cerf (Stanford) and
Bob Kahn in a now famous paper in 1974, with
the title: “A Protocol for Packet Network
Intercommunication”.
TCP called for reliable, in-sequence delivery
of data and included much of what we call
today the Network layer. In the early days
there was no notion of congestion control;
it was added to the Internet about 15 years
later.
By the end of 1970s, TCP and IP were separated,
making room for UDP to be added as an unreliable
transport service as well, originally for
packetized voice.
At the time, Vint Cerf was an Assistant Professor
here at Stanford. He moved to DARPA in 1976
to help shepherd the new Internet project.
He is now the Chief Internet Evangelist at
Google.
Bob Kahn was already at DARPA when the paper
was written. Together, they are considered
the fathers of the Internet.
In 1983 TCP/IP was first deployed across the
ARPAnet in a flag day when everyone upgraded
to use the new protocols.
By 1986 NSFNET was created by the US National
Science Foundation to interconnect supercomputers
at universities across the US, using links
running at 56kb/s. Other small networks started
to pop up all over the place, connecting to
the Internet.
By the end of the 1980s, there were about
100,000 connected hosts.
And then, around 1990 Tim Berners-Lee at CERN
invented the world wide web, with the first
browsers appearing in 1993 – most notably
the Mosaic browser written by Marc Andreessen.
I can still remember the day I first saw a
web browser in 1993 when I was a graduate
student. We knew immediately it would change
everything – but we didn’t realize how
huge that change would be. For many people,
this is the dawning of the Internet, although
of course we all know it goes much further
back than the world wide web. But within a
year, over a million people round the world
were using the Web. And before the end of
the 1990s, Yahoo, Google, Amazon and eBay
would all be household names.
If you would like to learn more about the
early days of networking and the Internet,
here are three excellent references that I
really enjoy.
I’d highly recommend you read them to learn
more about what led to an amazing transformation
of modern society.