Now that we've learned about the basics of
routing, flooding, shortest paths,
spanning trees, and so on.
We've also learned about the distance
vector protocol, Bellman-Ford Algorithm,
the link state protocol or Dijkstra's
Shortest Path First Algorithm.
In this video, I'm going to put it all
together and tell you about the structure
of the Internet.
How hierarchical routing works.
About interior and exterior routing
protocols and the breakdown of the
internet into autonomous systems.
I'm going to be talking about three main
things.
First of all, hierarchy and the
decomposition of the Internet to
autonomous systems.
The second is within those autonomous
systems, how we use the distance vector
and link state algorithms that we've
already seen.
And the third one is the resulting
structure of the Internet.
Let me start with the hierarchy.
When we learned about distance vector and
link state algorithms, we were considering
the network to be a single collection of
routers.
This is really, this is really
impractical.
The Internet is made up of millions of
routers interconnecting over a billion
different users.
And so simply for reasons of scale, we
need to decompose routing into smaller
set.
So we do this for, for scale with a large
number of routers, the sheer scale of
exchanging routing, routing information
between the routers and keeping it up to
date makes it too hard.
I mean, imagine, exchanging the link state
information with million other routers.
The network would just be flooded with
updates all the time.
And the distance-vector algorithm would
never converge.
So, that decomposition takes place into
different autonomous systems and there's
example shown here.
This would be one autonomous system.
And this autonomous system contains
different routers.
They, that's these.
This particular one has one exit point and
we'll see the significance of that in a
minute.
And within that autonomous system, the,
the, the system is free to pick its own
interior routing protocol.
In other words, they decide how packets
are routed around within this autonomous
system.
So, this particular type of autonomous
system is called a single-exit or a stub
autonomous system.
There's another type of autonomous system
called a multi-exit or multi-exit
autonomous system.
For example, this one here, this is one
where in this particular case, there are
three exit points.
And again, it's an autonomous system, so
they are to determine the way in which
packets are routed within that autonomous
system using the interior routing protocol
of that choice.
This is because they're trying to the
Internet was designed to give
administrative autonomy.
The internet was build up by many
different entities.
And so, an entity over here might be
Stanford's network.
Whereas, this here, might be, for example,
like provider, like AT&T who is who is
routing our packets to, to other networks.
And, because of the different entities
that grew up over time and there are tens
of thousands of them all in our own
individual goals and desires.
One of the original goals of the Internet
is to allow each organization to
independently decide how it would run its
own piece of the network, to allow it to
organically grow and in many ways, this
was a big factor in the success of the
organic growth of the Internet,
particularly during the 1990s and allowed
each one to decide what routing protocol
it would use inside its network.
So it means that, for example, at
Stanford, we might use the Interior
Routing Protocol, OSPF, in order to route
our packets, whereas inside AT&T, they
might use RIP or they might use another
one that's called ISIS.
It leads to local customization.
It leads to differentiation.
So, AT&T here might compete with Verizon
here and they can differentiate and
provide a different service, hopefully for
me, the end customer of better service as
a result through competition amongst the
operators.
And by allowing for local customization,
it means the vendors of the routers can
also offer different types of features and
functionality and so it leads to
competition amongst the router vendors as
well.
So, for all these reasons, the Internet
was divided into autonomous systems.
Autonomous systems or ASs are the basic
unit of hierarchy in the Internet.
Within an AS, the owner decides how
routing is done, and between ASs, we must
use BGP4, this is the Border Gateway
Protocol, and its defined by Internet RFC
1771.
And this allows for consistent a, a
consistent method for all of the different
ASs to communicate and we'll be learning
about BGP4 in a later video.
If you want to find an AS number, you can
do this in a number of ways.
One way to do it, actually the simplest,
is to, just do a traceroute to a
particular destination, with the -a
option, and this should give you the AS
numbers of the ones in between.
Most or many enterprises will have a
single AS, for example, Stanford's.
If you if you find it will, will be 32.
At&T is 797.
Some enterprises choose to breakdown their
own network into multiple autonomous
systems.
For example, Google has three that are
reported and some networks even, even have
dozens.
There's slightly more complicated way of
finding it but, but specifically querying
would be this way.
And that is to query using netcat, and see
if you perform this.
So it's essentially going to this
particular, whois provider, and then
entering a particular IP address.
It will tell you the autonomous system
that, that IP address belongs to.
So, if you wanted to find the AS number
for Stanford, you would first do a DNS
lookup for stanford.edu, find the, and in
its A record, this is the primary address.
Then, you can find the autonomous system
for that particular IP address by doing
this, by entering it here.
And then that will return AS32.
Let me show you a couple of examples of
those right now.
Let say, I wanted to find the AS number
for Stanford, I could start by, looking up
the record for Stanford and we can see it
here, the primary A record address.
And then, I can do the look up to the,
using netcat to the, whois this is just
folks that provide a particular one that I
like If I put in the address here for
Stanford and then, we'll see it returns
the AS of 32 down here in the left hand
corner for Stanford.
Similarly, if I wanted to find the AS
numbers for the routers along, in the
networks along the path from my computer
to say, netflix.com, I could use the,
traceroute -a option, and here
we go.
Let's look at this here.
So, at the top, we see, or near the top,
we see the AS32, corresponding to
Stanford.
Then on the bottom, we see the AS2906,
corresponding to Netflix.
We'll see one here which is AS65534.
This is basically saying that it's a
private address, 10.33.0.2, because it
begins with a ten as a private IP address
used inside Stanford.
So given it's a private address, it's not
able to return an AS number.
And in the middle here we see 2152, which
is of Cenic which is the California
network that connects us between
Stanford and some outside providers.
Now we know the basic structure.
Let's look at the interior routing
protocols.
I've already mentioned RIP or the Routing
Information Protocol and this was the
first widely-used interior routing
protocol in the Internet.
It uses distance vector in particular the
distributed Bellman-Ford algorithm.
It's described by an Internet RFC.
This is actually a version two of, of RIP,
which is the one most widely used.
It sends updates every 30 seconds and will
determine that a, a router has become
unavailable, if it hasn't heard within 180
seconds or three minutes.
So, there are no authentication for
updates meaning that there were definitely
some, some security implications of using,
of using RIP.
RIP became popular to start with, because
it was originally in the BSD version of
Unix and there was a, a daemon that was
widely used, widely available for routers
that were, that were using RIP.
And, and that was, it's pronounced "route"-
"dee" and you can find many references to this
on the web.
So, it was widely used for many years many
years.
It's used a little less now because the,
the convergence problems that people have
found with, with RIP.
And it tends to being mostly replaced by
OSPF or ISIS, which is a which is very
similar to OSPF.
So, OSPF is defined in Internet RFC 2328
and it's a link state algorithm.
So link state updates is sent using
flooding.
And, just in case I didn't say this
before, we use flooding because during the
time that we're trying to find the
topology of the network, we don't know how
to reach anyone so we don't have any
topology information that's why we're
flooding the link state information.
So, we can't route the link state
information to every router, because we
don't know the path.
So, flooding is the simplest routing table
free way of making sure that every router
in the network finds out the, the link
state.
So that's why flooding is used.
It runs Dijkstra's algorithm, as we know.
The updates are authenticated, meaning
that we're sure they belong to the router
that we that we are communicating with.
Because some autonomous systems are very
big, it's quite common to partition them
down into areas, so of our own campus
network here at Stanford is partitioned
into OSPF areas.
It's widely used, it's quite complex.
This is a gross simplification here, but
it gives us the basic ideas of how OSPF
works.
So, once we know how to route packets
within an autonomous system, it's whether
asking the question of how do we route
them from within an autonomous system to a
different autonomous system.
So, how do they make it first out of the
autonomous system?
How does the Interior Routing Protocol
isn't going to tell us directly how we
exit from an autonomous system 'cause it's
dealing with the addresses of, of routers
that are outside of this autonomous
system.
So, there are already two cases that we
need to think about.
One is when we're routing to a single exit
point.
So, this would be from a stub autonomous
system that's actually only has one exit
point.
It's much easier in this case than in the
more general case where, where there are
multiple exit points.
So, if there's only one exit point,
routers within the, within the autonomous
system can use what's called default
routing.
Each router knows all of the prefixes
within its autonomous system.
So, it knows all of the prefixes inside
the autonomous system and packets for
another autonomous system are sent to, to
what's called a default router and the
default router is the boarder gateway to
the next autonomous system.
So, it was nice and simple.
Essentially, it says, if you see an
address in a packet that you don't know
what to do with, then just forward it to
the default router.
And default routing means that the routing
tables in the single-exit AS tend to be
very small, because each router only needs
to hold the addresses for the prefixes
within its autonomous system.
Otherwise, it just forwards them out.
Nice and easy.
Life is more complicated when we need to
route the multiple exit points.
So, this would in the transit with
autonomous system or one way or the other,
multiple exit points.
This has actually become much more common
in the last few years 'cause nearly all
sizable enterprises like Stanford will
connect at multiple exit points to
different providers.
So, we might provide, we might connect to
an educational backbone, a research and
education network, and then we will
connect to one or two commercial
providers.
Just in case one of them goes down, one of
them is temporarily unavailable, one of
them is perhaps too expensive for a
particular route,
It allows us to choose and have control.
So multihoming is very common.
Now we need to choose for each outgoing
packet, which exit point it will take.
So, the problem here is that, each
internal router must be told which exit
point to use for a given destination
prefix.
This is the essence of the problem.
That means that when it sees a prefix
which is not inside the autonomous system,
it has to know which exit point to use.
So, this means, it requires very large
routing tables, so that it potentially
routes to every prefix.
And so, the routing tables in a autonomous
system with multiple exit points tend to
be very, very big.
Tens or hundreds of thousands of, of
prefix enteries.
This can maybe, can, can actually be made
a, a little simpler if the autonomous
system uses what's called hot-potato
routing.
Hot-potato routing is when instead of
making a, a smart choice in the best
interest of the packet and its
destination, it simply sends to the
closest exit point.
In other words, it says, for any given
router, it sends it to the exit point
closest to it if it decides it's not from,
for within the autonomous system.
Hot-potato routing is also seen as
offloading a somewhat selfish act by the
autonomous system, 'cause it's offloading
the packets as quickly as it can to become
somebody else's problem, and is not very,
not very popular with its neighboring
autonomous systems.
But is actually very widely used today,
in, in the Internet for both commercial
reasons and reasons of simplicity.
The more elaborate way would be to pick
the exit, which is closest to the
destination, or is on the lowest cost
path.
To the eventual destination and that
requires the dissemination of more
information within the autonomous system
in order to make that decision.
Now, we've learned a little bit about how
routing goes on within the autonomous
system.
And now I wanted to explain a little bit
about the Exterior Routing Protocol, BGP4.
Every autonomous system on the Internet
must interconnect to other autonomous
systems using BGP4.
Just like we're required to use IP, in
order to deliver our packets.
That's what the Internet uses, the thin
waste of routing protocols is BGP4.
In other words, it's the one that we must
all use.
So, I'm going to describe BGP4 in a
separate video, but I just want to tell
you a little about the problems that BGP4
was designed to try and solve.
First of all, it's It has a much, as a
very different problem for a, an exterior
routing protocol than, than for an
interior routing protocol.
Specifically, when, when we were
considering that topology, the, the
Internet is a,
Is a very complex mesh of different
autonomous systems and has very little
structure to it.
You've seen the picture which is the, the
logo for this, for this class and have
seen that it's a very unstructured
interconnection mesh.
And so, trying to exploit that, and the
structure is not going to get us very far.
Each of the autonomous systems is
autonomously controlled.
So they might define the link costs in
very different ways.
So it's not possible to find the lowest
cost paths.
We're simply going to have to find a set
of paths based on the number of autonomous
systems that they pass through.
Another thing that we need to consider is
trust.
When we're going between autonomous
systems we'll find that some autonomous
systems aren't willing to trust others.
Perhaps they don't trust them to advertise
good routes e.g., they might be uh, they
might be a competitor or they, they may
want to protect the privacy of the
traffic.
So, they might not want to send traffic
through another autonomous system, for
example, it might be a, a warring nation.
Another reason that or another thing that
BGP4 was set out to solve was the question
of independent policies.
So, different autonomous system have
different objectives.
Some might try to route over the fewest
hops.
They may prefer one provider over another,
they might have a lower cost arrangement
with one provider compared to another.
So, they have local policies that they
perhaps don't want to share with others.
And in general, these policies are kept
secret.
And so, BGP-4 is designed to work in a way
that will allow for that policy to be a
local, private matter for the autonomous
system.
We will see we will see BGP4 in more
detail in a different video.
Finally, I want to just tell you a little
bit about the structure of the Internet as
we've seen it so far.
So first, at the, at the, at the top-level
there are what we would, what we would all
recognize as Internet service providers.
They might be companies like AT&T they
might be, in Japan, it might be NTT.
There's about a dozen of these what I
so-called tier one.
Tier one ISPs.
And they are defined as ISPs that are
fully mesh interconnected with each other
and who peer each other without charging
each other.
It's called settlement-free peering.
In other words, there's, there's no, no
money that goes across this, this
interface between them.
They then connect down to what are called,
what are usually called regional ISP's,
which might correspond to a state, or a
county, or a region of a country.
And those in turn connect to below them,
to what are call the access ISP's, so
there will be many access ISP's along the
bottom here.
And these would be the ones that we
connect to as users.
So users are down below these access ISP's
down here.
And they will connect up here and the next
ISP might connect to multiple regional
ISPs, and the regional ISPs will generate
connect to multiple tier one ISPs.
So, this hierarchy is one in which there's a,
does a well-defined relationship between
each of these each of these entities.
So, in general, up above is the provider
and below is the customer.
So, the provider is providing service to
the customer and that goes on down, all
the way down.
So, in going down, this is the provider
and this is the customer.
And generally, the provider will charge
the customer.
So, in other words, in order to send
packet from packets from the regional to
the tier, their money is charge, a
settlement charge.
Generally, they keep track of all the data
that sent over there, over some period
like a month and then they will settle
after that time.
So, there would be money charged in that
direction but, there's no money going in
this direction across here.
So, in order to save money, it's quite
common for the regional ISP's to have
connections across here, so that the
packets between access ISP's, if there's a
lot of traffic, it can actually go through
the region ISP without going to the tier
one, and therefore they don't need to, to
pay for that.
So, this is the basic Internet
infrastructure.
Tier one ISPs, about a dozen of them
around the world.
And then, regional ISPs, generally, within
a country or within the region of a
country and then, access, access ISPs to
the ones that we connect to in order to
get access to the Internet.
So in summary, the Internet consists of
multiple autonomous systems, ASs.
Each are managed independently.
An AS runs its own interior routing
protocol.
In other words, it chooses the one that it
will run.
And in, in the case of stub ASs, they use
simple default routing, and so they're
very simple.
ASs with multiple exit points must decide
the best exit to use when routing packets
to other autonomous systems.
ASs must connect to each other using the
BGP4 protocol, which we're going to learn
about in a future video.
That's the end of this video.