So in the video about TCP Reno and
New-Reno, I said that additive-increase,
multiplicative-decrease turns out to be a
really powerful and very effective
mechanism for congestion control.
In this video,
I'm trying to give you an
intuition as to why ---
Why it turns out to work so well and why
it is that it's generally used on the
Internet?
So the way to think about this problem of
congestion control is that there really
are two conflicting requirements in the
network.
The first is a service provider.
What they want to do is they want to
maximize their length utilization.
That is, they want their network to be
completely utilized.
They don't want to have idle capacity
which is unused.
But users want to get a fair share of
that,
You know, a service provider would be
happy if one user just got the entire pipe
but then you're going to lose all of your
clients and users will be unhappy.
And so the idea is that you'd like an
algorithm for congestion control that has
the links operate close to utilization.
But will converge to a point where
every user, assuming everything else is
equal, will get approximately one nth, if
there are n users.
And doing this is going to avoid
congestion collapse, if they're still
doing useful data.
So these are the basic parameters of the
problem.
We want to maximize link utilization: we want to have
high link utilization. Meanwhile,
Everyone gets a fair share of that link
utilization, and we want to make sure the
network does not run itself into the
ground.
So what should your congestion window size
be?
So it turns out that the optimal congestion window
size, as we talked about before, is the
bandwidth delay product.
And this is, basically the idea that,
let's say I have my bandwidth between San
Francisco and Boston is ten
megabytes per second.
And the delay is 100 milliseconds.
Well, this means that if I can support ten
megabytes per second and a congestion
window lasts 100 milliseconds then my
congestion window should essentially be
one megabyte.
Right?
The product of 100 megabytes per second
times 100 milliseconds.
Similarly if my bandwidth is six megabytes
per second and my delay is, 90
milliseconds then I should be sending
approximately a congestion window of 540
kilobytes.
And this falls out from these values.
And then, if I'm sending one megabyte per
congestion window, and there are ten congestion
windows, then I'm going to be sending ten
megabytes per second.
Similarly, if my condition is 540
kilobytes, that's a congestion window
every 90 milliseconds.
That will break down to six megabytes per
second.
So now, a way to think about how a
congestion window works over time or
rather, how pairs of congestion windows
work over time is something called a Chiu
Jain plot.
And this is really part of the thing which
sort of laid out some of, or one of the
papers that laid out this first idea of,
sort of, why AIMD is a, is a good idea in a nice graphical way
So we have two flows that are competing for
the network.
And we're going to plot the rate of flow A
based on its congestion window size.
And the rate of on the X axis and the rate
flow B on the Y axis.
It's going to be a scatter plot.
Now if the network is fair, it will be
equal to B.
That is the rate which A gets will be
equal to the rate which B gets.
And so the scatter point dot,
should fall on this line.
And that's the user requirement.
Now, if we are, maintaining the service
provider requirement, that is we're
actually running the network at capacity,
then it should be that A plus B, the sum
of these two flows, is equal to the
capacity of the network.
So this is the service provider,
requirement.
And so, what we would like is a congestion
control algorithm that causes, you know,
starting wherever we are on this plot,
you know, pick some random point,
is going to cause flow A and flow B to
gravitate towards this desired point in
the center.
Where we are fair and efficient while fully
utilizing the link.
And so the way you can show this is if
we're to the right of this efficiency
line, that means we've overloaded the
network.
So chances are packets are going to be
dropped.
We're going to see triple duplicate acks.
If we're in the green region, we've under
loaded the network.
And so we want to get to this point where
we're operating right at the network
capacity, but we have fair capacity.
Now,  what this
shows you, the series of T1 through T6,
etc is how additive-increase
multiplicative-decrease behaves.
So let's just pick this arbitrary point
T1, where flow B is operating at well
above its fair share as you can see, this
distance.
And flow A is operating well before its
fair share, as you can see by this
distance here.
So what's going to happen?
Both are in additive-increase mode.
If they're both going to additively
increase their congestion window size and
their flow rate until at some point the
network becomes overloaded and it drops some
packets.
At which point then they multiplicatively
decrease their window size and go back
into additive increase.
And so here's the mutliplicitve decrease.
And then they additively increase.
Now, because the multiplicative decrease
decreases B's rate more than A
(it's a multiplicative factor),
this then makes in the plot, the comparison
of A and B, closer to fair.
You can see T3 here is bringing the pair
of flows closer to the fair line.
And that's what we're seeing.
And since we're reducing each flow by a
multiplicative factor.
Over time, and then increasing it by an
additive factor.
Over time,
they oscillate between overloaded and
underloaded, in the sense of they're going
to push the network until it's just a
little bit overloaded, and they back off a
little bit.
And over time, this scaling with
multiplicative of decrease, causes them to
converge towards this point.
And so in fact in the end case we will see, depending on exactly what
overload point causes a triple duplicate
acknowledgments
you'll see these two
flows oscillating along the fair line,
under-loading the network then increasing.
Then overloading it.
Oh, they back off, increasing.
And so over time, additive increase
multiplicative decrease causes a pair of
flows or a set of flows.
To achieve both desired properties.
They get a fair share of the capacity of
the network, right?
They end up moving along this line here,
but also, through their additive increase
they're going to be close to the network
capacity, right?
There going to go a little bit
past, then a little bit back, then a
little bit past.
But, generally speaking, additive increase
multiplicative decrease will cause flows
to converge on this point.
The desired equilibrium point of the network