So, in this video on names and  addresses.
I'm going to talk about the Dynamic Host
Configuration Protocol or DHCP,
Something which you probably use every day
when you access the internet.
So, if we take a step back and think about
what do we need to communicate with IP,
with internet protocol,
There are basically three things that a
host needs.
It needs first, an IP address.
It needs an address which it can give to
other nodes for to send packets to and
which it can put it own packets that nodes
know to send back to it.
It needs a subnet mask.
So, it needs to know what nodes are on its
own local subnet versus nodes it must
contact through a local gateway.
Sound It also needs to know the gateway
router, such that if a node is not on the
local subnet, what's the IP address of the
next hop, or the first hop towards
destinations outside of the local subnet.
So, these are the three things that you
have to have in order to communicate with
IP on internet as a whole.
In addition, often it's very useful to
have this fourth thing, which is the IP
address of the domain name service, server
or domain name system server.
This is basically where, what allows you to
translate names like www.cnn.com into an
IP address.
And so, you do not need this per se, to
communicate here with IP if you just know
the IP address, but it is very, very
useful for most applications and for
people.
So, there's this basic problem.
You take, you buy a new computer, and you
plug it into a network.
You need these three things, and hopefully
this fourth one, how do you get them?
How do you get these values?
So, in the old days, like actually when I
was, my first year in college, you'd get
them from your system administrator.
So, you'd fill out a request for a network
tap.
And then a couple days later, you get a
slip of paper, which had your, important
values.
It had your IP address,
It had your subnet mask,
It had your gateway address, and it had
the DNS server address.
And so, you get this slip of paper with
these four things on it, and a sheet of
usually a photocopy saying,
Okay, take these values and here's how you
open up your control panel and type them
in here.
And that was basically how you'd configure a
machine.
So, this is, I did at Brown when I went
there as an undergraduate in 1995.
By the time I graduated though, they moved
on.
So, as you imagine, on one hand, this can
work, but it has all kinds of problems.
If your machine moves, like if I take my
machine and I move it to a friend's a
friend's room, it no longer works because
that particular machine was configured for
that particular tap in the network
topology.
So, this question is, how long it lasts?
So, I, back then when you fill out this
slip of paper, it lasted a year.
And, in fact, if you didn't request it by
a certain point of the year, you couldn't
get one.
So, these addresses and configurations are
given out on a yearly basis.
One final question is, how do you collect
unused entries?
So, if I only want a machine for, you
know, plug in my machine for three days,
does this mean that I have to allocate an
entry for an entire year?
The answer is yes.
And so, while this works, it's remarkably
inefficient.
So, the approach that computers use today
and this is what was Brown started using
by the time I graduated across the entire
campus is something called DHCP, the
Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
specified in RFC 2131.
Basic idea is, a machine, when it
connects to a network, can request it's
configuration from a DHCP server. and if
you can just request your configuration,
say, what's my I.P address? What's my
subnet mask? What's my Gateway? What's my
DNS server?
This turns out to solve the three major
problems outlined.
If you move, well, you just do a
re-request.
You're in a different part of the network,
You need a different configuration. For
the duration, how long it lasts.
Well, when the DHCP server gives you a
configuration, it's associated with the
lease.
Saying, the configuration is this good for
this long.
And then, if you're nearing the end of
that lease, you can re-request the same
configuration, and usually the server will
give it to you.
So, there's a way to renew the lease.
These leases then make garbage collection
very easy.
Because if somebody doesn't re-request it,
you can reclaim say, that IP address.
And so, the basic interaction, the basic
packet exchange that you see in DHCP is,
there's a basic four step exchange.
And then, there's this optional release.
So when a node first joins the network and
it had, knows nothing about what's going
on, it sends out a discover message.
I want to discover what DHCP servers are
out there and what configurations they
might give you.
So, the client sends a discover.
Then, the DNS, sorry the DHCP servers that
can hear that discover respond with an
offer.
So, here are the servers.
And more than one server can be connected
and you might get more than one offer.
And they'll say, here, I'm going to offer
you this configuration.
The client then selects one of the
configurations, and sends a request to the
originating DHCP server saying, well, I'd
like to request that configuration you
offered me.
And then the server sends an
acknowledgment saying, I acknowledge you
can have that configuration.
This configuration is now valid for the
duration of its lease.
And a client can release it early if it
wants to or, if the lease starts to reach
the end, it does a re request.
So, the request mechanism is both in
response to an offer but also a way to
renew a lease.
So, let's walk through an example with a
client and two servers.
The first step a client connects to the
network and it sends a DHCP discover
message as a broadcast.
These are broadcast.
Server A and server B both hear this
message.
There happens to be two DHCP servers that
can hear the, the discover broadcast.
And let's say, both respond with offers
for different configurations.
So, here's a offer, offer B and offer A.
The client seeing these two offers, decides
that it wants offer B.
And so, it then sends a request to B
saying, I would like to request the
configuration that you offered me.
Server B can then acknowledge and say,
okay you have it.
Server A doesn't hear a request for the
offer and so at some point then that offer
will time out.
Now client A is configured, it has an IP
address, it has all it needs to
communicate.
If the, the lease on this offer gets close
to an end it can re-request and say,
receive an acknowledgement.
It will, you know, do this, you know, well before
the lease expires.
So now the lease has been extended. And
then, it can also optionally send what's
called a release, and say, oh, actually
I'm done with this.
I'm practice, clients often don't do this,
they just let the lease expire. But,
sometimes you see it in your control panel
and you can say release.
And I'll, I'll show you an example on a
Mac in a second.
So, here is a basic DHCP sequence, or
exchange of messages..
So, I've said you send these messages.
What do these messages look like?
The issue here is, you're trying to
bootstrap IP.
You're trying to get the, the beginning IP
configuration before you have any IP
information.
And so, the way it works is a client sends
UDP packets to port 67,
that's the DHCP port, from port 68.
And it sends these packets.
It doesn't know the IP address of the DHCP
server so it sends them to the broadcast
IP address and also makes them come from
the broadcast IP address because it
doesn't have an IP address.
In, cases where the DHCP servers not
on the exact same link, you can have
relays that will forward it across links.
And most switches, etc., will actually
just forward broadcast packets across all
of their, all of their ports.
And so, the way you bootstrap this is to
use the special IP address, communicate
using UDP packets.
Then, once a node has received its
configuration, it now can bootstrap with
its own IP address.
And so, this is then the message exchange
that we see.
So, to start with my iMac issuing a DHCP
discover.
It sends this, so here's my source
Ethernet address 04.54.53.10.78.e4, and it
sends it to the Ethernet broadcast
address, so all once.
The source address is 0.0.0.0, source IP
address.
The destination IP address is
255.255.255.255.
And you can see it's sending it from
source port UDP port eight, 68 to
destination port 67.
And if you look inside this message right,
this is basically is just the basic DHCP
discover message. Sends it once, doesn't
hear anything. So, it retries after a
second,
Doesn't hear anything. So, it retries
after another 2-1/2 seconds,
Then hears two offers.
Which, perhaps, might be a response to
these two different, discovers.
Who knows?
Since they the same transaction ID. So this
first offer is sent from 10.33.0.2 to IP
address 10.33.1.94.
The second one is 10.33.3.188.
But, if you look inside the Ethernet
frame, these are being sent from, you
know, some device and they're being sent
to my ethernet address.
So, these are offers that are sent in
response to my discovery and you can also
tell by the transaction ID. And so, this
is destined to this IP address because my
node knows that it does not have an IP
address,
This turns to be part of, in fact, the
information.
And so here, here's the reply, the offer.
And there's all this configuration
information.
It's basically saying, here.
I'm offering you, an IP address of
10.33.1.94 which maps up here,
10.33.1.94.
And same in the second one,
You'd see that it was offering 10.33.
3.188.
So, you've got two different IP addresses
and not one. turns that all kinds of
options in this message.
It's also going to tell me the subnet
mask, 255 255.48.0.
It's also going to tell me the router,
10.33.0.1.
And, its also going to tell me domain name
server.
It's going to tell me that my domain name
server is here's three servers I can use,
171.64.7. 55,121, and 99.
It's going to tell me the domain name, oh,
you're in stanford.edu.
And so, that's what these offers contain.
All this information which I can use to
configure my host when it starts up.
Then, in response when these offers, I
send a, my device sends a DHCP request,
Right?
And, so now, it's sending, again here's my
address sending as a broadcast, it
broadcasts its request.
And if we look which IP address did it
choose?
Right? So, here's all this information,
all these flags, options.
So, parameter request list.
So, I'm requesting a certain subnet mask,
router, a certain subnet mask, a certain
router, domain name, server, etc. etc.
etc.
And so we can see here, that my node ended
up requesting the first offer,
So 10.33.1.94.
And it also ended up requesting, a host
name, Phillip's iMac.
And so it's saying, hey, I would like to
respond to the request.
I would like to request the off, the offer
that you made for 10.33.1.94.
Then, the DHCP server acknowledges that
and all is well.
And so, now we open up my network control
panel, and we look.
We look at what, my configuration is,
that's in fact, what we see.
So, my IP address is 10.33.1.94.
My subnet mask is 255.255.248.0,
My router is 10.33.0.1.
And, if we're to check, my host name would
be philipsimac.stanford.edu.