So in this video I'm gonna talk about the
internet.
[laugh], why it's so important and why
really you should take this course.
And so the overarching theme here is that
there are some people who would argue that
in the past twenty or 30 years the most
important invention of our generation is
the internet in terms of what it's
accomplished, how it has transformed the
world, the economy, politics, and society,
and by understanding how it works,
understanding how it's been built, what it
can do, what it can't do, you'll have a
much greater understanding about this
tremendous engine of change.
So let's just take a few simple societal
examples.
So.
You know today if you think in terms of
economics, and the economic changes the
internet has brought, think about things
like black Friday.
So black Friday is the day after
thanksgiving in the United States when
it's given that name because all of the
stores go from the red, that is they've
lost money over the year to the black
because so much is bought for Christmas,
and so this is historically this time of
tremendous sales, and tremendous you know,
purchasing people will get up early to go
to the mall, all of that.
But today, Black Friday is still of course
important, but now there's Cyber Monday,
when people, after the Thanksgiving
holiday, the next Monday, log in online to
buy gifts for the holidays.
In the sense of its the ability for people
to buy things online so easily has really
changed our purchasing patterns.
Enough so now there is legislation in the
United States in the legislature to
examine whether or not it's fairer that
these online vendors don't have to pay,
the people who buy things from online
vendors don't have to pay sales tax,
whereas brick and mortar vendors, people
do have to pay sales tax.
Suddenly places like Amazon have a price
Benefit that they have, that they can give
a better price, because people don't have
to pay.
Taxes on things which are bought from
Amazon.
So there's been lots of legislation about
trying to control this and is it unfair to
brick and mortar, but the fact that the
presence of online purchasing is leading
to legislation because of concerns of
competition says something about the
economic effect that the Internet is
having.
Or you look at something far more
personal, such as dating.
So, before the internet, you know, how do
meet people?
Well, through friends.
Maybe there's, you know, classified ads in
the newspaper.
Or you go to a bar or try to meet people
that way.
Today, there are all these services.
Okcupid, Match.com, for connecting people
online.
So it's changing how people meet each
other, and how people date.
And as you know some of these sites will
claim that some significant fraction of
the people that meet on their sites
eventually become married.
Think in terms of knowledge.
So before, if you wanted to read a book,
you would go to the library and you'd
check it out.
Today, things like Google books, where
there are millions of books that have been
scanned in, and anyone can read at any
time.
Things like e-books delivered over these
wireless networks like the whispernet.
Or Wikipedia.
You used to, if you wanted to look
something up, you used to have to go to an
encyclopedia.
If you were very lucky, maybe you had an
old encyclopedia at home.
But usually, you'd go to the library.
Now, anytime you wanna know something
about.
And something that's not too obscure, you
can go to Wikipedia and learn something
about it.
Finally, communication, so, you know,
there are beginnings of IRC chat, chat
programs on the internet but think about
before we had instant messaging or
voice-over IP or video telephony.
Video Conferencing was this technology of
the future, the idea you could have a
video call and really it was the internet
and just this cheap inexpensive always on
omnipresent data communication system is
what made that possible.
So it really changed how we interact with
people on a day to day basis when it's
available.
So that's just society.
How we interact with one another in the
fabric of interpersonal relationships.
There's also been significant political
change brought by the internet.
So you look at something like the Arab
Spring, where.
People who are revolting against the
Government are coordinating using SMS, or
Twitter.
So, it's actually a story where during the
revolution in Iran, that Twitter was
planning on taking it's server down for
the weekend for an upgrade and the United
States of America State Department called
up twitter and said, 'We're sorry.
There's a revolution, or an uprising going
on and they're using twitter a lot.
Please keep your servers online.' So
political change in the world is greatly
effected by these technologies we're
seeing deployed on the internet.
Or think in terms of diplomacy with the
recent Wiki leaks about all of these
United States diplomatic cables and how
that effects diplomatic relations
throughout the world.
A tremendous effect that would have been
inconceivable before the very, very rapid
spread of information the internet makes
available.
Or you look within, say the United States,
are the occupy movement, Occupy Wall
Street, Occupy Oakland, organized through
Twitter and through Facebook, these online
social media which, for which the internet
is their backbone.
Finally, you also see politics not only in
terms of uprising and diplomacy but also,
in terms of politics by force.
So one of example of this is, the STUX
network, which was in internet capable
worm that shut down the centrifuges in a
row, damaged the centrifuges that were
being thought to be enriching nuclear
material.
So this is an example of, what looks like
a state, a government producing
essentially a cyber weapon which is
intended to spread over an internet style
network designed very specifically to
sabotage these devices at this location.
So you see the internet used not only for
personal connections, personal
interactions as well as organization.
But also even for political changes by
force.
Now in terms of the scope of these
economic changes, this was recently I just
went on April sixteenth, so just a few
months ago, and I looked up who are the
hundred richest people in the world.
So the top billionaires list from Forbes.
And if you look You know number 24 is
Sergey Brin and Larry Page co founders of
Google.
Number 26 Jeff Bezos CEO of Amazon.
Number 35 at the time was Mark Zuckerberg
CEO of Facebook.
These are all people whose billions have
been made by new services, applications
and uses of the internet.
And so just think about the through the
amount of.
Shift of capital and shift of economics
and economic models that the Internet is
bringing, that gosh, in, in the past decade
or so.
You're seeing some of the richest people
in the world have achieved that through
effectively the use and growth of the
Internet.
And I think this points at a more broader,
point, about technology and what's
happening today.
So I would argue that we're in the midst
of second or, depending on the count, it's
second or third industrial revolution.
This idea of this tremendous upheaval, of
how we conduct business, how we produce
goods.
In terms of trade, in terms of the kinds
of skills that are necessary for modern
industries.
And so, this is some data that I collected
from, this is United States data only,
from the United States Department of Labor
and Department of Education.
And so what it shows is for four
scientific engineering degrees, the number
of degrees granted in the United States
each year and the number of job openings
each year projected over the next ten
years.
So, there's data for the job openings
projected 2008-2018 from the U.S.
Department of Labor.
And the job, and the actual degrees are
2008 data from the United States
Department of Education.
And so if you want some details about how
I got this data, there's this url down
here.
But the basic point here is that you can
see that in most disciplines, you know
there are fewer jobs, than there are
degrees and that's normal because not
everyone who gets an engineering degree
say, goes into engineering, they can do
other things with that degree.
But there is this tremendous discrepancy
for computer science, that the number of
degrees which at least the United States
is producing each year in computer
science, is only a small fraction, you
know, effectively a third of the number of
job openings.
There's tremendous economic growth in this
area which we educationally, in terms of
societally  have not yet caught up with.
So, learning about these kind of things,
learning about the Internet, because it is
such a core aspect of this, is something
which is of tremendous, practical value in
the job market.
It's important in our every day society.
In fact, if you had pull apart those
160,000 jobs per year that are appearing
in the United States, in fact, you know
there are a lot of them are software
engineers, as you may think people who are
in software a lot of them are database
administrators, but if you look there are
a bunch of very large categories here.
Networking computer systems
administrators, people who are
administering computer systems and
networks.
People who are analyzing data
communication systems and network systems.
And so the point being that actually
there's significant, almost a quarter of
the computer science jobs each year.
So 40,000 jobs a year approximately have
to do with computer networks, which is not
to say that even these software
engineering jobs.
Many of them have to do with computer
networks as well.
You're building a new web application, new
web service.
This all involves the use of networks and
the internet.
So correspondingly, understanding how the
internet works, understanding the design
principles of networks.
How they work, why they're built this way.
Good design principles for building future
networks, future network applications,
future network systems is of tremendous
value going forward in terms of knowing it
as a practical skill but also to
understand what is becoming a tremendous
linchpin of modern society.
And so this course is gonna teach you
exactly that.
It's gonna teach you how computer networks
work.
Not only their implementation, as an
example of a very successful on the
internet, but also the design principles
that lead you there.
So as the internet evolves, as it does
every day, you'll understand the
principles that lead that evolution, that
guide that evolution.
Such that even if we use slightly
different protocols in five years, you'll
still be able to understand.
Because you'll understand the principles
behind network design.
And so.
In theory, or the hope would be that if
you take this course, you'll not only
understand the internet of today, but
you'll also have the
Intellectual tools to understand the
internet of tomorrow, as it evolves
towards that.
And it's also gonna give you a background
of what are the forces that shape the
internet.
So it's a technological marvel and an
amazing feat of engineering.
But what makes it especially interesting,
at least to me, is that it's shaped not
only by engineering concerns.
But also by real world economic political
and societal  concerns.
If you read about how the internet is
being used in politics, or it's effects on
the Arab spring, or the Stuxnet worm.
Or it's effects on economies, to whether
or not how internet commerce is going to
be regulated or governed.
What about things like off-shore gambling
and how that's managed?
All of these kinds of questions affect
legislation, affect how the Internet is
developed, affect how it's governed.
And that has tremendous implications on
its design.
So it's this interesting.
Interface and mix between not only deep
technical concepts but also the societal
needs, and the societal wants, and our
societal rules that we use to use those
concepts.
And, basically make a better world for the
future through data communication.
So now that's the, the basic overview.
Internet's astoundingly important.
It's going to become only more important
as time goes on.
And so understanding it is a, a very, very
valuable thing.
And so I encourage you to do so and take
this course.