Networks aren’t perfect, and neither are
the hosts that run on
them. They can introduce errors, and for a
network to be able to
run properly it needs to be able to detect
these errors. For
example, let’s say that a router along our
path has a bad memory
cell, such that sometimes flips a bit in a
packet. Imagine, for
example, if the bit flipped is the most significant
bit of the amount
to charge a credit card. We need to be able
to detect that error
occurred so we don’t accept the corrupted
data as correct data.
Networks today generally use three different
error detection
algorithms: checksums, cyclic redundancy codes,
CRCs, and
message authentication codes, MACs. Each of
them has very
different characteristics. Understanding their
differences is
important! I’ve actually been at meetings
in the IETF where a few
people weren’t aware of the differences!
If you don’t know, you
might make a bad protocol decision or analysis.
At a high level, error detection looks like
this. We have a
payload of data. We calculate some error detection
bits over
that data and either append it or prepend
it to the payload.
For example, Ethernet appends a cyclic redundancy
code,
Transport Layer Security appends a message
authentication
code, and IP prepends a checksum, which it
places in the IP
header. TLS and Ethernet have a footer, protocol
information
which follows the payload, which is where
they put the CRC
and MAC.
The first of the three commonly used error
detection algorithms is a checksum. You just
add all of the data in the packet. It’s
what TCP and IP use. Checksums are nice because
they are very fast and cheap to compute, even
in software. Back when the Internet started
and everything was in software, this was valuable.
Their major drawback is that they have pretty
weak error detection guarantees. While they
can catch a lot of random errors, it’s
easy to fool a checksum with as few as 2 bit
errors, if the two bit errors cancel each
other out. For example, if one bit error adds
32 and another bit error subtracts 32, then
a checksum won’t catch the error. So a checksum
can catch a lot of errors, but it turns out
to have very weak guarantees on what errors
it will catch.
The second of the three commonly used error
detection algorithms is a cyclic redundancy
code, or CRC. A CRC is much more computationally
expensive than a checksum, but also much more
robust. It computes the
remainder of a polynomial -- I’ll show what
this means and how it works in a few minutes.
With today’s processors, it’s easy to
do, and it’s easy to do in hardware. It’s
what Ethernet and many link layers use. In
some ways,
TCP and IP can get away with checksums because
the link layers use CRCs. If you have a CRC
that’s c bits long, a CRC can detect any
1 bit error, any 2 bit error, and single burst
of errors less than or equal to c bits long,
and
any odd number of errors. So it can provide
much stronger guarantees that a checksum.
The final algorithm is something called a
message authentication code, or MAC. A message
authentication code combines the packet with
some secret information to generate a value.
In theory, someone can only generate or
check the MAC if they have the secret. So
if you receive a packet and its MAC is correct,
then you’re pretty sure the computer that
computed the MAC has the secret. Unless I
have the secret, it’s amazingly difficult
to generate
the correct MAC for a packet. So a bad guy
can’t easily generate a new packet. In fact,
if you have a strong MAC algorithm, then given
one packet and its MAC, I have zero information
on what the MAC will look like if I flip a
single bit. Message authentication codes are
therefore robust to malicious modifications.
Message authentication codes are used in Transport
Layer Security, TLS, which is what you use
when you browse web pages securely
-- https.
But they’re actually not great for catching
errors. If I flip a single bit in a packet,
theres a 1 in 2 to the c chance that the changed
packet will have the same MAC! I’ve seen
people make this mistake when talking about
error
correction, thinking a MAC is just as good
as a CRC. It’s not! If I have a 16-bit CRC,
I’m assured that I will detect a burst of
errors that is 16 bits long or shorter. If
I have a 16-bit MAC, I’m only assured that
I’ll detect bit
errors with very high probability, 99.998
percent, or one in 65,536. That’s high,
but think about how many packets you’ve
received just watching this video...
I’ll now go into each of these algorithms
in greater detail.
Let’s start with a checksum. IP, UDP, and
TCP use one’s complement checksums. This
means they add up the
packet using one’s complement arithmetic,
a version of binary arithmetic some older
computers used. Most
today use two’s complement.
The algorithm is pretty simple. You start
by setting the checksum field of the packet
to zero. Then you add
every 16-bit word in the packet. Any time
you have to carry, because the sum is greater
than 65,535, then you
carry the bit back in. So 60,000 plus 8,000
is 68,000 - 65,535 + 1, or 2,466. Once you’ve
added up the
complete packet, flip the bits in your sum
and make this the checksum of the packet.
Then, if you add up the
complete packet, including the checksum value,
you should get 0xffff. There’s one edge
case: if the computed
checksum is 0xffff, you don’t make the checksum
field 0, you make it 0xffff. In IP, UDP, and
TCP, a checksum
field of 0 means there’s no checksum.
That’s it! You can write this in just a
few lines of C code. It’s fast, easy to
compute, and easy to check. All you
need to do is add the bytes of a packet. Given
that most early Internet implementations were
in software, this
was really helpful.
The drawback is that it’s really not that
robust. While it definitely detects lots of
random errors, the guarantees
it can give on what errors it detects are
really weak. In practice, it can only promise
to catch single bit errors.
But it works pretty well, and link layers
do a lot of heavy lifting for us.
Link layers do their heavy lifting with something
called a cyclic redundancy check, or CRC.
The idea of a CRC
is that I want to take n bits of source data
and somehow distill them down into c bits
of error detection
data, where c is much much smaller than N.
For example, I might have a 1500 byte Ethernet
frame with a 4
byte, 32 bit, CRC. USB and Bluetooth use 16-bit
CRCs.
Of course we can’t detect all errors. Given
some other random packet, the chances the
CRC matches is two
to the minus C, or one in two to the c. For
example, if I use an 8 bit CRC, then out of
the space of all
packets, one in two hundred and 256, or 0.4%,
have the same CRC as any given packet.
But CRCs are stronger than checksums. They
can detect there’s an error in any packet
with an odd number
of errors, 2 bit errors, or any single burst
of errors less than or equal to c bits long.
They can’t guarantee
detecting errors besides these, but do a good
job at it. For example, a 16-bit CRC can’t
guarantee it will
detect two bursts of 3 bit errors spaced far
apart in a packet, but it’s likely it will
detect the error.
Link layers typically use CRCs. They’re
pretty robust, and as many link layers are
vulnerable to bursts of
errors, the burst detection capability of
CRCs is useful. It’s not hard to make compute
them quickly in
hardware, and you can compute them incrementally,
as you read or write the packet.
How does a CRC work? It distills these n bits
into c bits using something called polynomial
long division. You take the bits of a message
and
use them to describe a polynomial M. Each
bit in a packet is the coefficient of one
term of the polynomial. If the bit is zero,
the term is
absent. If the bit is one, the term is present.
So, for example, a message of 10011101 is
the polynomial x to the 7th plus x the fourth
plus x to the third plus x squared plus one,
x to the
zero. This is because the 7th, 4th, 3rd, 2nd
and 0th bits are set in the message.
When we calculate a CRC, we have something
called a generator polynomial. This is defined
by the CRC algorithm. For example, the CRC-16
algorithm used by USB has a generator polynomial
of x to the 16th plus x to the 15th plus x
squared plus one. For frustrating historical
reasons, the generator polynomial is one term
longer than its number of bits: the first
term is always one. So the CRC-16 generator
polynomial is written as 0x8005 even though
it has an x to the 16th term.
To compute a CRC, you take the message M,
pad it with zeroes equal to the CRC length
and divide this padded value by G. The remainder
is
the CRC, which you append to the message.
To check a CRC, you divide the message plus
CRC by the generator polynomial G. If the
remainder is zero, then the CRC passes. I
won’t go into the details of how this works
mathematically, but it turns out it can be
implemented
very quickly and efficiently in hardware.
The strength of your CRC algorithm depends
on what generator polynomial G you pick: there’s
been
a lot of study of this and so many good options
which have the error detection properties
I mentioned earlier. But you might not get
the same
error detection strength if you pick your
own generator polynomial.
The third and final kind of error detection
algorithm you commonly see in networks is
a message authentication code, or MAC. Like
CRCs, there’s a deep and rich mathematical
background on how message authentication codes
work: there are good ones and bad ones. So
you generally want to use an existing scheme
rather than invent your own.
Thankfully standards usually specify what
MAC to use, and although there were some mistakes
in the late 90s where standards picked poor
algorithms, nowadays security is
important enough that everyone relies on a
small number of really well studied approaches.
Message authentication codes use cryptography,
a branch of mathematics that deals with secrets.
The idea behind most message authentication
codes is that the two parties share
a secret s. This secret is just a set of randomly
generated bits (random so it’s hard to guess).
To calculate a message authentication code
c, apply the MAC algorithm to the
message M and the secret s. MAC algorithms
have the property that if you don’t have
s, then it’s really hard to generate the
correct c for a message M. Furthermore, it’s
very hard
to create a message M whose message authentication
code is c. By “hard” I mean that in the
best case you’d just have to exhaustively
try: having M and c gives you almost no
information on what s is. This means that
if you receive a message M with the correct
message authentication code, this means the
computer that generated the message probably
has the secret (or someone replayed a message
generated by that computer).
Because the goal is to keep s a secret, cryptographically
strong message authentication codes have an
interesting property. If you change a single
bit in M, then this results in a
completely new c, where the probability any
bit in c is zero or one is seemingly random.
If this weren’t the case, then someone could
potentially take a message, flip a single
bit
(e.g., change a dollar value) and it wouldn’t
be that difficult to generate the correct
c. This means that message authentication
codes actually have no error detection guarantees.
If
you flip a single bit, you could end up with
the same MAC!
Message authentication codes are very useful,
but they’re first and foremost a security
mechanism. Being able to get both error detection
and security with one mechanism is
efficient and nice, but their security properties
mean their error detection isn’t as good
as other approaches.
Here’s a quiz. For each error detection
algorithm, mark which
errors it can guarantee catching, if any.
The CRCs use a good
generator polynomial and the MAC algorithm
is cryptographically
strong.
Let’s go over the answers.
Both checksums can detect a single bit error
-- remember that this is one of the errors
a checksum guarantees detecting.
Both CRCs can also detect a single bit error.
A MAC can’t guarantee that it will detect
a single bit error. For security reasons,
could be that the new MAC is the same as the
old one. So it can’t guarantee
detecting it. In fact, a MAC can’t guarantee
detecting any errors! So we can mark No for
all of the columns for the message authentication
code.
How about two bit errors? Checksums can’t
guarantee detecting two bit errors. So N for
both of them. CRCs, though, can guarantee
detecting bit error runs in
length less than or equal to the length of
the CRC. Since 2 bits is shorter than both
8 bits and 16 bits, both CRCs can detect a
run of 2 bit errors. Correspondingly,
an 8-bit CRC can’t guarantee detecting a
run of 9 bit errors, but a 16-bit CRC can.
So N for the 8 bit CRC and Y for the 16-bit
CRC.
How about two bit errors 100 bits apart? It
turns out none of these algorithms can guarantee
detecting this error. So N for all of them.
Looking at this matrix, you might think error
detection is a waste -- the algorithms promise
very little! But guarantee is a very strong
statement. While a 16-bit
checksum can’t guarantee that it will catch
a run of 9 bit errors, there’s a high probability
it will. Similarly, a 16-bit CRC has a very
high probability of detecting two bit
errors 100 bits apart. And in practice, high
probability is often good enough. If failures
are rare, then you only sometimes have to
do something more expensive to
recover. But it means in practice you tend
to have multiple layers of error detection:
the link layer detects them with CRCs, IP
detects them checksums, TCP detects
them with checksums, and then often the application
has its own error detection. So, all put together,
the changes of errors creeping through is
very very low.
So we’ve seen three error detection schemes:
checksums, CRCs, and message authentication
codes.
Checksums are fast and cheap, but not very
robust. They’re used in IP and TCP. Cyclic
redundancy codes are
much stronger. Computing them in hardware
is easy today, and they can detect a wide
range of errors. Link
layers, such as Ethernet, typically use CRCs.
The third algorithm is a message authentication
code, or MAC.
Message authentication codes are designed
for security, but you can also use them for
error detection.
However, since they’re designed for security
first, this means they’re really good against
malicious
modifications, but not that greater for detecting
errors.
Data error detection is a great example of
the end-to-end principle. It’s actually
what originally motivated
the principle -- the only way a layer can
be sure that it communicates data correctly
is to perform an endto-
end check. Ethernet needs to be sure that
its frames don’t have errors so it can parse
them correctly, so
it has a CRC. IP needs to be sure that its
packets don’t have errors so it can parse
them correctly. IP can’t
depend on Ethernet doing its checking for
it: the Ethernet card or driver might introduce
an error after it
checks the packet. So it has to do its own
end-to-end check at the network layer. TLS
using message
authentication codes is another example. It’s
especially interesting because TLS has very
different error
detection requirements than IP or Ethernet:
it wants security. So it has to provide its
own, end-to-end error
detection scheme, as that’s the only way
it can be sure its requirements are met.