So let's talk about BitTorrent. It's a fascinating
Internet application,
with a lot of interesting algorithms and approaches.
There's a
reason it works so well!
BitTorrent allows people to share and exchange
large files. A BitTorrent
client requests documents from other clients.
So that a single client can
request from many others in parallel, BitTorrent
breaks files up into
chunks of data called pieces. When a client
downloads a complete piece
from another client, it then tells other clients
it has that piece so they
can download it too. These collections of
collaborating clients are called
swarms. So we talk about a client joining
or leaving the swarm.
A client joins a swarm by downloading a Torrent
file that tells it information about the
file, such as how big it is, the size of its
pieces, and how to start contacting other
clients. It used to be that a torrent would
name a tracker, a computer that keeps track
of what clients are part of the swarm. When
a client joins the swarm, it requests a list
of other clients from the tracker. It then
starts contacting clients over TCP. A
BitTorrent client can have on the order of
100 open TCP connections at once.
After trackers started to receive a lot of
unwanted attention, in the late 2000s most
clients transitioned to using trackerless
torrents. These torrents contact a host that
tells them how to join something called a
distributed hash table, or DHT. A DHT is a
way to map a hash value to a node, where the
set of nodes supporting that DHT can
change a lot yet you can still find the node.
Rather than use a centralized table for
this lookup, the mapping is actually distributed
across all the participating nodes. It’s
basically a way for many nodes to collaboratively
store some data. In this case, they’re
storing lists of which clients are part of
a swarm.
BitTorrent breaks a files up into N pieces.
Each piece is 256kB or larger. This size is
intended to ensure a TCP stream transferring
the
file is long-lived enough that its congestion
window can grow to a reasonable size and so
support good throughput. But BitTorrent
also breaks up pieces into subpieces, such
that it can request parts of pieces from multiple
peers and so reduce latency.
A piece is also the unit that BitTorrent uses
to check integrity with. A torrent contains
the SHA1 hashes of each piece. SHA1 is
something called a cryptographic hash function.
It’s the primitive used in message authentication
codes. A strong cryptographic hash
function has the properties that, given a
hash, it’s really hard to create a piece
of data that has that hash value. This means
that if the
torrent says that the hash of piece 5 is H,
it’s hard to come up with a piece that isn’t
piece 5 which has hash H. So you can’t start
replacing the pieces of the torrent and screw
it up without a client noticing that the hash
isn’t right and retrying.
This brings up an interesting story. In 2006,
HBO had a new series, Rome. There were several
different torrents for it, each of which
had very large swarms. But many people found
their clients couldn’t download the series.
Looking into it, it turns out that there were
a
bunch of very very fast peers that many clients
were connecting to and downloading from. But
these peers provided pieces that didn’t
have the right hash. So a client would download
the piece, find the hash was wrong, throw
away the piece, and retry. Back then, the
clients assumed that this was just an error
so kept on requesting from the same peer.
So many clients would just enter an unending
loop of trying to download the same bad piece.
The hypothesis was that this was an effort
by HBO to prevent downloads. Nowadays
clients can “blacklist” peers that serve
up many bad pieces.
BitTorrent clients, when connected, periodically
exchange information
on which pieces they have. A client tries
to download the rarest piece
among its peers first. If a single piece becomes
unavailable, nobody can
download the file. Also, if only a few clients
have a piece, they’ll
become a bottleneck for downloading. This
is called the rarest first
policy.
The one exception to the rarest first policy
is when a client reaches the
end of the torrent and only needs a few more
pieces. At this point, it
requests for pieces from multiple peers. It
does this to counter the
edge case of asking for the last piece from
a very slow peer. This final
step means that the client might download
multiple copies of subpieces
and waste swarm bandwidth, but since there
are often 1000 or so
pieces in a swarm this cost is seen as small
and worth it.
So BitTorrent clients exchange metadata with
each other to learn what pieces they have.
A client
starts requesting pieces from its peers. But
if you sent data to every peer, you’d have
lots of very
slow pieces. Instead of having a hundred slow
TCP flows, BitTorrent tries to have a smaller
number of fast flows. You send data to peers
who send you data. That way, peers who contribute
can download faster. It creates an incentive
to send pieces to peers.
The way this works is through choking. Most
peers are choked and you send no data to them.
BitTorrent measures the rate at which it is
downloading from each of its peers and picks
the P
best of them. P is usually a small number,
like 4 or the square root of the number of
peers. It
unchokes these P peers and sends data to them.
One problem with this algorithm is that it
doesn’t explore much. There could be a really
good
peer out there who would send you data very
fast if only you started sending some data
first. So
every 30 seconds or so, BitTorrent unchokes
a random peer. This peer might then find its
way into
the P best.
The BitTorrent tit-for-tat algorithm seems
pretty robust: you send data preferentially
to other peers
who send you data. But it’s not perfect.
There was a nice paper in 2007 that proposed
something
called BitTyrant, which selfishly tried to
game the system. And it did! Using BitTyrant
you could
increase your BitTorrent throughput by 70%!
The basic observation is that in the standard
BitTorrent, a peer tries to share its uplink
capacity evenly
across its unchoked peers. So if a client
has P unchoked peers, then each one receives
1 over P of its
uplink capacity. But once you’re in this
top P, you get all of this. So the trick is
that you want to give a
peer *just enough* to make your way into its
top P, and no more. You should spend the extra
capacity
on trying to get into another peer’s top
P. So this way you try to give everyone just
enough that they
unchoke you, and maximize how many peers unchoke
you.
It’s a nice result. They also found that
if everyone used BitTyrant, performance can
improve slightly.
But you get the most benefit if you’re the
only tyrant. The URL here links to the paper.
So that’s a basic overview of BitTorrent.
Your client
downloads a torrent file, for example, over
HTTP. This
describes the file to download and how to
find peers to
download from. BitTorrent breaks the file
into pieces, and
peers exchange these pieces. They connect
over TCP/IP and
exchange metadata so they know what the distribution
of
pieces is over their part of the swarm. A
client then tries to
download the rarest piece first, in order
to balance
availability. Clients upload data only to
their top P
downloaders. So most of the peers are “choked”
and receive
no data, and the client gives data to those
who give you
data using a “tit-for-tat” algorithm.
To discover potentially
good new peers, the client also randomly unchokes
a peer
periodically.