A problem that can arise in networks  is
when you have different kinds of addresses
and you somehow need to resolve them and
you need to know what address is associated
with some other address.
One really common example of this that you
encounter is figuring out what is the
ethernet address associated with an IP
address.
And this problem or generally, the problem
of mapping network addresses and hardware
addresses is solved by something called
ARP, the Address Resolution Protocol.
The problem here is that you have
layers of names.
So, in the case of something like this
host, I have an IP address, say,
171.67.76.65.
I'm going to, here's my IPv6 address.
But I also have the interface address,
this is the, the Ethernet address of, say,
my Ethernet card.
And somehow, I need to associate these two
things.
I know that if I want to send an IP packet
to this host,
then this is the ethernet address I should
send it to.
So, let's go back to DHCP.
So, recall that, you know, I have this
client and I issue a DHCP request and I
get my IP address.
Let's just say, you know, it's
192.168.0.7.
So, one of the things that the DHCP server
will give me is my gateway IP address.
So, this is, if I want to send a packet
into the wider internet, I should send it
via this IP address.
But the problem is I don't need to just
send it through that node.
I don't want to send it to 192.168.0.1
I want to send it to sort of my
destination IP address. Let's say,
171.5.6.7, alright? That's what I sort of
what, I want that IP address to be the
destination address.
But I want to send it to this interface.
So, at the link layer, I want to send it
to the gateway, but the destination IP
address should be the destination IP
address I actually have off the internet
at large.
And so, my DHCP server, you know, it gives
me this information.
Here's my gateway, etc. I fill this in,
but the basic problem you encounter is
given the IP address of the gateway, or,
in fact, of any of the nodes in my local
subnet, I need to know the link layer
address that can properly address an
ethernet frame to and so, if the IP packet
destination is actually the gateway IP,
then I want the destination IP
address to be the gateway IP address,
and the destination ethernet address to be the gateway's ethernet address.
But if the packet destination is not the
gateway IP, it's somewhere in the larger
internet, then I want the destination to
be my destination's IP address.
I want the destination IP address to be, say,
Google's IP address but I want the
ethernet, the link to our destination
address, to be the ethernet address of the
gateway.
And so, how do I do this?
How do I get the ethernet address of the
gateway?
So, the answer is something called the
address, Address Resolution Protocol or
ARP.
Basically, what ARP does is it generates
mappings between layer two and layer three
addresses.
It's a simple request reply protocol, so
what you do is you send a message saying,
"Hey, who has address X? Who has network
address X?"
And someone can respond, saying, "I have
network address X."
There should be an exclamation point.
You send your request to link layer
broadcast address, so everyone hears it.
The reply is sent unicast to the requesting
address, not broadcast.
The packet format includes some redundant
data like you say, your own ethernet
address, your own network address so that
people who hear you ask a request can then
cache in the information. And it tells
them, oh, that's the mapping. If I
ever need to talk to that IP address, that's
the Ethernet address to go through.
This is also included to make debugging
much simpler.
Furthermore, there's no sharing of bad
state.
Nobody ever says what's the mapping between
a link and a network address
Nobody ever says it except the owner of
that mapping. So, you never speak for
anyone else's ethernet address or anyone
else's IP address.
And so, if I know it's generating a bad
state and you turn it off or you stop it
from generating bad state, that state will
eventually die right away it's not
like people are going to continue, are
going to repeat it forever.
So, the ARP packet looks like this and there is an
identifier saying, what is the hardware?
So, let's say, ethernet and then what's the
protocol, let's say, IP.
Then there's the length of a hardware
address and the length of a protocol address.
And then the Opcode is "this is a request/
this is a response". And then, here are the
four fields, or the five fields, the
source hardware, source protocol,
destination hardware, destination
protocol.
And then, you can also embed data in the
ARP request, and response if you want.
And so, the way this works is, if the
client wants to send a packet through the
wider internet, it knows from DHCP
that the gateway is 192.168.0.1.
And what it'll do is it will say, "ARP",
you know, "who is 192.168.0.1", and by the
way, it's going to say, "oh, and I'm
192.168.0.3 with 68:A8:60:05:85:22".
So now, anyone hearing this can put this
into their table.
Then, the gateway will respond, saying,
"aha", you know, "I am,
I'm 192.168.0.1 and I have 0:18:E7:R3:CE:1A".
Because that's the reply that comes back.
So, reverse ARP was kind of the opposite
of this.
It's something that is completely obsolete
and it's replaced by DHCP which is the way of
saying, hey, "I have a link address what's
my network address?"
And so now, DHCP is what does this. Rather
than say, "hey, this is my ethernet address,
what's my IP address", and you do an explicit
request through the Dynamic Host
Configuration Protocol to say, hey, I
would like an IP address.
And so, RARP is this thing which is nice to
mention, ARP and RARP. But in practice,
RARP is not used today.