In this video I am going to start out by
telling you some of the shortcomings of a
FIFO output queue and, some of the
problems it causes.
And I am going to describe two
alternatives.
Switches that provide, strict priorities
to give high priority and low priority
traffic and those who can give a
guaranteed rate to each of the flows
passing through it.
Let's start by reviewing what an output
queued packet switch looks like.
This is an example we saw before where we
had three packets arriving.
Their addresses will be looked up and they
will be switched to the correct output.
In this particular case two red packets.
Meaning they'll go to the middle red
output.
And, blue one to the top.
One of the red packets gets to go.
The other one is held back waiting for the
link to be free, and then it goes an it's
way, afterwards.
So, implicit here is the, the assumption
that the, the output queue is a FIFO,
first in first out, and that's pretty,
pretty reasonable assumption for most
router queues.
But in what are we going to be looking at
next.
We are gonna be focusing on this output
queue and seeing what some of the
consequences are, of it being a FIFO.
So, a FIFO queue is sometimes called a
free for all queue.
If there are many packets flowing through
this queue coming from the different
inputs.
So, I've drawn here three inputs to the
queue, representing the three inputs to
the other inputs to the switch.
So, these are all packets that are coming
through that are part of flows that are
going to this one output.
So we'll see packets coming out of here,
coming from all of those inputs.
And presumably, at any one time, when we
have congestion, we'll see packets queued
up in this, FIFO queue.
If there are many flows passing through
the queue.
Whoever sends at the highest rate.
Whoever sends the most packets will, in
fact, receive the highest usage of this
output link.
So, in other words, if this one up here is
able to get a whole load of packets into
here.
While this one down here, this the bottom
input is only able to get a small number.
This guy up here is going to hog this
output link.
So, if there's is a really big hog of a
flow going through, a little flow could
easily get squeezed out completely.
People say that this, this kind of FIFO
queue, while it's nice and simple, it
encourages bad behaviour, because the best
thing for a flow to do is to try and crowd
out every other flow by sending as fast as
it can.
It would be a little bit like when you're
downloading a web page, the thing to do
would be to try and get your packets sent
towards you at the highest possible rate
to maximise the amount of the, amount of
the queue that you can get.
It's not very friendly behaviour and it
doesn't provide a good incentive for good
behaviour.
Now, imagine that some of the traffic was
very urgent, for example, some control
traffic.
So, let's say we had some, some urgent red
packets here, and then we had some less
urgent green packets elsewhere maybe
there's another one that's squeezed in, in
front of that.
A green packet down here, and a green
packet down here and maybe let's just add
another a red packet for good measure.
So, it these ones were more important.
What the FIFO queue will do is simply send
them out in the order in which they came
in.
So, if we were to number the order in
which they arrived, say this was number
one, this was number two, this was the
third one to arrive, this was the fourth
one, this was the fifth one, and the sixth
one.
They're obviously just going to go out in
that order of one, two, three, four, five,
six on the outgoing line.
So, not very good for the urgent control
traffic or perhaps it's some important
video traffic.
So, the FIFO doesn't have any way to
distinguish important.
It just says, if you got here first, and
there was room in the queue, you are the
most important packet.
So, we can't say anything meaningful about
the rate of each flow sharing this queue.
One little observation that's going to
prove useful later, and it's why I've
labeled this as the size of the queue as
B.
And the rate at which it's being served,
the outgoing link R.
Notice that if a packet does make in into
the queue.
So, if I have a packet that does make it
into the queue, let's say this one ends up
at the tail of the queue.
The maximum time it has to wait is B over
R.
Alright.
So the delay through that queue we know is
less than or equal to B over R.
So, we're going to remember this.
We're going to use this observation later.
In this video.
I'm gonna describe two alternatives to
simple FIFO queuing.
The first one is called Strict Priorities
where we give higher priority to some
flows over others.
And the second one is Rate Guarantees
where we give a guaranteed rate or a
guaranteed fraction of the outgoing link
to each of the flows.
So, basically we're going to take our
single FIFO that we had before and replace
it with a more complicated mechanism here.
We simply replaced it with a high priority
queue and a low priority queue.
So, the inputs are just the same as
before.
These are where packets arrive from the
incoming links.
But now, as a packet arrives, we're gonna
decide whether we're to place it into the
high priority queue or into a low priority
queue and we do this based on bits in the
header.
So, when a packet arrives it might have a
bit in the header and in IP there's a
specific field for this.
It's called the type of service field.
And, we might use that to decide which
traffic is high priority and which is low
priority.
We might do this for example to say that
video traffic is more important that
email.
So, we might want to put the video in the
high priority queue, and the email in the
low priority queue.
Or we might say that control traffic is
more important that data, because we
always want to have high priority for the
management traffic on the network.
Or an operator might say that their gold
users, that their traffic takes strict
preference over their silver, customers.
And so, that's a way of classifying users
and giving preference to those who pay
more.
The way that this actually works is, when
the packets arrive so they would be
placed, and I'm going to put, I'm going to
put the red packets in here and I'm going
to put green packets in here for lower
priority.
The basic discipline is, is this.
There's a scheduler that sits at the
output here.
And it's always going to take packets from
the high priority if they are there.
And it's only going to serve the low
priority if there's nothing in the high
priority queue.
The consequence is that high priority
traffic doesn't see the low priority
traffic.
It's unaffected by it.
Because we only serve the low priority
queue if the high priority queue is empty.
It's as if the high priority traffic has
its own private network, and doesn't see
the low priority traffic at all.
This is great for many types of, of many
occasions where we want to give strict
preference to, to another one.
But it does run the danger of starving out
the low priority traffic.
So, you can only use it when there's a
reasonably small amount of high, high
priority traffic.
We don't want to completely hog the, hog
the link, and starve out this low priority
traffic at all.
But it is quite widely used and many
switchers and routers support this, the
capability today.
What if instead of strict priorities, we
wanted to have weighted priorities?
What I mean by that is, if a packet
arrives into this queue here.
And packets arrive into this queue here.
I want the, the, in, in, in some sense for
the traffic here to be considered to be
twice as important as this here.
Not, not always have a strict preference
but having twice as many opportunities to
send.
More precisely, I'm going to say that the
rate at which this queue served, is going
to be two over two plus one.
So, in other words, two is a fraction of
the total rate of the egress link.
Likewise, I'm going to say that the rate
that this one is going to be served is
one.
That's its weight, divided by the total
weight, times the outgoing link rate.
Okay.
That's what I'm trying to accomplish.
I can generalize this to, many queues, as
follows.
This is simply just, just increasing it
from two to n, where Q sub i.
Is going to receive W sub i bits, of
service.
And that's the, that, that, that's its,
its weight.
So for example, W1 here will have a rate
R1, is W1 divided by the sum of all of
the weights, alright that is the sum
over I have Wi times R.
All the way down to of course, W sub n,
just as before R of n equals W of n over
the sum.
I'll just write it like that, times R of
the outgoing link.
If all the packets were of the same length
this would actually be pretty easy.
We would simply visit each of the queues
in turn, and we will call that a round.
So, one round is when we visited all of
the queues in turn.
And then we would send W sub i units.
So, they could be bits or complete packets
from each queue in each round.
So, on the outgoing line, we could have,
we could have W sub one bits from here.
Then we would have all the way through to
W sub n bits from this one and then all
the intervening queues as well, and so
this would be a round, when we visited
over the queues.
And, you can see that the proportion that
each queue has, has been served in that
round is in proportion to the weights,
which is exactly what we wanted.
So, if we could serve the packets as bits
at a time and actually send them out as
bits at a time, which of course we can't.
But if we could, then this would be
actually pretty easy to accomplish what we
wanted.
We would simply classify the packets as
they arrive into the queue that they are
destined for.
And then we would serve those queues
according to, the W sub i bits in each
round and then send them out.
Of course, packets are variable length and
they don't consist of single bits.
And the problem is that real packets vary
in size from something like 64 bytes all
the way to, in, in the case of ethernet
about 1500 bytes.
There are jumbo frames that are even
longer than this but even, even here we've
got two orders of magnitude difference in
packet size.
So, if we were to serve this packet-by-
packet instead of bit by bit it would
really mess up the, the weights and we
wouldn't accomplish what we were trying to
do.
Clearly, we must take into account the
packet lengths if we want to prevent long
packets from crowding out the short ones.
So, let me describe how we, how we do
this.
I'm going to first describe it in terms of
a kind of a thought experiment.
I'm going to use this notion of rounds
again where we visit each queue in turn in
a round.
And then we're going to send W sub i bits
from each queue during that round.
But I am going to assume that in addition to
the, the queues that I have here that I
have another.
I'm going to call it a magic queue.
Just to remind us this really isn't a
queue.
It's just going to be a processing element
just to have us think about the problem.
We're going to get rid of this in a, in a
minute.
So in a round, the first queue gets to
send W sub one bits and the last queue
gets to send W n bits.
What we're going to do is, we're going to
imagine that we're going to serve each of
these queues by that number of bits in
each round.
And then when we get to an end-of-packet
marker, which is the last bit in, the last
bit in a packet.
So, this would be the end-of-packet here,
and then let's say this is the
end-of-packet here.
Once we've got to that end-of-packet
marker we will construct complete packets
and send them on to the outgoing links.
So, that's what this magic queue is going
to do.
It's going to turn those bit by bit into
packet-by-packet.
And so this will be the end-of-packet bit
here, and this is the end-of-packet bit
here.
But this is, this is recognizing the we
can't send them out in bits.
We wait until the full packet is
accumulated, and then send them out.
So, the question is, in what order should
we be sending these out on to the line?
When should we send them?
Because our goal is to meet the rate
guarantees where each queue gets that
weighted fair share of the outgoing line.
So, in what order should we send those
packets in order to accomplish that?
I'm going to describe that next.
So, just as before, we're going to assume
that time proceeds in rounds.
So, our unit of time is going to be
rounds.
And we're going to figure out, if we were
to service the packets bit by bit.
Which round would they have finished in.
Okay?
So, if we were to serve them bit by bit,
which round would they have finished in?
Well, I'm going to start by making an, an
observation that will give you a, give you
a clue as to how we're going to use this.
Let's consider a packet here that's
waiting to go.
And let's consider the round in which it
starts, we'll call that S of k.
And the round in which it finishes, and
we'll call that F sub k.
Because we're serving everything, in
rounds, and time progresses in rounds, we
can say the finishing time of this packet
is its starting time in rounds plus the
length of the packet divided by w of one.
That's because that first queue will
receive exactly W sub one bits of service
in each round.
So, it's finishing round is its starting
round plus its length divided by the
number of bits it gets served per round.
Okay.
So, this is the finishing time here.
Now, let's think about what happens when a
packet arrives.
So, we're going to try and calculate the
starting time of that packet when it
arrives.
In other words, what time will it enter
service and what time will it finish
service.
It might be surprising that we can do this
but I'm going to show you a way we can
calculate both it's starting time and it's
finishing time, when it arrives.
So, the, the starting time of that packet,
the time at which it starts to enter
service, is going to depend on what's
ahead of it in the queue.
So, if we're keeping track of the
finishing time of this packet, in rounds
and we want to know what the starting time
of this next packet here and its finishing
time.
We can do the following calculations.
So, this is the finishing time of the k-1
packet.
Its the one that's ahead of waiting in
queue.
We can say that the starting time of the
packet k is going to be simply the
finishing time of the packet ahead of it
because
It, we were proceeding in rounds, so it
will be immediately entering service as
soon as the one ahead of it is finished.
Unless the queue happens to be empty and
there's nothing ahead of us, in which case
it will enter service now.
There's going to be the max of these two
values.
The max of the finishing time of the
packet ahead of it and now.
The second thing that we can say is that
the finishing time of K is it's starting
time plus L over W1, just as before
because we know that's how much service.
So, the combination of these two gives us
a recursion that so long as we keep
calculating the finishing time and keep
track of that, we can calculate the
starting time and the finishing time of
packets as they arrive.
Those are pretty neat property.
And then what we're going to do is, we're
going to service the packets.
In other words, we're going to take the
packets from head of lines.
So, here is the scheduler.
Its going to be examining the head of line
packets, and its going to pick the one
with the lowest F, the lowest finishing
time.
So, it will pick the packet with the
lowest finishing time.
So, that's what the scheduler does.
So we, calculated the F of K when the
packet came in.
And then, when it gets to the of head of
line, it's competing with all the head of
line packets to leave, and the scheduler
is simply gonna pick the one with lowest
finishing time.
This has the nice property that finishing
times can be determined when the packet
arrives.
And, the packets are served in order of
their finishing time which at least
intuitively seems like the best thing to
do.
It turns out that it is more intui-, more
than just intuitively a good thing to do.
I'll show you why it actually is the right
thing to do.
If we plot the finishing time of the
packets, if they were being served bit by
bit.
In other words, the time that the end of
packet bit would leave on the outgoing
line if the packet was being served.
But it might look something like this.
This is just something I sketched.
If we look at the finishing time of the
packet-by-packet scheme, where each packet
goes and must wait for the packet ahead of
it to finish before it can go on the line.
Packets could end up actually departing a
little bit later, because they could be
held up by a packet that's still in
service.
So, there could be a little bit of a delta
between when the packet would finish
bit-by-bit, and we know if it's bit-by-bit
then the rate it will receive, the, the,
the, the Qi will receive, will be W sub i
over the sum of the Wj's.
In other words, the weight that we're
looking for of the out going line.
So, if this was being met then we know
that would be true.
In the packet-by-packet scheme, it can be
proved there the difference in the time
that it will depart under the packet-by-
packet scheme is no more than Lmax.
The maximum length packet divided by R
later than under the bit-by-bit scheme.
And that's true for every single packet in
the system.
So, this is really useful because over a
long period of time this tells us that the
same number of bits will have departed as
under the bit -by-bit scheme.
That will just be jiggled around a little
bit.
There will be a little variance in the
actual departure time but measured over a
long period of time.
So, under this packet-by-packet scheme RF
of i will be the same as it was before.
So it'll be that weight of I divided by
the sum over WJ of R.
So, this will accomplish exactly the rates
that we want.
This scheme is often called WFQ, or
Weighted Fair Queueing.
Weighted Fair Queueing is a pretty famous
technique.
You can find lots of references to it.
And it's also known as packet-by-packet
generalized processor sharing.
But if you look under WFQ, you can find
lots of references to it.
But what it essentially tells us is, tells
us a specific mechanism for calculating
the finishing time of packets and
scheduling them, so that we can give
weighted fairness, weighted usage of the
outgoing link, and rate guarantees to each
of the flows.
In summary, FIFO queues are a bit of a
free for all.
They have no priorities, no guaranteed
rates.
And there's an incentive for a, for a flow
to send as many packets as it can into the
queue, so that it maximizes it's share of
the outgoing links.
So, they kind of encourage bad behavior.
So instead, it's quite common to use
strict priorities.
High priority traffic, could see or
experience a network which appears to have
no low priority traffic at all.
It's unaffected by it.
This is useful if we have limited amounts
of high priority traffic like control
traffic in the network.
But if we want to do something which is
more of a weighted priority, then we need
to use something like weighted fair
queueing, which lets us give each flow a
guaranteed service rate, and we do that by
scheduling the packets in order of their
bit-by-bit finishing times.
That's the end of the video.