Let’s look at a worked example for delay
guarantees.
Q. Two end hosts are separated by three routers
and four 250km links running at 100Mb/s. The
end hosts want to send a flow of 1500byte
packets to each other at 15Mb/s, but they
don’t want their packets to take more than
10ms to go from end-to-end. If each router
serves the flow at 15Mb/s, how long will packets
be delayed in each router? (Assume a propagation
speed of 2x108 m/s and that queueing delay
is evenly distributed among the routers.)
From the question we know that a third of
the queueing delay will be in each of the
routers. So first, we need to figure out what
the queueing delay is. The queueing delay
will be the total delay, which is 10ms, minus
the fixed delay, which is the sum of the packetization
delay and the propagation delay.
Let’s first calculate the packetization
delay, which is the time to transmit a 1500byte
packet onto each of the four links along the
path. For each link, the packetization delay
is 1500bytes * 8bits/byte divided by 100Mb/s
or 10 to the power of 8. This gives us a total
packetization delay of 0.48ms.
Now let’s calculate the propagation delay,
which is the time taken for one bit to traverse
all four links. The time for each link is
250km times 1000m per km, divided by the speed
of propagation. The total time will be 5ms
across all four links. Our total fixed delay
is therefore 5.48ms. This means the queueing
delay is 10 – 5.48ms = 4.52ms, which we
are told is divided equally among the three
routers. Therefore, the queueing delay in
each router can be no more than 1.507ms. The
answer is therefore 1.507ms of delay per router.
We could go on and calculate the amount of
buffering needed in each router to hold 1.507ms
of data. Given that the queue is being served
at 15Mb/s, this corresponds to 1.507ms * 15Mb/s
= 22,605 bits. In practice, we’d round this
up to at least two packets, which is 24,000
bits per router.