So, in this video, Nick and I are going
to present the end-to-end principle in
network design.
So, if we look at how a network
application sees the world,
it sees something like this.
There's one computer running the
application, some other computer running
the application.
And then, in the middle, there's the
internet.
And, it's abstraction of the internet is
that it can send packets, each node A and
B can send packets address to each other.
And, the internet somehow magically
delivers them from one end to the other
end.
And, all it does, this is all the internet
really does, it just forwards these
packets along.
So, you can ask the question, why doesn't
the internet do more than that?
Why doesn't the internet help these
applications?
You know, they're just sending packets but
maybe it's a simple application and maybe
it could do something much better and the
network could help it do something much
better such as, the network could
automatically compress data reducing the
capacity needed and therefore increasing the throughout of the application.
It could reformat, or translate, or
improve requests, if it realizes that you
are requesting an HTML document in an
inefficient way, it could reformat the
request for you, so that you get a better
response.
Rather than give you that data from the
other computers if it has a cache closer
to you, it could just give you the cache
data.
It can add security, this will be really
useful, for running an application which
is insecure, then it could automatically
add securities.
There's confidentiality and integrity, so
people can't eavesdrop on what you're
doing.
There's all kinds of things that network
could possibly do to help you, right?
So, you could just send simple packets and
the network does the smart things to make
your application work better.
So, why doesn't it?
Or, why do we have this model, the
internet just forwarding packets?
>> So a, a, an early guiding principle for
the for, for the inventors and the early
pioneers of the internet was to try and
create a network that was dumb and
minimal.
And that it would do the least that it
possibly needed to do, and then pushes
much of the functionality and the
intelligence to the edges that's close to
the application as possible.
And this is widely referred to as the
end-to-end principle.
It's actually around, been around for, for
many years before the internet.
But, when the internet came along, this
was the, the biggest application or the
biggest use of this principle.
And so has become very widely used as a
defining principle in many computer
systems since.
>> And so, while this principle existed
for a long time before the internet, it
was really sort of, written down and
codified in this very seminal paper by
Saltzer, , Reed, and Clarke called
End-to-End Arguments in System Design.
It was published in 1984.
This is the intent principle.
The function in question can be completely
and correctly implemented only with the
knowledge and help of the application
standing at the endpoints of the
communication system.
And so, the, the idea is that, if I have
some piece of application logic or some
application function, well, the network
can possibly help.
Ultimately, the endpoints of that
communication have to be responsible of
making sure it works correctly.
And so, the communication system itself
providing, providing that questioned
function as a feature of the communication
system itself is not possible.
So, sometimes the communication layer of
the internet could, could help you.
Could improve performance.
But, ultimately, it has to be up to the
endpoints to ensure correctness.
They call this line of reasoning the end
to end argument.
But, if you want to accomplish some
application goal, ultimately, that goal
must be implemented end-to-end.
Something in the middle might help you
out, but you can't assume that that will be
there.
You can't assume that will be correct, and
you must have the correctness implemented
end-to-end.
>> So, lets take a look at certain
examples of where the end-to-end principle
comes to, to, to, to help us.
So, the most classic example is file
transfer.
File transfer where we are taking a file
from one computer and delivering it intact
correctly in correct order and, to, to the
other end.
So, what we would hope of the entire
end-to-end connection is that file would
be delivered correctly such that every
byte of one end is correctly delivered to
the other end in order.
Such that if any are lost in transit, that
they will be re-transmitted so that we can
be sure that they eventually correct,
eventually get them.
Now, the network, the intervening network
could make sure that the file is
transferred to some intermediate point.
And then, from that intermediate path,
stored and forwarded along the path.
Or, on every link along the way, it could
make sure that if there is data that's
dropped, it could retransmit that data.
What the, the end-to-end argument says is,
even if the intervening network is trying
to do that, the only way to ensure that
end-to-end, that the data is delivered
correctly and in order is for the
end-to-end to be responsible for it.
And, have the means to both check it and
that any missed data is filled in and the
out of sequence data is put back into the
correct order.
>> So, the original paper actually went
into a specific example that the authors
encountered with the Multics operating
system which is the predecessor of UNIX.
Where they had a file transfer protocol
which assumed on each hop that had
re-transmissions, that had re-assembly such
that if I wanted to get the file from A to
B, and it's traversing these intermediate
nodes C and D, these nodes would be
responsible for the reliability along each
link.
And the problem that occurred was that
there was some faulty memory in one of
these nodes.
And so, the packets of data were
transmitted, say, from A to C they were
transmitted correctly.
But then, while in C's memory, C corrupted
them.
And then C forwarded them along these
corrupted pieces of data and then
eventually, when the data arrived at B, it
had been corrupted.
So, the file was corrupted and they lost a
great deal of a big chunk of Multics source
code because of this.
And so the argument, the end-to-end
argument says that, while the fact that
the A to C link was doing retransmissions,
and doing reassembly, and able to then
ensure this reliable transfer from A to C,
the actual transfer from a to b requires
an end-to-end check.
That is, when b receives the data, it
should somehow verify with A that the data
it received is actually the data that A
sent.
The network can help by doing
retransmissions in the middle, etc., but
that help does not obviate A and B from
doing the end-to-end check for correctness
because there can be errors within the
network.
And so, another example of this and this
relates to the Multics example is link
reliability.
So, if I have a, a set of nodes say, along
a route, And so, here I have four nodes,
A, B, C, and D, and I want to ensure
perfect reliability from A to D.
One question you can ask is that, will
every packet that A sends will arrive at
D?
On one approach is that, you could just
have each link be perfectly reliable.
Such that when A sends a packet to B, B
either sends an acknowledgement.
If A doesn't hear acknowledgement it'll
retransmit, such that along each link
you'll have perfectly reliable transfer,
and same with B will do to C, and C will
do to D.
So now, each link has 100 percent
reliability.
And you could say, well, since each link
is reliable, the overall route is
reliable.
And so, we don't need for A to check with
D, whether it received all of the data.
But, so what happens if A sends data to B,
B receives it, B acknowledges it.
And then, B crashes and that data is lost
out of its memory.
This link was perfectly reliable that the
data was delivered to B.
But then, B lost it up above the link
layer, up above this communication layer.
And now, suddenly not all data would be
delivered to D.
And so the end-to-end principle in this
setup is that A needs an end-to-end check
that the data actually arrives at D.
>> And so, you can take this example and,
and use it then to think about how the
overall system is designed.
One could imagine the way in which each
link, or a system in which each link was
providing that, that retransmission.
And then, you did the end-to-end check as
well.
It then begs the question of, if you're
going to do the end-to-end check, should
you actually put in the checks and the
re-transmission on each link along the
way?
And that's a design choice when the system
is being, is being built.
And, the basic thinking and the, the idea
behind the end-to-end argument is not only
do you need to do it at the ends, but if
you are going to put it at the ends, then
one can draw the conclusion that you don't
need to put it in the middle.
Therefore, simplifying the network that
interconnects the end points.
>> And so, the original end-to-end
principle described in that seminal paper
said that you have to do an end-to-end
check and you can put some stuff in the
network if you want to improve things.
A general philosophy today in the design
of networks is that you should avoid
putting things into the network.
So, if you look at RFC 1958, this is what
I, I like call it the strong end-to-end
principle.
It's not that you have to do an end-to-end
check, or you have to do end-to-end
correctness, but rather you should also
avoid doing things inside the network.
And so, RFC 1958 says, the network's job
is to transit datagrams as efficiently and
flexibly as possible, flexi, flexibly as
possible.
Everything else should be done at the
fringes.
This argument that you, it's not that
everything has to be done at the, the
fringes but in fact, the network should do
very, very little if anything to help.
It should just forward datagrams.
>> So, throughout this course, we're going
to see lots and lots of examples of how
the internet works, why it was designed
the way that it was.
And you're going to see that there are,
that there is this general guiding
principle in the way that the internet was
designed to make the intervening the, the,
the network as simple as possible.
However, you're probably going to find
yourself wondering on many occasions
during this course.
And, in fact, we would encourage you to,
to think of it this way.
Does the network need to be doing that
function?
And, it's very, it's worth thinking
critically about this as we, as we go
along.
So, I will give you some, I will give you
some examples.
There've been many proposals to introduce
link by link encryption in which data
along a particular link is, is secured so
that it can't be listened to or interfered
with by, by another user.
So, an interesting question to ask is, if
the, if the network is doing this and then
I still have to do this end-to-end, what
is the point in the network, what is the
purpose of the network doing this?
And so, this creates lots of debate and
arguments among internet designers and people
who are building networking equipment as
to such a feature or function.
And we'll see some examples and some very
subtle, subtle points as we go.
For example, there's a very common,
there's a very common desire for the
network to replicate packets on our
behalf.
Imagine that your watching, listening to
a, or watching broadcast TV over the
network, it will be natural to suggest
that the network replicate the packets
from when they're being transmitted to
receive every, to be received by everyone
who is watching that, that broadcast.
And this is a very legitimate question,
should the network replicate the packet?
Or should the sender replicate the
packets?
And so, this is an area of, of lots of
controversy and some great debate over the
years.
And so, we will see that, that, that it's
a guiding principle that is a very
powerful principle and has served the
internet well and keeping it minimal,
simple, flexible, and streamlined.
Although there is a constant vigilance to
make sure that it stays that way.
>> So, another good example of this
relates to, sometimes a network provider
has a link that is very, very limited.
So, they have, say, some back-haul link
and capacity on that link is very limited.
And so, what they do is they want to take
the data that's going over the link.
Maybe it is just HTML, so it's ASCII text.
Ascii text is very compressible by about a
factor of eight to one even.
And so, if you were to take the data and
go across that link and compress it, then
suddenly you would increase the effective
capacity of that link, assuming it's a
mostly, mostly HTML traffic, HTTP by a
factor of eight.
Now, to do this requires looking inside
the packets that are going across the
link.
You get in a packet that is a certain
length or say a TCP segment, some higher
level protocol, you have to actually start
peering inside these transport layer
segments.
Layers above which you're supposed to be
concerned with at the network and start
changing the packets.
And so, there are situations where
providers do this.
But now, the code that they have, that
looks at these TCP segments, that looks at
these transport layer chunks of data, make
certain assumptions about the way the
transport layer works.
And if you try to do something new or
slightly different or something which that
code doesn't expect, then everything
breaks.
So, for example, there's one researcher,
there's a paper just as appeared this year
where you showed how, if you start doing
things which are perfectly legal under the
TCP specification but which are not
commonly what existing TCP stacks do,
these kinds of links that are rewriting
packets and generating new packets and
trying to simulate a link to compress data
fail.
And so, you're doing something which
end-to-end should just work.
The network shouldn't be looking at your
TCP segments.
But, because it does, it then causes your
transport stream to fail.
>> So, up until this point, Phil and I
have been talking about some of the
technical and architectural aspects of the
end-to-end argument.
But, turns out there are really interesting
business and political aspects to this
discussion as well.
The debate about net neutrality is largely
about the following problem.
If you are a user at home or in an
enterprise who is using the network and
you're, you're using the service or an
application that requires data to be
delivered to you, for example, your
streaming video or you're, you're on a
Voice Over IP communication.
Then, the question is, should that data,
should that data receive better treatment
because of the application that you're
using depending on what the application is
or where it's coming from decided by
somebody else so that they can make a
decision on your behalf of which data is
more important?
Because if your connection to the Internet
is in some way constrained, it doesn't
have a sufficient, sufficient data rate.
Then, it seems reasonable to think that
you will identify some traffic as more
important than others.
So, it comes from a, comes from a sense
that if there is a constraint and a
bottleneck, then it makes sense to
differentiate that traffic.
However, the controversy comes from who
gets to decide.
Who gets to decide that some data is more
important than others, and that some data
should be delivered more reliably, or more
quickly than others.
And that then enters a very, very
complicated economic and political
discussion.
Because it then gets, it gets to the point
of, who controls that connection that we
have with the outside world?
So, it then brings in all sorts of
questions and fears about walled gardens
and people preventing us from doing things
that we want to do, and takes us right in
to the question of censorship as well.
So, it's a very, very complex and
controversial topic.
>> So that, the end-to-end principle might
seem like this abstract concept about
how we build networks and re-transmitting
packets, but it has very real implications
today with respect to the politics of the
internet and the economics of the
internet.
In fact, in some ways, net neutrality is,
at some level, an articulation of the
strong end-to-end principle.
That the network should just dumbly
forward packets, it should not treat
packets differently, it shouldn't treat
packets from some applications different
than any others.
Because the network should just be this
simple, basic abstraction of delivering
packets.
And that's one of the arguments for net
neutrality.
And so, It's really about the strong
end-to-end principle.
But of course, people don't completely agree
about this.
And so, there are some people who are
strongly in favor of net neutrality.
So, there are two of the pioneers of the
internet, Vint Cerf and Bob Kahn.
And so, Vint Cerf testifying before
congress basically said, hey, allowing
these broadband carriers to control
what people see and do online, that is
control their packets, make some packets
faster or slower, it undermines the basic
principles of the internet.
In contrast, you know, Bob Kahn says that
he's totally opposed to mandating that
nothing interesting can happen inside the
network.
And, I mean, I think there's sort of this
tension, right?
About you mentioned, you're a service
provider, you want to make your service,
you're a carrier and to make your service
better to users you want to add some
optimizations.
And there's a concern.
By so doing, you're going to prevent
future users or existing users from doing
new and interesting things, right?
So, what actually trigger, that the event
that really triggered the whole, the net
neutrality debate, here's the interesting
example of the end-to-end principle,
whether the network should be smart or dumb, was when
BitTorrent really started to take off.
And so, as it turns out, that the way
Comcast, a particular service provider
constructed its network.
Nodes in Comcast's network had very large
download capacity.
So, here's the internet.
Here's the intranet.
There was very large download capacity to
these nodes to your, you know, machine at
your house, and a small upload capacity.
So, it was an asymmetric capacity.
So, you could download lots of stuff from
the web, but web requests are small.
But now, the things that BitTorrent, just
cuz of the way it works, really tries to
get symmetric traffic.
So, tries to be big, big uploads and big
downloads.
And so, what BitTorrent started to do was
to completely overload these small upload
links in Comcast's network.
And from Comcast's standpoint, there are a
couple of BitTorrent users who are using
BitTorrent and it is making the internet
amazingly slow for all of their other
users.
Because the other users just want to use the
web, but suddenly their web requests take
seconds rather than hundreds of
milliseconds.
And so, they were just seeing terrible
performance and they're trying to satisfy
the desires of, you know, their 95 percent
customers.
So, what Comcast did was it deployed this
technology which would detect that there
was a BitTorrent connection going on, a TCP
connection for BitTorrent and it would
generate what is called a reset packet.
And when we talk about TCP, we'll talk
about in more detail what this is.
But essentially, it would forge a packet
and tell your BitTorrent client to shut
down the connection that the transfer is
done.
And so, BitTorrent would start up, it
would start trying to send some data.
And then, these devices deployed in the
network by Comcast would shut down the
BitTorrent connections.
And, the reason this became very political
was that this is at the same time that
Comcast was starting to roll out it's own
video streaming service.
So, people were using BitTorrent to
exchange movies in some cases legally, in
some cases probably illegally.
And, this was then seen as, aha, you know,
Comcast is claiming that it is just trying
to protect its network, but it is also not
allowing people to use an alternative
service.
It's forcing people to use their video
streaming service.
And, this is what made the debate very
political about the conflicting, sort of,
the, the, you could say, a conflict of
interest on Comcast's part etc.
So, since then, people have figured out
now the IETF is working on making
BitTorrent not kill connections, etc.
But, it was this point where Comcast
started shutting down BitTorent, BitTorent
only, even for people who were using it
for perfectly valid and legal uses,
there's questions as to whether an ISP
could decide you can't run this
application.