In the last video you learned how different
applications -- such as BitTorrent, Skype
and the World Wide Web – communicate over
the Internet using a bi-directional reliable
byte stream.
It takes a lots of different pieces working
together to create this reliable communication
model for our applications. But even though
we use a huge variety of different Internet
applications, sending many kinds of data at
very different speeds, there are surprisingly
strong similarities in the way applications
send and receive data. For example, applications
want to send and receive data without having
to worry about the path, or route, that the
data takes across the Internet. And almost
all applications want to be confident that
their data is correctly delivered, with any
lost or corrupted data automatically retransmitted
until it is received correctly.
The early Internet pioneers created the “4
Layer Internet Model” to describe the hierarchy
of operations that make up the Internet, so
that applications can reuse the same building
blocks over and over again, without having
to create them from scratch for every application.
Layering is an important and frequently used
concept in networking and we’ll be seeing
it many times throughout this course. There
is even a video devoted just to the concept
of layering.
Let’s take a look at what each layer of
the 4 Layer Internet model does. It helps
to remember that all four layers are there
to enable applications in the end-hosts communicate
reliably.
To explain how it works, I’m going to start
at the bottom layer. We’ll see that each
layer has a different responsibility, with
each layer building a service on top of the
one below, all the way to the top where we
have the bi-directional reliable byte stream
communication between applications.
Let’s start with the Link Layer.
The Internet is made up of end-hosts, links
and routers. Data is delivered hop-by-hop
over each link in turn. Data is delivered
in packets. A packet consists of the data
we want to be delivered, along with a header
that tells the network where the packet is
to be delivered, where it came from and so
on.
<Draw topology and hop by hop delivery of
data>
The Link Layer’s job is to carry the data
over one link at a time. You’ve probably
heard of Ethernet and WiFi – these are two
examples of different Link layers.
The next layer up is, for us, the most important
layer: the Network layer.
The network layer’s job is to deliver packets
end-to-end across the Internet from the source
to the destination.
A packet is an important basic building block
in networks. A packet is the name we give
to a self-contained collection of data, plus
a header that describes what the data is,
where it is going and where it came from.
You will often see packets drawn like this:
Network layer packets are called datagrams.
They consist of some data and a head containing
the “To” and “From” addresses – just
like we put the “To:” and “From” addresses
on a letter. <Draw a datagram with To/From
addresses> .
The Network hands the datagram to the Link
Layer below , telling
it to send the datagram over the first link.
In other words, the Link Layer is providing
a *service* to the Network Layer. Essentially,
the Link Layer says: “if you give me a datagram
to send, I will transmit it over one link
for you”.
At the other end of the link is a router.
The Link Layer of the router accepts the datagram
from the link, and hands it up to the Network
Layer in the router. The Network Layer on
the router examines the destination address
of the datagram, and is responsible for routing
the datagram one hop at a time towards its
eventual destination. It does this by sending
to the Link Layer again, to carry it over
the next link. And so on until it reaches
the Network Layer at the destination. <sequence
of clicks shows the steps>
Notice that the Network Layer does not need
to concern itself with *how* the Link Layer
sends the datagram over the link. In fact,
different Link Layers work in very different
ways; Ethernet and WiFi are clearly very different.
This separation of concerns between the Network
Layer and the Link Layer allows each to focus
on its job, without worrying about how the
other layer works. It also means that a single
Network Layer has a common way to talk to
many different Link Layers by simply handing
them datagrams to send. This separation of
concerns is made possibly by the modularity
of each layer and a common well-defined API
to the layer below.
In the internet, the network layer is special:
When we send packets into the Internet, we
must use the Internet Protocol. It is the
Internet Protocol, or IP, that holds the Internet
together. We’ll learn more about the details
of IP in later videos. But for now it’s
good to know some basic facts about IP.
IP makes a best-effort attempt to deliver
our packets to the other end. But it makes
no promises.
IP packets can get lost, can be delivered
out of order, and can be corrupted. There
are no guarantees.
This may come as a surprise. How can the Internet
work at all when the packets are not guaranteed
to be delivered? Well, if an application wants
a guarantee that its data will be retransmitted
when necessary and will be delivered to the
application in order and without corruption
then it needs another protocol running on
top of IP. This is the job of the Transport
Layer….
The most common Transport Layer is TCP <draw
TCP: Transmission Control Protocol>, or the
Tranmission Control Protocol. (You have probably
heard of TCP/IP, which is when an application
uses both TCP and IP together).
TCP makes sure that data sent by an application
at one end of the Internet is correctly delivered
– in the right order - to the application
at the other end of the Internet. If the Network
Layers drops some datagrams, TCP will retransmit
them, multiple times if need-be. If the Network
Layer delivers them out of order – perhaps
because two packets follow a different path
to their destination – TCP will put the
data back into the right order again. In later
videos you will learn a lot about TCP and
how it works. For now, the main thing to remember
is that TCP provides a service to an application
guaranteeing correct in-order delivery of
data, running on top of the Network Layer
service, which provides an unreliable datagram
delivery service.
As I’m sure you can imagine, applications
such as a web client, or an email client,
find TCP very useful indeed. By employing
TCP to make sure data is delivered correctly,
they don’t have to worry about implementing
all of the mechanisms inside the application.
They can take advantage of the huge effort
that developers put into correctly implementing
TCP, and reuse it to deliver data correctly.
Reuse is another big advantage of layering.
But not all applications need data to be delivered
correctly. For example, if a video conference
application is sending a snippet of video
in a packet, there may be no point waiting
for the packet to be retransmitted multiple
times; better to just move on. Some applications
just don’t need the TCP service.
If an application doesn’t need reliable
delivery, it can use the much simpler UDP
– or user datagram protocol – instead
. UDP just
bundles up application data and hands it to
the Network Layer for delivery to the other
end. UDP offers no delivery guarantees.
In other words, an Application has the choice
of at least two different Transport Layer
services: TCP and UDP. There are in fact many
other choices too, but these are the most
commonly used transport layer services.
Finally we have the Application Layer at the
top of the 4 Layer Model. There are of course
many thousands of applications that use the
Internet. While each application is different,
it can reuse the Transport Layer by using
the well-defined API from the Application
Layer to the TCP or UDP service beneath.
As we saw in the last video, applications
typically want a bi-directional reliable byte
stream between two end points. They can send
whatever byte-stream they want, and Applications
have a protocol of their own that defines
the syntax and semantics of data flowing between
the two end points. <click to make second
4layer stack appear> For example, as we saw
in the last video, when a web client requests
a page from a web server <draw them on Application
layer>, the web client sends a GET request.
This is one of the commands of the hypertext
transfer protocol, or http. http dictates
that the GET command is sent as an ASCII string,
along with the URL of the page being requested.
As far as the Application Layer is concerned,
the GET request is sent directly to its peer
at the other end – the web server Application
<draw dotted lines to show peer communication
of GET request>. The Application doesn’t
need to know how it got there, or how many
times it needed to be retransmitted. At the
web client, the Application Layer hands the
GET request to the TCP layer, which provides
the service of making sure it is reliably
delivered. It does this using the services
of the Network layer, which in turn uses the
services of the Link Layer.
We say that each layer communicates with its
peer layer . It’s as
if each layer is only communicating with the
same layer at the other end of the link or
Internet, without regard for how the layer
below gets the data there.
Putting it all together then….
Network engineers find it convenient to arrange
all the functions that make up the Internet
into *Layers*.
At the top is the Application, such as BitTorrent
or Skype or the world wide web, which talks
to its peer layer at the destination <draw
dotted line>. When the application has data
to send, it hands the data to the Transport
layer , which has the
job of delivering the data reliably (or not)
to the other end. The Transport Layer sends
data to the other end by handing it to the
Network Layer , which
has the job of breaking the data into packets,
each with the correct destination address.
Finally, the packets are handed to the Link
Layer, which has the responsibility of delivering
the packet from one hop to the next along
its path.
The data makes its way, hop by hop, from one
router to the next. The Network Layer forwards
it to the next router, one at a time, until
it reaches the destination. There, the data
is passed up the layers, until it reaches
the Application.
Application: Bi-directional reliable byte
stream between two applications, using application-specific
semantics (e.g. http, bit-torrent).
Transport: Guarantees correct, in-order delivery
of data end-to-end. Controls congestion.
Network: Delivers datagrams end-to-end. Best-effort
delivery – no guarantees. Must use the Internet
Protocol (IP).
Link: Delivers data over a single link between
an end host and router, or between routers
Now we’ve seen what the 4 layers are, I’ll
finish with two extra things you need to know….
The first is that IP is often referred to
as “the thin waist” of the Internet. This
is because if we want to use the Internet,
we have to use the Internet Protocol, or IP.
We have no choice.
But we have lots of choices for Link Layers:
IP runs over many different Link Layers, such
as Ethernet, WiFi, DSL, 3G cellular, and so
on.
On top of the unreliable IP layer, we can
choose between many different transport layers
. We already saw TCP and UDP. There is RTP
for real time data and many others too. And
of course there are tens of thousands of different
applications.
The second thing you should know is that in
the 1980s the International Standards Organization,
or ISO created a 7-layer model to represent
any type of network. It was called the 7-layer
Open Systems Interconnection or OSI model.
We don’t spend any time on it in this course
because it has been replaced by the 4-layer
Internet model. If you’re interested, you’ll
find any networking textbook and Wikipedia
describes the 7 layers in lots of detail.
The 7 layer model defined layers that were
combined in the 4 layer Internet model. For
example, what we call the Link Layer today
was separated into the Link Layer – that
defined the framing format – and the Physical
Layer that defined things like the voltage
levels on a cable, or the physical dimensions
of a connector. The Network Layers are pretty
much the same. The Transport and Application
Layers are each represented by 2 layers in
the OSI model. These <annotate the text in
the middle> are examples of commonly used
Internet protocols, and how they map to the
OSI numbering scheme.
Today, the only real legacy of the 7-layer
OSI model is the numbering system. You’ll
often hear network engineers refer to the
Network Layer as “Layer 3”,
even though it is the 2nd layer up from the
bottom in the Internet Layer. Similarly, you’ll
hear people refer to Ethernet as a Layer 2
protocol , and the Application
as Layer 7 .