In the following demo we’re going to show
how an attacker can masquerade as a DHCP server,
causing Alice to use the wrong DNS server.
In our demo, three hosts are connected to
switch “s1”. Host 1 is Alice’s machine,
which is running a good DHCP client. Host
“dhcp” runs a good dhcp server. The DHCP
server configures Alice’s machine to use
the a Good DNS server. Host “evil” is
run by Eve the Attacker, and runs a rogue
DHCP server, a rogue DNS server and a web
server.
Initially, we will assume the Eve has not
started her attack, and we’ll see a Mininet
demo of the Good DHCP server correctly configuring
Alice’s machine, so that she can access
the Internet just fine.
Then, we’ll see what happens if Eve’s
machine masquerades as the local DHCP server,
replying faster than the Good DHCP server.
Eve will configure Alice’s machine to use
the Rogue DNS server, directing Eve’s web
traffic to Eve’s web server as well.
Let’s see what happens….
The demonstration shows how simple a DHCP
attack is, if the Attacker has access to the
local network, and can install a rogue dhcp
client close to the victim.
The demo I’m going to show you runs in the
Mininet emulation system, which means you
can easily and safely run it yourself on your
own computer, and I’ll tell you shortly
how. It also means the same code can easily
be replicated into a real network. The demo
was created by Bob Lantz, at the Open Networking
Lab in Palo Alto.
H1 runs a dhcp client and is initially configured
correctly by a nearby host running a good
dhcp server for the local network. "evil"
is run by Eve the Attacker and runs a rogue
DHCP server. The host "dhcp" is connected
to s1 via a 500ms link, to delay its dhcp
responses to Alice. We need the delay to be
sure Alice will hear the evil DHCP responses
before the good ones.
Alice uses host "h1" to browse the web using
her Firefox browser.
As we can see, she can successfully reach
the Stanford website. Her computer, h1, runs
a dhcp client to configure her IP address,
the address of her local router and her DNS
server. If we use the dig command to look
up another name like amazon.com, we can see
that the DNS server, in this case a public
DNS server run by Google at IP address 8.8.8.8
is responding to the query with Amazon’s
IP addresses, and the site loads as expected
in Firefox.
Eve the Attacker starts three processes on
the evil host: A rogue DHCP server, a rogue
DNS server and a web server. Eve is going
to force all Alice's web accesses to go to
Eve's web server instead. Every so often,
our dhcp client is required to renew the lease
on its IP address. In wireshark we can see
that when h1 issues a DHCP discover, the good
DHCP server at 10.0.0.50 responds with an
offer that contains the address of the legitimate
DNS server at 8.8.8.8, but (unfortunately)
Alice’s machine hears the offer from the
rogue DHCP server first and accepts it. She
is now in trouble. Alice’s machine now uses
Eve’s rogue DNS server, also at 10.0.0.66.
When Alice’s browser asks for the IP address
of google.com, the rogue DNS server tells
Alice’s machine to use Eve’s web server
instead.
When she revisits amazon.com, most of the
correct site appears since Firefox has cached
the DNS results, but as soon as Firefox does
a *new* DNS lookup, which we can force by
pressing shift-refresh, she is given the IP
addres of Eve’s rogue web server instead.
If she visits a new site like yahoo.com, then
she will also end up at the rogue site. You
can imagine many bad things Eve could do.
She could simply deny or block access to particular
web sites for Alice. Or she could copy the
look and feel of those websites Alice visits,
and masquerade as an ecommerce site, forcing
Alice to reveal her credit card or other personal
information. Or she could simply sit as a
transparent proxy watching and recording all
Alice's traffic.
When we switch off the DNS server and evil
dhcp client, Alice will eventually go back
to using the correct, local dhcp server. The
first time she revisits the same web site,
her browser (in this case, Firefox) might
have cached the bad DNS lookup and still try
and go to the evil web server. But eventually,
Alice's host will start using the correct
DNS server and her network will start working
correctly again.
The video shows just how scarily easy it is
to attack a network, if you have local access
to the network and can intercept - or beat
- DHCP lookups. If you would like, you can
reproduce this demo by downloading the script
from http://mininet.org/teaching and run it
in a Mininet instance.