Now that we've learned about CSMA/CD, I'm
going to tell you about Ethernet.
Ethernet started in the early 1970s,
originally at around, ten megabits per
second.
But it has evolved a long way since then.
In this first place, CSMA/CD was right at
the heart of how Ethernet worked.
And determined how many hosts would share
a single cable.
We'll see later that it became less
important as the speed went up.
The original Ethernet looked like this.
These are two pictures that were drawn by
Bob Metcalfe, one of the co-inventors of
Ethernet back in the early 70s.  He was
working at Xerox Parc at the time.
He later went on to found 3Com.
So, on the left, it's showing the original
topology that they had in mind of both
wired and wireless Ethernet.
And on the right, shows the specifics of
how the first Ethernet network was built.
There was this big, thick, yellow cable,
it was always yellow, it was very, very
thick and inflexible, and snaked around in
the ceiling, or in the walls, or under the
floor.
And then, these big taps would be screwed
down into the cable to make an electrical
contact for an interface, and then, a
computer.
It became much simpler over time, ending
up with what we use today.
This is the Ethernet frame format.
This is the format of the frames that are
put onto the link.
The first bit is shown on the left-hand
side and it starts with a preamble.
The preamble is a sequence of ones and
zeroes, just there to train the clock
recovery circuits to help them get
started, and to have recovered the clock
before the data actually starts to arrive.
There's a starter frame delimiter which is
a special symbol, which tells us that the
packet is just about to start.
And we then go into the destination
address, which we already know to be a
48-bit address.
This is a globally unique aadress assigned
by the manufacturer of the interface.
One bit tells us whether it's unicast or
multicast.
And one bit can be used, in fact, to make
it a locally defined address although
that's actually very unusual.
So, there's 46 bits that are there to
define the globally unique address.
And so there's a very, very large number
of Ethernet addresses to use.
The source address is just the address of
the local host that's sending the frame,
in the usual sense.
The type indicates what we'll
find inside the data.
For example, the Ether type 0x0800 is
telling us that there's IP inside here
which of course, a very common case.
You'll recall that there is a minimum size
for any CSMA/CD based network, a minimum
packet size, so we pad the packet if the
data is very short.
We pad it to make sure there are
sufficient number
of bytes so that we can detect collisions
reliably before we're finished sending the
packet.
So, they're padded out to a minimum of 46
data bytes, so if the amount of data is
over 46, then, of course, it won't pad it.
But otherwise, it will pad it just to make
sure there's enough.
And finally there's what's called a cyclic
redundancy check,
CRC, or the frame check sequence.
The CRC is checking the sequence using a
code like we saw in the error detection
videos that will tell us whether or
not there was an error in the bits.
For example, if the bits were corrupted on
the wire or in the end host before it
was processed.
The original ten megabits per second
Ethernet was standardized by IEEE.
And goes by the standard of IEEE 802.3.
You'll often hear Ethernet being referred
to as a dot three
network for this reason,
Just as an abbreviation of 802.3.
And this was just the standard's body name
that was used to write the spec that
defined the correct operation of Ethernet.
So, it has really two components.
It has the MAC protocol and the frame
structure that we've just seen.
And then underneath, you have
different options for the physical layer
that could be used.
There was originally what's called
the 10Base-5, which was that big, thick,
yellow cable that I described earlier.
And that went out of fashion quite a long
time ago.
Then, that was replaced by a thin coaxial
cable version that used the coaxial cable
similar to the RF cables we use for, for
TV.
But what really, really transformed
Ethernet was when it started to use this
type of cable here.
This is the RJ45 cable that we're all very
familiar with.
And that was not because of the
connector.
It was because of the type of cable that
it can use, and also the topology of the
network, and we'll see that in a moment.
But basically, it started to run over
voice grade, unshielded twisted pair that
was already present in the walls of many
buildings.
It's called category three telephone
cable, it's fairly low-grade cable that
was used for connecting telephones to the
exchange at a company.
There's also an optical fiber version
called 10Base-F. it was originally used
mostly by the military because they're
harder to tap. there were two optical
fibers and a single cable, one for
each direction.
Ethernet really took off when the 10Base-T
standard came along for running Ethernet
over twisted pair.
So, ten megabits per second was carried
over category three twisted pair telephone
wires that already existed in pretty much
every building in the world.
They were arranged in a star.
In other words, those, those twisted pair
cables would go to a wiring closet on
their way to the telephone exchange.
So,
Not only did the twisted pair cable really
help Ethernet be successful but this
topology of having an end host connected
by twisted pair into a hub.
And a hub was a repeater, it would take
every single coming in and then repeat it
over every outgoing cable except for the
one through which it entered.
So, it didn't actually understand the
packets, it would merely repeat them
electrically.
If there was a collision, then the
collision would take place anywhere within
here, it would be detected, and the hub
would make sure that the voltage levels
were sufficient to make sure that it could
be detected.
Also, this centralized management
in this hub this would be managed by the
network administrator.
And this central management, rather than
the distributed management of crawling
under the floorboards, or up in
the attic made it much, much
easier to manage Ethernet once these hubs
were placed in these central locations.
So, this led to a huge growth in Ethernet
in the mid-1980s.
Over the years, people wanted to make
Ethernet faster and faster.
So, ten mega bits per second gradually was
increased to a 100 mega bits per second
and then, gigabit per second.
And more recently, ten gigabits per
second.
So, a 1000 times faster than the original
Ethernet spec.
One problem that we have to solve when
increasing the size of Ethernet is,
if we're using CSMA/CD, then we need to
make sure that we keep this
requirement, that P over R is greater than
or equal to two L over c.
In other words, the duration of a packet,
is longer than the round-trip time so that
we can make sure that we're still
transmitting a packet when a collision is
detected.
So, when we increase
the speed of the network, when we increase
R, in order for this to be true, we either
need to make P larger to counterbalance
that increase in R, or we need to make L
smaller.
And so, this was a design choice when
Ethernet was made faster.
And the solution was to keep the
packet size the same.
Because if we made the packet size ten
times larger from 64 bytes, which was the
original, up to 640 bytes,
Then many of the packets that we'd like to
send would be smaller than that.
Things like acknowledgements and DNS
queries, things like that.
And so, it would be very inefficient.
So, the decision was to keep P the same
but to make L smaller.
So, 100 megabit per second Ethernet and
gigabit per second Ethernet, both have
this both have this requirement that L is
limited to 100 meters.
This turned out to be much easier with the
introduction of Ethernet switching, as
I'll describe in a few minutes.
So, as we made it faster and faster, the
Ethernet MAC protocol stayed the same.
That's the framing structure and the way
in which we decide when to send packets
onto the wire.
That stayed the same for a while.
And the 100 megabit per second Ethernet
was called Fast Ethernet.
It doesn't seem so fast these days.
And there were two standards for the
physical layer.
100Base-TX, which was the coding structure
used for twisted pair cable and then,
100Base-FX for optical fiber.
On the 100Base-TX, it uses category five
cable again, and the same RJ45 connector
that we've seen.
It actually started to be full duplex,
Meaning there were two pairs that were
used, rather than just one within the
cable.
One pair was used for 100 megabits per
second signaling in each direction.
Instead of using the Manchester encoding,
it started to use 4B5B encoding
which we saw as the means to introduce
transitions for clock recovery.
We saw that in the video
about clocks.
And, of course, it was limited to a
distance of a hundred meters.
Then later came along the one gigabit
Ethernet standard.
There was the 1000BASE-T and the
1000BASE-FX,
That should be 1000BASE-T.
The 1000BASE-T standard also runs over
category five cable using the RJ45
connector.  For many of the laptops and
servers that are sold today,
the Ethernet in them is one gigabit per
second or a 1000BASE-T.
It turns out it's very hard carry a one
gigabit per second signal over a category
five cable.
So, they actually use four pairs inside
the cable.
And they carry signals in both directions
at the same time over all four pairs.
So, there's no room for anything else on
this cable.
It can only be used for the gigabit
Ethernet.
It uses a very complex coding which is
beyond the level of what we are going to
be describing in this class and it uses five
level signaling.
So, instead of just using a binary on off
as was used in the original ten megabits
per second Ethernet,
It uses five different levels to try and
pack as much signal, as much information
onto the cable as it, as it can.
And as before, the distance is limited to
100 meters.
By the late 1980s, 10Base-T Ethernet was
extremely popular.
There was already work going on, on 100
megabit per second Ethernet and it was
clear that the networks would get faster
and faster.
The hubs in the repeaters in the wiring
closets meant that the network could be
really quite large and were being deployed
on a very large scale.
But it was clear also that for faster and
faster networks, each of the segments was
going to get very, very short, just down
to a 100 meters.
So, with a large number of hosts sharing a
small network the networks tended to
be overwhelmed with the number of
collisions that they would see, because
there were so many hosts all trying to
talk on the same network and so it became
natural to try and partition those
Ethernet networks to reduce the number of
collisions, what's often referred to as
reducing the collision domain.
At the same time, cost of switching
hardware was coming down.
It became easier to build ASICs, or
specialized chips for doing the, for doing
the switching.
And so, all these things together led to
partitioning networks using Ethernet
switches.
So, with a hub or a repeater, every
time a packet is sent, the whole medium of
all of these five links would become busy,
and would be used up.
So, within this circle here, the entire
capacity is, say, ten megabits per second
or 100 megabits per second depending on the rate.
So, with large networks with, say,
hundreds of end hosts all connected to a
hub or a set of hubs,
This would be very limiting in the total
overall capacity that they had to use.
What if we could allow several
communications to take place at the same
time?
So, for example, if A wants to talk to B
at the same time that C is talking to D.
Because they're talking to
different hosts, different sets of hosts,
Why don't we allow this by allowing the
communications to take place
independently?
So, instead of the hub repeating the
signal just as an electrical signal,
What if it was to actually interpret the
packets,
Send the packets only to the correct
destination, just like a router does,
But based on the Ethernet addresses rather
than the IP addresses.
So, this is what was called a switch.
Before being called Ethernet switches,
they were called bridges.
You will see, see those referred to
sometimes, but we're just going to call
them Ethernet switches.
So, the basic operation is if A is sending
to B, the packet will flow down to the
switch.
The switch will look at the Ethernet
address, to decide where to send it next.
If it has it in its table, then it will
forward it to B.
And at the same time, perhaps C is sending
a packet to D, and the same thing will be
happening over here, independently.
So, the collisions now are just held
within a single cable.
So, if there happen to be signals going in
both directions on the cable at the same
time, that might cause a collision.
Although, at the same time, there was also
introduced something called Full Duplex
Ethernet which was exploiting the fact
that communications could take place on
the cable in both directions without
colliding with each other at the same
time.
And so now, the switch could operate
without the use of CSMA/CD completely once
the switches were introduced and all of
the links were full duplex.
So,
This led to the very first Ethernet
switches being developed in the early
1990s.
And nearly all Ethernet networks
today are based on Ethernet switches.
It's very unusual to see an Ethernet hub
these days.
In fact, for one gigabit per second and
ten gigabit per second Ethernet, there is
no choice all those networks are switched.
So, the advantages are multiple concurrent
communications, full duplex links, they
can send and receive at the same time and
also there is a management benefit, that
if there are dead or faulty end hosts,
they could be isolated by the switch if
you could just switch off the link
and then isolate it from the network
completely to prevent it from harming
any other switches in the network.
So, Ethernet switches have become the
main way that Ethernet is put into
deployment today.
This is just a picture of an Ethernet switch
at Stanford.
This is the Ethernet switch over here,
with all these cables coming out going
into patch panels here that go off to
different offices in the building.
So, the way that an Ethernet switch works
is it does some very simple operations.
First is that it does forwarding
and learning, we've seen this before.
It forwards packets based on its
forwarding table, and then it learns the
contents of that forwarding table based on
addresses that it's seen.
So, when a frame arrives, first of all, it
examines the header of each arriving frame
to check for the destination
address.
If the Ethernet destination address is in
its forwarding table, it will forward the
frame to the correct outgoing port.
Or if it's multicast,
the set of ports.
If the Ethernet destination address is not
in its table, it will broadcast the frame
to all ports of the switch except the one
through which the frame arrived.
And then, entries in the table are learned
by examining the, the Ethernet source
address of arriving packets.
So, it will take the, the source address,
look it up in the table.
If it finds that it's not there, it will
populate the table with that entry that
says, "Okay if ever I see this as a
destination address, I now know how I
reach it by sending it back out of the
port that this address is connected to."
So, that way, the next time the frame
won't be broadcast, it will just be sent
on to its correct destination.
So, that is the forwarding and learning
function of an Ethernet switch.
And then, there is also the sort of
topology maintenance part.
It runs the spanning tree protocol, where
it exchanges those things called
bridge protocol data units, the BPDU's
that we saw in the spanning tree video.
And it runs the spanning tree protocol to
talk to the other switches to create a
loop free topology.
So, that allows it to decide which ports
to enable or block, to make sure that it
creates a loop free spanning tree among
all of the switches in the network.
As a consequence Ethernet switches are
very, very widely deployed.
And, here's an example of how
that might look in, say, a university
campus.
This is pretty much how our college
networks looks at Stanford.
Inside each building, so this might be a
building or one floor of the building.
This could be the third floor of my
building: the Gates building at
Stanford.
This could be the second floor, there's
another switch for that floor.
And then, they connect into the building
router.
They would often be connected in to
another router in another
building for, fault tolerance in case the,
the building router was to fail.
And this router may be running OSPF for
routing packets across our
campus.
So, these routers form the campus backbone
that spread all across our college campus.
And then they would eventually connect to
a BGP router, that connects to the public
internet.
So, this is speaking the BGP protocol to
the outside world to exchange prefixes for
paths to the outside world.
So, Ethernet switches can connect many,
many hosts, sometimes hundreds of hosts
together.
There are switches available with hundreds
of ports.
They then connect perhaps all the end hosts in
the building, or in the floor of a
building.
So, in summary,
Medium access control protocols come in
two main flavors:
random access and deterministic.
Random access protocols proved very
popular, because they're nice and simple,
they give transmitting hosts a nice,
quick, low delay access to the network
when it's being lightly used.
And over the years, CSMA/CD became the
most popular.
It's a simple access protocol that was
used in the first ten megabit per second
version of Ethernet.
Over the years, the Ethernet standards
emerged for 100 megabits per second
Ethernet, that's called "fast Ethernet."
And then, gigabit per second Ethernet and
more recently ten gigabits per second.
Limits on the link size and the need for
more capacity meant that CSMA/CD was
gradually replaced by Ethernet switching
in which end-hosts typically connect over
a full duplex link.
And so, can both send and receive at the
same time.
And Ethernet switches do pretty much full
routing, like a router does, but
on the Ethernet addresses.
They learn the Ethernet addresses to
populate their tables by learning the
source address of packets that go by.
And that way, they build up a nice, simple
forwarding table.
And then they use the spanning tree
protocol to build a loop free topology
connecting all the switches within the
network.
So, as a consequence, Ethernet switches
are ubiquitous today and used in pretty
much every organization that has a wired
network.