In the next few videos we're going to be
looking at congestion control.
Congestion control is a really important
topic, for networking because whenever we
have a network, particularly a packet
switched network like the internet, it
will always encounter congestion.
Either for short periods or long periods.
Controlling that congestion to stop the
network from collapsing is really, really
important and so we're going to be
learning about what congestion is and how
to control it.
Basic, basic approaches to congestion
control.
And then we're going to look specifically
at what happens in the Internet, and
congestion control happens inside the TCP
protocol.
And TCP has explicit support for
congestion control, and we're going to be
looking at how it does that, and how
that's evolved over time, and then what
some of the consequences are of those
decisions.
Let's start by thinking about what
congestion is.
Congestion can take place at multiple time
scales.
I'm going to offer you three examples
here.
And the first one is at a very short time
scale, when packets are colliding at a
router.
So for example, imagine that we've got two
packets.
The first one arriving here, in red, and
the second one arriving shortly
afterwards.
Both destined to the same output and
because they've both arrived at the same
time, one of them will get to leave.
The other one will be queued and there
will be a temporary build up of queue in
the router.
A second form of congestion at a slightly
longer time scale is at the flow level
operating at the time scale of round trip
times or multiple round trip times.
If you think of a flow as a communication
like a TCP flow, where the communication
is taking place over a fairly long period.
Over multiple round trip times, for
example downloading a web page, or sending
an e-email then the rate of the flow might
change.
And I've shown one here in red and one
here in green.
And these made both be passing through the
buffer of a router trying to get to the
same outgoing link.
If their combined rates exceed
the outgoing link rate,
as seems to be the case here.
Then the buffer will build up, and
eventually it will overflow.
And so we'll need to do something to
prevent those flows from continuing to
overwhelm that link.
Otherwise, we're just going to drop a
whole lot of packets, and have a collapse
in the, in the performance of the network.
The third type is at a much longer time
scale.
Which is at a very human time scale.
When there are just simply too many users
using a link at a peak hour. This might be
a link connecting to a very busy web
server like cnn.com or google.com and in
the morning people might come in and all
want to access the same link while they're
reading their coffee and it might
overwhelm it.
And so this would be at a longer time
scale.
The one that we're going to be most
interested in, when we're talking about
congestion control is this one in the
middle.
We're going to look at how congestion can
be controlled for TCP flows in particular
that are lasting multiple round trip
times, where we have the
opportunity to communicate
to the sender or send information back to
the sender, or for the sender simply to
learn that it should, should change the
amount of data that it puts into the
network, so as to prevent sustained
congestion from happening at the routers.
Let's take this a little bit further and
think about what congestion is by way of
an example.
So we look at the example here where
sources A and B are trying to send to the
same destination X. And the flows are,
they're both wanting to send at twelve
megabits per second at a sustained rate.
But the link from the router to x is only
capable of sending at twelve megabits per
second.
By the way, there's nothing magical about
the numbers twelve here, other than it's
going to make the math a little bit
easier.
So, A has a, consented a sustained rate of
twelve.
B consented a sustained rate of twelve.
And this link here, which is the, the
departure rate from the router buffer.
And the, just before the outgoing link, is
only able to send at rate twelve.
So if we look at one of our deterministic
queue models, and just assume that this is at
a sustained rate.
So, this will be T and this will be the
cumulative, the cumulative data sent.
So we'll just think of this as the
cumulative bits sent on a link.
We will have A1(t).
It will accumulate at twelve megabits per
second.
So the gradient of this will be twelve
megabits per second.
And so will A2 of T.
I'm not going to try and draw that,
superimpose that.
But so will d(t). So if we look at the
sum of A1 + A2.
So this would be A1 + A2.
And of course this here, let me draw this
in a different color.
This would be d(t).
Then we can see that there will be a queue
that we'll build up.
Q(t), and Q(t) is just going to grow
and grow and grow, just going to keep
growing as, because the arrival rate is
exceeding the departure rate, so hence
eventually packets will be dropped and
retransmitted.
Notice that the,
The transmissions are going to add to the
traffic in the network because there's
going to be more traffic sent down here
because of these re-transmissions.
And it's going to make it even more
congested.
So congestion can actually have a feedback
effective of making things worse by
causing even more traffic to be sent in,
in to the network.
Also it means that the, the that the
arrival rate here, although it will be a
sustained arrival rate into the queue, it
must at some, in some sense be truncated,
because the departure rate obviously can't
exceed twelve megabits per second.
Now, let's assume for a moment that the,
that, that the buffers are infinite and
think about what the, what we would
actually like to have happen here.
Let's say that instead of A1(t), this is
rate R1.
That the first that A would like to send
in it.
And we'll call this one R2.
And we'll say that the rate here is R
because then of course these could be any
values in, in practice.
It's reasonable to expect that if R1 and
R2 are both larger than R over two, then
we would give each one of them, we would
actually assign to each one of them, the
rate R over two, Right? So, if they're
both want more than half of that outgoing
link, then it would seem to make sense
that they would both get R2, R over two.
So this example is very simple.
In general congestion can happen at any
point in the network, with one flow, two
flows or any number of flows.
Some of the flows might have that
bottleneck at this particular congested
router.
Others might not.
They might have flows that are, that they
might be congested at a different router,
somewhere else in the network.
So let's look at a slightly more
complicated example.
Let's first look at what's going on.
We've got our sources A and B again
wanting to send at twelve megabits per
second.
And we've got a third source now wanting
to send at twelve megabits per second.
And we've got a second router.
And all the links both of the links here
are twelve megabits per second again.
First, notice that there are definitely
going to be packets dropped if the flow is
from A B and C run at the sustained twelve
megabits per second.
Clearly there's congestion in the network
and they all going to contribute to that
congestion.
Second, notice that any packets from A and
B that make it through the first router
and then dropped at the second router.
So if they are then dropped because of the
congestion at the second link are going to
be a waste of network traffic.
In other words, they've used this precious
congested resource here.
If they're then dropped here then there
was no, not really any point in sending
them.
So, it's worth while thinking about how we
get the information back to the source so
that it isn't going to send unnecessary
traffic through the network only to be
dropped at a downstream router.
Third, notice that it's not obvious what
the split of the last link should be.
If the routers simply split the usage at
each bottleneck, in other words we split
it 50-50, then at this point here, over
this link here, we would see six megabits
from A and six megabits from, per second
from B.
And then if we were to split here 50-50,
then we could see six mega bits per second
from c.
And we would see half of whatever came in
through the second router, so we would see
three from a and three from b summing to
twelve.
It's not clear that that's what we want.
It might be that we actually want each of
them to get four.
That might be a more reasonable thing so
that they each get equal access of that
last router.
So, it's going to be important to think
about how we divide up the capacity that's
available.
Now let's make it slightly more
complicated.
Imagine that we've got an extra sender, D
that wants to send just at one megabits
per second.
So D wants to send a less than at, at a
rate which is less than the others.
So what rate should it be allowed to send
out?
We might say that everyone should send at,
at less than their requested rate because
the link is congested.
In other words because the, the link over
here is going to be congested because
there's twelve, 24, 36, 37 megabytes per
second that wants to flow over it.
Everyone should run slower as a
consequence.
On the other hand, we might say that
because D is asking for less than its fair
share of the link.
So there's one link here and four of them.
Because it's asking for less than three
megabits per second, maybe we should give
it its full one.
So we are going to see some more examples
of this in a definition of fairness in a
little while.
Something else to note is congestion is
unavoidable in a packet switch network.
I mean arguably it's actually a good
thing.
We use packet switching because it makes
efficient use of the links because of
statistical multiplexing.
Therefore the buffers and the routers are
frequently occupied and quite likely to,
to overflow.
In fact if the buffers were always empty,
then the links would be, quiet much of the
time.
So delay would be low, but our usage of
the network would be low.
And so therefore, we'd be using the
network quite inefficiently.
If buffers are always occupied while the
delay is high, we'd be seeing the network
used very efficiently, 'cause it would be
busy all of the time.
So we're going to see congestion is, is a
really inevitable property of the network.
And having a little bit of congestion is a
good thing because it keeps the usage of
the network high.
We just need to be able to control it to
stop us, making the delay so high, the
drop so high, that the network becomes
unusable.
So.
Some observations of what we've seen so
far.
Congestion is inevitable, and arguably
desirable.
Congestion happens at different
timescales, from packets colliding, to
some flows sending too quickly, to flash
crow, crowds appearing in the network.
If packets are dropped, then tran,
retransmissions can make congestion even
worse.
When packets are dropped, they waste
resources upstream, before they were
dropped, so that's a bad thing.
And we're going to need a definition of
fairness to decide how we want flows to
share a bottleneck link.
Next we're going to explore the kind of
fairness that we would like in the network
because this is going to help us think
about how to design a congesting control
mechanism.
So let's consider an example of when I
have three routers in a network.
Here are the three routers, connected by
links and the first link I'm going to
assume is of rate two, the second one of
rate one.
And then I'm going to have three sources
A, B and C.
All connected and they're going to be
sending flows like this through the
network.
First one goes, the, B goes through the
second router and then stops.
C comes in at the second router, and then
goes out through the third.
So the question is, what would be a fair
allocation of rates if they all want to
send at maximum, maximum rate through the
network?
Let's think about the rates that we're
going to assign to each of these, each of
these flows.
The first allocation is one in which I'm
going to give, A.
A flow of .25, B a flow, a, a rate of 1.75,
and C a rate of .75.
See I've not exceeded the rate on any one
of them.
There's a total of one here and a total of
two here.
And the total throughput here is.
1.75 plus .75 is 2.5 (and plus .25) is 2.75.
Now let me consider a different rate
allocation and I'll call that one two, and
in this rate allocation I give A,
.5. I give C, .5.
And I'm going to give B 1.5.
This has a total of 1.5 plus .5.
Is two, (plus .5) is 2.5.
So essentially lower overall throughput,
but if you look at this link here, which
kind of the bottleneck link of the
network.
I've given the same to C as I have to A.
And so we might say that this one is more
fair.
So there's a trade off here between
fairness, one in which we're giving equal
usage of the bottleneck links versus the
throughput.
Where we're trying to maximize the overall
And, essentially, we can see here that A
is being penalized in the second, in, in
the first one, where it the first
allocation where it only has a rate of .25.
Because it's going through multiple links
in the, in the network.
We can therefore see the fairness in
throughput can be at odds with each other.
So, before you start designing or
comparing ways to control congestion, we
could, we could do with a definition of
the kind of fairness that we would like to
achieve.
So the definition that we are going to use
is, is called max-min fairness or
maximizing the minimum.
And it's a widely used definition of
fairness.
Well it's not the only definition we could
use.
It makes sense cause it tries to maximize
the rates of the little flows while making
sure that every flow that would like it
would get a share of it's bottleneck
link.
So the formal definition is shown here
allocation is max-min fair if you cannot
increase the rate of one flow.
Without decreasing the rate of another
flow with a lower rate.
Let's look at what that would mean in my
example before.
Here is the second allocation that I showed
you was in facts max-min fair.
Because, if we increase the rate of B, so
if we are trying to increase this one here
beyond 1.5, we would have to decrease R of
A, the rate of A.
And so this is a, we can only increase
whenever we increase one, we will decrease
one that's lower. And therefore this is the
max-min fair allocation.
What it essentially means is that links
that share a bottleneck, say for example
here will have an equal share.
If they want to use all of that link or
more, more than their fair share, they
will be curtailed to their fair share.
So they're each getting half of that.
Let me show you an example on a single
link, which will be easier to understand.
So in a very simple and intuitive
definition on a, on a single link.
So, if we have a router.
Let me draw a router here.
And I have A and B that want to connect to
that router at .5 megabits per second.
I'll just say .5.
And one.
And then it has a link of rate one coming
out of it.
And then, let's consider that there's a
third one, C, that wants to connect to it
at point two.
So the combined rate that we would like to
send through here from A, B, and C is 1.7,
but we've only got a rate of one.
So what would be the fair share?
Well, C is the minimum.
So we're going to start by allocating the
minimum.
And C wants less than its fair share.
In other words the fair share would be a
third each.
It wants .2.
Which is less than a third.
So we're going to allocate to it .2.
That's going to leave .8.
On this link.
And the fair share of the other two would
now be .4, half of .8.
Each.
A wants more than that so it's going to be
curtailed to .4. And B, also wants more,
then, then the .4, so its going to
get .4 as well.
So the total is going to sum to one.
If we increase the rate of any of them,
then it would be at the expense of a
slower flow.
And so this is the max-min fair
allocation.
Now that you understand what congestion
is, in the next few videos I am going to look at
different ways to design congestion control
algorithms.
So, we are going to stop from, start
looking at different techniques and end up
with how TCP works, look at that in some
detail and then look at some of the
consequences of those designs.
So, worthwhile having some goals, so that
can we bear them in mind when we designing
the algorithms and when we are comparing
one against another.
So, we've got a list here, some of which
we have seen and some of which will be new
but pretty obvious in why we are, why we
are considering the, The first one is, we
want high through put. We want to keep
lengths busy.
Because we want to make efficient use of
the network and we want flows to be fast
and to complete quickly.
Second one is that we would like it to be
fair.
And we're going to, we're going to
typically use our max-min fairness goal.
Because it gives a nice balance between
pretty good throughput through the
network.
But also making sure that all the flows
that are contending for a bottleneck link
get treated fairly.
And the little ones get a, a good access
to that link.
We would like the congestion control
mechanism to respond quickly to changing
network conditions.
If other flows arrive, and the congestion
increases, we need to be able to back off
a little bit, so that we don't cause too
much congestion in the network.
And if other flows go away and finish and
more capacity becomes available, we'd like
to be able to use that, use that quickly,
so that we can make efficient usage of the
network.
And finally, we want the control to be
distributed.
We can't rely on there being some central
arbiter that is going to decide the rates
for the entire network.
We need this to operate in a distributed
fashion in order for it to be scalable.
And these are the sorts if things we're
going to consider over the next few
videos.