Public key cryptography is a critical part
of many secure systems today. It’s different
than symmetric cryptography in that there’s
what’s called a “public” key, a key
that doesn’t have to be secret. You can
distribute this public key freely and still
communicate securely.
So how does that work? Like symmetric cryptography,
public key ciphers have three algorithms,
one to generate keys, one to encrypt, and
one to decrypt. But they differ it two major
ways. First, the generate algorithm generates
*two* keys, a public key K and a private key
K- inverse. To encrypt, you pass the public
key and a plaintext to obtain a ciphertext.
To decrypt, you pass the private key and the
ciphertext to obtain the plaintext. Therefore,
if you generate the keys, you can give out
the public key freely, hence its name, and
know that only someone with the private key
and decrypt something sent with the public
key.
Because the public key is reused many times,
this means the encryption process has to include
randomization. Otherwise, two parties that
send the same message will produce the same
ciphertext. If you’re dealing with small
messages, and adversary could just exhaustively
try all of the messages. So, for example,
you can prepend some random data to the plaintext
to generate the ciphertext.
So this is kind of magic: you can generate
two keys, one public, one private. People
with the public key can then send data only
someone with the private key can decrypt.
If each side had the other’s public key,
we wouldn’t need symmetric cryptography
at all! It turns out that’s not the case,
as I’ll explain in a little bit. Public
key cryptography is much, much computationally
expensive than symmetric cryptography. So
we can’t just use it all the time.
You can use public key cryptography for integrity
as well, using something called a signature.
Again, we have three functions: generate,
which generates a pair of keys, sign, which
takes the private key, and verify, which takes
the public key. A signature provides integrity
like a MAC. You can’t produce a valid signature
for a message m without the private key, but
anyone can verify it with the public key.
Furthermore, you can’t derive the public
key from the private one.
There are a lot of public key algorithms out
there. For encryption, we have RSA, Rabin,
and ElGamal. For signatures, we have RSA,
Rabin, ElGamal, and DSA.
But public key algorithms work differently
than symmetric ones. The basic idea behind
RSA, for example, is really simple: modular
exponentiation of large integers. However,
simple transformations of a message to a number
is not secure. So you have to be careful in
how you use them. I gave one example of that
earlier, how you have to add randomness. So,
generally speaking, it’s good to use existing,
tested implementations of these algorithms
rather than try to re-implement them yourself.
Or you can re-implement them, but then don’t
use your implementation in a secure system.
For many of these algorithms, you can use
the same key for encryption and signing. While
they use the same key, though, they use different
algorithms. You can’t, for example, sign
a document by “encrypting” it with the
private key.
I’m not going to go into all of the details,
but I want to give you a sense of how one
very famous of these algorithms, RSA, works.
RSA is named for its co-creators, Rivest,
Shamir, and Adleman. They won a Turing award,
the highest award in computing, for it. I’m
presenting RSA because conceptually it’s
very simple.
To generate RSA keys, you choose to distinct,
very large, prime numbers p and q. From p
and q you compute their product, n. You then
use p and q to derive K and K-inverse.
You advertise n and K as the public key. To
encrypt a message, you consider the message
M as a large number and raise it to the K
power, then take it modulo n. You send that
ciphertext number.
To decrypt, you consider the ciphertext message
M as a large number and raise it to the K-inverse
power, then take it modulo n. It turns out
that if you do this, you will recover the
original plaintext message.
So you derive K and K-inverse from p and q.
If an adversary learns p and q, then they
can generate the private key and break the
system. You can’t derive p and q from K.
It turns out you also can’t derive p and
q from n. N is the product of two primes.
Factoring n into p and q turns out to be computationally
hard. If someone figured out how to do it
quickly, all of RSA crashes down. As you can
imagine, a lot of people have put a huge amount
of effort into understanding how hard it is
to factor a product of two prime numbers.
For those of you who know a bit about computational
complexity, we know that the problem is in
the computational class NP, it’s suspected
to be outside the class P, but it’s suspected
to not be NP- complete. So that means our
best guess is that you can’t do it in polynomial
time, but it’s not as hard as the hardest
problems in NP, like traveling salesman.
So public key cryptography seems pretty amazing.
You can generate two keys, distribute one
publicly, and then have confidentiality, integrity,
and authenticity. Why do we use symmetric
cryptography at all?
There is, of course, a catch. Public key cryptography
is much, much slower than symmetric ciphers.
We can do symmetric crypto at line rate. Public
key systems, though, have execution times
in milliseconds. For example, if you run RSA
with a 2048-bit key,it takes nearly 6 milliseconds
to decrypt a message. And remember, the party
who has the private key does the decrypting.
So if you distribute your public key widely
so lots of other parties can communicate with
you, you’re the bottleneck on how many messages
can be handled.
So this is why hybrid schemes are very popular
today. The idea is that you start with public
key cryptography, and use it to encrypt a
symmetric key. Or you use it to exchange some
information, a secret session key, that you
use to generate symmetric keys. You bootstrap
the secure session with public key cryptography
to exchange a secret, then use that secret
for much more efficient symmetric cryptography.
If you want to see a detailed example of this,
I’ll cover one in the TLS video.
Now, one big pitfall people often run into
with public key cryptography is signing an
underspecified message. For example, if I
sign a message, I should specify whom the
message is for. And give it a lifetime. Otherwise,
someone can simply replay the message. Since
my public key doesn’t change very often,
a signed message is valid as long as people
are using my public key. By valid, I mean
it will properly pass the verify function.
So you want to limit its use at the application
level. Otherwise a signed message saying “You
can access this file” could be taken by
an adversary and used. Instead, you should
say “Nick can access this file until noon
on Halloween.”