This video I'm going to talk about a slightly
advanced flow control algorithm called
sliding window used in most high
performance protocols today.
So recall, a simple flow control algorithm
called stop and wait has at most one
packet in flight at any time.
So this is the basic simple protocol you
might, say, an algorithm might try to
implement the first time you're doing
reliable communication.
So sender sends a packet or chunk of data,
Receiver sends an acknowledgement, and
sender,
If it doesn't receive the acknowledgement,
times out, tries resending.
If it gets the acknowledgement it sends
more data.
And there's some issues with duplicates.
You can maintain a counter, a one bit
counter, to figure out if there's a
duplicate ack or an ack to duplicate new
data.
As long as thing aren't duplicated for
more than a round trip time, stop and wait
works.
It's great.
It's simple.
So while stop and wait works correctly it
has one major problem.
Let's hear it try to communicate between
Boston and San Francisco, and the
bottleneck is say 10Mb/s, so
if there is a 10Mb/s link here.
Or let's say the Boston node can receive
at 10Mb/s.
Basically that's the rate it can process
data.
Your round trip time is 50 milliseconds.
And let's just say for simplicity sake,
we're sending Ethernet frames.
So that's the, size of the data so what
your, basically 1.5 kilobytes, or twelve
kilobits.
Now our round trip time's 50 milliseconds.
That means that San Francisco can send one
packet, 50, and if that packet's received
successfully, 50 milliseconds later we'll
get an acknowledgement.
So we have 1,000 milliseconds per second
divided by 50 milliseconds, this means
that we can send at most twenty packets
per second on this on this path.
Now twenty packets per second times twelve
kilobits.
Kilobits per packet is equal to 240
kilobits, kilobits per second.
So this path, which is San Francisco and
Boston using a stop and wait protocol, can
send at most 240 kilobits per second
assuming no packets are lost, just a
constant RTT 50 milliseconds.
But the bottle neck is 10Mb/s,
so this means that this stop and
wait protocol is using two percent of the
capacity of what the communication could
be.
So stop and wait while it works, can be
astoundingly inefficient.
San Francisco could be sending data much
faster than what's stop and wait allows.
So the basic solution that most protocols
use today for this problem is something
called a sliding window.
And sliding windows are a generalization
of stop and waits.
Where a stop and wait allows one packet in
flight at any point in time, a sliding
window protocol allows up to N packets in
flight.
So, when n is equal to one, a sliding
window protocol acts like a stop and wait.
And so, let's say we have a sliding window
protocol with an N equal to let's say five
packets.
This means that San Francisco can have
five packets, In flight and simultaneously
their can be five acknowledgements, there
can be five acknowledgements coming back
from Boston.
And the idea here is that if you adapt, if
you set N to be the correct value, then
you can keep the pipe full.
That is San Francisco could send data to
Boston at ten megabits per second.
So let's say that's Boston's rate and so
Boston can, by configuring the sliding
window size, can have San Francisco send
data at a rate equal to ten megabits per
second.
And so in this particular case, alright,
if we have an RTT of 50 milliseconds and a
bottleneck of ten megabits per second,
let's say that we're sending ethernet
frames at ten kilobits per packet.
And we have twenty round trip times, that
essentially means that the sliding window
is gonna be ten megabits per second,
divided by twenty round trip times, which
basically, which is equal to 500 kilobits
per round trip time.
So we're looking at a sliding window of
around 49, sorry, around 41 packets.
40 is 480 kilobits per round trip time so
41 would be 492, and so if we had a
sliding window of 40 packets, then we'd
actually be able to sustain a ten megabit
connection from San Francisco to Boston
with a round trip time of 50 milliseconds.
So just to draw a picture, kinda show what
this looks like, so here is the original,
here's the stop and wait.
We have this one big counter, a data zero,
ack zero, data one, ack one, data zero,
ack zero, so the sliding window.
Let's say we have a sliding window of size
three.
Well the sender will send three packets.
Let's call them D0, D1, D2, and the
receiver can then acknowledge them.
Ack zero, ack one, ack two.
Well as soon as acknowledgement zero
arrives the sender can send data three.
As soon as acknowledgement one arrives,
the sender can send data four.
As soon as acknowledgement two arrives,
the sender can send data five.
This is the basic idea, rather than having
this one packet you could have many
packets.
So in the case of having a sending window
of size 40, you can imagine there are tons
and tons and tons of packets in flight.
So, let's look at more concretely what
this algorithm looks like for both the
sender and the receiver just as we did for
stop and wait.
So a sliding window sender, first in the
sliding window protocol, every segment has
a sequence number.
So in protocols like TCP this is usually
done in terms of bytes because they can be
a variable size, for simplicity sake we'll
just do it in terms of packet numbers.
So there's a sequence number for every
segment.
So, the sender maintains three variables,
the size of its sending window, the last
acknowledgement it received from the
receiver, and the last segment it sent.
And the sender's job is to maintain this
invariant, that the last segment sent
minus the last acknowledgement received
has to be less than or equal to the send
window size.
So this means that if it has received
packet N, a packet with a sequence number
of n, the sender cannot send packet past n
+ SWS.
So lets say we were sending window is
equal to five and the last acknowledgement
that's been received is equal to eleven.
Then this means that the sender cannot
send a packet past twelve, thirteen,
fourteen, fifteen, sixteen.
Its not allowed to send seventeen until it
gets acknowledgement for twelve.
When you get a new acknowledgement you
advance LAR, as necessary, and you buffer
up to sending window size segments, in
case suddenly you get an acknowledgment,
and then you want to send a whole bunch of
new data.
Let's pretend for a second, we have a
sending window size equal to three, and so
here's packets at zero, 1,2,3.
Say zero had been sent and acknowledged.
So our sending window size is three.
The last acknowledgement for the receiver
is zero, so LAR is equal to zero, SWS is
equal to three.
This just means that the last segment sent
is equal to three.
So, now when an acknowledgment arrives,
say, for one, then the sending window can
advance.
And so now the protocol can send four.
And let's say an acknowledgment for four
arrives.
Then the window can advance, and you can
send five, six and seven.
Now one thing that's important here is
that let's say we have a send window which
includes five, six and seven.
And five is lost, but six and seven arrive
at the receiver and are acknowledged.
The center cannot advance the window past
five.
Until five is acknowledged.
And so the window is what's called
stalling.
The window can stall.
Where although most of the data in the
window's been delivered, it can't move
past the first unacknowledged piece of
data.
So it can't advance the, the window past
that.
The receiver also maintains three
variables.
It has a receive window size, the last
acceptable segments.
This is the last segment that it will
receive and won't drop on the floor.
If it receives a segment past this value,
it'll assume something's wrong or it's not
gonna buffer, you know, it'll just discard
it.
Then there's the last segment that's
actually received.
And so, the sender, the receivers then
maintain this invariant, that the last
acceptable segment minus the last thing
that we received must be less than or
equal to the receive window size.
So, if you have a receive window size
equal to five and a last segment received
equal to three then it's not going to
accept anything past four, five, six,
seven, eight, right.
So if it receives suddenly segment ten, it
won't accept it and it'll drop it.
Now if the receive packet is less than
this acceptable segment, then it'll send
an acknowledgement.
And so if it receives any of these packets
it will send an acknowledgement.
Now, in a basic case, the way most sliding
window protocols work, these
acknowledgments are what are called
cumulative acknowledgments.
Such that you send an acknowledgment for,
not the data you received, but rather what
is the end of the contiguous data you
received, that is cumulative?
If I acknowledge three, that means that I
have received three in everything before
it, not just three.
And so it represents a cumulative state of
reception across the entire communication.
So in this example, if a receiver's
received one, two, three, and five and
then suddenly receives five, it doesn't
acknowledge five.
It acknowledges three.
Now there are some protocols that can do
things like actually selective
acknowledgements, but, the basic case is,
that use cumulative acknowledgements,
which is cumulatively, what is the
continuous chunk of data that you've
received.
So one little detail here.
TCP doesn't acknowledge the data it's
received but rather N plus one.
So TCP acknowledgements are in terms of
bytes, and so if TCP has received up to
byte N, its acknowledgement packets will
say N plus one.
So it's the first byte of data that's
expected.
So if you're ever looking at a TCP trace
or trying to see how the TCP protocol
works, just keep this in mind.
The acknowledgement value in a TCP header
isn't the last byte received, the
cumulative acknowledgement, rather the
next byte, the first missing byte.
So one of the things we talked about in
stop-and-wait protocol, in the stop and wait
protocol is that a counter of [inaudible],
a one bit counter was sufficient.
Assuming the packets weren't delayed more
than a round-trip time.
So what about sliding window protocol?
Suddenly we have a receive window, we have
a send window.
How big a sequence numbered space do we
need?
So the receive window is always greater
than one, the send window is always
greater than one, greater than or equal to
one.
And the receive window is greater than, is
less than or equal to the send window.
This is because if the receiver window is
ever greater then send window it's a
waste.
The send window, the sender would never have
those packets in flight.
And so there's this extra buffer space,
which will never be used.
However there are cases where the receive
window can be smaller than the send window
and the protocol still works.
So here's one interesting basic case of
that called Go-Back-N.
Well let's say if a receive window of size
one, and a sending window that's larger
than, larger than one.
Well in this case we're gonna need sending
window size plus one sequence numbers.
So what does this protocol look like?
Well the sender say, say is send window
size is equal to three.
So the sender sends zero, one, and two,
and let's say those are all acknowledged,
and so the receiver acknowledges a zero,
and acknowledges one, and acknowledges
two.
Well when it acknowledges zero, the
sender's gonna send three, slide the
window forward, when it acknowledges one
it's gonna send four, and when it
acknowledges two it's gonna send five.
So let's say that three is dropped.
Now the sender, the receiver - it's going
to still receive four and five and so it
can ack two, it's going to send ack two,
ack two.
The sender's going to time-out and re-send
three.
This is called Go-Back-N protocol.
Because, the receive window was size one,
the receiver can not buffer four or five.
You see when a single packet is lost in
the case three, the sender has to go back
and has to retransmit the entire send
window worth of packets.
It has to retransmit three, it'll have to
retransmit four, and it'll have to
retransmit five.
In contrast, if the receive window size
have been three then the receiver could've
buffered four and five.
The center would only have had to
re-transmit three, then you get in act
five, and it could go on and send six,
seven and eight.
And so here in the case of a Go-Back-N
protocol you need to send window size plus
one sequence numbers.
Cause you imagine if you have only the set
window size, there's zero, one, two.
And then remember what happened in stop
and wait, when there's a packet delay, or
hey, let's say that the ack for zero is
delayed, there's a time out, you
retransmit zero.
Now you can't distinguish whether or not
the delayed acknowledgement was for the
retransmission or for the old data.
Generally speaking if the two windows are
the same size you need twice basically
their sum, and that's the generalization
that you need RWS plus SWS sequence
number.
You need sequenced number spaces at least
as big as the sum of the window sizes.
So that's the basic sliding window
algorithm and the algorithm that the
sender and receiver use and how the sender
manages the window.
What does this look like in TCP?
So, TCP is a sliding window protocol and
uses that for flow control.
And so here's the TCP header.
And so the way TCP works is the set, the
receiver, specifies the flow control
window using the window field, this in
terms of bytes.
So it basically says, this is the buffer
size that I have on the receiver and so
the set of packets that I will accept.
And the basic rule is that here the data
sequence number and the acknowledgment
sequence number.
And so a TCP receiver will only handle
data equal to the acknowledged sequence
number plus the window.
So the sender isn't allowed to send data
past ack plus window.
That's to make sure it doesn't send data
which the receiver is not going to buffer.
And so this is a way for the receiver to
essentially set what the send window size
is.
So let's walk through an example.
So here, again I'm going to talk in terms
of packets rather than bytes like in TCP.
And here's the sequence number space for
the packets from you know, zero up to 29.
So let's say that we have a, a receive
window size equal to two and a send window
size equal to three.
So, communication begins, and the sender
is going to send zero, one, and two.
Let's say all three of those packets
arrive.
And so the receiver, receives zero, it's
gonna acknowledge zero.
It's then going to receive one,
acknowledge one, receive two, and
acknowledge two.
When the sender, here's ack zero, it will
advance the window, the send window, and
it'll send three.
When it hears the acknowledgement for one,
it will advance the window and send four.
When it hears the acknowledgment for two,
it will advance the window and send five.
Now let's say that packet three arrived
successfully and is acknowledged, but
packet four is lost in the network.
So now we have this case where ack three
has been sent, packet four is lost, then
packet five arrives at the receiver.
Now the receiver is going to send another
acknowledgement three, again because of
cumulative acknowledgements, and it's now
the sender heard ack three and then
another ack three, waits, time's out, and
re-sends four.
So it'll resend four.
And let's say four arrives.
Now, this receiver can acknowledge four so
it can ack four, but because its receive
window was a size two, it actually had
five buffered, and so it can also
acknowledge five.
And so it'll send back five.
So, a sliding window flow control
algorithm allows an unacknowledged, a
whole window of unacknowledged packets to
be in flight.
And so this allows, is if you can set that
window size appropriately, it allows a
sender to be able to actually fully
utilize the capacity that the receiver
has.
Unlike a stop and wait protocol where you
can have at most one packet in flight.
When acknowledgements arrive for new data,
the center advances the window.
Generally sliding window protocols use
cumulative acknowledgements.
And the exact sequence number space you
use depends on the window sizes.
So it turns out TCP uses a large sequence
number space just for ease of use and to
really be robust against heavily delayed
packets.
But if you're implementing your own
protocol you may be able to get away with
something a little bit smaller.