By now you know how to calculate the end
to end delay of a packet across a network,
and you know that the queuing delay makes
the end to end delay variable.
Most of the applications that we use don't
particularly care about this variability
in end to end delay, for example when
we're downloading a webpage or sending a
email we want it to complete quickly but
we don't particularly mind if individual
packets take ten or twelve milliseconds to
reach the other end.
But there are some applications that
really do care.
They have to care about the queuing delay,
particularly what we call real time
applications like streaming video and
voice.  So let's take a look at an example.
Over the next few minutes, I'm gonna
explain why queuing delay makes life hard
for these applications.
It serves as a good illustration of
queuing delay and, and how we might
mitigate the problem in practice.
Basically, because the applications don't
know precisely when the packets are gonna
show up, they can't be sure they will have
a voice or video sample in time to deliver
it to the user.
And so they build up a reserve of packets
in something called the playback buffer.
So we're gonna take a look at playback
buffers.
You've actually all seen a playback buffer
before.
This is a little screenshot from the
bottom of a YouTube client.
And, the red line on the left over here,
This shows the video that we've already
watched.
This here is the point of playback.
This dot shows where we've got to.
And this area over here is, this grey
line, shows the video that has been
buffered.
All the packets that have been buffered,
that have not yet been played back to the
user.
And this is the part that we're going to
be interested in.
This right here is the play back buffer.
So the client deliberately tries to build
up that playback buffer to try and get
ahead, in case some of the packets are
delayed, or they don't arrive in time, and
in case there is some kind of temporary
outage.
So when designing the playback buffer, we
have to think about how far ahead we want
the buffer to get.
So, if we were to build up the buffer all
the way over to here, and build up more
packets, then we've absorbed more data and
we can write out more variability in the
queuing delay.
If we make it very short down here if
there's a big change or big change in the
queing delay or sudden increase in queing
delay we may have run out of packets,
because they may not show up in time.
So designing this playback buffer is
pretty key to make this application work.
So how much we wanna accumulate in the
buffer when we start playing the back,
back the video to the user is key.
So let's take a closer look at this.
This is the point that we're playing.
This is the amount that we've buffered.
This is the contents in the pipeline
buffer.
We look down and do a little bit more
detail.
So we are going to take this as an example
this set up here.
So imagine we are watching the you tube
video on the laptop on the right so over
here and it's streaming the video from the
server, the you tube server over here.
So, we are going to assume that the video
is being streamed at one megabit per
second.
Now this is just a made up number.
There's all sorts of rate that could be
streamed out, this is just gonna make,
make it easy for us to think about.
And it's gonna pass through several
routers along the path, one two and three
in the figure here.
But it could be many more than that.
Be very common for our packets to go
through ten or fifteen routers on the path
from You Tube to our client.
And the thing that we're gonna be
concerned mostly about is the queuing
delay here.
So there's three places where we can
experience queuing delay.
And that variable queuing delay, is going
to mean that our packets show up at
slightly unpredictable times.
So let's look at a graph of what this
might look like.
This graph shows the cumulative number of
bytes sent by the server over time, as a
function of time.
Because it's sending at a fixed rate of
one megabit per second.
It means that the line is straight.
The cumulative number of bits or bytes
that it sent as a function of time is a
straight line.
And so after one second it will have sent
a megabit, a million bits, and after ten
seconds it will have sent ten million
bits.
Because of the variable queuing delay in
the network, the cumulative arrivals at
the laptop look a little bit different.
They might look like this.
So you see this wiggly line that I got
here.
What does this mean?
It means if we take the first byte here,
because they're arriving in first come first
sever order.
We can just draw horizontally across here
and see when a particular byte arrived.
So this one arrived here after that delay.
So the x axis is going to tell you how
long that particular that, that particular
byte took to get there.
Notice I'm saying bits and bytes it,
doesn't matter what our units are here.
So if we were to take any point here,
let's say this particular byte and we draw
horizontally, I'm not really good at
drawing straight lines, but that's
supposed to be horizontal.
And right here is the time at which that
particular byte arrived at a laptop.
So you can see that the delay is measured
by the horizontal distance.
Right.
The horizontal distance here.
And you can see that it's a variable
number, depending on the cuing delay
encountered by each of the individual,
packets.
We can also see foray at a given time.
By the given time, how big is the buffer,
the amount of buffering along the path?
Basically, how may bytes are in the path
from the server to the client?
And that would be showing by the vertical
distance here.
Because, it says that at a particular
time, this is the number that have been
sent, and this is the number that have
been received.
So, you can take quite a lot of
information from this graph.
We are going to be seeing some more
examples of this type of graph later.
Horizontal axis is the delayed, vertical
axis tells us how many bytes are buffered
right now in the network.
Okay.
So let's get back to our example.
So the biggest component in the delay is
the propagation and packetization delay.
That's the fixed component.
So we actually know quite a bit about the
shape of this of this lane, to the actual
shape could look very different.
I just made up this shape, however we do
know a couple of things.
First, the overall end to end delay can't
be less than the packetization and
propagation delay.
There are a lower bound.
So this has a lower bound in the
horizontal distance between the two here.
What it also has an upper bound.
So the buffers in the routers, the packet
buffers here, they're of finite size.
So there's a maximum delay that any packet
can experience going through one of those
buffers.
So if we add up the maximum of each of
these.
Add it to the packatization delay and the
propagation delay, it's going to represent
an upper bound.
So we have a lower bound and an upper
bound.
But the upper bound is not very useful
cause it can be very, very large.
In practice these routers may have half a
second of buffering.
So if we're going through many hops, it
would mean a ridiculous difference between
the lower bound and the upper bound.
So that's of not much use to us.
We also know that the cumulative arrivals
on the right-hand side are non-decreasing.
In other words, its value is always
increasing, cuz it's the cumulative number
of bytes and obviously we can't have a
negative number of bytes show up.
Finally, one more thing that we know is
because we know how fast, or there is an
upper bound on the rate of that of that
last link.
It could be a 100 megabit per second link
or gigabit per second link.
It tells us that the instantaneous arrival
rate here, the gradient of this line here,
can't exceed the speed, the data rate of
that link.
Okay so with all of those caveats.
Let's look at what the client actually
needs to do to make all of this work.
So this red line here shows the playback
rate of the video to the user.
So this what this tells us is that at this
time here it's playing back the first byte
that was sent by the server.
Which is, of course, the first byte
received by the receiver.
So if at any point we take a horizontal
line across here it will tell us the time
that a particular byte was sent, received,
and then played back.
What that means is that the horizontal
distance here tells us so in for example,
in the horizontal distance here tells us
how long a particular byte has been
buffered.
So at any one time, we can tell how long
it sat in the playback buffer before it
was played back to the receiver.
We also know how many bytes there are in
the playback buffer.
It's the vertical distance here.
At any one time it tells us what the
occupancy of the playback buffer is.
So you can see that the playback buffer
was very small to start with.
It accumulates to a very large value here.
Then it gets smaller as we fall behind, as
we fall behind, almost goes empty here,
we're very lucky that there must have been
some bytes that showed up late.
We just avoided underrunning the buffer.
And then at some time, we built up a
little bit more as we go up here.
Okay.
So, playing back at a constant one
megabits per second.
That's what's being played back to the
user.
So this is a good example.
We picked the right value, we waited long
enough, we built up enough buffer,
everything worked out fine in the end.
So, if we take a look inside the client,
it looks roughly like this.
So the playback buffer, is a buffer held
in the memory of the client.
The client is picking the playback point,
that's this here.
This is the point at which it has reached,
and that's that dot that we see on the
YouTube client.
After the bytes have been taken out of the
playback buffer, they're put into a video
decoder to turn them back into, to video
and then played out on the screen.
Okay, let us look at an example of when
things don't quite work out fine.
So the same example again, byte sent by
the server on the left, received by the
laptop on the right, but in this
particular case, we didn't wait long
enough before playing out the first byte.
You can see that here.
We have waited a very less time from when
the first pipe was received until we play
out that first byte.
Because once we stop playing out the bites
we committed, we got to play them one
megabits per second, otherwise we can't
keep putting the video on the screen.
So on this particular case here everything
looks fine to start with.
The buffer has a nice occupancy, nice
occupancy, nice occupancy.
It gets smaller and smaller and smaller
until eventually at this point here we
have a problem.
The buffer goes empty, which means we've
got no bytes to decode and put on the
screen.
So all of this area here is a time in
which we're in deficit.
This is not good.
What does the client do?
Well we've all seen this before.
It has to make the buffer bigger and it
does this by re-buffering.
By freezing the screen, waiting for some
bytes to accumulate, and so that it can
continue.
'Kay, so if you've been watching the video
over this particular video right now over
a slow link or if you're a long way away
and you have, you're packets are going
through many routers, you might experience
a re-buffering event watching this video.
You can fix the problem by streaming at a
slower rate or just simply by downloading
the video ahead of time.
So in summary, with a play back buffer,
when we have packet switching, end to end
delay is variable.
We use a playback buffer to absorb the
variation.
We could just make the playback buffer
very big, but then the video would be
delayed at the start.
That was the time that we were waiting
from the first byte to arrive until we
play it down on the screen.
We could make the buffer bigger but if we
would have make that buffer bigger, then
we would have to delay the up at the
starting point of the video which would be
kind of annoying, when we're watching our
videos.
So therefore, applications try to estimate
the delay, they try to estimate the delay
from the server to the laptop, set the
play back valley and then resize the
buffer, if the delay changes.
Okay, so now let's go back to our original
expression for the antwin delay.
So now we see that it has these three
components to it.
Packetization delay, propagation delay,
and then the variable queuing delay.
And the queuing adds variable and
unpredictable delay to the path, and to
the packets from end to end.
Okay so in summary, end to end delay
consists of three components, the first
two are fixed, propagation delay, which is
the time that it takes for a bit to
propagate over a link, the packetization
delay, which is the time that it takes to
put a packet onto a link, and then the
queuing delay, which is variable which is
dictated by the time that a packet spends
in the buffers in the routers along the
path.
Some applications as we saw, use playback
buffers, to absorb this variable queuing
delay.
To help the applications, stream the video
back to us, at a fixed rate.
So this is the end if packet switching
two.
I will see you again in packet switching
three.
Where I'm gonna tell you about a simple
deterministic model that helps us
understand this variable queuing delay.