>> Phil: Here I have Dan Boneh, who some of
you I hope know, fellow faculty, in fact senior
to me in the department, who researches cryptography
and security. So Dan, how did you get into
crytopgraphy and security of computer systems.
What's your background? >> Dan: Thanks Phil.
First of all it is a pleasure to do this.
I am happy to help the class. Let's see. I
fell in love with crypto at a very very young
age. I think it's one of those things for
god knows why but my Dad taught me the RSA
algorithm when I was 9 years old and I was
completely fascinated by this. These big numbers,
and all of these suddens there are these codes.
Then I went and encrypted a message to my
friend with RSA, and he thought I was completley
nuts. But it stuck with me. Then when I got
to college and I learned about crypto I just
realized that its such a fantastic field.
It's an area where you get to use really deep
math, literally 20th century math, as advanced
as mathematics that's used in computer science
gets, and at the same time you get to use
it for real world applications, so people
really care about the results. In fact, when
you communicate with Google these days, the
key exchange that you're doing is using what's
called elliptic curve Diffie-Hellman, that
is using extremely advanced Mathematics, as
I've said, 20th century Mathematics, and it's
amazing. People use it all day long, every
day, without even realizing that they are
doing it. So for me it is a lot of fun to
work in an area that involves both deep math,
and yet has real world applications. I should
say more broadly, there are two parts to my
work: I work on cryptography as one half,
and I also do a lot of work on computer security
more broadly. Cryptography is just a small
part of computer security. The problem of
security software is much much larger than
just cryptography. I should tell you that
computer security in general is also a fantastic
fantastic area to work in. As a career path,
it's a terrific career path.
>> Phil: There's tremendous job security in
security.
>> Dan: Yeah. You know if I go to sleep now
and you wake me up in a hundred years, the
first thing I'll ask is: "Is computer security
still a problem?", and I guarantee you compuer
security will only be worse than it is today
because we will be depending on computers
and networks so much more than we do today.
>> Phil: Students in the class have covered
actually Network Address Translators a bit,
or NATs, on wireless routers. You've done
some work on the security of these wireless
NAT's today and some of the issues. Do you
want to say a little bit about some of the
crazy holes that you've found?
>> Dan: Sure. We've done a lot of work on
security, for example, of embedded devices.
When you build an embedded device these days
- So what is an embedded device? I'm talking
about things like security cameras, photo
frames - these are frames that you put on
grandma's desk and you can upload pictures
to it so that she can see grand kids. Photo
frames, printers, routers, all of these embedded
devices that need to be configured somehow.
These days they are configured through a web
interface. When companies do this, they have
to build a small web application that sits
in the embedded device. Well traditionally
when you build a web application you would
use Rails or Django, or a lamp stack in general.
But a LAMP stack doesn't fit on a tiny little
security camera. There's no SQL server running
there. So what they end up doing is they end
up building their own web application and
their own infrascture basically for making
configuration possible. And as you, well hopefully
you will take one of our security classes,
which I'll plot in just a minute,
>> Phil: Yeah You teach 155.
>> Dan: I'll plot those in just a minute.
You'll learn from those that building a secure
web application is non-trivial. It actually
takes quite an effort to secure web applications
even from basic attacks. Things like cross-site
scripting, things like request forgeries,
and so on. We bought like 20 of these embedded
devices and we started looking one by one
at the different web applications embedded
in these devices, and it turns out that they
basically all have various sorts of vulnerabilities.
All. Again it's bascially a hardware company...
>> Phil: So somebody hacked my picture frame.
Why should I care?
>> Dan: Ah. Ok. So you should really care
about that. Because, if you're an enterprise
and one of your employees put a picture frame
on their desk in their office, that picture
frame is going to be connected to your corporate
network.
>> Phil: So I'm glad I'm not an enterprise.
>> Dan: There you go.
>> Phil: I don't care.
>> Dan: You can pretty much guess the rest.
>> Phil: Stanford's computer systems were
hacked all the time back then so I'm not concerend
about network vlunerabilities. I'm not the
kind of person you care to.
>> Dan: I see. Ok. Well anyhow, bascially
these devices are used as stepping stones
to larger attacks. If you have a security
camera at home, that security camera... or
even think of the Nest, like a thermostat
that is controlled remotely.Those devices,
if they're not properly secured - the Nest
we haven't looked at so I don't know what
the security status of that is - but those
devices can be used as stepping stones to
a larger attack on your home network, on your
corporate network.
>> Phil: chink in the armor.
>> Dan: Exactly. And by the way all the attacks,
they way all the attacks work today, is basically
using stepping stones. They break into one
machine. From that machine they start to do
a lateral traversal to try and find other
machines that can be broken into. From that
other machine that they've now taken control
they try to get into administrator accounts.
And so on and so on. They move slowly from
one machine to another until they get the
crown jewels, like the database or the active
directory, and then they just dump all the
data from there and, you know, away they go.
>> Phil: So, this past weekend there was the
CS faculty retreat and you gave a talk about
some of the revelations from the Snowden's
leaks, etc. And one of the things you talked
about is how there might be some suggestions
that certain crytpo systems might be weaker
than we thought. So without going into details,
going forward, given what we've learn from
snowden, if I want to design a secure system
then what... are there some extra steps I
should take, are there some things which we
thought might be ok but aren't now and when
I'm going forward do something slightly differently?
>> Dan: Yeah. Bascially there are two advice
to keep in mind. Well first, there is a zeroth
advice bit which you will learn - will be
drilled into you - once you take the crypto
class, 255, which is you never design your
own crypto. And not only should you not design
your own crypto, you should not even implement
your own crypto, because I guarantee you if
you implement your own crypto its going to
be vulnerable to timing attacks, its probably
going to have bad randomness and its going
to be vulnerable to other side channel attacks
and so on. So you should use existing...
>> Phil: Don't innovate.
>> Dan: I wouldn't quite say it that way.
I would say use existing standards and existing
open source well vetted implementations. So
that's the zeroth rule. The first rule that
I would say that is the result of the revelations
from the summer is make sure that whatever
you build is crypto agile in the sense that
if we discover at some point that there is
a vulnerability in a particular algorithm
its not going to take you six months to then
and under fire go ahead and build a new crypto
algorithm into your system, QA test it, and
then deploy it. That's a long process which
when you do under fire is a bad idea from
a security point of view. The idea is to make
your system crypto agile to begin with so
that the system will support multiple algorithms
at deployment time and if one algorithm turns
out to be insecure then all you have to do
is just flip a configuration switch and your
system moves to the other algorithm and everything
works fine. Now in the client/server model
that is actually more difficult because you
have to change both the clients and the servers,
but you have to start somewhere. For example,
if you build a web server, make sure that
the web server can support multiple algorithms.
The algorithm being used is not baked in,
somehow hardwired into the web server. When
you build, a very common example is a software
upgrade mechanism. So when you ship software
upgrades to your clients, those software updates
need to be signed, so that not anyone can
ship updates on your behalf. You cannot imagine
how many companies, when they build software
upgrade mechanisms they just hardwire RSA
as a signature mechanism. My point is, try
to make it so that even a software update
mechanism, something that is benign as that,
actually is agile in the sense that there
is an easy way to update the algorithm on
the fly so that just matter of simple configuration
and you move to signatures using a different
algorithm. So that's the first piece of advice.
Be agile. The second piece of advice, in particular
when you build an SSL based server. Today
many websites use what's called the RSA mechanism,
which is the browser chooses a premaster secret,
encrypts the premaster secret using its server
public RSA key, and sends the result over
to the server. The server decrypts and recovers
the premaster secret.
>> Phil: That's what I taught when we covered
how TLS works and its basic exchange.
>> Dan: Fantastic. So this is what I would
call the basic RSA key exchange. The problem
with that mechanism is that it doesn't provide
what's called forward secrecy. What do I mean
by that? Imagine that today someone recorded
the interaction between you and the webserver.
So they recorded the RSA encryption of the
premaster secret. Now a year from now somehow
they were able to break into the webserver
and recover the RSA secret key. What that
key would allow them to do then is go back
to what they recorded a year before, decrypt
the encrypted premaster secret, and now they
can recover the entire session.
>> Phil: Game over.
>> Dan: Exactly. The basic RSA mechanism doesn't
have what's called forward secrecy. There
is another key exchange mechanism in SSL.
It's a mechanism that supports forward secrecy,
and it's a mechanism that's based on Diffie-Hellman.
There are multiple names for it. It's called
ephemral Diffie-Hellman, in open SSL it's
called DHE, or ECDHE, we'll get to the difference
between those in a second. The idea there
is that the key exchange actually uses the
Diffie-Hellman protocol instead using RSA.
So what happens is each side: the browser
says to the server its part of the Diffie-Hellman
exchange, the server says to the browser its
part of the Diffie-Hellman exchange, and the
server's RSA key - it's only purpose is just
to authenticate the server's Diffie-Hellman
message.
>> Phil: It's just for signing.
>> Dan: Yeah exactly. The server's RSA key
is used for signing, not for encryption. So
even if the server's RSA key is stolen a year
from now, it doesn't matter.
>> Phil: So forward secrecy means that even
if somebody in the future cracks something
that I'm still secure going forward in time.
>> Dan: If the session was secure today, it
will be secure a year from now even if you
lose your secret key. Forward secrecty is
a pretty important concept. It's a good thing
to do. Especially it protects you from keys
being stolen and such. It also limits the
amount of time in which a particular key is
used because your session really now depends
only on that particular Diffie-Hellman exchange.
>> Phil: Unlike with the RSA key, where the
server has to get a new certificate, etc.
>> Dan: It's a long process. It takes a whole
year. The point is if someone breaks your
RSA key somehow not by stealing the private
key, but by a brute force attack, if they
break your RSA key they would recover all
session. With Diffie-Hellman they would have
to break every single individual Diffie-Hellman
exchange to recover the session which is a
lot more work.
>> Phil: So its clear going forward that network
applications, the internet, are increasingly
more and more applications are on the internet,
interconnected and correspondigly security
is increasingly important. So in terms of
the classes going forward, what are the classes
that students can take to learn more about
this? Because in 10 years not knowing something
about security is going to make you dead in
the water.
>> Dan: Exactly. Excellent question. The security
classes are kind of vital to undergraduate
education in computer science. We get many
complaints from industry about universities,
not us, but other universities graduating
students who know nothing about security and
as a result the code they write causes a lot
of problems down the road. The classes that
we offer are 1. CS155 - I would argue that
needs to be a required class - the point of
CS155 is A. to teach you a lot of defensive
programming, but more importantly is to get
you into the security mindset. The way we
do that is we teach you a lot of attacks.
The only way to learn how to defend against
attacks is to know how to do the attacks yourself.
So we teach you how to break things, but more
importantly we then draw lessons and then
teach you how to defend against those attacks,
and get into the security mindset. Whenever
you write code, think about how that code
can be exploited, and what can go wrong if
the code is exploited. The security mindset,
general principles for writing secure code,
things like defense in depth, least privilege,
and so on. These are things that we just go
on and on and give many many examples of those
issues in CS155. So that's offered in the
spring. It's co-taught by myself and John
Mitchel. Another class that's worth taking
is the crypto class. If you're more interested
in learning how cryptography works, and I
can tell you the interesting thing is that
there are many companies that actually use
crypto but they have very little crypto expertise.
By taking that class you'll know what needs
to be known about crypto in order to use it
properly, and whatever job you go to you would
actually become the goto person in that company
to deal with any crypto-like issues. So its
a valuable knowledge to have.
>> Phil: You're convicing me I should go back
to school. I haven't taken 155.
>> Dan: Please do! It's a fun class.
>> Phil: Awesome. Any other last comments
you think, or thoughts about what's going
on in security today, or computer systems?
Dan: We can be talking about this for hours.
Phil: Of course, it's Dan Boneh.
Dan: How long do you want to make this?
Phil: Why don't we be nice to these students
and make them in fact find out in 155 or 255?
Thanks a lot Dan.
Dan: See you in future courses.