The answer to the second question is CLOSED.
We start in
the closed state. Then the user program calls
connect and
we transition to the SYN SENT state. While
in the SYN SENT
state the user program calls close. There's
an edge from
SYN SENT on the close event, back to the CLOSED
state.
So now our sockets are in the ESTABLISHED
state. They’re exchanging data. The six
states in blue boxes are how TCP “tears
down” a connection, or how it closes it.
It’s sometimes useful to talk
about “tearing down” a connection because
the word “close” means something in terms
of system calls. A connection exists after
one side “closes” it, as we’ll see.
There’s symmetry between how TCP sets up
a connection and how it tears it down. Where
connection establishment uses synchronization
or SYN packets, connection teardown uses finish,
or FIN
packets. If one of the sides of the connection
calls close, it traverses along the right
edge on the left to the FIN WAIT 1 state.
This causes it to send a FIN packet to the
other side of the connection.
This is called the “active closer” because
it starts the operation. The other side receives
the FIN and takes the blue edge on the right
to the CLOSE WAIT state. It remains in this
state until the
program on its side calls close, at which
point it sends a FIN.
Here’s where it gets a little complicated.
A TCP connection is bidirectional. The active
closer has closed its direction of the connection,
so it can’t write any more data. But it
could be the passive
closer has more data to send. So it can continue
to send data, which the active closer receives
and acknowledges. Or it could close its side
of the connection to. Or it could even have
decided to
close the connection at the same time, such
that we have two FIN packets crossing each
other in the network.
From the FIN WAIT 1 state, where the active
closer is, there are three possible outcomes.
First, the passive closer might acknowledge
the FIN but not send a FIN. In this case,
the passive closer is in
the CLOSE WAIT state and can continue to send
data. This is the lowermost edge, where the
active closer enters the FIN WAIT 2 state.
Second, the passive closer might close its
side too,
acknowledging the FIN and send a FIN of its
own. This is the middle edge, to the TIME_WAIT
state. Finally, it could be that both sides
actively closed at almost the same time, and
sent FINs to each
other. In this case, both are in the FIN WAIT
1 state. Each one will see a FIN from the
other side that doesn’t ACK its own FIN.
In this case we transition to the CLOSING
state, and when our FIN is
acknowledged we transition to the TIME_WAIT
state, just as with the middle edge.
TCP transitions from FIN WAIT 2 to TIME WAIT
when we receive a FIN from the other side.
It then stays in TIME WAIT for a period of
time, until it can safely transition to close.
The final blue edge, from LAST ACK to CLOSED,
occurs when the passive closer’s FIN is
acknowledged.
On one hand, that’s a lot of detail. There
are 12 states,
covering lots of cases. But you can see how
this FSM takes
what was previously a few colloquial descriptions
and gives
them detail and precision. Trying to implement
a properly
interoperating TCP based on those descriptions
would be
hard. This diagram precisely specifies how
TCP behaves and
so is tremendously useful.