So in this video, we talk about wireless
networking, and why wireless systems turn
out in practice to be really different from
wired ones.
One of the big challenges you see today on
the Internet is, we all want to connect
wirelessly, yet there have been a lot of
assumptions made historically that
networks should behave like wired ones.
And actually reaching that to wireless is
often difficult, which is why we see poor
performance, say, on your laptop using
WiFi.
So in this video I'm going to talk really
about why is wireless different?
What are these properties that make it so
challenging and so difficult?
And why does it sometimes seem to be
flaky?
So in the context of this video, I'm going
to focus on access point networks, and by
that I mean.
Wireless networks, where, say you have your
laptop,
with some WiFi card,
and it connects to
some access point,
which then has a wired connection to the
internet .
And this access point is serving
- and it's often multiple devices,
like, here's your phone.
This is different than say a mobile phone
network or, you know, a 3G or 4G, which
are managed very differently.
Much more tightly controlled.
All kinds of different issues emerge in
those systems.
Here we're just going to focus on open,
open standards, access point networks, you
know, things which you just plug in at
home, connect to your wire connection to
bridge to the broader Internet.
So the first thing to realize about
wireless is that, unlike in a wired
network where the medium, the wire, is
completely under your control -
there's nobody fighting you for the
capacity of that wire.
It's for you and you alone.
In the wireless environment you're using
space, right you're using the
electromagnetic spectrum around you which
everyone else might be wanting to use as
well.
It's not a controlled medium.
It's a shared medium.
And so in practice what this means is that
it is very tightly regulated.
So this is a map of how, just in the
United States, radio spectrum is allocated.
So radio spectrum - here's kind of the big
picture of RF.
Or not of RF but of electromagnetic
spectrums down from very low frequency
stuff all the way up to cosmic rays.
That's this big thing down at the bottom.
So this is something you can get from the
US Department of Commerce, this is a free
government document.
And so generally, data communication is
occurring in this region down here,
different kinds of communication.
Either data communication, voice
communication, etc.
Up above, what's in this picture here,
this yellow region, is infrared, and then
here's visible light here.
So,
here's visible light, here's ultra-violet,
x-rays, gamma rays, et cetera.
But RF is down here.
So below visible light.
Lower frequencies.
And here's what the spectrum looks like.
And so you can see there's a huge chunk of
spectrum where it's going all the way from
three kilohertz.
So when you have 3000 waves per second, up
to 300 gigahertz up or 300 billion
waves per second.
So, if given that RF or that
electromagnetic wave moves at one foot per
nano second,
at 3 kilohertz you're looking at waves
that are on the order of 300,000
- sorry - yeah,
300,000 feet long.
Whereas down to the 300 gigahertz range.
You're looking at waves that are 1/300th
of a foot long.
So a huge, huge range of frequencies for
all kinds of things, you know?
There's TV, there's radio, there's data
communication.
There are maritime systems, there are
military systems.
There are satellites, etc.
But when we talk about access point
networks.
And modern data communication systems,
we're talking about these three, these
four narrow chunks.
So, these green ones are telephony.
So it's down to 800, 900 megahertz range.
700 this is the 1.9.
Telephony and WiMax and that stuff is
starting to move up but basically 3G
standards are down here.
And these two blocks, see these two red
blocks, this is Wifi.
And so when you think about all of the
data communication that we use today,
phones and laptops, it's all squished into
these two - these four tiny little slices.
Now the really important thing to realize
about wireless is that [laugh] as you can
imagine, wireless transmission, it's not a
wire.
The wireless medium is not a wire.
And what this means is that, unlike
something propagated on a wire, where
there's some attenuation or there's some
resistance in the copper, a wireless signal
is radiating over space.
Like, in the simplest, if you have a
perfect omnidirectional antenna, it's
radiating in a, it's getting sort of in a
sphere, out.
And what this means is that the signal
strength degrades with distance at R^2 or
faster, right?
A signal when you are twice as far away
from a transmitter,
the signal is at least attenuated by 75%.
It's at a quarter of the strength.
Just because - think of the surface of a
sphere.
And so what this means is that, unlike in
a wired system, where we can know, oh, the
cable, as long as it's good and it's no
longer than 100 meters, we're going to
have a strong signal strength.
In wireless systems, you often have a very
weak signal strength.
In fact, people are going to try and get
all the way to the edge, because they want
to be sitting out, you know, on the lawn,
using their wi-fi access point.
Furthermore, unlike a wire, where it's
tightly controlled, there's nobody doing
stuff.
Wireless is out in the world around you.
So, it can be that somebody steps between
you and your access point.
Now, suddenly, all these wireless signals
have to go through that person.
If there is a big bag of water,
the wireless is going to become much, much
weaker.
And so the signal strength is going to
change significantly over time.
As people open doors, people move around,
as you move around, as the humidity
changes.
Furthermore, there, everyone else is using
the medium as well.
There's lots of interference.
It's not like you have this wire to
yourself.
Instead, you know, the person next door
might be using their wireless network,
which is on the same frequency.
So let's look at the first of these signal strengths.
So.
The problem here is that there are
obstructions in the real world.
And they can move around.
And they weaken the signal.
If you stand behind a metal plate, your
wireless signal will be much weaker than
if you stood in front of it.
Furthermore, wireless signals reflect.
And so it can be that I'm standing, you
know, in some hallway here with my laptop.
And there's an access point here,
And it might be that the signal I get is
some weird reflection off of different
media,
off of different walls.
And the trick here is that, in practice,
this means that,
for example, here, I'm getting this
reflection.
But I'm also getting a direct signal, say,
through these walls.
It's that, unlike in a wire, in a wireless
environment, you can have something called
multipath.
That, you're getting the signal, but
you're getting multiple copies of it
across different paths or different
delays.
Think of it like echoes in a canyon.
Where there's the direct sound you hear.
But then all of these echoes are taking different
paths, reflecting off the walls of a
canyon.
There's no perfectly uniform antenna.
So if you move a little to the left, it
could be that, that antenna's no good and
that's actually much weaker where you are,
so suddenly the signal goes down and you
lose connection.
Furthermore, all these things are
continuously changing.
You can imagine, you move a little bit and
suddenly there the multipath changes, the
reflections change.
You can imagine I move a little bit, the
antenna's a little different, it's
oriented differently.
And so things are dynamically changing the
environment around you.
It's not controlled.
It could be somebody closes their office
door and suddenly your wireless signal
goes out.
Just to give you a sense of what this
looks like - so this is some data collected
by a student of mine who's now faculty at
Ohio State - Columb.
And what it is showing you is signal
strength over time, down here in the bottom,
what is called the received signal
strength indicator - signal strength.
And then at the top, the observed packet
reception ratios.
This is for an 802.15.4 link that is measured.
And so the transmitter is stationary,
the receiver is stationary,
And for every packet received, it
logged what was the received signal
strength and then he was observing what
percentage of packets were received over
time.
This red line shows the long-term average
of this communication.
So actually pretty good.
Around 93%.
But what we can see is that, over the space of
just a couple of seconds.
The signal strength is pretty solid up at
84 dBm, that's the units,
you know, it drops down a little bit.
Things get a little worse,
It drops down.
And then, suddenly it drops.
And it just drops by around 6, or
around 8 DBM, or around 8 DB.
So around a factor of ten or so, or
five, five to ten.
And then, what happens is that, that is
below the signal strength at which this
device can receive packets.
So the packet reception ratio drops to 0%.
- for a short period, then it comes up and
starts receiving packets again.
And so it's just over the space of here of
ten seconds or so.
We see that your link is going from your
99% down to 85%, back up to 90%,
down to 0% to 70%.
You see these significant changes over
time.
And so somehow your network,
- think about TCP, think about all those
retransmission schemes - has to deal with this kind
of behavior.
So here I'm going to show you, in fact, a
real-time video of a network we had to
plug here at Stanford called SWAN,
the Stanford Wireless Access Network.
It's an 802.11b/g test bed, so Wifi.
And it's around 25 nodes or so.
And essentially, what I'm going to show you is
what this network will collect over 2.5
seconds.
So this is with a time step of 25 milliseconds, there is 100 time steps, and each
of these nodes - Gates is the computer science
department, Packard is the EE-department, there
is this street in between, Serra Mall.
And I'm going to show you what this
network looked like over a time.
So for each node, there are lines between
nodes which show you the packet reception ratio
here of those links.
The dark line means that all the packets
are received,
And a very light line or no line, means
that no packets or very few packets are
received.
So watch what's happening with these
links.
How quickly they're changing.
This is 2.5 seconds.
And so we can see, links are coming and
going, they're changing and on the space
of 25 milliseconds or less.
Like, look at this link here at how
it's oscillating between 80% and 10%.
Back and forth.
And look at the links between the two.
So the point here is that in wireless
networks like WiFi networks, they're
highly, highly dynamic.
So in addition to position of the signal
strength changing over time, there's also
the issue of interference.
So, a lot of wireless communications today
is occurring in unlicensed
- like WiFi, it's access point networks that occur in
unlicensed bands.
Bands that don't require license from the
government.
Anyone can use this band.
And that's why they're so
popular. Because they're free.
But then lots and lots of different
technologies share the band.
So here's a map, for example, of just
what's going on in the 2.4, basically,
the 2.5
gigahertz range.
This is wifi.
Wifi's lower frequency.
So you can see, here's wifi 802.11b.
In this different ranges here, you can
see its bandwidth of 22 megahertz.
Here's channels one, six, and eleven.
But at the same frequency ranges, there's
802.15.4, Zigbee.
A low power, wireless system.
Which is using the same range of
frequencies.
Bluetooth uses the same range of
So this means that something in 802.11 can
receive interference with something
of 802.15.4, and vice versa.
These are challenges that all these
systems have to deal with, that,
they might have good signal.
They might have low noise.
But then someone's interfering with them.
And so for example, if you just look at
what wireless activity is like over time.
This is this nice graph which Omprakash Gnawali,
who is now professor at
University of Houston, generated.
This is taken at his data is from USC,
which is where he used to be a PhD student.
And you can see, look at all these WiFi
activity.
So here's time in seconds, from 0 to
2 minutes, in different WiFi channels, 1 to 11.
You can see that the channels 1 and
11 are really, really busy.
They're orange, showing lots and lots of
WiFi activity.
And so the lesson to take away here is
that wireless networks are becoming
increasingly important.
We'd much rather just connect the
Internet wirelessly rather than plug a wire
into our laptop.
But generally they don't work as well.
They're less reliable,
they're more flaky and this is because of
the fact that they're in this shared medium
that is uncontrolled.
Lots of different devices are
using it,
the environment is changing around them,
and there's lots of interference.
And so.
In practice what this means is that to try
to get wireless to be, you know, good
enough, as to be usable,
due to these different properties and different
behaviors, wireless actually ends up using
very different algorithms and protocols.
So wireless link layers look different
than wired link layers.
Wireless media access control systems look
different than wired ones.
So this next series of videos is going to
go into some of those differences and
explain how wireless today works.