So why does this matter? If two computers
are going to communicate, they need to agree
on whether they represent numbers using big
endian or little endian formats. This is complicated
by the fact that different processors use
different endianness. For example, x86 processors
from Intel and AMD are little endian: the
least significant byte comes first. ARM processors,
in contrast, such as those in the iPhone,
are big endian, where the most significant
byte comes first.
We don’t want two computers to care or know
whether the other side is big endian or little
endian. So protocol specification bodies typically
pick one and stick with it. For the Internet,
this means big endian. All protocols that
are Internet specifications use a big endian
format.
Here’s an example snippet of C code that
will tell you whether your computer is big
endian or little endian. It takes a 16-bite
value and casts a pointer to it that lets
the code look at the bytes individually. If
the byte at index 0 is 0x40, the most significant
byte comes first and it’s big endian. If
the byte at index 1 is 0x40, then it’s little
endian. If it’s neither, well, something
weird is going on.
But wait -- this creates a complication. You
need a packet to be in a big endian format,
but what if your processor is little endian?
Let’s say, for example, that you want to
set the port number of a TCP segment to be
80, the HTTP port. A simple way to do this
might be to create a C struct that has a field
port at the right offset. But if you use a
value 80 to compare with the port field, it
will be stored little endian, with 0x50 as
the first byte. Big endian needs 0x50 stored
in the second byte. So although the port field
in the segment is 80, this test will fail.
To make this easier, C networking libraries
provide utility functions that convert between
host order and network order. The function
htons() for example, takes a host short, 16-bit,
value as a parameter and returns a value in
network order. There’s also functions for
converting a network short to a host short,
and functions for longs, 32 bit values. So
the right way to test whether the packet port
is 80 is to read the port field of the packet
structure and call ntohs to convert it from
network order to host order. You can then
compare it with 80 and get the correct result.
In the case of a little endian architecture,
ntohs and htons reverse the order of the two
bytes. In the case of a big endian architecture,
they just return the value unchanged.
These functions provide you the mechanisms
by which you can write networking code that’s
independent of your processor architecture.
But be careful! I can’t stress this enough.
Be careful whenever you handle network data.
If you aren’t principled and rigorous about
when you translate between host and network
order, you’ll give yourself a tremendous
headache because you’ve forgotten to convert
or have inadvertently converted twice and
suddenly your protocol is behaving wrongly
or triggering all kinds of weird bugs.
Now that we know how Internet specifications
lay out multibyte values in network order,
or big endian, we can look at how Internet
specifications describe their packet formats.
For historical reasons, Internet specifications
are written in plain ASCII text. The block
of text on the left is taken verbatim from
Request for Comments (RFC) 791, which specifies
the IP protocol, version 4, or IPv4. The top
shows the bits from 0 to 31 -- packets are
written 4 bytes wide. Since IPv4 has 5 rows
of required fields, this means that an IPv4
header is at least 20 bytes long. Nick and
I often use a simpler visual format when we
show packets, like the one on the right.
To use this as an example, the total length
field of an IPv4 packet is 2 bytes, or 16
bits long. This means an IPv4 packet can’t
be longer than 65,535 bytes. That field in
the packet is stored big endian. A packet
of length 1400 bytes is stored as 0x0578.
So the third byte of an IP packet of that
length is 0x05.
Let’s see this in wireshark. I’m just
going to start wireshark and listen for packets.
This first packet is for something called
TLS, or transport layer security. It’s what
web browsers use for secure connections (https).
TLS hides the data of the packet from us,
but we can still see its headers. Using wireshark,
we can see that a TLS payload is inside a
TCP segment to port 443, the standard TLS
port. This TCP segment is inside an IPv4 header.
Looking in detail at the IPv4 header, we can
see that the packet’s total length field
is 1230. The hexidecimal for 1230 is 0x04ce:
1024, or 0x04 times 256 plus 106, or 0xce.
At the bottom, Wireshark shows us the actual
bytes of the packet. And there it is, 04 ce,
in big endian, or network order.
You’ve seen how different processors lay
out numbers differently. But since network
protocols need to agree, protocol specifications
decide how the numbers are laid out, which
can differ from your processor. To help with
this, C networking libraries provide helper
functions that convert between host and network
order. But use them carefully! Using them
haphazardly can easily lead you to many lost
hours of debugging which could be prevented
by being careful when you start and deciding
on a principled approach to converting in
your code.