So in this video about physical and link
layers, I'm going to talk about Forward
Error Correction or FEC.
So recall that for a given signal-to-noise
ratio in modulation scheme, we can compute
what the expected bit error rate is.
Now this bit error rate, while it can
become very, very small for, say, a high,
very high signal strength, it will never
read zero.
There's always a chance that there'll be a
bit error.
So in practice what this means, is that,
because these bit errors, although
uncommon, you expect them to happen.
Directly turning your link layer bits into
bits of the physical layer is very, very
inefficient,
In that the sparsity of the modulation
need, or the speed of the symbols that you
need in order to have a very, very low bit
error rates that packet bit errors are
uncommon is really, really inefficient.
It's going to be very, very far from the
Shannon limit.
That's not a good way to build a high
throughput system So instead, what you
want to do is coding.
So coding is a way where you add a little
bit of redundancy to the data.
In this case, we're talking about the
physical error but you can do it all kinds
of situations.
So you add a little bit of redundancy to
make up for these expected uncommon bit
errors.
And in adding in this little bit of
redundancy, its cost is much, much smaller
than its benefit.
By doing this you can greatly, greatly
improve reading throughput, because by
just adding a little bit of redundancy,
all your packets get through as to, as
opposed to none of your packets get
through, and this is true in theory as
well as in practice.
So when we talk about coding, we also talk
about coding gain, which is the ratio of
bits, in this case, the link layer with
bits at the physical layer.
Coding gain is more general than that, but
within the network we're usually talking
about the physical layer and the link
layer.
So one-half code means that we turn one
link layer bit into two physical layer
bits.
So there's one redundant bit for every
bit.
Three-quarter code is we turn three link
layer bits into four bits at the physical
layer.
And this process is, is forward error
correction.
The idea is proactively add some
additional, redundant data to protect, to
protract and be able to correct potential
errors.
It's called forward error correction,
because you're doing it proactively, for
you.
You're saying, hey look, I am not going to
have any errors, but beforehand I am just
going to add a bit of redundancies so that
you can recover from them.
This is nice, because you don't need any
exchanges.
The recipient will be able to just decode
the data. It's not going to have to say,
oh there is an error, can you resend this
part.
And so it saves you the cost of those
kinds of message changes.
So, how do you do this?
Well there's all kinds of coding
algorithms out there.
There's lots of different ones,
All kinds of different trade offs.
Here's just a couple of them.
So in this video I'm going to talk about
one in particular, Reed-Solomon.
So we're going to talk about Reed-Solomon
because it turns out, compared to many of
these others, it's actually mathematically
pretty simple.
It's also tremendously commonly used.
Cds use Reed-Solomon, DVDs, DSL lines
WiMAX RAID six storage arrays,
All of these systems, all of these
communication and storage systems you'd
Reed-Solomon, use Reed-Solomon.
Furthermore, compared to some of these
other coding algorithms, Reed-Solomon is
actually pretty mathematically simple.
I'm not going to go into all of the
details.
The simple, the, the basic concept is
simple, actually designing it so that you
can implement it very fast, involves a bit
more math, which I won't go into, but the
basic concept is very simple.
The key ideal behind Read-Solomon, is that
if I have a polynomial like here,
polynomial, like here, where I have a
parabola, right, so I have some ax,
squared plus bx plus c.
Then any polynomial of degree K, or here K
equals two is uniquely determined by a k+1
points.
What that means is that I give you three x
y points.
So if three x, y points will uniquely
determine for a parabola for a, b, and c.
So, why is this useful?
So, what I can do is I have some data that
I want to, want to encode with reed
solmon.
So I take K chunks of this data.
These K chunks become coefficients of a K
minus one degree polynomial.
So for example, I take three chunks of
data, and those three chunk become A, B
and C.
These three coefficients.
Then what I do is, I compute end points
along this polynomial right where N is
greater than or equal to K minus one,
answer should be minus one, right.
So I compute these end points then that's
what I send, I send those points along the
polynomial.
Now what happens is I'm sending endpoints.
But because the original polynomial is of
degree k minus one.
Any of those K points, where K is less
than N, would allow you to uniquely and
correctly determine what these
coefficients were.
So, for example, I have K, I have a second
degree polynomial which I generated from
three chunks of data A, B, and C.
Then what I do is I compute.0, .1, .2,
say.3, .4, .5.
Point six.
An assent.
P0, P1, P2, P3, P4, P5, P6.
Now turns out, that with any of these
three points, right?
With P1, P5, and P6, or P4, P1, and P3,
you can, if you know this is a parabola, you
can determine what A, B, and C are.
So that's the basic math.
I compute points along a polynomial who's
coefficients are the original data.
And then, if I'm able to recover enough of
those points along the polynomial, I can
then reconstitute what those coefficients
were.
There are some complications to this.
Like, I, I can't just like, P2 can't be a
million, because how will I represent a
million, and it's going to take up more
space.
And there's some thing where, there are
some complications where the actual
numbers you use aren't just basic
integers, the things numbers in a, a
finite field which means, sort of
mathematical construct where it's closed
over operations.
Just essentially means, that hey, I can
represent each of these points in a finite
number of bits, it's not like, certainly a
is, a million, and then that means p6 is
something totally off the charts and I
can't represent it in a finite space.
That's one of the other complications that
I'm not going to go into.
But this is the basic idea, is that I
represent the data as coefficients of a
polynomial.
I compute points along the polynomial,
then I send those points.
And then the other side from those points
can reconstitute the coefficients.
Now, a little bit more detail in terms of
what Reed-Solomon can do for you.
So it turns out in these kinds of systems,
there are two kinds of errors we care
about and it's important to distinguish
them.
The first are erasures.
So, these are errors we know that they
occurred like that piece of data is
missing, it's an erasure.
The other is a general error.
We don't know that, where the error
occurs.
So, this is what we know when we think of
in terms of, say, bit errors, whereas,
erased values are, say, you know, oh gosh,
this disk didn't answer, oh we missed that
packet.
And so what Reed-Solomon does, is you're
taking k chunks of data you're coding it
into n chunks, where n is greater than or
equal to k, worth and is equal to k,
you're not actually doing any coding, And
what Reed-Solomon will do is you can
correct up to n minus k erasurs, right,
because remember if we code, into n chunks
if we have k points and we know those k
points are correct they're just missing
others, we can reconstitute the data.
But it can also correct up to n minus k
divided by two errors.
So, l-, let's say we have a very common
Reed-Solomon code, is 223, 255,
Which means that we take the 223 bytes of
data and turned into 255 coded bytes of
data.
Well, 255 - 223 is equal to 32, so I mean
in this particular Reed-Soloman code can
protect against 32 erasures or sixteen
errors,
Where 32 of the eight-bit code words can
be missing, so long as we got 223, we can
reconstitute the original data, that's 223
points on are 222 degree, polynomial,
Or if sixteen, of, them, are, have bit
errors in them we can still reconstitute
the original data.
So, here's that conceptually.
Let's take 223 8-bit values, so we have,
take our data.
Break it into bytes, take 223 bytes.
We're going to consider those now the
coefficients of a 222 degree polynomial p.
We then compute p of zero, p of one, p of
two, etcetera, etcetera, etcetera as 8-bit
values.
There's this, again, this idea of using a
field rather than arbitrary numbers.
There's that mathematical concept.
So we can then represent them as 8-bit
values.
We then send these 255th, 255 points along
the polynomial.
And so this is a 255-223 code.
Each of these 255 code words come from 223
data words.
32 erasures, sixteen errors.
So we send these 255 values.
And that's the basic idea, is that if I
have up to sixteen errors I can still
figure out which ones are wrong and I can
reconstitute the polynomial I can
reconstitute the, polynomial coeffecients,
or I could be missing 32 of them as long I
get 223, if I have 32 erasers I can still
reconstitute the original polynomial.
As I said before this isn't exactly
what's, done in practice of for a bunch of
reasons. these values have to be in a
conical field, it turns out that this
exact scheme is.
Actually pretty expensive to decode, you
have to consider all possible parameters
and do an interpolation.
But it's giving the basic idea. The more
modern ones are a bit a bit more complex.
But the basic idea of holds of you using
the original data as coefficients on a
polynomial, computing points along that
polynomial and then sending those points.
So here is a simple example - I take these
six bytes that say hello.
I'm breaking them up into chunks of data I
then do my Reed-Solomon coding here.
This is the basic concept, right, I'm
adding my forward error correction here, some
redundant data, then when that data
arrives, I can decode it, and get the
original data.
So, let's walk through this as a specific
example.
So in this case, let's say we're using a
7,5 code.
What this means is that each initial data
word that we're going to use is three bits
long.
That's determined by the seven, two to the
three minus one.
So, we're breaking the data up into little
chunks of three bits.
And so we're going to start with five of
these, data words, so fifteen bits, and
each fifteen bits are going to be turned
into seven code words.
So here we have the first fifteen bits the
next fifteen bits, the next fifteen bits,
so it turns out we have 48 bits here, 48
not easily divisible by fifteen, so that
45, plus three, so we'll just pad this
with zeros.
So original data is going to grow from 48
to 60 bits.
We then perform the Reed-Solomon coding to
turn these fifteen bits.
Into 21 bits, and then send these total of
84 bits along say the wire or on the
wireless.
This 84 bits transmitted, received, the
other side gets these 84 coded bits, then
runs and reads on the decoder, and from
that can regenerate the original data.
So since this is a seven, five code, that
means that we can recover from one error
or two erasures.
But note that these errors in our ratios
are for code words,
And so it's possible in fact that if we
have, let's say we have bit errors that
look like this.
Here's a bit error here's a bit error,
here are 2-bit errors.
Can ask the question, will we be able to
recover from these bit errors?
So, for this first code block, the answer
is yes, there is single bit error.
A single bit error will corrupt at most
one code word.
We can recover from one errored co-, one
code word with an error.
And so, this first block we'll be able to
successfully recover.
The same with the second code block.
We have one bit error, it means one code
will be in error, so we can recover from
that.
For the third code block, well this is a
tricky question.
So one of our code words can be in error,
and we have two bid errors.
So this now depends on where those bid
errors fall.
If, let's say here our code word's spaced
out.
Here's two, three, four, five, six, seven,
let's say they look like this.
Well, if the two bit errors are in the
same code word, they will be okay, because
we just have one error, one code word with
an error.
So in that case, we'll be alright.
However,
If the bit errors are in different code
words, then, we will not be alright.
We have two errors, we can't recover from
two errors.
So this might not seem very good, but
compared to what happens if we were not to
use any coding whatsoever, here we've been
able to protect against at least two bit
errors, and maybe even up to four.
There's one other trick than you can use.
This is very common, this for example is
done in CD.
So, one of the assumptions people, you
often have, is that errors in the physical
layer, and some of them are, are just
interspersed at random. Those are easy to
handle, what's harder are bursts of
errors.
And so the way you can make your coding
scheme more robust to bursts of errors is
through something called interleaving.
So imagine for example I have, here's my
data and there is twelve chunks of 75
code.
That means each of these chunks is in
terms of the coded data is 21 bits long,
remember from the prior showing it's seven
code words of that are three bits long
each.
And so here I have twelve code blocks from
eight to L with bits A 03, A twenty and
its L0 to L20.
So let's think about what happens when we
have a burst of errors.
So it's possible, with, let's sat a, burst
of, one error, well I know for sure I'm
going to recover from that, because that's
going to corrupt at most one code word in
one block, and I can recover from one
error.
So that would be okay, one, bit error.
I'm okay.
How'bout two bit errors?
Well again, recall, it's going to matter on
whether they fall in the same code word or
if they say fall on different code words.
In fact, its possible that they can each
fall on a burst of two errors, one falls
on a code word in one block, that block
can be recovered.
Another falls on a code word in another
block, that can be recovered, we would be
okay.
So, in this case we would be okay.
If they both fell within a single.
A code word, we'll be okay.
But, if they fell on two different code
words within the same block, then we won't
be able to recover from that.
There'll be two errors within a single
block.
In fact it turns out, if we were to look
at what's the, the longest string of bit
errors that we could possibly recover
from.
That's a good question.
So it turns out that the longest that we
can recover from is six bit errors.
And we can recover from a burst of six bit
errors if and only if, it happens to be
that three of them fall on the last code
word of one block.
And then three fall on the first code word
of the next block.
So you can imagine if we add one more,
it's going to corrupt the second code
word.
So that is possible, but unlikely.
So that's the longest possible string of
errors you could correct from using just a
basic coding.
So what we can do instead is something
called interleaving.
So rather than send our data as A through,
A0 through A20, B through BZ, B20, where
then a burst of errors is concentrated on
the block.
Instead, what we send is these bits,
interleaved.
.
For example, we send A zero, B zero, C
zero, D zero, etc., etc., etc., to L zero,
A one, B one, C one, dot, dot, dot to L
one, then at the end we are going to send
K twenty, L20.
And so now it happens that a burst of
errors at the physical layer, is spread
out across, all, of the different code
blocks.
So in this case, if we have even a string
of twelve bit errors, a string of twelve
bit errors is going to, to cause one bit
error on every single one of the code
blocks.
So it cause one bit error in a, one bit error in
b, one bit error in c, and one bit error in l.
And so in that way, it will suddenly
become more robust.
So with interleaving, by interleaving all
of these bits, we can recover up to twelve
bit errors with interleaving.
.
We're even, where we didn't have
interleaving, even 2-bit errors can cause
our system to fail, and 6-bit errors the
most we could ever do.
But if all we do is interleave these bits,
we can deterministically, knowingly,
recover a burst up to twelve bits long.
So interleaving is a very common and a
very popular technique.
So this concludes the video on coding.
If you want to read more, there's all
kinds of interesting coding algorithms out
there.
I also suggest, if you want, dig into the
math, Reed-Solomon, in terms of how it
works in practice to make efficient and
coding and decoding.