Continuing on our theme on routing, in
this video I'm going to tell you about the
link state algorithm In particular,
Dijkstra's Shortest-Path First Algorithm.
This is an example of a link-state
protocol where the routers start by
flooding to each other the all the
information about the topology of the
network: which links are there, which
links are up, which ones are down.
And then from there each router is going
to calculate its shortest path tree from
it to every other router.
Dijkstra's shortest path first algorithm
is an example of what's more generally
called a link state algorithm.
In link state algorithms the routers start
by exchanging all the links state.
In other words they're going to learn the
topology of the network by exchanging with
each other the, the state of the links
connected to each router.
So a router is going to flood to every
other router, the state of the links
connected to it.
So every router has a full topology map
and they're going to do this periodically
and whenever the link state changes so
they get quick updates.
And then specific to Dijkstra's algorithm,
we're going to run Dijkstra's algorithm.
In other words, once we've got that
typology map, each router is going to
independently run Dijkstra's shortest path
first algorithm.
If it was a different link state
algorithm, then we would run a different
algorithm, but because Dijkstra is so
widely used, that's the example I'm going
to be using here.
So, at the end of the day, each router
finds the minimum cost spanning tree to
reach every other router.
Let's work through an example, of
Dijkstra's algorithm, on this, topology
here.
So this topology has, eight routers,
connected by links, that are annotated
with the cost of using those links.
And we're going to go through the example
of finding the lowest cost, spanning tree
from R8 to every other router.
So let me just draw an example of what
that might look like.
This won't actually be the, the right one.
But, it will give us an example of how it
might, how it might look.
So it's going to start from here.
And maybe go out this way, go out this
way, go out this way, go out this way.
Maybe we're going to have this one, this
one, and this one.
So that would be a spanning tree.
It happens not to be the lowest cost
spanning tree.
But, we're going to calculate that using
Dykstra's algorithm in a moment.
So, I'm just going to draw out how this
will evolve, I'm just going to go through
the steps and then take you through more
formal way of calculating it afterwards.
So, let's start with R8, down at the
bottom right hand corner.
In the first step of Dijkstra's algorithm,
we're going to add the router that has the
lowest cost path back to R8.
And so, that's R7, because it has a path
of one back to R8.
So, I'm going to draw that on here, R7,
With a cost of one.
Next I'm going to look at the router that
will directly connect to this tree, this
little fledgling tree with the lowest cost
path back to R8.
I've got two choices, either R4, which
will connect back with a cost of two, or
R6, that will connect with a cost of two
So I'm just going to toss a coin and
randomly pick R6 It doesn't matter.
So it's going to have a cost of two.
Next I am going to add the next router
with the lowest cost path and that's going
to be R4 clearly.
And each time I've added a router, I'm not
going to consider adding it again, of
course, 'cause I've already added it into
the, this tree that is evolving in the
bottom right hand corner of the slide
here.
Next, I'm going to add the one with I've
added the ones with up to a cost of two.
So is there one with a cost of three?
No, there isn't.
Is there one with a cost of four?
Yeah, I've got two candidates here.
I've got both R3 and R5.
Both will connect.
Okay well, I'll arbitrarily add R5 first.
That has a cost of four.
Back to R8, and then I'll add R3.
Do I have one with a cost of five?
Yes I do, I've got R2, that has a cost of
five.
That adds, that's a cost of five back to
R8.
Do I have one with a cost of six?
Well, I've got two that are, have a cost
of six.
But they're already connected into the
tree at a lower cost.
So R3 and R4.
So I'm not goign to add those.
They're already on the tree.
But I've also got R1.
I can now count, add that one in at a cost
of six.
So that's one, two, three, four, five,
six.
I've now added them all, and I'm done.
Let's go through those steps, because
basically the same steps that I just went
through, adding each of those routers in
turn.
So first of all I added R6 because it has
a cost of two.
Then I added R4 because it has a cost of
two.
Then I added R5 because it has a cost of
four and then also R3 it has a cost of
four.
Then I added R2 and then finally I added
R1,
And then I'm done.
We can think of this more systematically
by following through this table.
So I want to populate this table as I go
and then I will show you what it looks
like when fully populated afterwards.
So this is just going to repeat exactly
what, the, the steps I just did.
So, I start with at step zero.
The candidate set of all those routers
that directly could connect to R8.
So my shortest path set is going to be the
set of routers that are in the shortest
path tree.
So I start with R8 in my shortest path
set, and the candidate set are those that
connect to it, directly to it, directly to
the current fledgling sub-tree.
So that's R3, R5, R6, and R7,
And I'm going to pick the one with the
lowest cost path back to R8, in this case R7.
So I'm going to add R7 in first.
So I have chosen R7 and in which case if
I've chosen R7, I'm going to add it into
my shortest path set.
So my shortest path set is going to be R8
and R7.
My candidate set of the set of routers
that directly connect to this sub tree.
So the ones that directly connect are R3
and R5, still of course because I haven't
used them yet.
R6 because I haven't used that one yet.
I've used R7.
So now R4 becomes added to the candidates
set.
And I'll pick from that set the one with
the lowest cost path back to R8.
That can either be R4 which has a cost of
two or it can be R6 and I'm just going to
arbitrarily pick R6.
So now my shortest path set is going to be
R8, I'm running out of space here but that
doesn't matter, and R6.
And my candidate set is going be R3, R5.
I've used R6 it'll have R4 in it.
Because I've added R6 well I'm adding no
more routers in now to my candidate set.
So that's going to stay at the same thing
and so on.
Eventually I will fill out the table until
the very last one that will add will be in
I would choose R1 here and so at this
point I will add one into my shortest path
set and then I'm going to be done.
Okay.
I'm going to add one router at each step.
I'm going to add the router that is the
lowest cost path and because that is its
lowest cost path we know the way we are
done with that router.
Thers's nothing else left to do.
So it's nice and simple, when we always
run the number of iterations equal to the
number of routers in the network.
So if you fill out this table  you would
find that it looks like this.
And, you can just check whether that
matches what I did earlier.
So, if you run this algorithm and, we will
give you some exercises where you run
through, and fill out tables like this.
You see, on after few times you done it
that, oh yeah, of course, it is actually
generating the full lowest cost minimum,
the lowest cost spanning tree.
So, some questions worth asking about
Dijkstra's Algorithm.
First one, how long does the algorithm
take to run?
Well, it's a nice simple answer.
By the end of the Kth iteration, we've
added K routers to the graph.
So if we have n routers to start with, it
will always terminate after exactly n
iterations.
Nice and easy.
What happens when link costs change, or
when the routers or links fail?
Nice and easy again, every time there's a
change in the link state, in other words,
every time a link goes up or down, the
routers are going to flood that state to
every other router in the network.
They then rerun Dijkstra's algorithm,
Calculate the lowest cost spanning tree
out to every other router, and we're back
up and going again.
In other words, every time there's a
change, we recalculate from scratch, and
we move on.
So we don't have to worry about the, the
cases like, bad news travels slowly, etc.,
that we have to worry about with the
Bellman/Ford algorithm.
Because everything is recalculated from
scratch every time there's a change.
So let's see how Dijkstra's algorithm is
used in practice.
Dijkstra's algorithm is an example of a
linked-state algorithm.
That means that the linked state is known
by every router.
In other words, that it's flooded amongst
the routers to make sure that all of the
routers know the entire topology and the
state of the links in the network.
And then each router independently
calculates the shortest path spanning tree
from itself to every other router in the
network.
Dijkstra's algorithm is the basis of the
OSPF or Open Shortest Path First
algorithm, a, a very widely used routing
protocol in the Internet,
And we're going to see that in a later
video.
There's another way of thinking about
Dijkstra's algorithm, that I want to tell
you about, next.
I first learned about this from Professor
Jean Walrand at Berkeley.
And, it's a very nice way to think about
what's going on.
So, take a look at this example here, with
a set of routers interconnected by,
Links and the red numbers as before
represent the cost of each link.
I am actually going to represent them by tennis
balls, the yellow routers and a white and
pink ball representing the top and the
bottom, A and B.
And we're going to calculate the lowest
cost spanning tree and by connecting it by
strings between each ball where the length
of the string equals the cost shown in
red.
So lets start with them down on the ground
like this and then if we tug and pull them
by A, each link that goes to, or,
each string that goes toward is going to
be on that lowest-cost spending tree from
A through the network.
So eventually, we will end up with
something that looks like this,
Where A is connected to B through R3 and
R5 with a total cost of nine and all the
solid links here represent the strings
that will be tight.
All the ones that are dotted, the two in
the bottom left hand corner, will be, will
be slack or loose, because they're not on
the lowest cost spanning tree.
I'm going to lift them up like this and,
this is the same topology as before.
So A to R1 goes tight, then A to R2 and
three and R1 goes tight because they're
all on the least cost spanning tree.
Now A4 goes tight and then R5 because
they're all on the least cost spanning
tree.
I lift it up further and eventually the
line A, R3, R5, B will all go tight because
they're all on the least cost spanning
tree.
And that's the end of the video about
Dijkstra's algorithm.