So in this video, I'm going to go over all
the different kinds of NATs.
Or not all of them.
Many of the different kinds of NATs that
exist.
So it seems like a very simple abstraction
of translating addresses from an internal
to an external, in, eck, internal to an
external interface.
Well, it turns out there's all kinds of
different ways you might implement that,
and a lot of them are deployed out in the
wild, and understanding these differences
gives you a sense, then, of
Why NATs can be such a complicating factor
when building applications.
So recall, the model of a NAT is that, or
generally the way it works is that, when
there's some kind of communication from a
node behind the NAT to an external node on
the internet, the NAT sets up an internal
mapping between the NAT being you know
internally to in its memory, between its
internal IP address and associated port
to, an external IP address and port.
And so, when this server A, tries to open
a connection to the web server on S at,
18.181.0.31, so it's going to port 88 on
this host, and it's coming from port 4512.
The NAt rewrites that, that say.
The, all of those packets, including TCP
SYN, and all the data packets to be
coming from its own IP address and port
6641.
That's what the server sees, and then when
the server sends messages back, the NAT
translates them back to port 4512.
So that's the simple model and there are
two basic questions that come up.
First is, what packets does a NAT allow to
traverse these mappings.
The second is how and when does a NAT
assign these mapping, when does it create
them.
So I said when you generate packets but
turns out it can be a little more
complicated than that, when does it tear
down those mappings.
It doesn't keep the mapping for ever.
So it turns out there's a nice RFC that soft of goes
through some of the classifications in
terminology I'm going to use in rest of this
video RFC3489.
So if you're going to read little bit more
about some details in really precise ways
that are laid out, take a look at RFC3489.
So the first kind of NAT is what's called
a full cone NAT.
And this in some ways is the, is the one
that plays the nicest.
And full cone NAT is called, is called
that because it is the least restrictive
in terms of what packets it allows to
traverse a mapping.
In that way it's a full cone, and that's
where the things which are allowed in are
large.
And so the basic model of a full cone NAT
is that any packet.
That, say, this is for the particular,
say, protocol TCP.
Any TCP packet that comes into the NAT to
this IP address/port pair will be
translated to this IP address, this port
pair, regardless of what the source
address and source port are.
This is the least restrictive.
So if I have some other server, let's say,
S2, that has, you know, some IP address,
A, and it's sending a packet from port A
prime.
And that packet with source A, source port
A prime, is sent to twelve, 128.34.22.8 port
6641, then NAT will translate it.
And my server, my host here, will see
something coming from A, A prime, arriving
at port 10.0.0.101, port 4512.
It might discard that packet, it might
send an ICMP error.
But the point is, the NAT will do the
translation.
It's the least restrictive.
It's a full cone.
So in addition to full cone nats, there
are also restricted cone nats.
And what restricted cone NAT does, is it
filters.
Based on the source IP address.
So in restricted cone NAT, the NAT will
translate packets that come from the same
source address as intended on the external
mapping.
So when the NAT sets up the mapping
between the internal address in port pair
and the external address in port pair, it
includes the address of the other end
point.
And so, in this case, if I have S2, which
tries to send a packet from A colon, A
prime, address A, A prime.
The net will not allow that packet to
traverse.
It'll discard the, it'll either send an
ICMP error or generally will not translate
that packet and host A will never see it.
However, if server S were to send a packet
from IP address S.
And then let's just say, port, let's say
port, you now, 10,099.
That will be able to traverse the mapping,
in the sense of, it's coming from 18.181.0.31
and so host A will see a packet
from eighteen 18.181.0.31 port 1099.
It'll come in destined to 10.0.0.101, port
4512.
So that's a restricted cone NAT.
It will filter it based on the IP address
but not the port.
So the last kind of a NAT or of these
three major classifications is a
port restricted NAT.
Where it behaves like a restricted cone,
except it also filters on port.
So in this case, when a packet comes in
from some external host to 128.34.22.8
, 6641.
The NAT is storing also what the expected
IP address and port are.
So in this case, if I again, I have some
server S2 that tries to send something
from A, A prime.
And that will not translate that which
seen as an error, by ICPM etc, not route to
host, whatever error it thinks is correct
to specify, depending on the conditions.
But similarly, if server S tries to send a
message from port 1099.
That will not traverse either, because it
doesn't match the port in the mapping.
So only packets from this IP address/port
pair 18.181.0.31, port 80, will be allowed to
translate to 10.0.0.1:4512.
So only this particular pair.
Can traverse the mapping.
So the last and the final kind of NAT is
something called the symmetric NAT.
And what makes a symmetric NAT different
is not only, is that first of all, it's
sort of by definition port restricted but
there's the fact that packets coming from
the same source address and port internal
to the NAT, that are going to different
destination addresses and ports are given
different external address port mappings.
So when you look at this figure, you'll
see what I'm saying.
So here, I have host A, and it's sending
packets from 10.0.0.101, port 4512,
Right?
And, first it's sending them to eighteen
18.181.0.31 port 3311.
So the NAT sets up a mapping.
And the mapping between this internal
address port pair and this internal
address port pair is 128.34.22.8:6641
So packets that A sends to Port 3311
on this IP address will be translated to
have this IP address and this port.
However, if A sends packets to a different
external IP address and port like let's
say, even the same port and the IP address
differs in one bit.
So it's also sending packets to S prime of
18.181.0.32 port 3311, the NAT sets
up a completely different mapping.
So, even though.
This port address pair is the same for
both of these streams of packets.
The fact that the, that the
destination port address pair is different
means the NAT sets of a separate mapping,
port 6641 and port 9821.
So different destinations receive
different mappings .
So, turns out that and this is just to
give you one concrete example in ways in
which NATs can really disrupt
applications.
So, let's pretend, that Host A is sending
UDP traffic and this UDP traffic is for
massively multiplayer online game.
This is, this is a true story, a friend of
mine that is working on the service for
this, when this happened.
It's back in the late 90's and he made an
angry call to Linux, NAT developers.
And so the issue is that this massively
multiplayer game runs on many servers, and
there's times when, you know, somebody
runs from one island to another, or
wherever, and they need to change which
server they're on.
And so what the system would do is it
would tell.
The, the client.
Oh, okay.
Hey, you've been talking to, server
18.181.0.31.
You should start talking to server S prime
18.181.0.32.
On this port, even the same port.
Doesn't matter.
Like here, I say, port 3311.
On both of them, I'm going to port 3311.
So hey, please start trans-, talking on
this other, to this other host.
And the issue is, that the NAT, this
symmetric NAT, would create a new mapping.
And so S was seeing the client coming from
port 6641, but now, suddenly the client is
coming from port 9821.
There is no way for the system back here
to know that because the NAT just sets
this up and it can arbitrarily decide, so
the connection, when it breaks, the biz-,
observed behavior with the, 'cause there
was a symmetric NAT.
Then whenever someone would try to migrate
from one server to another, they would
disconnect.
Here's an example, by adding the smarts
into the network.
Suddenly you're seeing a behavior
different from the simple, you know,
strong end-to-end argument.
And there's this added behavior, which is
really hard to manage and really hard to
take into consideraion because there's no
way, really, for S prime to know that port
9821 is the port that A is going to start
communicating on.
So this is just the most basic overview of
some ways in which NATs can differ in
their behavior.
It turns out that there is many more
complications, all kinds of different
things NATs could do.
And that RFC I mentioned earlier in fact
goes through all the really diverse
behaviors you saw when NATs first became
popular, before there was really
standardization of what should happen.
There's all kinds of things like static
mapping, as you can tell the NAT, Hey,
just set up this static mapping between
the external host, IP port pair.
My external IP address and port into an
internal one.
This is say, if you have a web server
behind or not.
You can tell hey, anything that comes to
port 80 forward to this server on port 80. If you
have things like triggers, if you see
packets going out in one direction, then
also set up this additional mapping.
This was really useful in some of the
early days of first person shooters online
games where, again, they had to build NATs
in miond.
There was really diverse NAT behavior.
There's all kinds of more complex things
that happen but as it turns out, because
of all of the headaches and messes that
NATs are creating applications, the IETF,
went and came up with a bunch of
recommendations as to how NAT should
behave.
So the general behavioral recommendations
specified in RFC5382 for TCP, and RFC4787
for UDP.
So, just to give you one example of kind
of, some of the weird edge cases that a
NAT can consider, and some of the things
that are specified here, I'm going to talk
about hairpinning.
Which is this process of what happens when
you have a node that's behind your NAT.
And it sends a packet to one of the
external interface port pairs that the NAT
has.
One of its mappings.
So, basically, I have a node that's behind
the NAT and it's trying to traverse one of
the nat's mappings.
So, here's the, the example.
I have this NAT, 128.34.22.8.
And I've host A and B that are behind the
NAT.
And, they are both connected to a switch.
Alright.
So A has port has address 10.0.0.101, B
has 10.0.0.99.
Now, let's say we're doing some kind of IP
telephony which is coming from port, this
is a UDP traffic so it's port 4512 on host
A.
So it's using port 4512.
And this is translated to port 6641 on the
NAT.
The question is what happens when B tries
to send traffic to 128.34.22.8 port 6641.
Basic question is.
So, the packet is going to arrive at the NAT
and the NAT is going to translate it.
It's going to translate this, assuming
that it is a full-cone NAT
It's going to translate this to 10.0.0.101
port 4512.
One question you can ask is that, while
it's going to translate the destination IP
address and port, what should it do to the
source IP address and port?
Should it translate that as well?
That is, should this packet arrive at A
seemingly coming from 128.34.22.8, or
should this packet arrive at A coming from
10.0.0.99?
Well, so let's walk through what happens
if the NAT doesn't translate the source
address and port.
So this packet will go through the switch,
it'll go to the NAT, the NAT will rewrite
it to be going to 10.0.0.101:4512, and
so what A will see is a packet with source
10.0.0.99, let's just say port X, doesn't
really matter destination 10.0.0.101, port
4512.
And let's say it likes this packet, it
wants to respond, and it sends a response.
That packet is never going to reach the
NAT.
It's going to possibly just go directly
through the switch and because it doesn't
go through the NAT it's not going to be
translated.
So B, is going to send a packet to
128.34.22.8 port 6641 and we'll see in
response, a packet from, 10.0.0.101.
4512, so this break, this is not
what you want to do.
Instead, when this packet goes up to the
NAT, the NAT needs to translate it.
So it comes in as a packet from, so
source.
10.0.0.99 for X destination 128.34.22.8:6641
needs to be
rewritten to be source 128.34.22.8 with
some port, let's just call it X prime.
Destination.
10.0.0.101, port 4512.
And by so doing then, because now, the
source is coming from the NAT when A sends
a response, it will go back up to the NAT
where the NAT can re-translate it and
forward it back to B.
So it's called hair-pinning through the
model because you have to actually go back
through this device, sort of like a
hairpin, it comes back from telephony
networks, as the terminology.
And so here's this example of a very
specific behavior the NAT has to have, and
if it doesn't, then this little edge case
where B ends up sending a packet to A
based on an external mapping.
If you don't do this, it will break.
So this is just one of the many tricky
edge cases that NAT introduce, NATs
introduce, and which are specified in
these RFCs.