Phil: In this unit, you learned about network
security, and just how dangerous the Internet
can be.
You learned that, when thinking about security,
this is the model you should assume. The network
isn’t your friend. It’s controlled by
the adversary.
Specifically, an adversary can eavesdrop on
anything you transmit. An adversary can tamper
with and rewrite your messages. An adversary
can suppress messages you send so they don’t
arrive. An adversary can spoof to be someone
else or you. An Adversary can act as a man
in the middle and intercept your traffic before
passing it on. An adversary can redirect or
hijack communication at layer 2, through Ethernet
mechanisms, at layer 3, through ICMP or other
protocols, and at layer 4 by injecting new
segments into a TCP stream. Many mechanisms
designed with the best of intentions turn
out to be powerful weapons in the hands of
an adversary, both for accessing your data
and for denying access to networked systems.
Nick: But there’s hope! You learned that
three basic security principles can empower
you to build secure systems even in the face
of such attacks.
The first, confidentiality, lets you communicate
secretly even if someone can read your messages.
Using confidentiality, you can communicate
with another party over an untrusted network
and be confident that no-one else can read
your traffic. Or, at the the very least, it’s
computationally intractable for someone to
read your traffic.
The second principle is integrity. Integrity
lets you be sure that no-one has tampered
with your data. You learned about cryptographic
mechanisms that let you very inexpensively
verify that a piece of data hasn’t been
changed.
The third principle is authenticity. With
authenticity, you can be sure that the other
party has a secret. This can be a secret you’ve
shared beforehand, or a secret that they can
prove they have. You of course can’t be
sure who the other party is, but you can at
least be sure they have a secret that only
someone else you trust has.
Practically speaking, you also learned a whole
bunch of security tools that achieve these
principles. You learned about symmetric cryptography,
where two parties share a secret. You learned
about block ciphers, which transform fixed
blocks of data. You learned about the dangers
of electronic code book mode and how cipher
block chaining mode solves them.
You also learned about cryptographic hashes.
They have the wonderful property that they
are easy to compute, but it would be intractable
for an attacker to generate an input which
would compute to a specific hash value. So
if someone tells you the hash value of your
software, you can check it’s correct. It’s
nearly impossible for someone to create a
new piece of software that has the same hash
value. This is called “collision resistance.”
You learned how you can combine cryptographic
hashes with a shared secret to generate a
message authentication code, or MAC. With
a MAC, you can be sure that no-one has tampered
with the message and that its sender has the
secret. Simple ways of generating a MAC are
fraught with peril, though, so be careful
But how do we learn these secrets? You learned
about a different kind of cryptographic system
than symmetric cryptography, called public
key cryptography. With public key cryptography,
there are two keys, one public and one private.
Information encrypted with the public key
can only be decrypted with the private key.
So you can share your public key freely and
everyone else can send you encrypted data
that only you can read. There are also ways
to generate message authentication codes using
public key encrytpion, called signatures,
which only a private key can create but which
the public key can verify.
Finally, certificates are a way of establishing
a chain of trust to learn public keys. If
you trust Apple, for example, then Apple can
sign a document telling you someone else’s
public key. You can then use that public key
to communicate with them.
Phil: You’ve learned some of the basics
of network security and cryptography. There
were a lot of details, as we tried to give
you a sense of how these very important mechanisms
work. If you take away one lesson from this
unit, however, it shouldn’t be exactly how
a block cipher works. It should be that in
security, it’s very easy to make a mistake.
So don’t try to implement these mechanisms
yourself – it’s too easy to miss a detail
that turns out to be a vulnerability. Use
existing, open source implementations of crypto
systems. Use well-tested and well-understood
approaches that people have examined for a
long time. Finally, be careful, and follow
best practices.