I'm going to explain finite state machines,
something very
commonly used when specifying network protocols
and systems.
I'll also explain the common way they're
drawn in network
protocols. I'll conclude by showing you
the finite state machine
that's part of the TCP specification, which
defines how TCP
connections are set up and torn down. So you'll
see how you can
describe something like the three-way-handshake
of TCP in a
finite state machine.
As the name suggests, a finite state machine
is composed of
a finite number of states. A state is a particular
configuration of the system. I'm going to
start with an
abstract example. In this example, we have
three states:
state one, state two, and state three. So
our system can be
in one of these three states.
Edges between the states define how we transition
between
them. When we draw an edge, we first specify
what events
cause the transition to occur. Below this
we can state what
actions the system will take when that transition
occurs.
This part is optional, because not all transitions
have actions
associated with them. But if there is an action,
you should
specify it. Otherwise you have an incomplete
specification
and people might not test or implement it
correctly. If the
system is in a state and an event arrives
for which there is
no transition described, then the behavior
of the FSM is
undefined.
There can be multiple transitions from a single
state. So
here we have a second transition from state
1, a different
event that will take the system into state
3. For any given
state, the transition for an event must be
unique. In this
example, an event can cause state 1 to transition
to state 2,
OR transition to state 3. But you can't
have the same event
associated with both transitions, otherwise
the transition is
ambiguous. If the event occurs, are you in
state 2 or state 3?
The system can only be in one state.
So let's walk through an example, an HTTP
request. In practice HTTP requests are a bit
more complex than this, there all kinds of
options, so for this example we'll just
use a very
simple form.
Let's describe our system this way. In our
starting state we are are viewing a page or
otherwise idle. When we want to load a new
page, we transition to the page requesting
state.
So the event is load new page, and the action
is open a connection to the web server. Once
we've opened a connection, we're now in
the page requesting state. We'll transition
back to the idle state when the connection
closes or when we finish requesting every
resource on the page.
We need one more state, which describes where
we are in requesting a page. On the event
of having more resources to request, we take
the action of requesting a resource with
an HTTP GET. This puts us in the request pending
state. On the event of receiving the response,
our system transitions back to the page requesting
state.
So here we have a three state system. Idle,
page requesting, and request pending.
On one hand, this is a nice, simple FSM. But
if you were to try to implement it, it leaves
a lot unsaid. Specifically, we have 4 events
in the system: page request, more requests,
receive response, and connection closed. So
what happens if the connection closes when
we're in the request pending state? Or when
we receive a page request while in the page
requesting state? Or receive response while
in the idle state?
If you want to be completely explicit and
careful, you should specify what happens on
each state for every event. But this can lead
to complicated FSMs which have tons of edges.
So often instead you'll write down just
the common cases, for ease of understanding,
and have some supporting text about other
transitions. Or, in some cases, it can even
be
acceptable to leave something undefined. The
Internet Engineering Task Force, for example,
often doesn't completely specify every FSM.
The idea is that by specifying only the
parts that are necessary for interoperability,
you can leave the specification flexible for
future exploration. As people use the protocol,
they'll figure out if something is important
and if so can specify that extra part later.
So let's walk through a real example of
an FSM, probably the most famous FSM in the
Internet. This
diagram here describes the finite state machine
of TCP. I know it looks very complicated -- it
has 12
states -- but I'll walk though it bit by
bit and you'll see how it all fits together.
First off, the diagram really has four parts,
which we can look at separately. These top
4 states are what
describe how you open a TCP connection. This
center state, "ESTABLISHED" is when TCP
is sending and
receiving data. It's after the connection
has been established but before it's been
closed. These 6 states
describe how connections close. This state
at the bottom, CLOSED, denotes the connection
has closed
and the node can forget about it. Note that
the top state is also the closed state -- before
we open the
connection.
Recall that you start a TCP connection with
a three way handshake -- SYN, SYN/ACK, ACK.
The client, or
active opener, sends a SYN, synchronization,
message to a program listening for connection
requests.
When it receives a SYN, it responds with a
SYN/ACK, synchronizing and acknowledging the
original
synchronization. The active opener, on receiving
the SYN/ACK, responds with an acknowledgement.
The state diagram here describes how TCP behaves
on both sides of the TCP three-way handshake.
A passive opener is a server. It listens for
requests
for connections from active openers, clients.
So when a program calls listen(), the socket
transitions from the orange closed state to
the yellow listen
state. The protocol takes no actions when
this happens -- it doesn't send any messages.
If the server calls close on the socket when
it's in the listen
state, it transitions immediately to the closed
state.
Let's walk through the three way handshake
starting with the first step, when a client
tries to open a connection and sends a SYN
packet to the server.
We can see this first transition for the client
side of the connection as this orange arrow
from closed to the SYN SENT state. This happens
when the client
program calls connect -- the event -- and
the client sends a SYN message.
So once the first SYN is sent, the client
is in the SYN SENT state and the server is
in the LISTEN state. When the SYN arrives
at the server, this leads to this
blue transition. You can see the event is
receiving a SYN message. The action is to
send a SYN/ACK message in response. Now the
server is in the SYN
RECEIVED state.
Let's jump back to the client. Remember,
it was in the SYN SENT stage. Now, when it
receives the SYN/ACK from the server, it transitions
to the
ESTABLISHED state. Its action is to send an
ACK message, the third message of the SYN,
SYN/ACK, ACK handshake. Now the client can
start sending data
to the server.
Finally, let's go back to the server, which
is in the SYN RECEIVED state. When it receives
the ACK from the client, it transitions to
the ESTABLISHED state
and can send data.
There are a couple more transitions during
connection opening -- don't worry about
them for now, I discuss them in detail in
the video on connection
setup and teardown.