To continue on our theme of packet
switching, in this video I'm going to tell you
how packet switches work.
That's things like Ethernet switches,
Internet routers, and so on.
In this video we're going to learn about
what a packet switch looks like, what a
packet switch does, whether it's an
ethernet switch or a Internet router and
how address lookups work.
So let's start with a picture of a generic
packet switch.
The three main stages of a packet switch
are that when a packet arrives.
The first thing that we do is look up at
the address.
This means looking at the destination
address to figure out where it's going to
go next.
We do this by looking up in a forwarding
table.
We send the destination address down to
the forwarding table which will tell us
the egress link or the port that it's
going to and that helps us decide where to
send it next.
The next thing that we may need to do is
to update the header.
So, for example, if it's an Internet
router we have to decrement the TTL
and update the checksum.
The next thing we have to do is to queue
the packet.
This is because in there may be some
congestion.
There may be many packets trying to get to
this outgoing link at the same time.
So we use a buffer memory to hold some
packets that are waiting their turn to
depart on the egress line.
Course, this one input, one output packet
switch is not very interesting.
Packet switches, in general, will have
multiple input, and outputs.
Here's one with three inputs and three
outputs.
Packets will arrive and I've color coded
these ones.
The red packets are going to the red
output over here, and the blue one is
going to the blue output up here.
So.
Just as before, the packets are gonna be
processed the address is gonna be looked
up, we're gonna update the header if we
need to.
Then we're gonna transfer it across that
back plane.
This is supposed to represent a shared bus
over which all of these packets are gonna
pass.
And then they're gonna find their way to
the upper queue.
In this case, we've got two red packets
that are gonna contend for the same
output.
So what we'll need to do is we can send
the blue one to its output.
We can send one of the red ones all the
way through to its output.
But because we can only send one packet at
a time, the other red packet is gonna have
to wait in the buffer memory until the
first one is gone.
Once it's gone, this one can go on it's
way.
So this is sort of the generic structure
of a packet switch.
More specifically, one very common type of
packet switch is an Ethernet switch.
These are the four
basic operations that an Ethernet switch
must perform.
So an Ethernet switch is an example
of a packet switch.
It's just a very specific one that's
dealing with Ethernet frames.
So the first thing it does is it examines
the header of each arriving frame.
If the Ethernet destination address is the
Ethernet destination address.
And these are 48 bit addresses with the
Ethernet.
If it finds that address in the forwarding
table, it's gonna forward the frame to the
correct outgoing port.
Or maybe a selection of ports if it's a
multicast packet.
If it finds that the Ethernet destination
address is not in the table, in an
Ethernet switch it broadcasts the frames
to all ports.
Well all ports except the one through
which the frame arrived.
In other words, it doesn't know where to
send it, so it's going to flood it to
everybody, in the hope it'll reach its
destination.
How does it populate the table in the
first place?
Well, it does this by learning addresses
that it sees on the wire.
More specifically, when a packet arrives,
the entries in the table are learnt by
examining the Ethernet source address of
arriving packets.
So when packets first come through, the
destination address is not in the table.
It's broadcast to everybody.
Hopefully the other end will respond, send
a packet back, we'll see it's source
address and we will therefore learn that
in the future we must send packets through
that particular port to reach that
particular address.
So these are the four basic operations of
an Ethernet switch.
Let's contrast that with an Internet
router another type of packet switch which
processes the internet destination, the IP
destination address instead.
So there's seven basic operations.
Because it's dealing with, IP datagrams
that are encapsulated in Ethernet packets.
First of all, it's going to check to see
whether the Ethernet destination address
of the arriving frame belongs to the
router.
In other words, is it specifically
addressed to this router?
If it isn't accepted, if it doesn't, it
drops it because it's clearly not destined
for us.
The next thing it does is to check that
the IP version number is four if its an
IPV4 router, and checks the length of the
data ground, next it's going to decrement
the TTL, and update the IP header check
sum because the check sum includes the
TTL, it checks to see if the TTL equals
zero, if it does ot drops the packet, if
it doesn't it can continue to forward it.
Next it's going to look up in the
forwarding table.
If the AP destination address is in the
forwarding table, it's going to forward it
to the correct egress port or ports if
it's multicast.
And this is the correct ports to reach the
next hop because AP is doing hop by hop
routing.
Now that it's decided which port it's
going to depart from, it encapsulates the
IP datagram back into an ethernet frame,
and it has to figure out the correct
ethernet destination address for the next
hop router.
We'll learn this process later at
something called ARP.
So it will encapsulate the IP datagram
into the ethernet frame, create the new
ethernet frame and send it to the wire.
So the basic operations of a packet switch
are to look up the address.
So we're going to ask the question how is
this address looked up in the forwarding
table?
I'm going to show you some examples in a
moment.
The second operation is switching, once
it's figured out which egress port it
needs to go to, it now has to send it to
that correct output, it's got to deliver
it to that correct output port so it can
leave on the correct outgoing link.
I'm going to start with the look up
address, and in the next video we're going
to learn about switching.
So for Ethernet switches looking up the
address is very straightforward.
It will have a forwarding table, which
I've drawn in very simplified form here.
This is the match that it's gonna perform.
This is what it's gonna try and match the
Ethernet destination address on.
And this is then the action it's gonna
perform if it finds a match.
If an incoming Ethernet frame has a
destination address that matches this one
here, then.
It's going to forward it to port seven.
If it matches on this addresses here then
it's gonna forward it to port three.
I just turned on the 48-bit addresses here
as a hexadecimal numbers.
Okay, so the Ethernet forwarding table has
a number of rows, one for each address and
for each address, it's gonna tell it which
port that it needs to forward to.
And if it misses then it broke off; that's
what the Ethernet switches do when they
don't know the address to send it to.
Now to do this look up, the way that it
performs this look up, is that typically
it stores these addresses in a hash table,
because these are 48 bit addresses, but
there's nothing like two to the 48
entries, there may be 100,000, maybe even
1,000,000 entries, so nothing like two to
the power of 48 so it's a very sparse
table.
So typically they store addresses in a
hash table, it might be a two way hash to
increase the probability of having a hit
on the first try, and then it will look up
the match by looking for an exact match in
the table.
Another words it's looking for an exact
match on the 48 bit address.
So that's how address look ups are done in
an Ethernet switch.
Now let's look how they done in an IP
router, an internet router.
So, IP addresses are bit more complicated,
IP addresses we don't just look up on an
exact match, we look up on what's called a
longest prefix match.
We'll learn about why that is later when
we learn about IP addresses.
But it suffices to know right now we are
performing longer prefix match rather than
an exact match.
So just as before we've got some, some
matches here of some IP prefixes.
And I'll tell you what those are in a
moment.
And then this is the action that we would
perform.
So for example if we if we had a match on
this IP destination address.
At this on here.
And this is a specific IP destination
address.
127.43.57.99.
So that'll be a 32-bit address.
We're gonna forward it to this IP address.
So this is actually the IP address of the
interface of the next router that we're
going to.
After it's made this decision it's going
to resolve this.
It's going to turn this IP address into
the equivalent Ethernet destination
address of that interface so that it knows
what to encapsulate the packet into.
But anyway, for inside the forwarding
table it maintains it as an IP address.
So if we see something that matches here
then this is the action that we perform.
So let's look at what a longest prefix
match is.
Along here, I've got the IP version for
address number-line.
Although it's all of the possible two to
the 32 different addresses that we can
have in an IP destination address.
And what I've got up here is some line
segments.
These line segments are prefixes, and
they're always represented as in the
following form.
This line segment here corresponds to all
of the addresses that start with 65.
The interpretation of this is.
All of those with 65 as the first eight
bits so if a packet, an incoming
destination address has 65 as the first
eight bits of address then it's gonna
match on this line segment and this line
segment represents all the IP addresses
that start with 65.
In the first eight bit locations.
Similarly, this line segment here,
corresponds to all of the IP addresses
that their first sixteen bits are 128.9.
So there are two to the pair of sixteen
addresses here, all with the first sixteen
bits 128.9.
And so we represent that prefix as
128.9.00/16, corresponding to those first
sixteen bits.
Finally one more example.
This one up here, which is a very short
line segment, is all those addresses that
share the first 24 bits.
This means there are two to the eight of
them, or 256 different addresses, that all
start with 128.9.176.
Okay.
So when a packet arrives with a particular
destination address.
And here's an example here.
This one is clearly gonna match on this
line segment right here.
So, this is the address on the number
line.
This is where it matches here.
So that we know that the prefix that we've
matched on to the table is this one.
So the table will contain this entry here.
This address will match on this entry in
the table.
Similarly, this address 128.9.16.14 is
gonna match on this line segment here.
Notice that it matched on this one.
But this one is, is a longer matching
prefix.
More of the bits match on this one then I
do on this one.
This is a longest, longer prefix it's a
21-bits prefix, whereas this one is only a
16-bit prefix.
So because it matches on both, and this is
the longest one, the.
The dress this address here will match on
this prefix here in the table.
So in routing lookups what we do is we
find the longest matching prefix also
known as the most specific route amongst
all the prefixes that match the
destination address.
Let's look at how we might implement this
in a table.
And, one common implementation is to use,
what's called a Binary Trie, TRIE.
And, there are many variations of this.
But, this is the most common one here.
Let's say that we had a prefix table, look
like this.
This prefix table is a bit strange
because, all the prefixes are very short,
I am just doing that they can be clearly
represented in this table.
So, I've got, one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, ten different
entries in, In the table.
And I'm going to populate them on this
trie right here.
Because the matching of an incoming
address is, going to have variable length,
we need a data structure to hold variable
length entries.
So the way that this data structure holds
these entries is, let's take the, 00001.
This is zero, this is zero, this is zero,
this is zero, and then this is one.
In other words, we take the left branch
for a zero and the right branch for a one.
And so we encode or store this entry A at
this particular leaf corresponding to that
entry.
And certainly the other extreme, let's
take a look at J.
That's 1,1,1,1,0,0,0,0.
Corresponding to this entry here, and this
is where we'll find J at the leaf Once
we've got this data structure for storing
the entries when a packet comes in with a
particular destination address we can just
do a bit by bit comparison traverse this
tree and it will tell us which entry is
the longest matching prefix.
If we get to a leaf and find that there's
nothing there we go back to the nearest
matching one that shared bits in common
with that address.
You might want to experiment this with
other entries in table.
So this is one common way of stirring and
performing the look up for a longest
lasting prefix and there's another entry
another mechanism which Is quite commonly
used to.
That's to use a special type of memory
device called a Ternary Content Addressable
Memory, or a T-CAM.
And a TCAM that here's the table again
that we had that we had before.
And we start by storing it in a slightly
different representation in the table.
So entry A would be stored as four 0's and
a one.
And here we've rounded everything out to
eight bits as if they're eight bit eight
bit prefixes and this mask value here.
Is telling us which bits in the value
above actually matter.
So wherever there was a 01, we put a one
to say these are all valid.
And wherever we have an X, we put a zero.
So these two bits, these two
representations here, we can either think
of them as a ternary value or two binary
values that are storing in this entry.
They tell us which bits have which values
and which ones don't matter.
So the process of performing a look-up,
it's kind of brute force.
We compare an incoming address against
every masked entry at the same time in
parallel on the table.
So these specialized memories consume
quite a bit of power, because they're
doing all of that at the same time.
But they can be really, really fast, and
so they're quite commonly used the longest
prefix matches in routers.
One of the last thing I wanted to point
out is this is sort of an increasing
interest these days in what we might call
generic lookups.
You know, I made the observation before
that these tables are holding a match
field and an action field, and so we can
generalize this or abstract this and say
pretty much any packet switch is doing a
lookup which is a match followed by an
action, and the match might be on any
fields like an IP address or Ethernet
destination address and an IP address if
we wanted, and we might have actions like
forward or drop or.
Or, encapsulate or do other things.
So we can generalize the specification of
a packet switch and Nowadays packet
switches are designed that can do all
sorts of different types of forwarding for
layer two.
Layer three at the same time.
Or they could be they could be for, for
things like switches.
Routers.
Firewalls.
All sorts of devices like that.
So in summary, packet switches perform two
basic operations.
They perform the look ups, for looking up
addresses in a forwarding table, and then
they switch the packet to the correct
outgoing port.
But high level, Ethernet switches and
internet routers perform very similar
operations.
Their basically processing these packets
in a very similar way.
Address look up is different in switches
and routers.
And we saw some examples of those for both
Ethernet addresses and IP addresses.
That's the end of this video.