Nick: By now you’ve heard it said several
times during the quarter that IP is the “narrow
waist” of the Internet. You probably remember
this figure from Unit 1….
Nick: If we want to use the Internet, we have
to use the Internet Protocol, IP. We have
no choice.
But we have lots and lots of choices for Link
Layers: IP runs over many different Link Layers,
such as Ethernet, WiFi, DSL, 3G cellular,
and so on. On top of the unreliable IP layer,
we can choose between many different transport
layers . We already saw TCP and UDP. There
is RTP for real time data and many others
too. And of course there are tens of thousands
of different applications. .
In this unit you learned about different link
layers. You learned about the Link Layer Service
Model, how Etherhet works, incuding the different
speeds it runs at. You watched several videos
about wireless networks: Why wireless is different
and why we need medium access control protocols
to share access to the air. You learned about
Shannon capacity and how it helps us determine
the maximum data rate, or capacity, of a communication
channel. And you learned about error correction
mechanisms.
Phil: We started by exploring the most commonly
used wired network: Ethernet. If you’ve
ever physically plugged your computer into
a network, it was almost certainly an Ethernet
network. Although many different wired networks
were proposed in 1990s, and several were standardized,
built and sold, Ethernet won the day and is
now almost universally used for wired networks.
This is because it is very simple, cheap and
reliable. In a switched Ethernet network,
when you have data to send, you can just go
ahead and send it. The network learns addresses,
so there are no complicated routing protocols
to worry about. And Ethernet runs over the
wiring that is installed in almost every office
building – making it very easy to install.
Nowadays, almost all Ethernet networks use
Ethernet switches, allowing many simultaneous
communications in the network, and every link
is full duplex, allowing data to flow in both
directions at the same time. In the next few
years we will start to see 40Gb/s Ethernet,
100Gb/s Ethernet and beyond. Ethernet looks
certain to remain the dominant wired link
layer for years to come.
All link layer networks have a maximum packet
size they can carry. For Ethernet, this is
1500bytes by default. Other link layers can
carry larger packets, such as the FDDI standard
of the 1990s that carried packets up to 4500bytes
long. Some Ethernet networks are configured
to carry so-called Jumbo frames up to 9kbtyes
long. We call the longest packet a link can
carry its “MTU”, or maximum transmission
unit. When a router interconnects two links
with different MTUs, it might need to fragment
IP datagrams going from the link with the
larger MTU to the smaller one. You learned
how a router does this using the fragment
fields in the IPv4 header to break IP datagrams
into new self-contained IP datagrams. The
network doesn’t reassemble the fragments;
the destination host uses information in the
IPv4 header to put the data back into the
correct order before handing it to TCP. IP
fragmentation is less common than it used
to be, for two reasons. First, most wired
networks use Ethernet today, and so the MTU
tends to be 1500bytes on most links and there
is no need to fragment. Second, hosts often
use MTU discovery when creating a TCP connection,
to identify the shortest MTU along the path.
The senders don’t send packets larger than
the MTU, eliminating the need for fragmentation
along the way. When we talk about the MSS,
or maximum segment size, of a transport protocol,
it’s the smallest MTU along a path between
the IP endpoints.
Wireless networks are very different from
wired networks. In a wired network the links
have a constant data rate, but in a wireless
network the link speed is always changing.
This is for several reasons: interference
from nearby wireless networks, and from other
devices operating in the same frequency band,
such as microwave ovens and cordless phones.
It can also be caused by fades in the channel
due to shadowing and multipath. Wireless networks
also suffer from the so-called hidden terminal
problem; this happens when two clients can’t
communicate directly with each other, but
can both communicate with an access point.
Because they don’t hear each other, they
don’t know to avoid transmitting at the
same time, requiring extra coordination in
the network. Another way in which wireless
networks are different is that the channel
naturally broadcasts all communications. This
means senders need to take turns to transmit,
leading to medium access control protocols,
such as the CSMA protocol used in WiFi. A
shared broadcast channel also means we need
to be more careful with securing our data
– everyone in the neighborhood can more
easily eavesdrop on our conversations than
in a wired network.
Nick: You also learned some of the underlying
principles of communications that dictate
how we build physical links.
You learned about bit errors and how they
can lead us to incorrectly decode a packet
on the wire; and you learn about ways to code
data to make it easier to detect errors when
they happen.
And you learned about how error correcting
codes work, and when we use them. Generally
speaking, we use error correcting codes in
environments where bit errors are frequent,
or where the cost of retransmitting a corrupted
packet would be high: for example, in a network
with a very large bandwidth-delay product.
Finally, but perhaps most importantly of all,
you learned about Shannon capacity. Claude
Shannon created the wonderfully powerful field
of information theory, and the centerpiece
of his work was deducing the maximum errror-free
rate that a channel can communicate at, now
referred to as the Shannon capacity. The remarkable
property of the Shannon capacity is that it
gives a fundamental, inescapable limit to
the maximum rate information can be carried
over a channel, regardless of the clever coding
schemes we invent.
All of the communications principles we describe
give you a taste of some of the material you
would learn in an electrical engineering class
on communications theory or information theory.
If you really enjoyed this material, you might
consider taking EE classes in future.