Continuing with our theme of packet
switching.
In this video, I'm going to tell you about
some useful properties of queues.
These are going to come in handy whenever
we're thinking about how a queue evolves,
how a packet buffer changes to affect the
queuing delay of packets through in that
work.
As you have seen before, we can think of a
network as a set of queues interconnected
by some links and those links are carrying
the traffic or the packets from many, many
different users.
And when multiplexed together when
statistically multiplexed together they,
that whole process of packet arrival is
very, very complicated.
So, we usually think of the arrival
processes as being random events each one
of it was of course, deterministically
generated but the aggregate we can think
of as a random process.
So, its going to be good for us to
understand how queues with random arrival
processes work and so that's going to be
the topic that I am going to be discussing
today.
So, usually arrival process is
complicated in systems like networks so
we often model them using random
processes and the study of queues with
random arrival processes is called queuing
theory.
And queuing theory you've probably heard of
before, has a reputation for having very
hairy mathematics.
But despite that hairy mathematics, queues
with random arrival processes have some
really interesting properties that's gonna
be good for us to understand.
They're gonna really help us understand
the dynamics of networks.
So I'm going through a set of properties
I'm gonna be starting with this one here
that the burstiness tends to increase
delay and it's at this level I want you to
remember these properties.
The details of mathematics we're not gonna
worry about so much. I want you, want
you to understand these basic intuitive
properties of queuing systems.
It all comes down to the way the queue
evolves.
I'm just going to sketch here my queue
again.
This is the arrivals to the queue of our
packets, you'll hear people call customers
as well because queuing theory applies to
many other systems so I'll, if I say
customers I mean packets in this context,
and so this is our arrivals, these are our
departures, and we're going to be thinking
about the evolution of the Q occupancy, Q(t),
Q as a function of time.
On this timeline down here, I've drawn a
sequence of arrivals and departures,
packet arrivals happening up these blue
downward arrows representing the time or
the epoch of the arrival, and then these
red upward arrows being
the departures, the time in which the
queue was serviced.
And, just like in many queues for networks,
we're gonna think of this is, as
representing a link of a fixed rate R.
Which means that their inter-departure
opportunities are one over R apart.
Now, let us look at the, evolution of the
queue.
The queue here has this the first arrival
with blue one, which takes it up to one,
and then we have the service, the outward
red arrow which is gonna take us to zero.
There's a new arrival, which is gonna take
us back to one again, then this departure
here, which is gonna take us to zero, then
back up to one again, then zero etc.
But, this point here, we had two arrivals
in a row, which is gonna take us back to
queue occupancy of two, and so on.
So this is gonna be the, the evolution of
the queue.
Now, lets look at this one here this,
departure opportunity, the reason I've
drawn this as a dotted line.
This is, sometimes people call this a
shadow departure.
It was a departure opportunity where we
could have sent a packet, but the queue
was empty.
So that we never actually sent the packet
cause we can't actually go down to a
negative Q occupancy.
That wouldn't be, that wouldn't be
possible.
And so the Q sticks at zero even though we
missed this opportunity.
It's going to turn out that these missed
opportunities are quite important.
You can't have a negative queue occupancy.
So some people say you don't get credit
for good behavior by not having an arrival
during this interval here.
It meant that the queue occupancy is stuck
at zero but we don't get any credit for it
and so if we have random arrivals with arrivals that are
spread out.
If we miss an opportunity to send it's
tough we never get, we never get that back
again.
Now let's take a look at the first
property I wanted to explain.
That is that,
burstiness, or bursty arrivals tend to
increase delay.
We'll start with a very simple example
where there is no burstiness, where we
have the simplest arrival process which is
a sequence of arrivals, all exactly one
second apart.
So this is one packet per second.
And in fact it's one packet exactly every
second.
Nothing random about this at all.
Let's look at the sequence of departures
and we are going to assume that there is one
departure every second.
So if we were to sketch the q occupancy
here.
I won't sketch the graph. I'll just put the
numbers in.
If we were to sample the occupancy here
There's been an arrival but no departure.
So we'd have one and then zero.
And then it's one again.
And then zero, one, zero.
So there's a long.
and this is the way I've drawn it here there
are long periods of zero.
And then there are short periods of one when
there's been arrival but no departure.
But of course I could shift either the
arrivals and departures and make those 0's
and 1's be of different duration.
Okay, so now we'll just carry on because
everything's nice and periodic.
The interesting thing to note here is Q of
T, the Q occupancy is either zero or a
one.
So we can say it's always less than or
equal to one.
And the average queue occupancy is gonna
be somewhere between zero and one.
We know that for sure, just because of the
structure of the problem.
So periodic arrivals make for a nice
simple understanding of the queue or
queue evolution.
Now let's look at a different example when
things are more bursty.
So just as before, the arrivals are gonna
be at the rate of one per second, but
they're gonna arrive in bursts.
And in fact we're gonna have N arrivals,
every N seconds.
So N packets every N seconds.
But they're gonna come in these bursts of
N.
In this particular case it's five packets
every five seconds.
The service opportunities or the
departures are gonna be the same as
before.
We're gonna have one per second.
So in terms of the rates, the arrival rate
and the departure rate, everything is
exactly the same as before, it's one
packet per second.
It's just that the burstiness of the
arrival is gonna change things.
And let's look at the way in which they,
they change.
So.
Here we've got a sudden burst of arrivals
of five.
So depending on whether, when we sample
it, sample the queue occupancy.
We're gonna have Q(T) equals zero all
the way thru to five, depending on when we
sample.
During this time here it's four, then
three, then two, then one, then zero.
And then it's gonna go up to five again
sometime in here and four and so on, and
so on, and so on.
Okay.
So, before our Q occupancy was zero or
one.
But now even with the same arrival rate,
and even with the same departure rate, our
Q occupancy can be between zero and five.
So our arrival average Q occupancy is
higher.
And the variance of the Q occupancy is
higher too.
Because it's varying all the way across
zero to five.
So average and the variance have both
increased, even though the rate hasn't
changed.
So clearly, the burstiness is gonna make a
big difference.
And, in general, we say, burstiness
increases delay.
And that simple example that illustrates
it doesn't prove it.
But hopefully, it gives you intuition as
to why burstiness will increase delay.
The second property, which is very similar
to the first.
It's almost the counter balance of the
first is that determinism, tends to
minimize delay.
But it's enough for us to know that in
general, determinism minimizes delay.
In other words, random arrivals wait
longer on average than simple, periodic
arrivals.
Okay, let me move on to the third property
that I'd like you to know about, and that
is a well-known result called Little's
Result.
Queues are very complicated, and as you've,
as I've already given an indication.
The mathematics tends to get very hairy,
but there's some simple results that you
really need to know, and its important
first to understand.
Because they're gonna come in handy, when we're
understanding, the basic properties of
queues.
And this one, Little's result is
deceptively simple.
So, in any queuing system, like the one
shown here, there's a following property
which is a little surprising.
If I've got a well defined arrival rate,
let's call that Lambda.
And I've got a average number of queues in
the system L.
And I want to know what the average delay
is, and I'm going to call this D equals
average delay, of the customer or a packet
through the queue.
Then Little's result tells us, that there
is in general, the number of customers in
the system, equals the average arrival
rate Times the average delay of a customer
thru the queue.
That's it.
This deceptively simple result applies for
any queuing system for which there are no
customers that are lost or dropped.
So if none lost or dropped.
So it doesn't matter what the arrival
process is.
It isn't gonna help us [inaudible], so
long as it has a well defined arrival
rate, lambda, then we can make this
miscalculation.
So you can go to any queue, and we'll look
at some examples in a moment.
And you can calculate the average number
in the queue as a function of the arrival
rate and the average delay or of course,
if you know L and Lambda, then you can
figure out the average delay that's going
to be seen by a customer through this
queue.
Now L, is the average number.
that are in the queue, plus currently
being serviced, so long as D is the
average delay of customers that arrive
until they've completed service.
It turns out this result also holds if we
say L is the average time, I'm sorry, the
average number of customers in just the
queue but not yet entering service, so
long as D also equals the average delay
through the queue prior to entering
service.
So, both of those are true.
We're gonna be using this result quite a
lot throughout the quarter.
Having told you about those three
properties of queues.
Something I need to tell you before we get
on to the fourth property, and that is
the, the Poisson process.
You're going to hear a lot about the
Poisson process whenever you study queues or
any complicated system that, that we model
probabilistically.
First of all I'm going to tell you what
the Poisson process is, then I'm going to
tell you why it's interesting and some
caveats about using it.
So the Poisson process is, is an arrival
process in our case, and an arrival
process we say is Poisson if.
And in fact, and only if, the probability
of there being K arrivals in an interval
of T seconds is given by this expression
here, kind of a hairy expression but the,
the important thing is that, that we can
express this as the expected number of
arrivals within an interval T is simply
lambdaT, where lambda is the arrival rate.
Also, successive inter-arrival times are
independent.
What this means is that once we've picked
one arrival.
From this expression here, this will lead
to a, an arrival event happening.
Then the next arrival is independent of
the first one, and, in fact, if we take a
sliding window and move that over the
arrival process within any, within any
period, the inter-arrival times within one
period are independent of the next.
That means that there's no burstiness or
coupling of one arrival to another.
Okay, that's what the Poisson process is.
You'd pick up any book on probability,
then you can find, a more detailed
description, if that's something new to
you.
So why the Poisson process?
Why do we, why are we interested in the
Poisson process?
Well the Poisson process, happens to,
model, an aggregation of many independent
random events, very well.
For example, it's used in models of new
phone calls arriving to a switch.
So when we have a telephone switch, we
say, we want to model the arrival of a new
phone call that is being placed through
the day.
Then, a Poisson process is a very good
model of this.
Or the decay of many independent nuclear
particles where we have huge number of
particles all operating independently of
each other.
They will decay at certain times.
That decay.
As a aggregation of many random events
tends to a Poisson process, as we have a
large number of particles.
And you may also be familiar with shot
noise in an electrical circuit, which is
also modeled as a Poisson process.
The final thing, despite the complexity of
the equation on the previous slide, it
actually makes the math very easy, and this
is a big reason that it gets used very
widely as well.
At this point I should give you some
warnings, network traffic is very bursty,
there's nothing independent about one
packet arrival after another.
As we will see later packets tend very
frequently to arrive in bursts, and many
things in the network help actually to
keep them that way, and make them very
bursty.
So packet arrivals are not, and I can't
over-emphasise this, they are not Poisson,
there's been some classic papers, research
papers that have shown this.
However, it does model quite well the
arrival of new flows, of new
communications.
For example, the inter-arrival times of
web requests, or sending emails.
For any one individual, they may be
somewhat Poisson, but when you take the
aggregation of many users putting their
network traffic into the network, that is
actually modeled quite well by a Poisson
process.
And sometimes, sometimes we can use some
of the results that apply to queues with
Poisson arrivals, to give us an intuition and
understanding of maybe what's happening
even at the packet level.
But we must do that very, very carefully.
Let's look at a very common example of
where we use the Poisson process.
This is something called the M/M/1 Queue.
The M/M/1 Queue is about the simplest type
of queue that is commonly analyzed.
The notation is that the M.
Stands for a Markovian arrival process.
Which, in our case is Poisson.
Markovian service process which is
exponential, in our case.
Which means that the time that it takes to
service a packet is exponentially
distributed, and each one has a service
time independent of all of the others.
And that there is one server.
In other words, that there's one outgoing
line servicing this queue.
This is very widely used,
because it, it assumes a nice simple Poisson arrival, with independent arrivals from
one packet to the next.
But it's also used, because the math is
very simple, and the result is very
intuitive.
So.
If we were to analyze this, and we can
analyze it using, using continuous time
Markov chains, we will discover that the
average delay of a packet going through
this queue is given by the simple
expression, one over Mu minus Lambda.
What this tells us is that it's a one over
the, one over the difference between the
service rate and the arrival rate.
So as the load increases, and the load
gets closer and closer to the service rate
then, this number will grow very rapidly.
And, if we plot this on a graph.
So, as a function of lambda over mu, so
that's lambda over mu, as we get closer
and closer to one, in other words where
they're equal, the average delay of a
packet through this queue will increase
very, very steeply.
And this is the case for almost any
queuing system not just the M/M/1 queue.
The reason that we use the M/M/1 Queue sometimes
as a placeholder for a more complicated
system is only that the math is simpler and this
expression is simple.
But you see a very similar shape for
almost any queuing system.
We can use Little's result to figure out
what the average queue occupancy is.
And we know that L equals Lambda times D,
which in this case is, simply going to be
Lambda over MU.
Divided by one minus lambda over mu.
The reason of writing it in terms of
lambda over mu is simply that lambda over
mu represents the intensity just as I
sketch on the graph here.
As lambda approaches mu, lambda over mu
approaches one, and the denominator turns
to zero and the queue occupancy, and the
average delay will blow up and turn
towards infinity.
So the M/M/1 queue provides us a good
intuition.
Though never assume that this is the actual
representative measure of, of the queue
occupancy or the average delay but it can
often help to give an intuitive sense of
what's going on in a network.
So in summary, the main queue properties I
want you to take away from this video are,
that burstiness tends to increase delay.
So bursty arrivals tend to make queuing
delays longer.
Little's result gives us a nice
relationship between the average occupancy
of a queue, L, lambda the arrival rate,
and D, the average delay of a customer
through that queue.
While packet arrivals are not poisson.
Some events are, such as web requests, and
new flow arrivals.
And poisson process also forms the basis
of the M/M/1 Queue.
Which is a simple queuing model that often
can give us some intuition about the delay
properties of a network.
That's the end of this video.