In this video we’ll look at common attacks
that can be performed locally by compromising
Layer 2 networks.
Eavesdropping is quite easy if we put our
network interface into promiscuous mode. In
promiscuous mode, your network interface will
capture all of the packets passing by, not
just those addressed to your Ethernet address.
Computers allow this mode of operation so
they can act as an Ethernet switch – for
example, the Linux operating system comes
with Ethernet switching code built in. When
wireshark runs it first puts your interface
into promiscuous mode so it can see all the
packets.
This is particularly easy in a WiFi network
and early Ethernet networks where packets
were broadcast onto a single shared link.
It doesn’t work so well with modern Ethernet
networks that use EThernet switches, because
packets are usually private to the links between
the source and the destination.
In this video I’ll show you how we can force
packets to be broadcast in any Ethernet network
by overflowing the forwarding tables. We do
this by prventing the switch from learning
addresses correctly. Once we have forced them
to be broadcast, we can then eavesdrop using
Wireshark.
The next approach is for the attacker to set
up a computer that masquerades as a DHCP or
ARP server, redirecting packets from the sender
via another server.
Eavesdropping is very easy when packets are
broadcast on a shared medium. Just like WiFi
packets are broadcast in the air for everyone
to hear, the earliest versions of Ethernet
broadcast packets on a common cable attached
to all end hosts. Eavesdropping is easy in
a network that shares a single broadcast communication
channel.
But as we saw in Unit 7, Ethernet has changed
over the years. Today, Ethernet networks use
switches rather than a single shared cable.
We use switches because they allow many simultaneous
communications in the network. This is good
news for performance. But it is bad news for
the attacker because our packets only pass
over the two links between Alice and Bob.
The Attacker can’t see our packets.
A common exploit is to attack the tables in
the Ethernet switches. As you will recall,
an Ethernet switch learns the addresses of
end hosts by watching packets in the network.
For example, the switch between Alice and
Bob shown here learns their Ethernet addresses
whenever they send packets. Here is what the
forwarding table might look like in the switch
after it has learned some addresses. In practice
the tables are much bigger than this – usually
tens or hundreds of thousands of entries – but
I show only a few here to keep things simple.
Remember that if a switch receives a packet
with an Ethernet destination address that
is not in its forwarding table, then it broadcasts
the packets. So how can the Attacker persaude
the switch to broadcast packets? It can keep
filling up the forwarding table with other
addresses. So, what an attacker can do is
keep sending – at very high rate – packets
with new Ethernet addresses. The switches
will learn these addresses, displacing entries
already in the switches. Typically, the replacement
policy is least recently used, so if the Attacker
sends at a high enough rate, the table will
keep evicting the entries for Alice and Bob.
All the packets will be broadcast, and will
be seen by the Attacker.
This is called a MAC Overflow attack.
Another common type of attack is to set up
a rogue DHCP server.
In this attack, The Attacker is going to try
and persuade you to use a rogue DHCP server.
Recall that DHCP is a service offered by a
network to help configure your computer when
it boots or first attaches to the network.
Your computer sends out a sequence of broadcast
discovery packets to find the DHCP server,
which is usually hosted on the nearest router.
After your computer has found the DHCP server,
it sends a request, asking to be allocated
an IP address on the local network, along
with the address of the default router and
the addresses of the DNS servers it should
use.
If the Rogue DHCP server can respond faster
than the legitimate server, it can respond
to Alice first, giving her whatever configuration
information it wants. For example, the Attacker
can give Alice a bad router address, so she
sends traffic to the Attacker instead of the
router. This makes it easy for the Attacker
to set up a man in the middle attack without
Alice knowing.
A second way is for the Attacker to give Alice
the IP address of a remote rogue DNS server.
When Alice looks up IP addresses in future
– for example, next time she visits google.com
– the rogue DNS server can return the IP
address of a different server, and intercept
Alice’s traffic.
Finally, the Attacker can set up a rogue ARP
server. When Alice is sending packets to a
local host, or via the router, she will first
send an ARP request to find out the Ethernet
address of the next hop. First she sends a
broadcast ARP request packet to the ARP server,
which replies with the legitimate Ethernet
address she is looking for.
But if the Attacker sets up a Rogue ARP server
that responds faster than the legitimate ARP
server, the Attacker can give Alice the wrong
information. If the Attacker replies with
the Ethernet address of a rogue server in
the local network, then all of Alice’s traffic
will be sent to the rogue server. This is
an easy way to setup a man in the middle attack,
by passing all of Alice’s traffic through
a rogue server without Alice knowing.