There’s one last security primitive that’s
very common today. You use it every time you
establish an SSH or HTTP session. They’re
certificates. Public key cryptography lets
us verify that someone with the private key
associated with a public key signed a document.
But how do we know what the right public key
is? How do we know that www.ebay.com has a
public key? The answer is certificates.
Let’s say we want to securely communicate
with a server, such as www.amazon.com. Now,
using public key cryptography, if I know www.amazon.com’s
public key, then I can communicate securely
with that server. I can verify that www.amazon.com
has the private key associated with the public
key I’m using. We can then use public key
encryption to exchange symmetric keys. All
is well.
But there’s a missing step here. How do
I get the server’s public key? Do I find
it on a web page? If I just found it somewhere
random or insecure, then how can I be sure
it’s really that server’s public key and
not an adversary pretending to be that server?
For example, imagine this very simple attack.
I want to communicate with a server. So I
ask it for its public key. It gives me the
key, then I can verify that it has the associated
private key.
This is completely open to a man in the middle
attack. An attacker can pretend to to be the
server and give me its own public key. I have
no way of telling whose key is right -- the
attacker looks just like the server, except
that it has a different key. The attacker
can then open up a connection to the server
and pretend to be you. It sees everything
you send, since you’re communicating with
it, and forwards it along to the server. It
can rewrite or suppress anything you send,
or even insert new traffic. You leak passwords,
all kinds of stuff.
I need some way to be able to receive the
public key for www.amazon.com and be reasonably
sure that it’s actually www.amazon.com.
In the best case, I’d have someone I trust
tell me what www.amazon.com’s key is.
That’s exactly what a certificate does.
Abstractly, a certificate is a digital document,
just a chunk of bytes, that bind a name to
a value. This document is signed by a private
key K1-inverse. If I already have the public
key K1, then I can verify this was signed
with the right private key. If I trust the
party who has K1-inverse, then I can trust
their claim that the name, e.g., a hostname,
has the public key K2. I can then use K2 when
communicating with N. In this way I establish
a chain of trust. If I start with the public
key of one party that I trust, then that party
can give me public keys for other parties.
Those parties could give me further public
keys.
If you browse the web a lot, you’ve probably
seen an error message like this come up many
times. This one is for Firefox. It tells you
that it can’t trust that the site is secure.
Why? Generally you see this error because
there is a mistake in certificates. Take,
for example, the host at Stanford my research
group runs, sing.stanford.edu. It has a few
other names, such as tinyos.stanford.edu.
Stanford provided me with a certificate that
says that these names are associated with
the server’s public key. But if I added
a new name to Stanford’s DNS, such as “bad-sing.stanford.edu”,
then the certificate wouldn’t have this
name. If you tried connecting to bad-sing.stanford.edu
over https, you’d receive this error, because
the certificate doesn’t cover that name.
So you often run into this error when someone
has aliases for a host, or issued a certificate
for an old name and hasn’t updated it. But
it could be an adversary, running a different
server and trying to convince you it’s trustable.
Generally speaking, seeing this error means
someone has misconfigured their system for
security. But when I see an error like this
I never say OK -- even if it’s just a little
mistake, given how subtle and hard security
is, and how obvious this mistake is, I don’t
want to trust the server.
And so this is how things work today. Everyone
trusts a few signing authorities and knows
their public keys. These keys are hard-baked
into your browser or operating system -- a
good reason to check your programs for integrity!
Here, let’s take a look at the keys installed
in my Mac. I open up applications, utilities,
keychain access, select certificates. They
they are --
the certificates hard-baked into the OS. You
can see a bunch from Apple, and there’s
Verisign.
These root authorities can then sign keys
for other parties. For example, let’s go
to google. I’m accessing google over https.
I’ve also installed a plugin into Firefox,
called CipherFox, that lets me look at certificate
details. I can click on the lock and now see
the certificate. You can see that www.google.com
is signed by the Google Internet Authority,
which is in turn signed by the GeoTrust global
Certificate Authority. Signing authorities
are often called CAs, for Certificate Authorities.
But realize that all a certificate says is
that someone testifies that a host has this
key! If there’s an adversary along the certificate
chain, then you could be fooled. It turns
out there are actually different kinds of
certificates for this reason. Some, such as
the one I have on sing.stanford.edu, doesn’t
require much more than filling out a web form.
Others requires paper validation and possibly
meeting someone in person.
This is how TLS/HTTPS works today, when you
see the padlock in our browser bar. You connect
to a server, and it provides a certificate
with its public key. If the certificate chain
ends in a root CA that you trust, that is,
already have the public key for so can verify
its signature, then you trust the key in the
certificate and can encrypt data to the server.
I’ll explain the details of this in the
TLS video.