>> Phil: So Here I am with Jon Peterson Who's
an old friend of mine and kind of an important
person in the internet.
Maybe you
should start with how did you get involved
>> Jon: That's a good question I Lucky enough
to be around with the dot com boom in the
late 1990's
When the small startup that I worked for in
boston was acquired by level 3 communications,
they moved me out to scenic boulder colorado.
Uh where phil actually was as well at roughly
the same time. And Level 3 is of course one
of the tier one, backbone providers of the
internet,
and they have a profound engagement with the
internet engineering task force, one of the
standards bodies that helped make the internet,
that defined how the internet works.
And when I got there, that was one of the
things that most attracted me about this oppurtinity.
Would be the ability to really work with the
top minds that were out there.
So I started attending the IETF. I had been
on mailing lists amd things like that before
hand but I first started attending when I
worked at level 3.
I just found it to be a fascinating community,
that had such intellectual rigor, that had
so much interest in trying to find the right
solution. You don't go to the IETF and represent
a company, you go there and you put forward
what you think is the best idea.
And it is a place where there really is a
meritocracy of ideas. Once you get the [inaudible]
you discover there are all of these other
dimensions to internet governance.
If you are there at the IETF, you may end
up dealing with the W3C if you work on application
because they have responsibility for the standards
associated with the world wide web.
You may end up working with ICANN, people
that do domain name assignments. And I kind
of made the rounds of these interenet governance
circles and working on the intersection between
technology and public policy, tends to take
you to some pretty interesting places.
>> Phil: Well, so the first work that you
did was SIP -- the session initiation protocol.
Do you want to talk about this IP telephony
and kind of what this path was to where SIP
is today and what your part in it was?
>> Jon: Sure, it's important to remember that
in the early 1990's, there really wasn't anything
like voice over ip, not really.
There was some experimental technologies that
people had rigged up and ran on some of the
unix environments in labs in California,
but there was no commerical product that you
could buy that would let you talk to someone
over the internet.
Remember as well that in the mid 1990's you
know a lot of computer's didn't have adequate
sound cards, there certainly wasn't adequate
video capture.
Network interfaces were spotty at best and
the actual commercial service that you could
purchase at the consumer level were -- to
get enough bandwidth to communicate for something
like voice over IP didn't exist.
Sometime around 1996, 1997 we hit a sweet
spot where the computing power was there,
the network was there, computers tended to
have the right interfaces to do this so we
started to see the first voice over IP offerings
around that time.
When I started working on this around 1997,
I worked on the infrastructure dimension of
this. The startup that I worked for in boston
was focussed on the particular problem of
how you could take a traditional telephone
switch and these telephone switches made by
nortell and eusend, they were more of these
expensive, monolithic, special purpose devices
that required a ton of operational oversite.
They didn't really fit into the internet software
model or the internet disruptive innovation
that we all associate with technology today.
So I was one of the first people to work on
something called soft switching. The idea
that you could take a general purpose computer,
take a solaris box a unix box and put the
control plane logic for a telephone switch
on a box like that and just have it control
telephone circuits, just literally switching
from one customer from another.
To handle those instead of dumb devices. And
this created an extremely disruptive influence
on the telephone switch market and today,
I think it's safe to say, that it has become
dominant, that you can't really buy things
like these nortell switches anymore except
on the secondary market.
You own one today and you need replacement
parts for one, you pretty much have to get
them on E-Bay
Once you build a soft switch, now naturally
some of these unix boxes have internet access
then you need ways for these switches to talk
to one another to be able to coordinate calls
that don't use the outdated x25 based ss7
systems that are used in the traditional telephone
network.
And thats where tools like SIP started to
come into play.
A lot of my early work on the Session Initiation
Protocol was on telephony replacement, was
on how you would not touch that traditional
network but how you would instead do all of
this over the internet, how you would set
up calls at the end and um this started to
be an important dimension of adopting Voice
over IP Protocols.
It's one thing to build a tool that lets you
talk to anybody else who happens to have a
good computer, right in the 1990's when people
didn't have the technology that you have.
It was a very different matter to actually
call someone on the telphone network.
And these soft switched became bridges between
people in the traditional network and people
in the VOIP space.
But these have been essential going forward
to how VOIP has become successful, to the
ability for programs like, say, skype today,
to be able to call out from your PC to someone
who has a normal ground line [inaudible] phone.
>> PHIL: and so one of the things that you
worked on in sort of the more refined versions
of SIP was sort of it's security model. How
do you actually secure the signal in the protocol.
So as I'm sure you can imagine given some
of the recent events in uh the internet with
respect to the Snowden releases.
This is kind of an interesting question, do
you see something about the implications of
stuff like SIP and security with resoect to
then like PSTN, wiretapping laws, those sorts
of questions? Where do you think this is going
or how is it different?
>> Jon: [laugh] Big question. Yeah so I do
recall that when we were building the RFC
for SIP, RFC3261 we basically drew straws
for who was going to draw straws for who was
going to do what parts and I got to do the
review of how SIP operated with a one paragraph
statement
I got to do adressing, I got to do user behavior
and then I drew the straw to do security.
And I said OK I have a security background
this shouldn't be too difficult and the initial
planned one section on security in SIP actually
ended up being 4 chapters of the RFC
At the time this was the largest RFC ever
published and SIP Security has always been
a problem child. And um these revelations
obviously put the ietf and people who develop
standards in a very interesting position.
You know no less of an authority than Bruce
Snyder who is one of the greatest minds today
thinking about security has formally called
on the ietf to drop what it's doing and to
refocus all of its efforts in our upcoming
meeting which will be in vancouver on how
we are going to resolve the problems that
have been raised by prism.
And we studied the privacy properties of these
protocols, the security properties of these
protocols very extensively.
I'm as convinced now as I ever was that we
made a lot of compromises in the SIP security
becuase they were necessary for it to be adopted
in the marketplace.
It'd be great to design protocol that had
built-in security that can guarantee integrity
and confidentiallity between one end point
that is trying to make a call and another
endpoint that is trying to make a call.
As soon as some intermediaries are playing
some role in the delivery of that. As soon
as something needs to help you to find the
right endpoint, and this dynamic capability
that SIP has to allow you to -- you know if
I wanted to have five devices that were to
my SIP name: a deskphone my cell phone an
iPad, various other devices, They all need
to connect to some server somewhere that will
be responsible for routing traffic to them.
The degree to which that server has access
to signalling, has access to who's calling
me, what are the media streams that are going
to be set up and what are the IP endpoints
that the media is going to be sent between.
We could have done more to protect that with
the design of SIP. And I think if we had,
we wouldn't be talking about SIP right now
because it wouldn't have succeeded enough
for it to even be noteworthy.
>> Phil: so, Can you talk about, so Sip Might
be a protocol that most people don't realize
they are using or about where it is being
used. Do you want to talk a little about where
it has been succesful and where it has been
adopted?
>> Jon: Sure. So I mentioned Skype, you do
Skype in or Skype out, Skype's internal protocol
is converted into SIP for transfer to a gateway
and then go to the telephone network.
Um basically, if you use a VOIP service for
a land line in your house, that comes from
either FiOS or a cable provider that, surely
SIP is going to be used in the background.
The third generation cell phones, things that
are 3g pt based all use SIP inside them.
Now these networks, especially we talk about
mobile phones and about the networks we see
and the cable NSOs and so on, they use a version
of SIP that is relatively archetecturally
similar to the telphone network.
They in fact applied the protocol machinery
of SIP to generate a system that has many
of the same properties that the telephone
network has. And this too is a fundamental
tradeoff -- the design of these things.
I would love to see a SIP that was much less
dependent on the network elements shaping
traffic and deciding based on that. If it
were much more driven by the end points.
This is just kind of the fundamental end to
end principle of the internet. That you want
to have the smarts be at the end points. You
don't want to have an intermediary have to
understand what the end points want to do.
It shouldn't get in their way, it shouldn't
prevent them from negotiating. In fact, If
I made up a great new codec tomorrow and I
have copy and you have a copy that sits on
our two machines, I don't want that thing
in the middle of the network to have to know
anything about that codec for us to connect
and use it.
The realities though of how these things actually
get implemented, especially when you are doing
something as complex as the act of replacing
the telephone network.
Replacing a more than a century old system
with its reliability constraints with its
emergency services implications. So where
you go when you call 911
Just getting the basic services you associate
with this right. It requires you to make compromises
and I can't say that I'm always proud in retrospect
of the compromises we needed to make for the
protocol to be successful.
But, I do acknowledge in retrospect that if
we had pushed back on some of those compromises,
it certainly would have led to the death of
the protocol. As people who design standards,
this is a heart breaking thing. That you come
up against time and time again.
Now, we can be smarter about this and I think
that if there is a silver lining to these
increasingly disturbing revelations that are
coming out about widespread surveillance in
the Internet. It might create the political
veil to see a change in what we can get consensus
for and, hopefully, what we can get people
to be willing to deploy.
You now I believe that when you go to the
IETF and it is consensus based, there are
things that we can get consensus to do that
I think would be very radical at this point.
Because the people that go to the IETF are
so well informed are so energized are so interested
in individual liberties.
I would hate to see the IETF, though, to become
an organization that is developing standards
that never see the light of day, because it
has swung to far in this direction. So it
is very difficult for us to understand what
the right direction is, for us to chart at
this point.
>> Phil: Interesting. So I'd like to wind
back a little bit and where how you mentioned
sort of building the first soft switch and
how all the logic was in a general purpose
computer then in I guess a Sun box. Do you
see sort of a parallel between that and software
defined networking today? Where we see that
sort of transition maybe happening in the
internet? And some of the methods currently
behind SDN?
>> Jon: I certainly see many parallels. I'm
not sure those parallels will play out exactly
the way because companies like Cisco and Juniper
would not stand to be disrupted by this the
same way that Nortel and Eusend were in the
90's.
They are more agile companies, they are companies
that are taking these technologies and trying
to figure out a middle path. For instance
the is the I2RS the interface to the routing
system, a standard proposal circulating in
the IETF now.
It's very different from the very low layer
software defined networking approach that
we see in say the open networking foundation,
but it is nonetheless a way that software
can interact with it and help higher level
routing decisions get made.
I think the routing vendors view this as one
tool among many that will help decide how
packets are going to be forwarded.
They are figuring out ways in other words
to subsume this.
That will allow their device to take advantage
of the strengths of this but without necessarily
a road in the market control. And the lengthy
install base that they have of the maintenance
tools and so on that have proven so successful
to the internet in the past.
I don't know that core routers have that to
the degree that old telephone switches did
that impeded innovation in the network. And
that was another real driver for soft switching
was that these telephone switches were so
[inaudible] that that had no programability,
they had no sophisticated interfaces that
you could use to modify their behavior without
doing open heart surgery.
The situation is very different for core routers
but the parallels, they do stand. I wouldn't
dismiss it out of hand and I certainly know
people who work for major router vendors who,
if you find them at the bar at the right hour,
will cry on your shoulder about exactly their
concerns about this.
It is a real challenge for that business.
>> Phil: If you were to look at all the different
pieces of work, so how many working groups
are in the ietf today?
>> Jon: Off the top of my head I'm not sure
I could say. Order of 100
>> Phil: If you were to think what's something
you'd suggest to somebody, "Hey this is something
you should keep your eye on. This is something
that I think is some of the most interesting
work going on in the internet." So stuff which
is currently in progress and really might
significantly change what the network is like
in three or so years. Where would you suggest
looking?
>> Jon: Well actually that I2RS group is something
that is very interesting right now.
There is a new effort that has just been spotted
that's unclear if it's going to be a working
group or not, it's called per-pass, which
is the IETF's forum for discussing prism.
For discussing how these security things could
be addressed.
There are already some proposals that are
circulating there that are really about structural
changes about how the ICANN process would
work. Should standards be the new bar to obviate
the increasingly very real concerns that are
coming to light about all of this.
If you were coming to Vancouver this time,
these are certainly things I'd point you to.
There are things that I happen to be working
on That I think are very interesting and pratical
that might not extend to exactly that level
but I continue to be very interested in CDNs
and the degree of traffic that is now being
directed by content distribution networks.
We're doing a lot of work today on understanding
intefaces for how CDNs express their coverage
areas, how CDNs can advertise services that
they provide, in order to allow collaboration
or peering among CDNs. To make more optimal
selections among CDNs.
I think this will have potentially tremendous
impact on the efficiency of internet traffic.
It will alleviate some of the bottlenecks
with more and more video and content in the
internet. That's a personal pet project of
mine.
And I'm also still working on somethings at
the intersection of the Telephone network
and the internet. One thing that's been a
major issue, you know robo-calling has become
an increasing problem as the internet and
the telphone network have become more and
more interconnected.
And right now I'm looking at how we can do
better identity services, so it is harder
to spoof calls, so it's easier to figure out
who is responsible for a telephone call that
is coming off of the internet before it hits
the PSDN as the numbers for this are just
going up and up.
The FTC and the FCC are profoundly interested
in finding a solution for this. This is being
discussed in congressional subcommitees already
as it is going on in the IETF so I think that
is a place where we can really make a difference.
And it is something that is hurting consumers
and it's something that will be a big deal
going forward.
>> PHIL: So if we stop receiving robo-calls,
we have you to thank?
Great well thanks for stopping by, thanks
for your time and...
>> Jon: My pleasure
>> Phil: And thank you