In this unit, you learned about some of the
major applications in the internet today and
how NATs, or network address translators can
complicate them.
nowadays, a new NAT you buy tends to be reasonably
well behaved, but there's still many old NATs
out there that have some troublesome or difficult
behavior.
Let's start with NATs. In this unit, you learned
what a network address translator is and how
it works. It's a router that allows many device
to share one IP address.
It does this by rewriting packets as they
pass through it. A NAT device has an external
interface to communicate with the outside
world, which has a publicly routable IP address.
It manages a set or subnet of private internal
addresses. For example, all the IP addresses
starting with 10. or all of the IP addresses
starting with 192.168.
The NAT device assigns one of the private
addresses to itself. For example, 192.168.0.1
and then assigns the remaining addresses to
the devices in the internal network.
If you have a home wifi router, it probably
acts as a NAT device as well, using the 192.168.
subnet of IPv4 addresses.
You learned that when a NAT routes a packet,
from the internal network to the external
internet, it modifies the packet header so
that it looks like it is coming from the NAT's
single external IP.
Its essentially multiplexing all the packets
from different internal addresses on to one
external IP Address.
For this to work, it needs a way to distinguish
the reply packets flowing in the other direction,
so that it can correctly forward them to the
correct internal device.
NAT devices do this by modifying the transport
port numbers to encode which internal device
the transport flow comes from. This means
a NAT is aware of the transport layers and
modifies them, too.
When a packet arrives from the external internet,
it checks if the transport port number matches
a mapping to an internal device.
If it does, it modifies it and forwards it
to the internal network.
Because a NAT typically only creates a map
from internal ip addresses to external port
numbers, when packets are flowing towards
the outside world, it doesn't know what to
do with packets showing up from the outside
world that are trying to reach an internal
device.
To some, this is a security benefit. By default,
you can only create outgoing connections,
protecting your internal devices from attack
from the outside world.
But to others, this is a nuisance because
you can't initiate a new TCP connection from
the outside world to the inside.
The NAT will drop the TCP Syn packet. There
are a lot of different NAT designs and there
are many ways to map the ip addresses to out
going port numbers and we saw some of them
in this unit, each with its own complications.
The general consensus is that simple, less
restrictive mappings are better, because they
give the appearance of end-to-end connectivity.
You also learned about some of the techniques
that people use to work around NATs like NAT
hole punching and simultaneous open, but the
main take away from this unit is NATs make
it hard to deploy applications in the internet
that require a TCP connection to be setup
from the outside world to devices behind NATs
and it's hard to deploy new transport protocols,
because the NAT devices don't know how to
process them.
In general, when people have created new transport
protocols, they either masquerade as TCP or
run on top of UDP.
You learned about the Domain Name System,
an application that uses UDP. On one hand,
its critical infrastructure, without which,
the internet would be much less useful.
On the other, it's just an application.
You learned that the basic idea of the Domain
Name System is that you can map heirarchical
names, such as www.stanford.edu, to different
kinds of information called records.
For example, you can ask what the IPv4 address
of www.stanford.edu is. You can ask what the
name server for stanford.edu is.
You can ask what the mailserver for cs.stanford.edu
is.
You learned that the Domain Name System works
through a heirarchy of servers. For Example,
to find the address for www.stanford.edu,
you first ask a root server, where you can
find out about the .edu, then ask .edu where
you can find stanford and finally ask stanford
for the address of www.stanford.edu.
Each of these records, the Address records
and the nameserver records, on each step can
be cached, often for a long while to reduce
load.
To make this caching work even better, often
many clients share a resolver, a computer
who queries the Domain Name Service for you.
That way, it can cache all of those results
and share them among clients. That way, all
of stanford only needs to do a single lookup
for Google, as long as the record lasts, rather
than having every laptop contacting Google's
DNS servers.
HTTP is the hypertext transfer protocol. It
runs on TCP. We've been using the same version
of HTTP, that's version 1.1, for almost 20
years now. Basically, it's unchanged. You
learned that HTTP is a request / response
protocol.
Both the request and the response are in ASCII
text, which is useful because it's very easy
to read.
One of the big improvements in HTTP1.1 was
something called keep alive. In HTTP1.0, each
request was made on a separate TCP connection.
So to download a page with 40 resources on
it, your client had to open 40 TCP connections.
HTTP 1.1 allows a client to request many resources
all on the same connection.
This means, less time is spend in the three-way
handshake, and the TCP connection has more
time to grow its connection window.
You learned ways to roughly calculate the
download time for downloading a complete page
and all of its resources.
Using this, you saw how connection setup time
could be a significant overhead for TCP connections
that transfer only a little bit of data.
Finally, you heard a little bit about SPDY,
the protocol that has become the basis of
HTTP/2.0.
The Third Application you learned about was
BitTorrent. Like HTTP, BitTorrent uses TCP,
but unlike HTTP, which is a client server
application, BitTorrent is a large collection
of collaborating clients called a swarm. Use
BitTorrent to share large, say 100MB files.
BitTorrent breaks these files up into small
chunks called pieces.
You learned that each BitTorrent client opens
connections to scores, sometimes as many as
100 other clients. A client request data from
other clients using a rarest-first policy,
So it tries avoiding a piece disappearing
from the swarm and also to remove bottlenecks.
You also learned that while BitTorrent is
happy to request data from lots of peers,
it is very careful about whom it sends data
to. BitTorrent tries to setup an incentive
system where you want to contribute data and
let others transfer from you.
So the way it works is a node will send data
to the P peers who are sending it the most
data. That way, the best way to get data from
a peer is to send it data.
To better figure out who those best peers
are, BitTorrent occaisionally starts sending
to a new random peer in order to discover
new potential partners in exchange.
This algorithm, is called the tit for tat
algorithm.
So you have seen three major applications
on the Internet today. You've seen how the
simple abstractions that UDP and TCP provide,
can be used in complex ways for very interesting
applications.
You also learned how Network Address Translators
can complicate applications by making it hard
to discover peers or open connections as well
as a few techniques for working around them.
You now should have a good understanding of
some of the techniques you can use and challenges
you might run into when you go out and develop
the next generation of network applications.