Continuing on a theme of routing, by now,
you've learned about the basics of
routing, distance vector and link state
algorithms and how routing works in the
internet.
The structure of the internet autonomous
systems, the hierarchy of those autonomous
systems, exterior routing protocols,
interior routing protocols.
So, in this video, I'm going to tell you
about the specific exterior routing
protocol but all autonomous system must be
used when connecting to their neighbors.
That's BGP or the border gateway protocol
currently in version four.
Okay, lets start with the basics of BGP4.
BGP is not a link state or a distance
vector routing protocol.
Instead, it's used, it uses what's called
a path vector.
And the way this works is that the BGP
routers at the boundary of each autonomous
system will advertise a complete path.
And that path has a list of AS's that you
passed through in order to reach a
particular destination prefix.
This is also called the AS path.
And that's the, the path vector.
So, an example of a advertisement might
look like this.
Says the, the network prefix 171.64/16 can
be reached via the path going through
these three AS's, one, five, and thirteen.
So that might be an, an example of
advertisement that, that, the BGP might
advertise to one of its neighbors.
The consequence of sending out a path, is
that paths with loops are very easily
detected locally.
You just look for repetition of an AS and
then you can simply remove those, or just
completely ignore those advertisements.
And that, that makes it very easy to find
and eliminate loops.
But perhaps the most important feature of
BGP is that local policies that are
private and secret to a particular
autonomous system, can pick the preferred
path among those that are advertised to
it.
So, if a number of neighboring autonomous
systems advertise different paths to reach
the same prefix, then the local policy can
pick whichever one it chooses, whichever
one it wants.
It's not accountable to anyone else when
it's picking that.
Finally, when a link or a router fails,
the path is withdrawn just like an
advertisement comes with it's just like
the one above.
A withdraw would look very similar, in
which it would say, this particular prefix
can no longer be reached via this path.
So, BGP4 starts with a relationship
between customers and providers.
Let's take a look at this.
So, let's start with drawing a particular
AS.
This would be the provider AS.
The one that's the, the one sitting above
in the, in the hierarchy.
And then the customer AS sitting below.
The relationship between them is although
traffic can flow to or from the customer
through the provider in either direction
and may go off through multiple exit
points,
Because of this specific relationship
between them, and that relationship is one
of provider to customer.
It has specific implications.
And one of them is that the customer will
always pay the provider to carry its
packets.
So, if we're thinking of, of how money
flows,
Money is flowing up in this direction
here.
The customer is praying, paying the
provider in order to carry its packets.
So, this hierarchy of customers to
providers continues.
And so, if we have multiple AS's, so let's
draw some AS's here and some down here.
These could be the axis AS's that we saw
before.
Then this relationship between them, of
provider towards customer, could go like
this.
And what that tells us is that the that
the,
As before, the money is actually flowing
in the other direction, for settlement
charges between them.
And IP traffic can go in the following in
the following way.
So, IP traffic could flow from a from a
customer up to its provider, up to its
provider down through its customer and
down through its customer down here.
Similarly, a something from here, traffic
from here could flow through this way. If
there was another, there was another
relationship, for example, this
particular, this particular one access AS
down here had relationships with providers
above it in two places,
Traffic is allowed to flow through any of
these any of these paths.
So, it could flow down this way or down
this way.
In general,
They will not flow through a an, an
intermediate at the same level.
And we'll see an example of that of that a
little bit later.
So, this,
The reason for telling about this customer
provider hierarchy is we're going to see
it show up a little bit later in the
policies that BGP uses.
And basically, the peering relationship is
as follows.
So, looking at this example here, where we
have, just as before, we have three AS's
here, here and here, which are the
providers and then three down here, that
are the customers of those and, and the
key here is telling us what the provided
customer relationship.
And these ones up here are peers of each
other.
So, in general, a peer cannot be a transit
for its other peers.
In other words, this particular path
that's shown here, the black-dotted line
is not allowed because it's going through
this one, this, this peer.
That's because typically, the relationship
here between two peers is settlement free.
There's no dollars flowing across here.
So, peers do not provide transit between
peers.
Now, let's take a look at BGP messages,
and then we'll look at the policies that
BGP implements.
So, there are basically four types of BGP
message.
There's an open message to establish a BGP
session.
There's a keep alive, in order to provide
a handshake at regular intervals.
That's just basically an occasional
message just to be able to check that the
BGP session is still alive between two
routers that are connected to each other.
And there's a notification to shut down a
peering session.
So, these three here, open, keep alive and
notification, are basically the ones that
keep the session alive.
The ones that actually announce and then
withdraw routes are the update messages.
And these are the, the most important
ones.
They announce new routes or they withdraw
ones that were previously announced.
And these are the, the, the, the, the, we
saw an example of that earlier with the
advertisement of the particular path for a
prefix.
An announcement basically consists of the
pre, the prefix and then the path
attributes.
So, it'll be the path of the AS's and then
attributes associated with it and we'll
see an example of that now.
So, the path at attributes are the next
hop information where you go in order to
be able to use this otherwise, who it is
that's advertising this, this particular
path to S,
The particular path AS path.
So, that's the sequence of AS's that you
would go through. And then various other
things the local preference and the multi-exit
discriminator and there,
There is other parameters that are passed
as well, that tell us information that
would allow us to pick the pick the, the
particular path when we receive multiple
advertisements from different peers.
So, these are used to select amongst
multiple options for paths because we may
hear from multiple peers of how to reach a
particular destination prefix.
And basically, when we have a choice,
The, the, the sequence goes something like
this.
So,
We start with the, the highest local
preference.
This is the highest local preference,
we'll see an example of that in a moment.
It's a local preference that tells us how
we enforce relationships we might prefer
customer routes over peer routes and we'll
see an example of that in, in a moment.
If the local preference, which is
essentially our local policy,
If that doesn't tell us which particular
path to pick when we have some choice,
The next one is we'll simply pick the
shortest autonomous system path.
You know, it's the shortest path to a
destination.
And then, there are various other
parameters that we might pick, they're all
to do with helping us do good traffic
engineering.
What this means is that we will tend to
send traffic over, over lightly loaded
paths and will cause less congestion in
the network.
But the ones that we most, are most
interested, interested in are highest
local preference and the shortest AS path.
If all of these fail to distinguish or
identify a particular path that we should
choose, then we simply go with the lowest
router ID.
In other words, that's the lowest.
Router ID of one of our neighbors and that
is essentially throwing up our hands in a
means of breaking ties if there is no
other way to pick between advertised
routes.
Let's take a look at how the autonomous
system path, the AS path attribute might
work.
So, we'll look at an example of how we
might pick the, the, the shortest, the
shortest path.
So, let's say, that we are sitting over
here, at this particular autonomous system
here.
And we're hearing about a prefix that
originated down here.
Here's the prefix,
135.207.0.0/16.
And it originated from here and so it will
initially be advertised up here and then
it will be advertised up here.
When it gets advertised here, it will say,
you can reach this particular prefix
135.207.0.0/16.
You can reach it via AS7018 followed by
6341.
And then, that will flow around here and
then they have added one AS to the path
and so it gets advertised here.
So, by the time it comes down here, we
will find out that the prefix 135.207/16
can be reached through 1129,
1755, and so on until we get to 7018.
And likewise there'll be an advertisement
that will come around this path that will
say, hey, I can get you to 135.207/16
through the sequence 7018,3549, so it's
over all a much shorter path.
So, in this particular case,
If I haven't got a higher local
preference, then the, the router will say,
this is the shorter path and so I will
pick as my favorite to send packets this
way in order to reach this particular
prefix.
And so, it will install that decision
locally in its routers that says, when I
see this, a packet with this prefix, then
I'm going to send it out this direction,
and that's my choice.
There could be many, many choices so let's
look at an example here.
So, in this particular network, Frank's
Internet Barn is trying to, is trying to
decide which route it should pick in order
to reach this prefix 13.13/16 which is
down here in AS1.
The nature of the relationship here is
that Frank is connected directly to a
provider, AS4.
It's connected to a peer, AS3 and it's
connected to a customer, AS2 which in turn
is connected to another customer down
here.
So, we could have a number of different,
local preferences and it might say, I'm
going to,
I'm going to give a local preference of
let's say, 100 to my peer, or the customer
or my provider to customer relationship.
In other words, I'm going to give
preference of 100 to routes that are
advertised by my customers to me.
And maybe, I just say, I'll give a local
preference of 80 to ones that are received
from my provider.
And 90 to ones that are received from my
peer.
What that basically says is, if I hear a
route, that is, arrives from my customer,
I'm going to take that very seriously,
because that's a paying relationship
and I would prefer to send it to my
customer rather than sending it over to a
provider where I'm going to have to pay.
So, I'm going to give preference from if
they are coming up through the from, from
the customer.
My second favorite choice is from my peer
because I don't pay there either because
its presumably settlement free.
But where I actually have to pay for the
traffic is to the providers. So, if I hear
a route that's advertised down here, I'm
going to not like you to pick that unless
that's my only, that's my only choice.
So, basically I'm saying in terms of my
choice, customer,
Customer advertised routes are more better
than peer advertised routes better than
provider advertised routes.
And this is a pretty common for,
It's it, it's not baked into BGP.
You can just set the preference values to
do this.
You could also set the preference values
to be the opposite, although that would be
pretty unlikely.
,, when these, these advertisements are
going to arrive for this particular AS,
They're going to up through here to Frank.
They're going to come up through here to
Frank.
And they're going to come this way to
Frank is going to pick the one that goes
down through the customer.
So, when he sends traffic, he's going to
send traffic down this way to AS1, because
that's his favorite path, because that's
the one with the lowest local preference.
So, local preference is the one that I use
first.
And if that doesn't tell me my, my choice,
then I'll pick the shortest AS path.
And then, I'll walk down that list that
was on the previous slide.
So, in summary all autonomous systems in
the internet must connect using BGP4,
that's the exterior protocol that they
must use to talk to their peers, or to
their neighbors, the routers of their
neighboring autonomous system.
Bgp4 is a path vector algorithm.
That means a list of the autonomous
systems is sent along with every
advertised prefix and this allows loops to
be detected very easily and for a router
to examine that path and choose whether it
wants to use it or not, depending on its
policies.
Bgp4 has a rich and complex interface to
let autonomous systems choose a local
private policy based on all sorts of
things.
You could, you could spend a whole quarter
learning about nothing else than how BGP
works and what the consequences are.
There have been many, many papers written
on the, on the consequences of these
policies.
So, each AS decides a local policy for
traffic engineering security and any other
private preferences that it might have so
that it can choose amongst advertised
paths coming from different neighboring
autonomous systems.
That's the end of this video about BGP.