In the first video on packet switching, I
told you about what packet switching is
and why it was used for the internet.
Packet switching is gonna feature very
prominently throughout this course, so
we're gonna spend quite a bit of time on
it.
And many of the properties of the Internet
follow directly from the choice of packet
switching.
So in this video I'm gonna give you some
useful definitions for propagation delay
and packetization delay, and we're gonna
use those definitions to come up with an
expression for the end-to-end delay of a
packet across a network.
I'm also gonna tell you about queueing
delay.
And how it makes the end to end delay
unpredictable.
So, let's start with some useful
definitions.
We'll start with the definition of propagation
delay.
So, the propagation delay is the time that
it takes a single bit of information to
travel over a link at propagation speed c.
So, look at the picture here and you see
we have the, the computer on the left and
we are going to consider the time that it
takes for a bit to propagate from the one on
the left to the one on the right.
That time, the propagation delay or t sub
l is simply l over c.
So the propagation delay is simply
determined by how long the link is,
L in our case.
And the speed that a bit travels.
C.
We use the variable C in most of the links
we're interested in because C, the speed
of propagation, is very close to the speed
of light.
For example, in, in a twisted pair of
electrical cables, a bit propagates at
about 70 percent of the speed of light,
and then in an optical fiber, the speed of
propagation is a tiny bit slower.
In most of our examples, we'll assume that
the bit propagates at two times ten to the
eight meters per second, which is, which
is close enough.
There you go.
There's the bit going along the link.
Let's have a look at that again.
So it's the speed at which, or the time
which it takes to propagate over the link.
So, for example.
If we were considering how long it would
take a bit to travel a 1,000 kilometres or
a 1,000,000 metres in an optical fiber
where the propogation speed was two times
ten to the eight metres per second.
Well, t sub l is 1,000 times ten to the
three divided by two times ten to the
eight or five milliseconds.
In a little bit, we're gonna look at some
examples and you're gonna do some examples
in the multiple choice exercises embedded
in the video.
Notice that the propagation delay doesn't
depend on the data rate of the link.
Doesn't matter if the link is running at
one kilobits per second or, or ten
gigabits per second.
The propagation delay is just a function
of the speed of propagation of each bit
and the length of the cable.
Another useful definition is the
packetization delay.
This is the time from when the first bit of a
packet is put onto the link until the last
bit is put onto the link.
Let's take a look at an example here.
So see that packet there going on to the
link.
The time that it takes to put all of the
bits onto the link is gonna be a function
of the number of bits we're putting onto
the link, and the distance between them all.
The number of bits per second that we can
put onto the link.
So essentially the data rate of a link is
determined by how close together we can
pack the bits.
If for example, a link runs at one gigabit
per second, we can put onto, we can put
one bit onto the link every nanosecond.
We'll see in a later video about physical
links what actually limits the data rate
of a link.
So the packetization delay is determined
by how fast we can put bits on the link,
or the data rate R.
If a link runs at one kilobytes per
second, we can put 1000 new bits onto the
link every second.
If it runs at ten gigabits per second,
then we can put 10 billion bits onto
the link every second.
Then look at a couple of examples.
If we had a 64 byte packet, that's 512
bits.
It would take 5.12 microseconds to be
transmitted on to a 100 megabits-per-second link.
Why is that?
Well, t sub p = p over r.
So p, in our case, is 64 times eight, 512, divided by
r.
And r would be 100 times ten to the six.
Another example.
A kilobit packet.
Takes 1.024 seconds to be transmitted onto a one kilobit per second link
So where did this 1.024 come from?
Well, this is useful, useful example here.
Because the one kilobit per second.
Sorry.
The one kilobit packet that we see here.
One kilobit when we're measuring a number
of bits in a packet or in memory.
One kilobit, as you know, is 1024, or two
to the power of ten.
So that's why we have 1.024 seconds in
order to transmit it or do a one kilobit
per second link.
So in this case it's a little bit
confusing.
One kilobit per second means 1,000 bits
per second, whereas one kilobit in the
packet is 1,024 bits.
This is standard throughout networking and
we'll see this happen over and over
again.
So notice that the, packetization delay.
Is only a function of the length of the
packet.
That's p here and the rate at which we can
put bits onto the link, or r bits per
second.
Makes no difference how long the link is
or how fast bits propagate
along it.
So next we're going to see how we can use
our two different types of delay to
determine the overall end-to-end delay.
That's the time it takes a packet to go
across a network from the source to the
destination.
So the end to end delay is the time from
when we send the first bit, on the first
link.
That would be over here.
Until the last bit, of the packet arrives
at the destination, B.
So, we can calculate the end to end delay
by adding up the propagation and
packetization delays on every link along
the path.
That is, we can look at those, those
numbers we calculated before, that how
long it takes the packet from the first
bit until, first bit is sent until the
last bit arrives on this link here.
And then we can add it to the time on
here, on here, and on here.
So, in our case that's gonna depend on the
length of the first link and the rate at
which it runs.
And then we can use our expressions to calculate the end to end delay.
And we're going to come up with an
expression that looks like this.
The end to end delay, t, equals the sum of,
the, first of all,
the delay here, which is the packetization
delay.
The time that it takes to put the packet
onto link.
And then the time that it takes for one
bit to propagate along that link.
So we're going to sum up all of those to
get the end to end delay.
Let's look at this in a little bit, a
little bit more example, because I think
it will become a bit clearer.
So in our example here, the packet is
gonna traverse four lengths.
So we're gonna repeat the process on every
link along the path.
And it's gonna look something like this.
Here we're taking a closer by stretching
out the links and the switches.
And remove the rest of the network, just
to make it a little bit clearer.
This here is a, a timeline.
And this timeline, with time increasing
from the left to the right, is gonna show
how bits propagate.
And how the whole, whole packet propagates
from A over to B.
So the first bit is gonna take L1 over
C, that's the length of that first link,
divided by the propagation speed.
It's gonna take that number of seconds to
propagate from A to S1.
So here we can see the bit starting from
here and then propagating along the link.
L1 over C is the time, and this is it
propagating the distance from A to S1.
After we sent the first bit, it's gonna
take P over R1 seconds until we can put
the last bit of the packet onto the link.
So after P over R1, we've put the last bit
onto the link.
And then at the time, L1C + P / R1.
That last bit will arrive at switch S1.
Okay.
So, at this point, by the time we get to
this point here, the entire packet has
arrived at S1.
So, Internet routers are what we call
store and forward devices.
What that means is that switch S1 is gonna
wait until the whole packet arrives, until
it looks up the address and decides where
to send it next.
It could, instead, start forwarding the
packet after it had just seen the header,
and not wait for the whole packet to
arrive.
That's something we call cut through
switching, but internet routers generally
don't do that.
In a later video, and in some of the
exercises, we'll see examples of cut
through packet switches.
But getting back to our example, which is
a store and forward network where every
switch is going to store and forward the
packets.
Switch one, S1, is gonna look at the
packet after its completely arrived, and
then it's gonna send it on to the next
link.
It's gonna send it on to S2.
So here we can see that packet going on
to, to S2.
So just as before, it takes L2/C
for the first bit to arrive at S2 and then
the last bit will arrive P/R2 seconds
later.
And we can just repeat this whole process
for each of the links in turn until we get
to B.
So the overall end-to-end delay expression
is just the sum of those from end to end,
which is the same expression we had
before.
Okay, so it turns out I've only told you
part of the story.
Let me tell you the rest of the story.
See, the thing about packet switching is
that your packets share the links with
packets from other users.
When several packets show up at the same
time wanting to go on the same link.
And you can see this here.
We've got packets coming from here, may be
from another link entering the packet
switch.
And from here coming into the packet
switch from another link.
All wanting to go on the outgoing link
from S2 to S3.
When this happens all of the packets are
gonna have to fight or contend for that
outgoing link.
So when several packets show up at the
same time, wanting to go on the same link,
in this case from S2 to S3.
Then some of the packets have to wait in
the router's queue.
And this little symbol here, see this
little red symbol here is the, the picture
that I'm gonna draw for a queue.
Some people call that a packet buffer.
In general that's a first come, first
serve queue, in which the packets are
gonna depart in the same order that they
arrive.
We're gonna say that the link from S2 to
S3 is congested, because there are lots of
packets queued waiting to travel along it.
The packet buffer helps prevent us from
having to drop any packets.
The bigger the buffer is the less likely
we are to have to drop a packet that wants
to travel across the link.
So these packet buffers.
They're going to be in all of the
switches.
Every packet switch has buffers, and
they're fundamental to packet switching.
If we didn't have packet buffers, then
we'd lose a packet every time two packets
showed up at the same time wanting to
travel across a link.
So packet buffers are our friends.
But the packet buffers themselves are
going to change our expression for the end
to end delay.
If our packet arrives and the, the queue
has some packets in it, then it's going to
delay the time that it can be forwarded
onto the next link.
Because it will have to wait for the
packets that are ahead of it to leave
first before our packet gets to go.
So, I've just shown this is, here is, q2
of t.
Meaning, it's going over the link from s2
and I've said it's q2 of t because, it's
gonna vary with time.
It's gonna depend on how many other
packets are showing up from other users.
So if there are three packets ahead of us,
we'll have to wait for three packetization
delays before it's our turn to go.
I've shown this just in one queue, of
course this could be in all of the
switches along the way it just makes the
figure a bit more complicated so I've just
shown it in queue two.
So our end to end delay now has a third
component to it.
It has in it the packetization delay that
we saw before.
That's P over R sub I.
Then it has the
Propagation delay over the link and then
it has this new expression QI of T which
is the delay of the packet in the queue
waiting for other packets.
And this could be zero if there are no
other packets of course but in general,
it's gonna be some non deterministic value
because we don't know whoever else is
sending packets at the same time.
So the most important thing to note here
is, everything is deterministic except the
queuing delay.
P over R sub I, LI over C, they're both
deterministic.
It's QI sub, QI of T, the queuing delay,
that is the variable component.
And to convince you that, really in
practice, there are.
There is variability.
I'm gonna show you an example in a moment.
One last thing.
So you may have noticed that, that I, that
I use the, the British spelling for
queuing.
That's not cuz I'm English but very common
in, in, when talking about the internet,
to spell queuing Q, U, E, U, E, I, N, G
seems like too many vowels, I know.
But this was the convention adopted by
Kleinrock, one of the pioneers and
inventors of the Internet back in the
1960s.
But you'll see both, both the UK and the
US spelling and that's just fine.
So in summary, is our overall expression
for the end-to-end delay.
It's taking into consideration the queuing
delay at each packet switch along the way.
It's really important to remember that the
queuing delay is unpredictable, it depends
on the traffic sent by other users in the
network.
As far as we're concerned the queuing
delay is a random variable, it's the only
random variable in our expression for end
to end delay.
Everything else is deterministic.
So in case you don't believe me, that the
end to end delay is unpredictable, we're
gonna measure it.
I'm gonna use a very widely used tool
called PING, P-I-N-G, to measure the end
to end delay between my computer and other
computers in the internet.
Ping is gonna measure this end to end
delay.
In fact, it's gonna measure the round trip
time, which is end to end, sum of the end
to end delay in both directions.
You'll find the PING command on your
computer.
And you can use it to repeat the
measurements I'm about to do on your own
computer.
And it's kind of a fun thing to do.
We can measure the delay of packet to
cross the internet using the ping command.
I'm gonna show you an example of the ping
command right now.
So, I'm going to ping from my computer to
princeton.edu.
Princeton is a university in New Jersey in the
United States.
It's about 4,000 kilometers or two and a
half thousand miles from where, where I
am.
And as I do this, you can see.
Over on the right hand side it's showing
me the time that it takes for the packets
that I sent to go to Princeton and back
again.
So let's see if I can highlight these so
if you see them.
Like, here, these are the times of the
packets to go there and back again.
So those numbers there are about 100
milliseconds, corresponding to the time
that it takes for a packet to go there and
back, or round trip time.
Let's see how that compares say with
if I ping to let's try the University of,
Tsinghua University in, in, Beijing in
China.
So you're gonna see that's a lot further
away, that's about 10,000 kilometers away
from me or about 6,000 miles.
You can see that the ping times are much
greater.
So if I can just highlight those, we can
see those, they're more like 200
milliseconds.
So I used ping to measure a few hundred
RTT values from my computer at Stanford to
Princeton, and as I said earlier, it's
about 4,000 kilometers or two and a half
thousand miles away.
The graph shows the CDF, that's the
cumulative distribution function for the
values that I measured.
So zero%, this means that none of the
values were below this value here which is
about 100 milliseconds.
And 100 percent of them were less than
let's say, 300 milliseconds.
A little hard to tell on this graph here.
So this shows the, the range and also the,
the variation in the, the values that I
measured.
And the overall variance is about the
variation is about 50 milliseconds.
And the, the 90 percent of the samples
fell between 100 and 120 milliseconds.
Now, let's look what happened when I
repeated the experiment from Stanford to
Tsinghua University which is in Beijing in
China.
So, a lot further away.
It's about 10,000 kilometers away or 6000
miles and as I would expect, the RTT
values are much larger because the
propagation delay is much higher.
But also notice that the RTT samples have
much greater variance.
They vary by a lot more.
Look at this value over here.
These, this range of values.
They're varying by a lot more than the
ones over the shorter length from Stanford
to Princeton.
So that variation here comes from the
queueing delay.
My packets are encountering more queues,
more congestion, more other users, more
other user's traffic when they're going
across the Pacific to, to China.
My packets meet other packets in the
router buffers along the way, and so they
get held up, they have to wait for longer,
and I guess probably because there are
more hops and more likely to encounter
other peoples' packets along the way.
With a range of about 200 milliseconds,
you know it's about 320 down here and
maybe they're going up to about 520, with
a range of about 200 milliseconds.
The queueing delay is making up almost
half of the overall end to end delay,
that's pretty high, in fact that's kind of
unusually high,
which is why I showed you this, as an example,
just to get a point across.
In summary, the end-to-end delay is
determined by three components.
The first is the propagation delay along
the links, which is determined by the
length of the links and the propagation
speed.
The second is the packetization delay,
which is determined by the length of the
packet and the data rate of each link.
The third is the queuing delay, which is
determined by the congestion and the
queuing delay in the buffers and the
routers along the path.
This is the end of the video on end-to-end
delay in packet switching.
In the next video, I will be explaining
what some of the consequences are of these
variable queuing delay, particularly in
real-time applications which frequently
use playback buffers to absorb this variation.