So let’s suppose we have a good block cipher.
How do we use it? Messages are typically longer
than one 64 or 128 bit block.
One straight-forward approach is something
called ECB, or electronic code book mode.
This is simple: we take our message M and
break it into blocks. We then encrypt each
one individually. So m1 becomes c1, m2 becomes
c2, etc. This is fast, because we can do them
all in parallel, something great on modern
multicore processors. Assuming that our encryption
algorithm is secure, then an adversary can’t
decrypt any block, and so our message is secure.
Futhermore, we can reuse our keys, since every
block encrypted with the cipher will be secure.
Simple, fast, and secure.
NOPE! It’s not secure at all. Using electronic
code book mode, an attacker will learn of
repeated plaintext blocks. Since encryption
is deterministic, then if M1 equals M2, C1
will equal C2. If we’re transmitting a sparse
file, for example, this is bad. An adversary
could see where the non-zero regions of the
file are. Here’s a visual example of the
problem, using an image of Tux. The center
image shows the result of encrypting the image
with ECB. Identical regions of the image,
such as the white space, show up identically,
and you can see a general outline of Tux.
The image on the right is more like what we
want, where there’s no pattern and an adversary
can’t learn anything from the ciphertext.
One way to achieve this desired degree of
confidentiality is Cipher Block Chaining,
or CBC mode. In CBC mode, you choose an initialization
vector IV, the same size as the block. You
XOR M1 with this initialization vector, and
encrypt it to produce C1. You then take C1
and XOR it with M2 before encrypting it to
produce C2.
If you use a key to encrypt only one message,
than IV can be zero. The basic danger is that
you don’t want to re-use an initialization
vector. Suppose you do. So you set IV to be
zero for one message, then reuse and IV of
zero for a second message. If the plaintexts
are identical, then the ciphertexts will be
identical, and you’ve leaked information
to the adversary.
If we use CBC mode on the Tux image, then
we compute the ciphertext on the right. So
problem solved. But again, for this to work
across multiple messages and remain secure,
you need to be careful with how you pick and
use initialization vectors.
Electronic code book and cipher block chaining
mode are just two ways to use block ciphers.
There are many more, with different properties,
strengths, and weaknesses. Cipher feedback
mode, for example, XORs the message with an
encryption of the prior ciphertext. This is
useful if your message isn’t a multiple
of the block size and you don’t want to
pad it with zeros. In ECB and CBC mode, you
pass the message block to encrypt so you can’t
then trim the ciphertext.
Or there’s output feedback mode, where you
repeatedly encrypt the initialization vector
and use it like a stream cipher. Or counter
mode, where you encrypt incrementing values
with the key and XOR them with message blocks.
This is easily parallelizable, but mean that
you can use a key for only one message, unless
you do something smart with the value i.
One final quiz. Let’s suppose we have a
shared secret key, which only you and the
other party know. You encrypt your messages
with a good cipher using CBC mode and transmit
these messages over the network. Are they
secure?