In another video about the basics of
routing, I told you about what multicast
routing is, in principle.
In this video, I'm going to be telling you
about a number of techniques related to IP
multicast.
So far we've assumed that all packets go
to a single destination, or that they're
unicast,
There are some applications where we want
packets to be duplicated to a number of
hosts, to a set of hosts.
So, for example, A might want to send to
B, C and X and E without sending to D.
For example, it could be a broadcast TV,
where B, C, X, and E are all watching the
same TV or radio station.
It could be a video conference among a
certain number of participants.
It could be automatic updates to a large
number of hosts and so on.
So, while we could easily send packets
one at a time to each destination as I
showed, it's natural to ask if the network
can or should do the replication for us.
So, for example, if the network was to
duplicate the packets.
R1 here and then, then it can more
efficiently deliver to the
end hosts.
A only sends one packet, yet the packets
are delivered correctly to all of the end
destinations.
So, in this video, I'm going to look at a
number of different techniques for
doing this.
I'm going to start with the, the general
techniques and principles and then move on
to the practice.
What is actually done in the internet.
So, we always already saw one way in which
packets could be delivered to a large
number of hosts with a rather simplistic
approach of flooding.
So, in flooding, I've got a source A
and it's sending through the network to a
to a number of routers.
Let's say, to B down here.
I said that if the network is, is
flooding,
If we use flooding as an approch to, to,
to reach B, then packets from A could
simply be replicated at each router along
the path by sending out every interface
except the one through which the packet
arrived.
So, packets from A could come down to this
first router, go up this way and this way
then when it gets to this
router, it could be sent out this way and
this way and likewise here and eventually,
clearly the packet is going to get
delivered to B.
In fact, it'll be delivered to every leaf
in the network.
The basic problem in the flooding is that when there are
loops in the topology, packets can loop
forever because when it gets packets
coming from this direction hit this
router,
This router will say, aha, the packet came
in through this interface, I'm going to
send out of all the interfaces except the
one through which it came and then, of
course, it's going to keep looping
forever.
So, we saw in the spanning tree protocol
how these loops were broken.
We don't look at a different way they can
be avoided in the first place and that
approach is called reverse path broadcast.
And this is the basis for the early
multicast methods that we used in the, in
the internet.
The first technique I'm going to be
describing is called reverse path
broadcast, also known as reverse past
forwarding.
It's a very clever technique that's widely
used and was, was used in the very first
internet multicast routing protocols and
it builds on a very simple observation and
that observation is that before A has even
started sending multicast, the, the
network will have already built a unicast,
minimum cost spanning tree covering all of
the hosts that A can reach.
And we saw how that was done in the
unicast routing protocols earlier.
So, for example R1 already knows how the
what the minimum cost spanning tree is for
all of the packets going towards A.
So, there is essentially a minimum cost
spanning tree in the network that has been
built by all of the routers together on
how to reach A.
So, A can use that as a loop-free method
in order to deliver packets to everybody
else.
So, first let me describe the broadcast
case which is like flooding but without
the loop packets
lasting forever.
So, imagine now that A is sending a packet
to everybody else.
And that packet is going to have an
address in it, and I'll talk, I'll talk
about the addresses later.
So, it's going to have a group address
corresponding to who it's sending to, but
it'll have the source address A in it.
And because this packet came from A, the
routers at each hop along the way can ask
the question, is the interface over which
this packet arrives?
So, this, this interface here.
Is it on the shortest path spanning tree
from me to A?
And you look can that up in its, in its
forwarding table to see whether, if it was
sending a unicast packet to A rather than
a multicast packet from A.
If it was sending a unicast packet to A,
is this the path?
This is the interface through which it
would depart from this router.
So, it looks up the address, the source
address in its table.
And it's going to look that up in its
forwarding table.
And if this is the interface through which
it would send it, if it was sending a
unicast, then it will accept it and send
it out of every other interface.
So, it will send it out of every other
interface.
Likewise, when it gets to R2, R2 will ask
the same question.
If it was sending a unicast packet to A,
is this the interface through which it
would send it?
The answer is yes, so therefore, it will
send it out of every other interface.
So, it's a little bit like flooding but
its asking a more detailed question, is
this the interface through which I would
send it if it was a unicast packet going
to A?
So, you can see here that R3 would also
ask the same question, and it would say,
yes, this is the interface through which I
would send it to A so therefore, I am
going to send it out all of the other
ports.
However, when this packet reaches R2, it
will come through this interface which is
not on the green shortest path tree back
to A. So therefore, R2 will drop that
packet.
It won't send it.
And you can see that it's just broken the
loop.
Same thing will happen over here at R8,
this is known on the green shortest path
tree so that packet will be dropped.
And you can convince yourself that there,
in fact, will be no loops because packets
will follow that spanning tree
that is already being built.
This is sort of a clever idea that you can
see why its called reverse path broadcast
because its using the spanning tree that
is in the opposite direction.
Now, this is all very well as a means for
broadcast but we're talking about
multicast.
In this particular case, the, the packet
would've been delivered to all of the end
hosts whereas, in fact, we wanted it to be
delivered to every end host except D.
That was the set of hosts that we were
trained to deliver to.
So, as a simple extension to this, there
is something that's, that's called pruning
and usually referred to reverse path
broadcast plus pruning, RPB plus pruning,
in which those routers that don't have any
connected hosts interested in receiving
the packet, so in our case, D is not part
of the multicast group.
So, R6 would send what's called a prune
message, which I'll just show as a dotted
line, so it'll send prune and say, hey, I
actually don't have any end hosts
interested in receiving this.
Please don't send me multicast packets for
this group address anymore.
And so, it will prune G and say, I have no
interest in this.
So, in this case this would then be
removed from the, from the reverse path
broadcast tree and now that tree will only
reach the end hosts that are interested in
it.
So, its a way of decreasing the
inefficiency of, of broadcast.
However, it clearly has the inefficiency
still that  to start with
every router will hear about it before
starts pruning. So, at very, very large
network, this is probably, this is
probably impractical.
So, in summary, reverse path
broadcast plus pruning packets are
delivered loop-free to every end host.
Routers with no
interested hosts attached to them will
send prune messages back towards the
source and, of course, they can use the
unicast address of the source, in order to
send that prune message.
So, it will follow the tree back towards
the source.
The resulting tree is the
minimum cost spanning tree from the source
to the set of interested hosts.
So, it's an efficient way, an efficient
tree that we end up with although the
method to get there is a little
inefficient, because we have to start by
communicating to all of the routers in the
network.
One question that, that you may be
wondering, do we build one tree or do we
build several trees?
In my example, I showed A wanting to
send to this set of destinations B, C,
X, and E.
But what if it's a video conference and
after A has spoken and, and sent packets
to everybody else, what if it's B's turn
to send?
What is, what is the tree, the multicast
tree that packets from B should follow?
So, going from B back to A again, they
would follow the same way.
B to C and B to X.
But going from B to E, it would seem more
likely that the packets would flow this
way.
In other words, the tree is specific to a
source.
The shortest path tree specific to a
source and that should be clear from my
previous example of the reverse path
broadcast in which the packets are going
to follow the shortest path spanning tree
in the opposite direction.
And so given that they will be a shortest
path spanning tree from every source and
to every destination, it's not surprising
that the packets will take a different a
different path.
So, ideally, we would build a separate
tree for every sender, a source specific
tree so that all packets follow the
shortest cost spanning tree to the end
hosts.
But in communications where they're, where
the multicast group of end host is very
small, it might be easier instead of
building a whole load of trees, one for
every source, to establish some, some
rendezvous points and we'll see an example
of this later.
So, for example, we might elect R5 as a
rendezvous through which all of the
multicast packets are going to go.
So, when everyone's sending a multicast,
they could send them to R5. And then, R5
would build a shortest path spanning tree
to everybody else within the group.
Now, there is one shortest path spanning
tree from R5, the rendezvous point to
everybody.
And then everybody uses the normal unicast
routing method in order to reach R5.
So, there's really a design choice in
practice as to whether we maintain one
tree or one for every source.
So, I told you a little bit about some of
the techniques and principles, and I'm
going to tell you a little bit about the
practice how multicast is used in the
internet today.
So, one thing that I haven't mentioned so
far is about addresses.
There is a class of IPv4 addresses that
are different from the unicast
addresses.
They are set of class D and
they're sixteen bits so there are two^16
different multicast addresses and they
don't correspond to a particular location
on the topology like a unicast address
does.
They refer to a group.
So, every, every recipent of packets
within a group will receive packets with
the same multicast address.
So, it's a little bit of like an
indirection.
The router will look up on the label.
And, in fact, routers typically maintain
an entry for each tuple of (multicast
address, source pair), so that they can
route packets on the source-specific tree.
We also need a way for hosts to indicate
their interest in joining our group.
One of the interesting things about
multicast is that generally the source
does not need to know who the packets are
being delivered to.
It's the network, it's the tree that
figures that out.
So, each of the leaves of the tree, each
of the hosts needs to indicate an interest
in receiving packets and it does this by
using IGMP, the Internet Group Management
Protocol, RFC3376.
So, this is the protocol that runs between
the host, between an end host and its
directly attached router.
The, the hosts periodically will ask to
receive packets belonging to a particular
multicast group.
In fact, the routers will,
Will probe or will send out a request to
all of the hosts connected to them and
say, what multicast groups are you
interested in?
And then, the hosts will respond and will
say which groups they want to receive
from.
And if they don't receive any reply after
a while then the membership times out.
In other words, it says, I will no longer
deliver packets belonging to this
multicast group if no one is interested in
it.
This is an example of what's called soft
state.
The state is only maintained, it isn't
exclusively removed, it will just time out
if no one actually renews their interest
in receiving it.
So, let me tell you about multicast
routing in the internet very briefly.
The very first multicast routing protocol
was called DVMRP, the Distance Vector
Multicast Routing Protocol described in
RFC 1075.
It was first introduced in the, in the
1980s and it basically used the Reverse
Path Broadcast plus prune.
So, it was based on this observation,
hence, the distance vector name at the
beginning.
It's based on the observation that the
unicast routing protocol has already built
the tree for us, we're just going to, to
use it in the reverse direction.
An alternative is called Protocol
Independent Multicast or PIM.
And this, this recognizes two different
modes of multicast.
One called dense mode, in which all of the
routers or a very large number of the
routers are expected to be involved in
multicast, in which case RPB plus prune is,
is fine because most of the routers will
be involved and very few of them will need
to prune.
So, that uses DVMRP or something very
similar to DVMRP and is described in RFC
3973.
An alternative way is called
Sparse mode PIM, in which a relatively
small number of the routers are expected
to be involved in the multicast and
therefore, it will be very inefficient to
the RPB plus prune because there would be
way to many prune messages in the network.
And in this case it, it explicitly builds
rendezvous points through which the
packets that are sent will join a small
set of spanning trees from the rendezvous
points to all of the destinations of a
group.
And so a lot of work went
into how you pick these rendezvous points.
It's a fairly subtle problem
in it's own right.
So, DVMRP and PIM, so really overall,
there are three well, widely-used methods
protocols described in the three RFCs
mentioned here.
So, in practice, multicast is used a
little less than what's originally
expected.
It was originally anticipated that it
would be used for a very large amount of
communication in the internet because at
the time the multicast was first
conceived, it was still the case that
majority of communications in the world
with TV and radio, they were broadcast
medium.
And so, it was anticipated that this will
be a very common type of communication.
And in fact, in practice, this has turned
out to be less true than what's originally
thought and it seems that, over the last
twenty or so years,
Communication has become much more
individualized.
We tend to ask for content that we
specifically want to watch at a specific
time.
There's less interest in broadcast than
there used to be,
Except for events like sporting events,
big political rallies, or a rocket
launching, or something like that.
So this individualized time shifting
that's common place today
and has really reduced the demand for
multicast in the network.
Also some of the earlier implementations
were pretty inefficient like DVMRP and
were found to have scaling problems and so
it, it reduced some of the interest or
enthusiasm that people had for introducing
multicast.
Today, it is used for some broadcast IP TV
dissemination and some applications to
sort of an application-layer specific
multicast not using the network
infrastructure but building their own
overlay tree for themselves.
Multicast also raises some interesting
questions.
And they're really to do with the state
that one would have to maintain in order
to maintain reliable TCP-like
communications with an end host.
So, for example, imagine that a source is
sending to hundreds or thousands or
hundreds of thousands of destinations in a
group.
If you wanted that communication to be
reliable, in which it was maintaining a,
keeping track of which packets had been
reliably received at which destinations,
This would be a horrendous task for a
single source to, to manage.
In fact, anything that requires state,
like flow-control or supporting different
rates to different end users, it's not
clear how to do that either, or how to
make it secure.
All of these are quite are quite big
problems.
There's been lots of interest from a
research point of view but, but generally
speaking, there aren't considered to be
good solutions to these.
So generally, multicast is used for
delivering data that is primarily in one
direction.
For example, like TV, in which that data
is being moved from a source without
modification to a set of end hosts.
And that's the end of the video on multicast