In this final video, as part of the attack
series, we're going to talk about denial
of service. In February of 2000 Yahoo's
router, one day, just started crashing.
And the engineers had problems with the
router previously, but this time, it was
worse, and they couldn't figure out what
was going wrong, why that every time they
brought up the router, it kept crashing.
and it took them many hours to figure out
that they were being flooded with ICMP
echo reply packets, at such a high rate
that it was causing their router to crash.
And in the weeks and months that followed,
there were many of these so-called
distributed denial of service or DDOS
attacks against a bunch of high-profile
sites. So, basically, what a denial of
service attack is, is something that
prevents a, a service from, from being
available and the easiest denial of
service attack you can do is to overload
either a server or a network with too many
packets so that it can no longer function
properly and serve legitimate clients. So,
of course, you want to, as an attacker,
you want to maximize the costs of each
packet to the server, in terms of, you
know, network resources, CPU, and memory.
The reason distributed denial of service
or DDOS is so effective is that the attack
comes from all over the place so it's hard
to just filter out one bad person. Also,
because it's coming from a number of hosts
there's, each of those hosts has some of
resources, so you, you've got a lot of
traffic coming in, if it's a, a widely
distributed DDOS attack. How do attackers
do this? Well, they can penetrate many
machines in a, in a semiautomatic fashion
with malware, and then they turn the hosts
into zombies that will basically attack on
command. And then, at some point, they
later decide, hey, I want to attack this
victim, like yahoo.com, you know, push a
button, and boom, all of these compromised
machines will start flooding Yahoo with
packets. Now, in general, DoS attacks are,
are attacks that just target availability.
and you might wonder well, is, is, why is
that useful? Right, is not like you are
breaking into a bank and convincing it to
send you money or something. But it turns
out that a lot of people perform these DoS
attacks for a number of reasons. One is
extortion right, you go to, attackers will
go to some company maybe the company is
doing something a little bit fringe like
an offshore gambling site or something.
And, they'll say hey, pay us a small
amount of money or we'll take down your
site. And at that point the people who run
the site might think, well we don't really
want to go to the FBI with this maybe we
should just pay the money, but of course
if they do that it'll probably even you
know a month later the price will, will
double, because they've now proven that
they're willing to into the extortion. But
nonetheless people try to do this. Another
thing is that people use it for revenge.
So, for example spammers mounted a
denial-of-service-attack that permanently
shut down an anti-spam company called Blue
Security once. And you know, finally of
course people do it for bragging rights.
so denial of service can happen at many
different layers of abstraction. You do it
at the link layer, at the network layer,
transport layer, or at the application
layer. So, here's a kind of a warm-up,
some very simple denial of service
attacks. One is jam a wireless network at
the physical layer, right? So, you could
maybe even just buy some off-the-shelf
cordless phone or build a very simple
circuit that would make a wireless network
inoperable, essentially. Another thing you
could do is exploit properties or features
of the link layer. So, for example, in
802.11, there's this feature called the
net allocation vector, which is used to
suggest when the network might be free.
and what you can do that, is you can do,
use that repeatedly to reserve the network
for the maximum number of seconds, and
then if, essentially at that point, no one
will end up transmitting. You'll have,
have effectively disabled that wireless
network. Here's an example of DoS attack
at the network l ayer, you can flood ping
a victim. So, for example on most machines
you, run ping-fvictim.com and it will
flood the victim with ICMP echo request
packets as fast as possible. Of course,
what makes a denial of service attack
particularly devastating is if you can
somehow amplify the, the resources
required to handle the packets at the
servers. So, what the attacker really
wants is to, you know, expend a small
number of resources, you know, send, send
some stream of packets. But that, somehow,
that costs a lot more to process at the
server than it does for the attacker to
send. Well, it turns out that there are
many ways to do exactly that. For example
EDNS has some, some queries that result in
responses that are like 40 times the size
of a query. And there also happen to be a
large number of open DNS resolvers around
the Internet, say, you know, half a
million or so. So, one of the things you
could do is flood the victim with DNS
responses. What you do is you send a
request to a DNS server that's forged to
look like the request is coming from the
victim. And, you know, the request might
be like some 60-byte EDNS request but the
reply will 3,000 bytes. And the, so,
you're getting kind of a 40-times
amplification in bandwith for, for these
requests and responses. And because you
can send these requests to many, many
different open DNS resolvers it's, it's
very easy to, to amplify this attack even
from a, from a small number of hosts that
are originally sending these forged DNS
requests. Another nice thing from the
attacker's point of view is that it's not
clear who's actually mounting the attack.
By the time the request has made it to the
server and the server has responded, what
you get is a packet from the DNS server to
the victim, but the, the, the attacker's
identity doesn't figure anywhere in the
packet. Its Mac address isn't there. Its
IP address was never there, since it was
forging the IP address to begin with, and,
and it's not on the path between the DNS
server and the target. So again, it's,
it's hard to f ilter out to, to kick the
bad guy off the network as a way to try to
deal with this kind of attack when it's
underway. Yet another one of these attacks
is known as a SMURF attack. This is
actually the attack that was being used
against Yahoo. And here taking advantage
of the fact that ICMP echo, the, the ping
protocol, supports pinging an IP broadcast
address. So, this is actually useful if
you want to know what machines are on your
network, you ping the broadcast address,
and you get an echo reply from every
machine that's connected to the network.
Unfortunately, this provides a big
amplification opportunity for a flooding
attack. Imagine they compromised one
machine on a network with, say, 200
machines, and then you stick a bunch of
broadcast ping packets that purport to be
from the victim's IP address. Then, all
200 machines on the network are going to
reply to that IP address. And, and so
again, that's, that's what was used to
take down Yahoo. The same thing was used
against buy.com, and Amazon back in 2000.
Now, moving up the protocol stack, you can
also attack at the transport layer. So,
remember, TCP has this initial handshake,
right? The, the client sends a server SYN
packet, then the server sends a SYN-ACK
packet back to the client. And finally,
the client sends server of the third ACK
packet. So, has implemented at the server,
well, when the server receives a SYN
packet it you know, allocates some data
structure, sticks it in a hash table and,
and sends back the SYN-ACK packet, and
then it waits for this, this third ACK
packet here for some amount of time, like
a minute. And then, if after a minute, it,
it basically garbage collects it and says,
okay, I guess this connection is not
happening. So, every time a packet comes
in, every time an ACK packet comes in, it
needs to be compared to all the existing
connections to see if this is an ACK for
a, a partially open connection. And
unfortunately, the operating system can't
handle an arbitrary number of partial
connections. I mean especially at the time
t hese attacks started getting
popularized, I mean, there, there would
only be, you know, only a small number of,
of the partially open connections that the
OS would be willing to cache and then it
would just drop the SYN packets, so or
would drop future SYN packets. So,
basically, the SYN-bomb attack consists of
sending a stream of SYN packets all from
bogus addresses, the SYN-ACKs go off into
wherever, and at that point, the, the
servers' tables fill up and it stops
accepting connections and legitimate
clients can't actually connect. And the
thing that was so devastating about the
stack is just a, a few hundred packets per
second could completely disable most
servers. So, you really didn't need a lot
of horsepower to mount this attack against
a server you didn't like. So, an example
of SYN bombs in the wild, there was a worm
called the MS Blaster worm, that basically
flooded port 80 of windowsupdate.com with
SYN packets. And it sent about 50 SYN
packets per second, that's, that's again,
they each only 40 bytes each. So, really
not a lot of bandwidth being consumed. It
randomize the last two bytes of the source
IP address, so making it hard to track
down the exact machines that were actually
infected. And what made this particularly
devastating is that clients couldn't
connect to Windows Update to actually
solve the problem. So, eventually, what
Microsoft had to do was change the update
URL to be windowsupdate.microsoft.com
instead of windowsupdate.com. That still
wasn't good enough, because there was
still old machines that were infected with
the blaster worm and were actually trying
to connect to windowsupdate.com, which at
that point they had given up on, so what
they eventually had to do was actually use
a content distribution network, Akamai,
had a really high capacity to serve
windowsupdate.com so those machines could
get updated and take care of the
infection. Okay. Other attacks that can
happen. IP fragment flooding. Well, it's
kind of similar to a SYN bomb attack
where, when, when you receive in, an IP
fra gment, you have to allocate some space
and keep that around until the remaining
fragments that are part of that IP packet
come in. And so you could basically forge
a host send a stream of bogus fragments to
a server and never bother to send the
remaining fragments, so the server will
never be able to reconstruct these
packets, it will just have to time out the
fragments, eventually. Another attack is
that there's a UDP service known as the,
the echo service, which is on port seven
and if you send a packet to port seven on
a server that's running the echo service,
which a lot of hosts used to by default it
will simply reply. So, I mean, this is
kind of a, a really dumb attack. You could
just forge a packet from port seven on one
machine to port seven on another machine,
and the two packet, the two machines will
start sending traffic back and forth until
a packet is dropped. and, and so,
obviously there's a pretty easy fix, which
is that a sane echo server should actually
drop the packet on the floor if the source
port is port seven, right? The source port
should be something higher, like over
1,024, anyway. Finally, there is, of
course application-level denial of
service. So examples of this are, well,
it's anything where just a, something you
can do on the client can be much more
expensive to the server than it is to the
client. So, for example, DNS supports both
TCP and UDP. And the way the TCP protocols
works is that you connect to the server
and then, you send requests, but because
TCP is a stream protocol, not a datagram
protocol, you need to say where the
boundaries are between requests and
responses. And so, the protocol works, you
sent a 16-bit length followed by that many
bytes. And it turned out a lot of DNS
implementations blocked while reading the
message. So, if you sent a large length
but then didn't actually send that many
bytes afterwards, you could end up causing
a DNS server to hang. And, and just
completely take it out, right? So, very
little effort on the client's part, server
becomes completely inoperable. Another
example is SSL, which requires a fairly
expensive public key decryption to happen
at the server, and again, you can burn a
lot of CPU time at the server by sending
bogus connection requests, a lot more time
CPU time than is required at the client to
mount the attack.