Phil: Hi, so I’m here with Kevin Fall at
a computer science conference at the symposium
of operating systems principles. I have run
into him here, so I thought that actually
hearing a bit about what he has to say about
the Internet would be interesting. So, Kevin,
you’re currently the author of TCP/IP Illustrated,
so how did that happen? What’s your relationship
with TCP and the stuff that you’ve done
in the past. What’s your background with
TCP/IP?
Kevin: So, I guess, right after I graduated,
and shortly after I got to Berkeley, somebody
demonstrated to me that they could send some
packet to Europe and back to Berkeley in under
a second, and I thought networking became
sort of an interesting thing to look at. Fast
forward a number of years, I worked on networking
implementation of Berkeley unix on a Cray
for a while, that got me a little bit into
the HPC community, but then I worked at Lawrence
Berkeley National Lab after my graduate work
at UC San Diego. So at UC San Diego, I was
doing some protocol work and some operating
system work, but then with the networking
group at LBL, that was all quite a bit in
the networking side, and worked on network
simulators, the NS simulator and so on. What
happened though is I got to know this stuff
pretty well, and by the early 90s or mid 90s
when the Internet was becoming more widely
known, people took an interest in what is
the TCP IP stuff, and this particular book,
TCP IP illustrated, was the standard reference
text, and the volume one is still quite a
good book. I was teaching out of it, teaching
professionals from Cisco and places like that,
and so I got to know the material quite well,
but as the years went on and on and on, there
were things that it would be nice to be updated
in that book, and so there were places I had
heard where some people were approached to
rewrite it, other people approached the editor,
Addison, to rewrite it, and for whatever reason,
it never happened. And so I threw in my table
of contents and sample chapter, and got the
job some seven years later finished off the
entire task of something that’s over 1,000
pages long.
Phil: So what’s an example of something
that you thought sort of had changed and needed
to be introduced, but wasn’t in the original
text?
Kevin: One of the major ones is security.
So there’s like 100 pages of security that
goes through the introduction of, what are
the sort of basic primitives, what are the
sort of things you might want to protect against,
all the various details of the protocols that
actually does that. Really, with security,
not only the cryptographic parts of security,
but things like firewalls and stuff, really
barely existed when the first work was done.
There’s also a new chapter at the beginning,
that’s sort of the architectural underpinnings.
What was in the minds of people when they
were thinking about the design decisions when
this stuff was made? So I always found that
quite interesting, and being an operating
systems guy originally, how people came up
with abstractions and how programs access
those things and not quite users necessarily,
and what are the sort of architectural concerns?
So I was always quite interested in papers
and thoughts in the architectural area.
Phil: And so last night we were talking, and
you said that today people use the terms datagram
and packet interchangeably, but those were
not interchangeable terms. They actually meant
something quite different, which is now sort
of lost in time.
Kevin: So I think I mentioned this in part
of the book, and packets were sort of a fascinating
new concept, that you could divide your larger
message into little parts, and move them around
the network. But they were originally, at
least some variant, were part of virtual circuits,
and so for example, the destination in a packet
was the destination of an index of a table
in the next hop. So you would sort of set
up the route ahead of time, and then if that
failed for some reason, you have a bunch of
work to do to go back, and there’s all the
history of circuits. But datagrams were a
maybe even more radical idea, where the final
destination is identified in the packet structure,
which when I would teach this class, I would
say if I laid out the network in a two-dimensional
space, with this datagram type property, I
could take it and drop it from the air down
onto any router, and it would find it’s
way through, because the final destination
was listed. But of course that was a tradeoff,
because now you have more bits that you have
to allocate, because there’s presumably
a larger number of destinations available.
So these were the kind of nuances that were
actually pretty neat to get the details from
by going back in the architectural history
and thinking and learning about what people
were sort of arguing about what people were
sort of arguing about at the time.
Phil: Cool, so what are you working on now?
What are the most interesting things, do you
think, in networking, and the Internet, and
systems that you’re trying to tackle.
Kevin: So there’s a couple areas that I
think are fun and sort of worth mentioning,
at least one of which we have some work on.
The first one, we don’t have so much work
on, but is the him and some of his colleagues
and predecessors had envisioned that not only
to we have a thing that winds up essentially
being today’s Internet, that there’s communication
in these communities. But there’s also a
physical way of moving things around, which
was like a global pneumatic tube system. So
you could take your thing, shove it, and it
would sort of find its way, which would be
a very cool thing to have. But I don’t think
we’re quite there yet. But on the other
hand, I think that 3d printing technology,
as combined with what’s going on with the
free and easy dissemination of information,
becomes quite interesting, especially when
you can print things other than plastics and
so on. So I had in my hand a demonstration
that was a titanium 3d printed nose replacement
part, a prosthetic nose, and it was strands
of titanium printed on top of each other,
and if you can load up your device with the
right materials, pretty much any material
thing you want to create almost, could be
created. So even into the world of sensor
networks, things people looked at sensing
the world, maybe even actuating the world,
but like building the world on demand in combination
with those other things is pretty interesting,
and I wonder if that’s not kind of the way
to get to the vision of pneumatic tubes, but
instead of removing it, you just make another
one. And so how far in the future will it
be that you just carry around in your backpack
or your car the basic system, and then you
just download whatever the thing is you happen
to need. There was literally, not even a few
months ago, there was a meeting in Washington
DC about the security implications of additive
manufacturing.
Phil: There’s all these questions about
firearms, for example. So generally in firearms,
there’s one piece of the gun that’s strongly
regulated, it’s the one that everything
has to stick onto, and somebody 3 printed
one, it’s normally something you need a
license for, and so there’s an interesting
question about what the implications are going
forward, with things like DRM.
Kevin: Yeah, there’s lots of policy questions.
I think, as is often the case, technology
will outpace the policy ability to comprehend
and instantiate reasonable laws about things,
whatever that may be. And so this idea that
bits become interchangeable with physical
objects, and we have traditionally regulated
the control of physical objects, but now do
we have to include digital objects? It’s
pretty interesting, so that’s one of the
topics, and it actually gets into other things
that you can compute with and maybe print
and compute, like synthetic biology, like
I want to create a little organism that takes
one thing and something comes out the other
end, well I have biologicals in my 3d printer,
and not just download the designs, but have
the tools to do the designs of the biological
systems. So that’s one whole category, that
when I was thinking about the pneumatic tubes,
and then looking at 3d printing and its capabilities,
and now the price is knocked down, so people
can go get them, it’s a pretty interesting
thing.
Phil: Cool, well it was great chatting with
you, and thank you for your time, so yeah.
See you next time.