Nick:
In this unit you learned a lot about packet
switching – this was an intense unit.
We started out with a look at why modern networks
including the Internet are built on a foundation
of packet switching. Packet switching is simple
in the sense that each packet is a self-contained
unit of data that carries information necessary
for it to reach its destination. Packet switching
is efficient in the sense that it keeps a
link busy whenever there is work to be done,
rather than have dedicated capacity reserved
for each user or application. Packet switching
can potentially help the network recover quickly
from failures: the simple forwarding paradigm,
with no per-flow state in each router, makes
it easier to quickly route around link and
router failures.
Next we dived deep deep deep into some of
the consequences of packet switching. This
took us on a journey that included more math
than you will see in any other unit of this
course. Packet switching determines many of
the timing and performance characteristics
of the Internet, and so you really need to
have a strong understanding of packet dynamics.
The main mathematical ideas are not so complicated
and it is worth mastering them now so you
can build a strong intuition. You now know
why two packets traveling between the same
two end hosts might encounter a different
delay. While the time they spend traversing
each link is the same, the packets might take
different paths and experience different queueing
delays in the router buffers. It is absolutely
crucial that you fully understand the three
main components of packet delay: the packetization
delay, the propagation delay, and the queueing
delay; and that you understand the physical
processes that cause them. You should get
into the habit of sketching and using the
simple deterministic queue model that I taught
you. It’s a simple geometric construct that
lets you visualize what is going on. It tells
us why routers have buffers, and gets us thinking
about how big they should be. It tells us
why streaming applications need a playback
buffer to give a smooth listening or viewing
experience for the user. We’ll use it later
when we study congestion control.
We then used the simple deterministic model
to learn how a network can go beyond just
simple FCFS packet delivery. A packet switched
network can guarantee the rate that each flow
receives and even bound the delay a packet
experiences from one end of the network to
the other. These required some careful thinking
about; don’t worry if it took you a while
to get the hang of how they work as they are
difficult concepts at first. They are also
important – if you can understand how a
packet switched network can provide rate and
delay guarantees, then you have a strong understanding
of how packet switching works.
Phil:
You learned a lot in this unit.
First, “Queueing delay and end-to-end delay”.
You learned that the time it takes for a packet
to travel between two end hosts is determined
by three components. First, we have to transmit
the packet over each link in turn. The time
it takes to write the packet onto each link
is determined by the time to write each bit,
multiplied by the number of bits in the packet.
We call this the packetization delay. Second,
the bits have to propagate down the cable
or through the air to the other end of the
link. The propagation delay is determined
by the speed of propagation (which is close
to the speed of light) and the distance the
bits travel. Make sure the difference between
propagation delay and packetization delay
are clear in your mind, because it’s a frequent
cause for confusion. Third, the end to end
delay has a variable component, the queueing
delay. Because the Internet uses packet switching,
the routers have buffers to hold packets during
time of congestion, and so the queueing delay
depends on how busy the network is right now.
Later, when we study wireless, you’ll see
that wireless links add more variability to
the delay, because wireless links are noisy,
so packets frequently need to be retransmitted
and can have changing packetization delays.
“Why streaming applications use a playback
buffer”
Realtime streaming applications – such as
Skype, YouTube and Netflix – need to deliver
continuous realtime voice and video to our
ears and eyes, even though the network delivers
packets at unpredictable times. All streaming
applications use a playback buffer to smooth
out the variations in packet delay, so they
can play the video and audio to the user without
having to pause and wait for new data in the
middle. You learned how to design a playback
buffer, and you learned why it is not possible
in the Internet to completely avoid pauses
in the playback – packets can experience
a large delay, causing the playback buffer
to run dry. If you fully understand how a
playback is designed, then you have a good
understanding of packet dynamics in the Internet.
A simple deterministic queue model.
Queueing delay in routers is a complex topic
all on its own. The field of queueing theory
is very mathematically rich and you can take
classes and read many books on the topic.
In general, queues with complicated, random
arrival processes are complex beasts. A network
consisting of a series of router queues, with
many competing flows coming from random users
and different applications is way to hard
to analyze in closed form. But our goal here
is less ambitious. We want you to develop
some intuition about how queues evolve and
to become familiar with their dynamics. Just
like the queue at airport security, a router
queue holds the packets that have arrived
but not yet departed. If we can keep track
of arrivals and departures, then we know how
deep the queue is, and how long an arriving
packet must wait. The deterministic queue
model is a geometric representation of the
packets in the queue, letting us visualize
how the queue evolves over time. It’s good
practice to use this geometric model to help
you build your intuition of how the math works.
The deterministic queue model helps us understand:
Rate guarantees.
Sometimes we want a particular flow of packets
to receive a particular fraction of the network
capacity. For example, Stanford might have
a contract with AT&T guaranteeing that its
traffic will always receive at least 10Gb/s
of service. Over the link that attaches us
to AT&T that’s easy to do – we simply
connect with a 10Gb/s link. AT&T could also
make this guarantee by putting all the Stanford
packets into a queue in their routers, and
making sure they have 10Gb/s of service. This
can be done on very aggregated traffic, like
all of Stanford’s packets. Or it can be
done on individual applications: We might
ask Comcast to provide at least 1Mb/s to stream
our Netflix videos.
You learned how to serve every queue in a
router at a minimum rate. If all packets were
the same length, this would be trivial. But
different packets have different lengths,
so we need to take into consideration how
long each packet is. This is where Weighted
Fair Queueing comes in. It tells us the correct
order to serve packets in the router queues,
so as to take into consideration the length
of individual packets.
The same idea can be extended to provide
Delay guarantees.
Now we know how to control the rate at which
a queue is served, we can control the maximum
delay a packet can experience in the queue.
It is simply the length of the queue divided
by the rate. All we need to do is limit the
length of the queue so we can bound the delay.
Finally, you learned
How packets are switched and forwarded.
As you saw, Ethernet switches and Internet
routers work in very similar ways. When a
packet arrives, it looks up the destination
address in its forwarding table. If it finds
the address, it forwards the packet towards
its destination, holding it in a buffer if
the outgoing link is currently busy. Ethernet
switches and Internet routers differ in which
address they use and how they organize the
forwarding tables; and of course an Internet
router needs to decrement the TTL field to
prevent loops. But at a high level, packet
switches all operate in roughly the same way.
Nick:
The things you learned in this unit will help
you in several ways:
1. You can take the description of a network
– the rates and length of the links – and
the length of a packet, and figure out the
fixed component of the packet’s end to end
delay.
2. You can visualize the variable queueing
delay by sketching the queue, which is the
most common cause for variable end to end
delay in a network.
3. you can explain how a packet switch works,
such as an Ethernet switch or Internet router.
4. You can design a playback buffer for a
realtime application.
5. You can explain how a flow traversing a
packet switched network can be delivered at
a minimum rate. And you can explain how individual
packets can have a bounded delay from end
to end.