Answer: It will take 150 milliseconds. So
250 milliseconds in total.
In this figure, blue lines are segments from
the client to server, and red are from the
server to client. The SYN SYN-ACK exchange
takes 100 milliseconds
The first request will take 60 milliseconds
to arrive, at which point, 160 ms, the server
can begin sending a
response. It enqueues two segments to send.
As the first response segment goes out over
the link,
the server receives the second request, and
enqueues 2 more response segments. This means
that
the responses will take a total of 90 milliseconds
to arrive after the first request arrives.
The
additional packetization delay of the 2nd
request is masked by the queueing of responses.
So this means it will take a total of 480
milliseconds: 230 milliseconds for the initial
request / response of the HTTP page, then
an addition 250 milliseconds to fetch the
two images.