This  video goes into the details of what
DNS queries actually look like, and their
format and their structure.
So, queries and the resource records that
compose them.
As you recall, a DNS query starts from a
client.
Say, it asks a resolver, what's
www.stanford.edu?
And this is a recursive query.
And then, a resolver might either answer
from its cache, or use cache entries.
And if it doesn't have a cache entry for
any stage of the query, it can ask
questions from external servers.
So, whom would I ask about edu?
Whom would I ask about Stanford.edu?
Hey, what's www.stanford.edu?
Each of these are non-recursive queries
and the resolver then caches those
results.
So, edu, stanford.edu and
www.stanford.edu.
So, that's a query at a high level.
But, the details, the way DNS works is
that all DNS information and every DNS
message is represented in terms of things
called Resource Records, RRs.
In the form of Resource Records is
generally pretty simple.
It has a name, also a kind of resource
record, sort of, name of the, the name
associated with this record.
There can be a time to live, and a class,
then there is the type of record, and then
the record data.
So, for example, a research record would
be named say, www.stanford.edu.
So, this is a record for www.stanford.edu.
TTL, how long is this record good.
Class, it's just the address class.
So, typically, it's almost always IN 1
it's class one so for, this for
Internet, for the Internet.
There's the type of the record and then
the data.
And so here, I'm going to walk through two
critical RR types, Resource Record types.
Type A, which is an ad..., or an IPv4
address, and NS, which is a Name Server.
So, an A record tells you an address
associated with a name.
So, it'll say, type A, the R data's an
address, it's the address associated with
a name.
Whereas in name server record, an NS
record will telly you the address of a
name server associated with a name.
So, a great way to explore DNS and what
records look like and what kinds of records
should you get is to use this cool tool
called dig which I'll use several times.
A DNS message, an actual DNS message, its
structure looks like this.
This is specified in the RFC 1035.
So, beginning, there's a header which
describes the overall, what's in a
message.
There's the question that this message is
for.
If it's a query, then it's the question to
query.
If it's a response, then it's a question's
response, too.
And then, there are other sections which
are empty inquiries, the answer authority
and additional sections.
So, it's possible, for example, I send a
DNS query with multiple questions if you
want.
Each of these can have multiple entries.
So, there's a header and the question and
answer authority and additional sections
are all made up of resource records.
So, let's look at an example of this.
So, if I dig www.stanford.edu, this simply
just I'm asking, I'm discussing, I'd like
to send a DNS query of, to, for the
address of www.stanford.edu.
And this is what we see come back.
So, here, here's the dig output, tell you
the version of dig.
Here's the header, some header
information.
We'll talk a little bit more about that
later.
Now, here's the question.
I was asking for an address record of
www.stanford.edu, so you see here's a
record, resource record, even the question
section.
And, the answer has two records in it.
The first is what's called the CNAME
record, which we'll talk a little bit more
later.
This data says that www.stanford.edu is
actually the canonical name for that so
what CNAME stands for, CNAME stands for is
www-v6.stanford.edu.
So, there are six different, maybe there's
six different web servers for Stanford.
Then, the address of www-v6, here's,
here's the Internet IN, so it's IN1,
that's the class, TTL is 1800, this is an
A record and it's for this address.
In addition to that, the authority section
is telling me who are the authoritative names.
These are the NS and the name server
records for stanford.edu.
So here, all of these different servers I
could ask about addresses in Stanford.
The additional section then gives me a
whole bunch of just additional stuff like,
here's the address record for Argus.
Here's the address record for Aerathea.
Here's the address record for Atlanta.
Here's the, Atalante, here's the address
for Avallone.
And so, we're going to think of what DNS
is often doing, and the reason why you see
this message is so big is that, given this
is going to send a response, it tries to
send you a whole bunch of extra data, a
whole bunch of extra information just to
maybe prevent you from asking other query.
And so, these are A Records, these are
IPv4 addresses.
So, quad A records, AAAA, these are IPv6
addresses.
And so, it turns out Stanford's DNS server
is giving you not only the address records
of the Stanford name servers but also
their, you know, the A Record close to
IPv6 in case I want to query them for
IPv6.
So, this is what a response to a DNS query
looks like.
So, you can see that there's the header,
there's the question section, the answer
section, the authority section, and then
additional section.
So, if we look inside the header,
specified RFC 1035.
The header is ten bytes long, sorry, twelve
bytes long so it's pretty short.
The first two bytes are an ID so you can
pair queries and responses.
And then, the second, the first two byte
is an ID, the second two bytes are a bunch
of flags.
So, there's the, first, that bit I mentioned
whether this is a query or response,
there's a OPCODE.
So, standard queries, and there's a return
code if there's an error code, and there's
a bunch of flags.
So, it's an authoritative answer, is it
truncated all of these sort of things.
So, you can see here, at the bottom
recursion desired and recursion available.
There are ways where you can in fact ask a
result over for non-recursive query
if you want.
Then, after this first four bytes, there
are four two byte values which say how
many resource records are there in each
section.
So, how many queries are there, how many
answers are there, how many authorities
are there, and how many additional records
are there.
Now then, within each of these, of the
four sections that have resource records,
resource record is pretty simple.
It has a name that could be a variable,
number of, of bytes long.
I don't know how long it is.
Then, there's a type, class and the TTL
within an RD length field specifying the R
data.
So here, here's the basic DNS name and the
type and then the class, TTL, RD length, R
data.
And so, this is one of the sort of on the
wire with the byte format of a resource
record looks like.
Now, notice that the beginning of a
resource record is a name but it doesn't
say how long the name is that's because the
length of the name just self-describing.
It turns out that the DNS does a lot of
name compression because it's trying to
pack everything in the 512 bytes.
Then, names that are repeated through the
packet are just, rather than repeated, are
just referenced.
And so, imagine if I'm asking a query
about say, www.stanford.edu, I don't
necessarily want to have that repeated
many times in the packet.
I can just put it once and then referred
with.
So, the first thing that DNS does is it
breaks a name into separate labels related
to the steps of the hierarchy.
So, www.stanford.edu is three separate
labels, www, Standford, and edu.
Then, each label is encoded as a length
and then text values.
The length is in binary so it's basically
some number, it's just one byte, and then
the text is an ASCII.
So, for example, if I will encode
3www, so w is 0x77.
The way that it is encoded in the bits in
the packet is 0x0377 0x7777.
So, this tells me, these are three bytes
and here they are.
Now, one trick in that, the name
progression uses in order to take
advantage of the fact that this means
longer period at the time in the packet,
is if the length field here in the label
is greater than 192, that is, some of the
higher bits are set.
Then, the next fourteen bits specify an
offset in the packet.
And so, the way that I think of this is
that, if I see here that the first two
bits of the length.
So, 128 plus 64 is 192, or one, one, then
this length is actually two bytes long,
this length field, and the later fourteen
bits specify an offset in the packet.
So, for example, if I see 0xc00c, this
means that the name that this label, that
this label refers to is at this value
minus, take out this first two bits, is at
offset twelve within the packet.
So, if I were just to go to offset twelve,
that's the label that this refers to.
So, if like something for Stanford, which
is eight characters long, rather than
repeat Stanford many times, would actually
be the [inaudible] because we need the length,
right at the zero, or the, at 0x08, then
the bytes at Stanford I can just say, 0xc0
and then the offset at Stanford and they
will be only two bytes long.
So, this is a little bit detail, it's
important for when we, I'm going to open up
Wireshark so I can show you what's in a DNS
query in responses looks like.
Otherwise, it would be really hard to
figure out, wait, what are these resource
records and what are these weird values
that aren't actually specifying names.
So, just to give you an idea.
So, what the DNSA, the DNS-A, or address
record looks like.
So, let's just say, for
market.scs.stanford.edu.
So, the first, the name region would say
This might be compressed so it might
become shorter.
Then, the next two bytes would say one,
this is an address record.
The next two bytes would say one, this is
for the Internet.
The next four bytes say 3600 so the TTL of
this record, the time to leave is an hour.
Then, the length of the R data, the length
of the Internet address is four bytes, and
then here are the four bytes.
And so, if you ever see it printed out
say, if you're using dig and you'd see
this, but the overall record actually
looks like this.
An NS record, say, the name server record
of scs.stanfordedu looks similar where
here, we have scs.stanfordedu and the name
section, again, it might be compressed.
Then, we have 2 saying that this is NS
record against the Internet, time to leave
is 3600.
And then, the length is say, ten because
it turns out that scs.stanford.edu is
compressed because, well, it's been
mentioned elsewhere.
So, we really have mission, one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven, right?
And then, we have a one, the, the one, the
length for mission.
And then, the two which is the compressed
indication of the scs.stanford.edu.
The first two bytes in  the R data
are going to point to
scs.stanford.edu, then we have a byte say,
the length of mission seven, and the seven
mission bytes for a total of ten bytes.
So, let's dig for market.scs.stanford.edu.
So, just use the tool and see what
happens.
So, we're asking, what is the address of
marketscs.stanford.edu?
So, we're asking for an address record, we
get the answer.
Its address is 171.66.3.10, and here's the,
the time to leave is 2050.
Authority section, here are the name servers that
answered, that can answer this question.
Here's a bunch fs.n mission to
scs.stanford.edu, and here's some
additional information, address records
for these name servers.
So that's what it looks like when you ask
dig.
We can also ask dig what is the NS record
for market, for scs.stanford.edu.
And so, here is, we're querying for the NS
record, scs.stanford.edu.
We see there's a whole bunch of name
servers that serve scs.stanford.edu, NS3,
NS1, garage, market, mission, and then
here is the additional section, which is
giving you their IP addresses.
Some of them are just IPv4 addresses, some
of them IPv4 and IPv6 addresses.
And so, here we consider so many name
server and what that means is that if any
one of these goes down, I can still
access, I can still go to another one.
So, even if, say, three of these name
servers went down, let's say, NS3, garage,
and market, I can still contact NS1 or
mission to ask questions what names in
scs.stanford.edu.
So now, let's see what those queries look
like in Wireshark.
So, here, I open up Wireshark and I setup
a filter, UDP Port 53, is  the DNS Port
and IP addr, my IP address.
This is going to look at D, DNS request
and responses from, from my machine.
And so, if we were to ask this question,
dig market.scs.stanford.edu, we see, we got
a query and response.
And so, here is the DNS query,
right?
Again, Internet Protocol version four,
sourced.
There's my DNS server.
And so, here's the query, right?
There's a standard query, there's one
question, no other records.
And so, the question is
market.scs.stanford.edu.
Type A, so I'm asking for an address
record, class IN, name,
market.scs.stanford.edu, type A, host
address, class Internet.
And so here, in fact, we're looking inside
the bytes of the packet, here's all the
information about the size, right?
We can see here down these bytes are
00000.
Here is, this the header of the DNS,
transaction ID right there, 0x3eaa.
Flags, questions, etc., 00.
And then, here is the query itself.
So, this is the query section.
This is market.scs.stanford.edu.
If you look down at the bytes, this byte
is first byte for market is 06, that's
because market is six characters long.
So, it's 06, then M, A, R, K, E, T, then
SCS which is three, so three long, 3scs.
Then, Stanford which is eight long, so
it's eight S, T, A, N, F, O, R, D, then
three long E, D, U.
And then, that's the, and then type A, so
01 class IN01, great.
Now, if we look at the response, it's a
lot more complicated because remember, how
many entries there are in a response?
So, let's look inside this.
So, it's telling us for the transaction ID
is 03eaa.
Saying, response is here,
there's one question, one answer, five
authorities, seven additional.
So, let's look at the query section.
So the query here, you can see, again,
market.scs.stanford.edu.
Type A, class IN.
And so here's the answer, market.
Scs.stanford.edu, blah, blah, blah, here's
the address.
But now, if you look at this, the name
section of this resource record is only
two bytes long.
It's using name compression.
So, here's that c00c.
What it's saying is that c, the first two
bits are one, this is a compressed name.
And the start of the name is at offset 0c
or twelve within the packet.
And if you would count the bytes within
the DNS packet, you can see that market
starts at byte twelve.
This is saying this name is right there.
And so, then here's type A, IN, 30, etc.
Etc.
So that, you can see, so we've going to
take  market.scs.stanford.edu and
compress the name entirely.
But, it turns that you can do some other
types of compression.
So, here is the authoritative, here's an
answer for scs.stanford.edu.
And so, we see again this name for
scs.stanford.edu's compress, so c0, it's
compressed, thirteen.
This is an address, the one where that
represents sixteen.
This is an address nineteen within the
packet or offset nineteen, so why 19?
Well, if you think, the original
market.scs name, which is an offset
twelve.
Then, there's the length byte for market,
and then the six market bytes, so a total
of seven bytes.
And so, offset nineteen within the packet
is scs.stanford.edu.
So, you can address not only into the
beginning of the series of labels, but any
label within there.
And so, you'll see this happen many times.
And so, if you start doing some, digging
some requests, and open up in Wireshark
you can see this kind of name compression.
And what this means in practice right, is
that this packet which had all of this
information in it, right?
Look at all the stuff is in this packet.
All of these different records, the
address records, name server records,
quad address records fits in 311 bytes.
So, it's a 311 byte DNS response.