In this video I will provide a worked example
for a single flow with AIMD congestion control.
Alice is streaming a high definition video
at 10Mb/s from a remote server in San Francisco.
All packets are 250bytes long. She measures
the ping time to the server and the minimum
time she measures is 5ms. Once the AIMD window
reaches steady state, for the rest of the
video, the sawtooth oscillates between constant
minimum and maximum values. The buffer is
perfectly sized so that it is just big enough
to never go empty.
1. What is the smallest value of the AIMD
window (in bytes)?
The minimum ping time of 5ms is when the buffer
is empty but the bottleneck link is full.
At 10Mb/s, there is therefore 50,000 bits
in the “pipe”.
This means the minimum or “trough” of
the AIMD sawtooth is 50,000 bits, or 6250
bytes. So therefore the answer is 6250 bytes.
Part 2.
What is the largest value of the AIMD window
in bytes?
When the buffer is full, the RTT is doubled
from 5ms to 10ms.
At 10Mb/s, the maximum RTT will hold 100,000
bits. 50,000bits are in flight, and 50,000
bits are in the buffer.
Therefore the maximum or “peak” of the
AIMD sawtooth is 100,000 bits or 12,500 bytes.
Part 3.
How big is the packet buffer in the router
in bytes?
We already decided in Q2 that when full, the
buffer holds one minimum RTT, or 50,000 bits.
After a packet is dropped, how long does it
take for the window to reach its maximum value
again?
Part 4.
Packets are 2,000 bits long and so the window
will increase by 2,000 bits every RTT.
Therefore, it takes 25 RTTs to increase the
RTT by 50,000 bits and fill the buffer.
The average RTT is 7.5ms, therefore it will
take 187.5ms.
Part 5.
If Alice now tries to watch the same video
from a server in Australia (with RTT 250ms),
how big should the router buffer be (in bytes)
if the network still runs at 10Mb/s?
The minimum RTT is 250ms, so the buffer needs
to be at least 250ms * 10Mb/s = 2.5 x 10^6
bits.
Because we express storage in powers of 2,
the answer is 2.4Mbits or 298 Kbytes.
Part 6.
When the server is in Australia, after a packet
is dropped, how long does it take for the
window to reach its maximum value again (in
seconds)?
As before, the window increases by 2,000 bits
every round.
To fill the buffer will take 2.5 x 10^6 / 2
x 10^3 = 1,250 rounds.
The average RTT is 375ms.
So the time to reach the maximum again is
468.75 seconds, or almost 8 minutes!
The answer might surprise you. It takes a
long time for the AIMD flow to recover from
a single packet drop. This would be a real
problem in practice, which motivates us to
look for better and quicker ways for TCP to
recover from dropped packets.