Nick: In this unit, you’ve seen how transport
and packet switching interact through congestion
control. Flow control is about the end hosts.
It ensures the source host doesn't overwhelm
the destination host by sending more than
it can receive. Congestion control, on the
other hand, is about preventing the source
hosts from overwhelming the links and routers
in between them. When a source host put too
many packets into the network or when lots
of sources put packets into the network, they
can fill up the router queues until they overflow.
In TCP, a congestion control algorithm running
on the sending host tells it how many packets
it can have outstanding in the network so
as not to overfill the router queues. TCP
will always lead to some packets being dropped,
because this is the feedback signal is uses
to know when the router queues are full. But
when it's working well, TCP keeps the packet
drop rate low, links nice and full, and allows
the flow to have a high throughput.
Phil: First, Nick explained the principles
of network congestion. We learned what happens
when a router starts receiving packets faster
than it can send them. If the congestion is
short lived, then a router can absorb this
extra traffic into a queue and drain the queue.
If the congestion is long lived, long lived
enough that the queue overflows, then the
router has to drop some packets. Nick introduced
a very valuable way to think about this. Rather
than come up with a scheme for dropping packets,
think about what you want the overall network
behavior to be. We want the network to be
fair and explained what that means, introducing
the concept of max-min fairness. Max-min fairness
says that the network is fair if you can’t
increase the rate of a flow without decreasing
the rate of flow with a lower rate.
There are a lot of ways to achieve this goal,
and networks today have many different mechanisms.
But we focused on one in particular, how TCP
can control the number of outstanding packets
in the network. We introduced the basic algorithm
TCP uses, called additive increase, multiplicative
decrease, or AIMD. When running smoothly,
TCP increases the number of bytes it can have
outstanding by one segment size per round
trip time. When TCP detects a packet is dropped,
it halves the number of bytes it can have
outstanding.
You learned what this behavior looks like
using a TCP sawtooth diagram. While each individual
flow has a sawtooth, over link that many flows
share these all average out to a consistently
high use of the link. Using the sawtooth,
we derived TCP’s throughput using simple
AIMD. If you assume that a network drops packets
at a uniform rate p, then the throughput of
a TCP flow is the square root of three halves
times the inverse of RTT times the square
root of p. If you increase the round trip
time, throughput goes down. This equation
makes a lot of simplifying assumptions, but
it turns out to be generally pretty accurate
in many cases and so a very valuable tool
when thinking about how a network might behave.
Nick: You've learned how TCP realizes these
principles in practice. Phil told you about
how the Internet collapsed in the late 1980s
due to congestion, and the fixes made to TCP,
which are still in use today. You learned
about three versions of TCP: TCP Tahoe, TCP
Reno, and TCP New Reno.
The first important idea we covered is that
a TCP endpoint maintains a congestion window.
A TCP flow can have N unacknowledged bytes
outstanding in the network, where N is the
minimum of its flow control window and its
congestion control window. You don’t put
more packets into the network than the other
end can handle or more than the links and
routers can handle in between. You learned
how TCP controls the size of this congestion
control window using two states: slow start
and congestion avoidance. Slow start lets
TCP quickly find something close to the right
congestion window size, while congestion avoidance
uses AIMD. TCP starts in slow start and transitions
to congestion avoidance when it first detects
a loss. You learned how TCP estimates the
round trip time of its connection. It needs
this estimate to figure out when an acknowledgment
times out. By keeping track of both the average
as well as the variance of how long it takes
to receive an ack for a segment, TCP can avoid
unnecessary retransmissions as well as not
wait too long. You learned how TCP controls
when it puts packets in the network using
a technique called “self clocking” You
first saw self-clocking when I showed you
an animation of TCP’s behavior. Phil then
walked you through some examples of this.
With self clocking, TCP only puts a new packet
into the network when it receives an acknowledgment
or when there’s a timeout. This is really
helpful in preventing congestion, as it means
TCP only puts packets into the network when
packets have left the network.
Finally, we covered three optimizations added
in TCP Reno and TCP New Reno. Fast retransmit
lets TCP keep on making progress when only
one packet has been dropped. Rather than wait
for a timeout, TCP retransmits a segment when
it detects three duplicate acknowledgments
for the previous segment. This is a sign that
TCP is continuing to receive segments but
hasn’t received that particular one. Using
fast recovery, TCP Reno doesn’t drop back
into slow start on three duplicate acks, it
just cuts the congestion window in half and
stays in congestion avoidance. Finally, TCP
New Reno adds an additional optimization,
window inflation, such that three duplicate
acks don’t cause TCP to lose an RTT worth
of transmissions as it waits for the missing
segment to be acked.
Phil: Now what’s really fascinating about
congestion was that it’s something we discovered
as the Internet evolved. Nobody had really
thought something like this might happen,
or how to control it. It was an emergent behavior
once the network became large and heavily
used enough. Nowadays it’s a basic concept
in networking, seen as critical to building
robust networks that have high performance.
Nick: Modern versions of TCP are a bit more
advanced than what we’ve talked about in
class, but mostly they’ve evolved to handle
much, much faster networks. The TCP versions
shipped in operating systems have TCP Reno
or TCP New Reno in their algorithms, with
new additional features and modes of operation
to handle very fast networks. Take a look
at the Linux source code, you’ll see these
algorithms in there.
Phil: But what’s also neat is that these
nitty-gritty algorithms have a sound conceptual
basis and theory behind them. On one hand,
we can talk about RTT variance estimation,
fast recovery, and self-clocking. On the other,
we’re also talking about AIMD flows that
can converge to max-min fairness.