This is the first of three videos about
the domain name system or DNS.
So, let's look at the URL for a second.
If we look at a basic URL like you would
put in your web browser, it has three
basic parts.
It has, first, the front the application
protocol and port.
So, this is saying that we're going to be
requesting a file over HTTP and by
default, that means port 80,  TCP
port 80.
You could also tell this URL after the
host to do some other things say port 1001
or something.
But by default, this means port 80.
The middle part of a name is specifying a
host.
So, in this case, cs144.scs.stanford.edu.
This is a human-readable name, delimited
by periods into four parts.
And it's specifying the actual node that
we want to contact.
The last is, then the file, so this is the
application level for HTTP the application
level specification of what file we want
to request, HTTP.
And so, the question is, so far, we've
been talking about the internet in terms
of IP addresses, usually IPv4 addresses.
But when we type the URL, we have this
human-readable name describing the
computer, the host that we want to
contact.
And the question is, how do we translate
this human-readable name to an IP address?
Well, it turns out, you can of course
enter a URL without using a host name,
instead just by entering an IP address.
So you could rather type in
CS144.scs.stanford.edu, you could actually
write the IP address that's associated
with that name if you'd like.
But, these human readable names are very, very
useful.
And people realized that human-readable
names were useful even from the beginnings of the Internet.
beginning of the internet.
And so, way back when, when internet was
tiny, there was a file called hosts.txt
and it turns out that every single host on
the internet was in this file hosts.txt,
and it was maintained by the Network
Information Center.
So, it's maintained at SRI, so, the
SRI-NIC.ARPA at this particular IP
address.
So if you go and read this particular RFC, RFC952, it talks a
little bit about this.
And essentially, if you are a node on the
internet, what you'd do is periodically
contact this node at SRI and use a File
Transfer Protocol to download a new
version of it.
And this new version, would have all the new
hosts and then you'd be able to map those
host names to IP addresses.
Of course, if you don't have too many
hosts, this isn't bad, but, generally
speaking, the network capacity required by this
scales as n squared, in that
periodically end nodes, are going through
across the file, this in order n in
length.
So this was not seen as a scalable, good,
long term solution.
It's fine with just a couple of hosts, but
as the Internet grew, it clearly, it
quickly became a problem.
And this is what led to the birth of
what's called the Domain Name System or
DNS.
The basic problem DNS is trying to solve,
the basic tasks it's trying to complete is
to map names, human-neadable names to
addresses or more generally these days,
to values.
Originally, it was to map IP addresses, it
turns out nowadays, you can use it
for much more.
And there are a couple of design
considerations for the Domain Name System.
The first is we'd like it to be able to handle a
huge number of records.
In theory, there are two to the 32 IP addresses,
we should be able to map names on that
kind of order.
Furthermore, we'd like to have distributed
control.
One of the problems with hosts.txt is
there's a single, centralized repository.  It should be that  that we can say, this set of
names, you can manage them, this other set of names, you can manage them.
So, Stanford, you can manage names under
Stanford but Amazon you can manage names
under Amazon.
Furthermore, we'd like this system to be
robust to individual node failures.
It shouldn't be that if one node goes
down, the entire domain name system comes
down, because if that's the case, then
suddenly we can no longer map names to
addresses and lots of things would grind to
a halt, so we want to be robust.
And this might seem like an amazingly
challenging problem.
We want to handle, you know, billions of
records distributed hierarchically across
the entire Internet and which is robust to
failures.
But, there are two things
which turn out to make this problem
tractable, to make the design
feasible.
The first is that this database that maps
names to values is read-only or read
mostly.  There are updates to it, but
we generally expect that it is going to be
read much more than it's written.
There are nodes
coming in and out all the time, but
nothing compared to the way which we're
looking nodes up.
Furthermore, we don't need perfect
consistency.
We can have, have something called loose
So, if a node connects to the internet or
if say, a node, a mapping between a name
and an address changes, it's okay if
there's some delay before everyone sees
that.
It might be some people see it a little
earlier than others, but it's okay if
there's some delay.
And so, it turns out that these two
properties together, that it's a read
mostly database and that it's okay if things
are slightly out of date, allows DNS to,
to have extensive caching.
The idea is that once you have a result,
you can hold onto it for a long time, and
then, maybe when it expires, request a new
result, but rather than have one place
that has to be asked for everything,
You can ask some place once, and then
cache that result  and answer it for
other people.
So you can look up a name and then keep
the result for a long time and then use it
to answer other queries.
So, recall that one of the requirements is
that names be hierarchically administered, so
that you can distribute the administration
of names.
And to accomplish that, DNS uses a
hierarchy of names and we're all familiar
with this.
So, at the top, there's implicitly what's
called dot or what's called the root of
the DNS namespace.
It's an
empty name.
So these are called the root servers, just
dot.
Then beneath them are what's called the
top-level domains, or TLDs
TLDs such as EDU, COM, ORG, US, France, and
China.
And underneath each of those top-level
domains, there are what we often think of
as domain names, say stanford.edu, or
cisco.com, or buydoo.cn.
And, of course, within those domains the
owner of those domains can hand out
additional names, additional domains.
So, for example, Stanford, generally,
there's just one level of names below
Stanford.
So, there's cs.stanford.edu, www.stanford.edu.
Berkeley has another layer.
So, there is cs.berkeley, there is the cs
domain, and there are names under the cs
domain like www.cs.berkeley.edu.
Similarly, Google has maps.google.com.
So, now the way DNS servers work is that
there are these hierarchical zones.
There's the root zone, then the TLDs, then
the domains, and then there can be
subdomains.
So Stanford for example, as you may have seen
so far, it does have a subdomain SCS
managed by David Mazieres.
And the key thing is that, each of these
zones can be separately administered.
So, Stanford can grant David Mazieres the
domain SCS, so it'll answer questions
about SCS.
But then, David can completely control all
of the host names underneath SCS.
Similarly, EDU can grant Stanford the name
Stanford, but then it's completely up to
Stanford to manage all of the names
beneath Stanford.
Furthermore, each zone can be served from
several replicated servers.
And so, rather than there's being one
server that serves Stanford's name, there
are in fact many servers, replicated, and
there's some rules as to how they're
replicated.
The idea is that if one server goes down,
there are others that can still answer
questions about Stanford.
So, it turns out the root zone, so the
zone you'd ask for, hey, who do I ask about
EDU?
There are thirteen servers labeled A to M
and they're highly replicated.
And so there's, sort of this bootstrapping
process of your computer comes up for the
first time and wants to ask a name and it
knows nothing.
Well, it needs to talk to a root server in
order to contact, say a top-level domain
server.
But how does it find the root servers?
It turns out that these are generally just
IPs that are stored in a name, in the
file in the name servers.
So, the name server comes up and it has
some IP addresses for root servers.
And then, the first query that comes in,
let's say, it's for stanford.edu, it knows
that it needs to talk to the EDU servers,
and so, it can ask the root servers, hey,
who has EDU?
Then, when it gets the response who has
EDU, it can contact the EDU server, hey,
who has Stanford?
In addition to having these thirteen
different servers, they're highly
replicated through something called
anycast, IP Anycast, where it turns out
that there are many machines that have the
same IP address, which basically causes
you to contact the one that is closest to
you.
So this makes the root servers highly,
highly robust.
Often, when you hear about large-scale
distributed denial-of-service or DDoS
attacks against the root servers.
This is exactly what they're talking
about.
It's when people are trying to attack the DNS
root servers to try to cause the DNS system to
grind to a halt.
As of yet, nobody has yet succeeded.
There are so many of these servers, that
is so robust and it turns out their job is
so simple that people haven't been able to do it. But they
keep on trying.
So, here is a map of the DNS root server.
So, A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K, L J,
K, L, M.
So I colored, all these
different A servers or A server, A, B A,
B, D, E, G, H, L.
And then for the anycast instances for C,
F, I, J, K, M you can see that they're
spread all over the world.
So, this means, let's say, if you're
somebody in Saudi
Arabia and you want to issue a DNS query, you
don't have to go very far.
There's some that are very close by.
Okay.
So, that's the basic naming architecture
and it gives a sense as to what DNS servers are
and how they are structured into these
hierarchies.
So, what does a query actually look like?
So, there are two kinds of DNS queries,
recursive and non-recursive.
A recursive query asks the server you
contact to resolve the entire
query.
So, you're asking it a question, and then
if there's many steps to the question, then
it should ask each of those steps.
As opposed to a non-recursive query, where
you're going to contact the server, it's
just going to answer one step of the
query.
And, I'll show why this difference occurs
in a second.
And you  specify just a bit in the query, to say
whether it's a recursive or nonrecursive
query.
So, DNS usually uses UDP port 53 and
there's a 512 byte message limit.
You can use TCP port 53 and then
all the DNS messages have a sixteen bit
length field so you know how long
they are since they are not datagrams, they're a stream.
So, let's say that I'm a client.
So, here is me.
And I want to ask the question, hey, what
is the IP address associated with
www.stanford.edu?
So, using DHCP I have an address for a DNS
server and so, let's just, let's call this
here a resolver and it has some address R.
And so, I send a DNS request or DNS query
saying I need the IP address for
www.stanford.edu and I send this message
to the resolver.
So, I'm asking for the  address of
www.stanford.edu.
And I asked this as a recursive query.
So the resolver is going to, resolve this
entire query recursively for me.
Let's say, my resolver has nothing cached.
It doesn't know anything about the world.
It just has the IP address of some root
servers.
Well, the first thing it's going to do is
it needs to figure out whom to ask a
question about EDU.
So, where are the servers for
EDU?
So, it sends a query to one of the root
servers saying, hey, who do I ask about
EDU?
This is a non-recursive query.
I can't ask the root
servers to answer the whole query for me
and start contacting other people.
They're just going to answer one step,
they'll answer, hey, who shall I talk to
about EDU?
And the root will send a response saying,
here's some information for who you should
talk about EDU.
Now, the resolver knows, okay, now
I can cache the entry for EDU, great, I
can put it in my cache.
This is the IP address I should contact
for the question about EDU, now let me
contact that IP address.
That's going to ask EDU, hey, who should I
ask about Stanford?
Again, this is a non-recursive query.
The edu sever is going to say, okay,
here's your information about whom you
should ask about Stanford.
I can then cache that result, and ask that
server, that's the domain server.
So now I'm going to say, Stanford, what's
the address for WWW?
And Stanford can respond, say aha!, here
is the address for www.stanford.edu.
And then the resolver can cache this
result.
Www.stanford.edu.
Now, the resolver can cache these values, so that  if I want to ask the question about
EDU, what DNS server should I talk to.
If I want to ask a question about
stanford.edu, what DNS server should I
talk to and what's the address for
www.stanford.edu?
And then, it can return this result to the
client.
Here is the IP address for
www.stanford.edu.
And that's the basic operation of a DNS
query.
It starts with the client asking recursive
query of the resolver.
The resolver may then ask non-recursive
queries to servers in the network in order
to generate the response, which it then sends
to the client.
It could also be that the resolver had
answered this question before.
And so, rather than go and ask all the
servers, it can just answer from its cache.
So, if a couple minutes later, another
client asks the same question, "hey, what's
the address of www.stanford.edu," this
resolver, rather than contact
anyone, can just return the cached result.
And so, if you ever hear in the, the news, about
DNS cache poisoning.
There's this aspect of DNS, attacks
try to take advantage of, which is that, if you can
get a bad record into the resolver,
somehow convince it that
www.stanford.edu actually points at
www.evil.com, or something, such that if
you try to go to Stanford, instead you'll
go to evil hacker's server.
So if you can get that cache entry into
the resolver, and poison the cache, then
anybody who asks that question is going to
get that answer.
And so, later in the course we talked
about security, we'll see some of the ways
in which that can happen and some ways in
which DNS can help solve it.