So in this video, we're talking about
congestion control.
Particularly the basic motivation for, for
congestion control and transport
protocols, and protocols in general,
And walk through the first example of a
protocol that really identified and
tackled this problem, TCP,
Particular version TCP called TCP Tahoe.
And I'll talk about the first mechanism
that TCP Tahoe uses to try and deal with
congestion, something called slow start.
So the basic motivation for congestion
control is that flow control tells an
endpoint say, is going to tell, Boston is
going to tell San Francisco the amount of
data they can accept.
And so flow control specifies the
limitations of the endpoint.
However, it can very well be that this
node in Boston is able to receive data
much, much faster than the network can
support it. So for example, while this
node in Boston might have, you know a
buffer that allows it to receive 100
packets per RTT, per RTT, it could be that
some bottleneck link on the path from San
Francisco to Boston can really only
support about five packets per RTT.
And so, the idea's that if San Francisco
communicates with Boston, this node in San
Francisco communicates with a node in
Boston at a rate which flow control would
allow. Then it's going to send packets
much faster than it can support and most
of these packets are going to be dropped
and it's going to spend a lot of its time
doing retransmissions trying to recover
from these heavy errors.
You don't want to saturate the network,
because everything will work less
efficiently than if most packets, arrive
require less control over head will
generally work better.
And so, the basic idea of congestion
control is tnat end point should can
control their data rate,
So that they do not overload the network.
This will generally increase the
performance of the network.
So if we just take a step back in terms of
congestion control, what really led to it
as this very important area of study and
of engineering in the Internet, it all
comes from TCP.
So basic history of TCP in 1974,
established in 3-way handshake, you know syn, syn-ack ack.
In 1978, TCP and IP were split were split.
It used to be that the internet, or at
that point the ARPAnet just supported TCP,
but they realized, oh, we need to split
them because we need stuff like UDP.
Then January one 1983, that was, you know,
the, the switch date when suddenly the
entire ARPAnet switched over to TCP/IP,
IPv4.
Three years after that, the Internet began
to suffer congestion collapse, where links
were saturated.
They were sending, you know, operating at
line speed, yet no worse, useful work was
being done.
Instead, all the packets being transmitted
were unnecessary retransmissions or
acknowledgments.
So you're seeing full utilization of
links, while simultaneously no application
level throughput.
So then, Van Jacobson in the seminal paper
fixed TCP, figured out what was going on
and he published this seminal TCP paper
which described TCP Tahoe These names
Tahoe and Reno come from the versions of
hardware for Berekely Unix that these TCP
implementations occurred on.
And so, you read about Tahoe, Reno and
then after they start getting names like
New Reno, Vegas, Daytona, just to follow
that theme.
But Tahoe and Reno were denoted by
versions of Berkeley, of Berkeley Unix.
They were distributed in the hardware they
were for. So then about, you know, a
couple years after, this first TCP Tahoe,
A fast recovery and fast retransmit,
Assuming it's in a future TCP version,
we'll talk about it in a later,
Video TCP Reno.
Which were, are common today,
But at the time, they were new ideas, were
added.
And so if you look, basically all TCP
implementations today have the mechanisms
that are in TCP Tahoe and TCP Reno and so
we're going to go through them in this
series of videos.
So, there are basically three questions
that a transport protocol needs to answer,
if it is going to provide reliable
transport.
Alright? The first is, when should it send
new data?
That is, when should it send data, which,
you know, has never put all in a network
before?
Second is, when should it send a
retransmission?
When should it try to retransmit data it
has sent before?
And finally, when should it send
acknowledgements for data that it
successfully received?
These are these basic things of as to when
is it going to generate packets?
Alright?
Whether they're data packets,
retransmissions of data packets, or
acknowledgement packets. You know, of course
often, we talk about data and
acknowledgement packets as being
independent, but in TCP they're not.
The acknowledgements are simply a field
and a header, and you can of course,
piggyback data in an acknowledgement.
But often we just talk about data
acknowledgment separately, just pretending
that the flow is unidirectional though
often it might not be.
It might be bidirectional.
The point being that it can be that you
have no data to send, but you do need to
send an acknowledgment.
So what did TCP look like before TCP
Tahoe?
So essentially, what happens is you set up
a connection through the, through a
handshake and an endpoint now has the flow
control window size, denoted by the window
field of a TCP header.
And so what, pre-Tahoe, what TCP would do
is, this seemed like a simple thing.
It would just send a full window of
packets of the window said, Ah-ha!
I'm 30 kilobytes, it would send 30
kilobytes worth of packets.
So it's just obeying the flow control.
We then start a retransmit timer for each
packet, and then, if it didn't receive an
acknowledgement for that packet by the
time the transmit retransmit timer fired,
it would then retransmit that packet.
And so, the basic problem this encounters,
what happens if the flow control window is
much larger than what the network can
support?
It might be that your endpoint has space
for 30 kilobytes, but you know, the link
is already saturated, you can't suddenly
just dump another 30 kilobytes on it.
I mean these numbers might seem small now,
but back then these were, you know, you
had 50, you, you have relatively slow
links in comparison to today's speed.
So I think of it is more of like your
window suddenly advertised 30 megabytes.
You don't usually want to dump 30
megabytes onto your DSL or your cable
modem link immediately.
So, if you implement that algorithm, you
just send a window of packets,
What happens?
Well, see here's the picture.
So, here it's showing, on the X-axis is
the time in seconds and the Y-axis is the
packet frequency number, the, in terms of
kilo bytes,
So the sequence number of the byte that
TCP has sent.
And so, what you see is, on connection
establishment, it immediately sends a full
buffer of packets, about twenty kilobytes
worth.
And then it's getting some
acknowledgments,
So it's sending some more data.
But then, suddenly it's window is, a
certain size, the flow control window, and
it hasn't received an acknowledgment for
this, this segment here.
And so, at this point TCP is blocked.
Right the, here's the, these dots are
showing the packet they are transmitted
to.
So at this point it's blocked in that it
has sent up to the last acknowledged byte
plus the window size and it can't send any
more and the reason is that this packet
probably was lost.
So then here's the, basically, here's the
time out and it retransmits that packet
then as you can see, it's able to send a
whole bunch more packets.
It gets a whole bunch of acknowledgments
or it gets accumulative acknowledgment
allowing the window to move forward,
etcetera, etcetera.
But the basic point to see here is that
there are these huge sawtooths that you
see, big bursts of packets followed by
idle timeouts.
Big bursts of packets followed by idle
timeouts.
And that many of these packets are
redundant like this particular packet,
here, is sent three times.
This one is also sent three times.
So, you've seen lots of additional
retransmissions and overall, the protocol
is not performing very well.
It's sending all this packets, but if you
look at the actual slope of this line, the
sense of the data out sending, the slope
isn't very high.
If TCP were operating at line speed,
operating at the correct speed, it should
be following this line here, but instead,
it's following the line of the much lower
slope.
It's actually sending data much slower
than it should be able to.
So this is what was observed, that TCP is
very slow because it's sending lots of
retransmissions unnecessarily and there
are lots of time outs.
So based on this Van Jacobson proposed
three improvements.
The first is the idea of a congestion
window, the second is better timeout
estimation, and the last is self-clocking.
I'm going to walk through each of those.
Congestion, the congestion window, going
to talk about in this video.
In future videos, I'll talk about timeout
estimation and self-clocking.
So, the congestion window.
So, the basic insight is that the flow
control window is only about the endpoint.
And so what you want to do is have TCP
estimate a congestion window, that is how
much can the network support, when I, in
the sense of how quickly can I send data
and have the network deliver it reliably?
And then the sender windows can be the
minimum of these two.
Since there is no point sending data
faster than the network can support nor is
there any point sending data faster than
the end host can support.
And then, what you do is based on this
idea of a congestion window, you separate
how you behave in terms of sending packets
in the size of this congestion window into
two states.
The first is something called slow start.
The second is congestion avoidance.
You slow start when you're doing
connection start up or when there's a
packet timeout,
When something has gone very wrong and you
want to back off completely and figure out
what it is that the network can support.
Congestion avoidance, in contrast, is when
the network, when you're behaving pretty
well,
That is, you're operating close to the
network capacity and so you don't want to
start sending things much faster nor much
slower.
You're operating close to what you think
the congestion window of the network is.
So the idea of slow start is that, what
the node does, is rather than start its
window at the flow control window size, it
starts its window at the size of a, maximium segment size.
So basically, one, one packet's worth of
data.
Today nodes might start with two or four
there's some, some rules about that, two,
three, two, three or four, but the
original version started at one.
And then, everytime a packet's
acknowledged, everytime you receive a new
acknowledgment, you increase this window
by the maximum segment size.
And what this means in terms of practice
is that in the first roundtrip time,
you're going to send a single packet,
it'll be acknowledged,
And now your segment size, now your window
size is two, so you'll send two packets.
They'll both be acknowledged.
You'll increase by two and it'll send four
packets.
They'll be acknowledged.
You'll then send eight packets.
There's this exponential growth.
And so that's what you're seeing here.
See, here's one packet, two packets, or
there's, one, two, four, you know, eight,
etcetera.
There's exponential growth scaling up,
So in a log, logarithmic number of steps,
you can hopefully what is the, the
congestion window size of the network.
So this might seem, exponential growth is
not slow, and so the name is, it can be a
little confusing.
The reason it's called slow is that it's
slow compared to the prior approach.
It's actually the most faster mode of TCP
today, but compared to sending an entire
flow control window of packets, doing this
exponential scale up through logarithmic
number of steps was comparatively slow.
So it's an interesting sort of historic
compare to the modern, modern idea.
And so you can see in this figure, this is
also from Van Jacobson's paper that, the
packet sequence number, you know it's
increasing this way and you see this
exponential growth, and then using slow
start, you end up plus then the congestion
avoidance state, that I'll talk about in a
moment, you end up hitting this nice
steady state and while it takes you a
little bit of time to discover what the
line speed is. Eventually the behavior of
the protocol is very close to this line
speed and it's operating close to
capacity.
It's not overwhelming it and you're not
seeing these sawtooths of terrible
performance.
.
So that's the slow start state.
So, in the slow start state, you are
increasing the congestion window by a
maximum of segment size for each
acknowledgement,
This leads to an exponential increase in
the window size.
The second state that you can be in is
called congestion avoidance.
And in this model, when you're in the
congestion avoidance state,
You increase the congestion window by end,
the maximum segment side squared divided
by the congestion window for each
acknowledgement.
And what this behavior results is rather
than increase by the window by maximum
segment size for each acknowledgement, you
end up increasing the maximum segment size
for each roundtrip time.
So it's an additive increase where as this
is growing the window size exponentially.
This is growing the window size linearly.
.
So we have these two states,
Slow start and congestion avoidance.
How do we transmission between them?
Well, really there are these, there are
these two goals.
One is slow start to quickly find what the
network congestion capacity is.
That is, how fast can we send things
before the network enters congestion and
starts buffering packets and dropping
packets.
And so then, once we are close to that
capacity, one is congestion avoidance, to
very carefully probe.
So we're below the congestion points.
Let's just start slowly increasing until
we reach it then maybe drop down a bit
then start slowly increasing it till we
reach it,
But basically can use that to stay close
to that value and be close to the network
capacity.
And we have three signals to accomplish
this.
Right?
The first is, if we're seeing increasing
acknowledgements,
That means that data transfer's going
well,
Maybe we can speed things up a bit.
The second is if we have duplicate
acknowledgements.
Remember, TCP's using cumulative
acknowledgement.
So if we're seeing many acknowledgements
for the same piece of data, that means TCP
is receiving segments, but one of them's
missing.
So this means something was lost or
delayed.
The final signal is that there's a
timeout.
If we sent a whole bunch of packets or a
window of packets and we've heard nothing
and there's a timeout, that means
something very wrong has happened.
We're maybe way off of what the congestion
is or maybe the network has suddenly
become congested, 'because it itself can
have dynamic traffic.
So this is the TCP Tahoe finite state
machine.
I am going to walk through it bit by bit.
So, when you open a TCP Tahoe connection,
you start in the slow start state with a
maximum, with a window of a maximum
segment size and recall that your actual
window will never grow larger than your
flow control window, the minimum of the
flow control window and congestion control
window, so this is controlling the
congestion control window size.
Then everytime we're in the slow start
state and receive an acknowledgement, we
increase the congestion window, this cwnd
by the maximum segment size.
So this is the exponential increase here.
Then, we have a parameter ssthresh, which
is this, stands for slow start threshold.
If the congestion window grows larger than
the slow start threshold, then we
transition to the congestion avoidance
state.
This means that hey, we suddenly have a
big enough congestion window than we
should slow down our growth and so we
transition the congestion avoidance.
Now in the congestion avoidance state, if
we receive an acknowledgement, increase
the congestion window by a maximum segment
size squared divided by the congestion
window, this is the linear increase.
And so, we see that the window size will
look like this over time effective, where
here is where we hit ssthres,.
And this part corresponds to this state,
this part corresponds to this state.
But now, what happens if we're in the
congestion avoidance state, and this
linear increase goes beyond the congestion
capacity of the network?
Well, what's going to happen is we're
going to see a time-out or a triple
duplicate ack.
A triple duplicate ack, this implies a
packet was lost.
We're seeing this, this many
acknowledgements.
And so what TCP Tahoe does on seeing
either a time-out or triple duplicate ack
is it resets the congestion window to be
one and sets the ssthresh to the old
congestion window divided by two.
And so what this is going to do, is after,
say this, we see this linear growth,
And then at this point, say we see a
triple duplicate ack.
What'll happen is that TCP Tahoe is going
to set,
This blue, is going to set ssthresh to be
half of what the congestion window is at
that time.
It's then going to re-enter slow start, do
an exponential increase until it reaches
this ssthresh, and which point, will then,
SS threshold, at which point will then
enter congestion avoidance and do a linear
increase.
And so a way to think of this is that upon
this triple-duplicate ack, or this
time-out,
The TCP Tahoe has discovered what it
thinks is too much, too fast a
transmission rate, the window is too big.
So then what it does is it says, okay, I'm
going to exponentially grow my window
until I reach half of that point and then
it'll start linearly increasing it.
And so that way you can hopefully quickly
get back to, you know, close to capacity
in a logarithmic number of steps, but
then you don't want to get too close and
so you start with half of, half of what
that old value was and start linearly
increasing again.
So this is the basic Finite State Machine
for TCP Tahoe.
So here I will walk through a simple
example.
So we start with a sender, and let's just
say, ssthresh,
Is equal to four when it starts up.
So, first it's going to send a single TCP
segment; single maximum segment size
segment.
The receiver let's just call this one, I'll
number them a packets for simplicity,
The receiver sends an acknowledgement.
So at this point here our congestion
window is equal to one.
Now since we are in the slow start state
it will become two.
It comes two, and so the sender can send
two packets.
Three and four.
The receiver receives them.
I'm sorry, two and three.
The receiver receives them, sends
acknowledgments.
Now our congestion window is four,
Which means that we will send, four
packets,
Which would be four, five, six, seven.
Now, at this point, congestion window has
reached the slow start threshold, which
means that TCP Tahoe is going to exit
the slow start state and enter the
congestion avoidance state. And so when
these acknowledgements come back,
It's going to increase the window by one
and so rather than send eight packets,
congestion window will be five.
.
And you'll send five packets.
So let's just say I was drawing one arrow
here of packets eight, nine, ten, eleven,
twelve.
Now, let's say that packet eight is lost.
It's dropped in the network.
We've actually reached our congestion
point.
Well, what will happen?
Well, the receiver is going to acknowledge
eight.
It's going to acknowledge that eight was
received and remember this TCP so the
ac\k would actually say nine but it'll just write,
write eight for simplicity's sake.
So we're going to say, aha, I've received
eight,
Then ten, eleven, and twelve arrive.
Now, TCP is going to then send
acknowledgment, eight,
Eight, eight,
Because it's accumulative
acknowledgements, it hasn't received nine,
it can only say I've received eight, I've
received eight, received eight.
This is a triple duplicate acknowledgement
we have three duplicates.
So what now, TCP, Tahoe is going to do, is
it's going to transition back to the slow
start state.
My congestion window is five, so I'm going
to set my slow start threshold to be equal
to half of the congestion window.
Right?
So, let's just say we are going to set it
to basically 2.5 and enter the slow start
state again,
So I'll send a single packet.
Right.
Now this packet is going to be sent on a
time-out,
So essentially I'm waiting for the
acknowledgement nine.
I haven't heard it, I'll time-out and I
will send, I will resend nine,
Then that's the number of packets I can
have outstanding.
Then if an acknowledgement for nine comes
back, I can set my congestion window to
two.
But this acknowledgment won't just be for
nine because it received ten, eleven and
twelve,
So that acknowledgment is actually going
to say is acknowledge twelve.
So I now move my congestion window to two, I
know twelve has been received.
I can send thirteen and fourteen and I'm back
in the slow start state, until I reach
this ssthreshold in which point I'll
transition back to congestion avoidance.
So that's a basic walk through of TCP
Tahoe and how it behaves.
It's moving between slow start and
congestion avoidance and how it's using
triple duplicate acts in order to infer
that something has gone wrong.
And we're turned back to the slow start
state.
It's using that to infer that there's
congestion and slow down.