So, in this video we talk about
Fragmentation and Assembly.
So here's the basic problem that
fragmentation assembly tries to solve.
Let's say that myth is some some
machine I'm using at Stanford in the myth
cluster and I wanna request a web page
from Google.
And Google's web page that it sends, this
HTTP response, is ten kilobytes long.
Well a ten kilobyte chunk of data is
pretty big, and the problem is there might
be some hop along the path from Google to
Myth that can't support a ten kilobyte
packet.
In fact in Ethernet the maximum transfer
unit that many speeds of ethernet supports is
1500 bytes.
And so what I need to do is take this ten
kilobyte packet, and break it into a series
of chunks, smaller pieces called fragments
which the network can support.
So imagine like the extreme case if I'm downloading something
really big, I don't want to be sending one
gigabyte packets.
They're gonna occupy the, the channel for
huge amounts of time, so I wanna break
things into smaller chunks.
So in this case, if I had say, an ethernet
frame size of 1.5 kB, I'll need to
split this ten kilobytes into seven
fragments, where these first six could be
1.5 kB each, and the last one say is one
kilobyte.
So that's the process of fragmentation.
And these fragments arrive at myth, and
its job is to assemble
(this is assembly)
So to take these seven fragments, two,
three, four, five, six, seven And
reassemble them to the original ten
kilobytes of data.
And so generally speaking, fragmentation
and assembly occur when a higher layer's
data unit is larger than what a lower
layer can support.
So, fragmentation, the process of taking a
large chunk of data and breaking it into
smaller pieces that the lower layer can
support.
And assembly is in the process of taking
these fragments and reassembling them into
the original data.
This occurs in many different places in
networks at, different layers.
For example, it can occur at the
transport layer.
So, TCP does this when it takes a stream
of data.
It breaks it into segments, which are then
transmitted and reassembled at the other
side into a reliable stream.
And this assembly is now current, end to
end, between the two TCP end points.
Such that a given TCP segment, once it's
generated by an end point, is then
indivisible, and arrives at the other end.
You never see a segment broken into two
separate segments.
Although underneath it might be broken
into packets or frames, as we will show.
Contrast to the network layer, it's
operating on a host to host basis.
This is unlike TCP, where once segment is
sent, that's the segment the end point
will receive, if it arrives.
With IP, at the network layer is possible to
some intermediate node takes the packet
and breaks it up.
So, an IP packet, reversing the network at
some intermediate point, might be broken
into multiple IP fragments, which then the
end point has to reassemble into the
original IP packet.
This is at the network layer, and so can
occur within the network.
Finally, it can also occur at link layer.
So, one example is, there's a link layer
called, Zigbee or 802.15.4 that has a very
small frame size of approximately 120
bytes.
(It's 127 bytes, but you have to include header in
that.)
At times you wanna send large packets on
this frame size like an IPv6 packet, which
can be 1280 bytes.
And so what happens is that the IP layer
passes a 1,280 byte packet to 6-LoPAN
called IPV6 low power personal area
network.
It's to link layer support of IPV6.
And 6-LoPAN, the link layer, breaks it
up into fragments, which are then sent
over the link, reassembled at the other
end of the link Into an original packet.
So in this case the fragments are purely
on the link, and the network layer doesn't
see it.
In the IP case, the network layer sees it.
In the transport case, transport layer
sees it.
But the other actual transport
segments are not broken.
So let's walk through a concrete example.
One of the really common cases
of a fragmentation, or rather it's not
common, people try to avoid it but it's a
very simple mechanism so it's good to
explain, is how fragmentation works in IP,
at the internet protocol.
So let's imagine we have a route between
across three hops where the first and
second, the first and third hops use
ethernet with a maximum transfer unit of
1500 bytes, but the middle hop uses a
point to point link with a maximum
transfer unit of 576 bytes.
This means that at the link layer the
frames can only support, say 576 bytes of
data or 1,500 bytes of data in their
payload.
So what happens now is, some
application, the host on the left wants
to send a 1,400 byte payload.
And so on the first hop, this is fine.
We can take a 1400 byte payload.
An IP header is twenty bytes, and so we'd
have 1420 bytes.
We can then put that in ethernet frame
1420, fits just fine inside ethernet.
But what happens when we hit the second
host?
We can't take this 1400 byte payload and
put it in a PPP frame, because it won't
fit.
So what IP does is it takes the original
packet and splits it into three fragments.
So this is something which is gonna occur
here, at this node.
This node is going to receive an IP packet
with a 1400 byte payload and
its given IP header, Then realizing it
should go out over this PPP link, will
take it and generate three separate IP
packets, I'll show how they're formed by
in a minute, as separate PPP frames with
smaller payloads.
In this case, say 512, 512, and 376 bytes.
But so the trick though is that once this
packet has been fragmented at this second
node, those fragments then pass through
the network unchanged.
So the third node, here, does not
reassemble them.
Instead, what's gonna happen is that it's
going to just forward them along.
And put these three IP fragments inside
ethernet frames and forward them along to
the destination.
And then hopefully the destination will
receive all of them and reassemble the
original data of 1400 bytes.
So, how does this work?
So, if we look at an IP header there are a
couple of fields in it which allow this to
happen.
So basically, there's the "ident" field in
an IP packet here.
And the ident field is what allows the
fragmentation of assembly layer in IP, or
the fragmentation of assembly in IP, to be
able to tell whether or not these are
fragments of the same original packet.
So before fragmentation, we're gonna see a
packet that looks like this, where its
ident is, say, some value X.
And remember here, this is the, more
fragment bit, of the IP header.
This was zero here.
This is the more fragment bit.
And there's the offset field.
And so this is original packet, This
standard IP packet, it's just an
identifier.
There are no fragments.
There's an offset of zero.
And it's just a 1400 byte fragment.
But then after the packet is fragmented,
the more fragment bit is set for all with
the last fragment, so here, this first
fragment, here, and the second fragment,
both have the more fragment bits set to
indicate that more fragments are coming.
The last one does not.
And then the offset field tells a receiver
where this data begins.
And says we could see here, this is a 512
bytes of payload.
And so, this goes from offset zero to 511.
Now this second fragment is, is gonna
start at byte 512 and goes from byte 512
to 1024.
And so the offset field is what indicates
this.
So the offset field is not in terms of
bytes but rather in eight byte chunks.
And so 64 times eight is 512.
And so this tells the receiver that this
second fragment occurs at offset 512 within the
packet at offset zero.
And this is of course at offset 1024.
The ident field is identical in all three
fragments.
And so this means that now an, an endpoint
receiving these three fragments can
properly reassemble the origninal IP
datagram.
And so the combination of the ident field
and the source address is what allows it
to cluster these three fragments together.
And now since the offset field is encoded
in eight byte chunks, that means that each
of these chunks, or these fragments, must
be a multiple of eight
bytes long, except for the last one.
So fragmentation is, in the IP case,
really helpful cause it means an endpoint
can generate an IP packet without having
to worry about what the intermediate
maximum transfer units of the links are.
So it's a great way for an endpoint to be
able to generate packets without having to
know properties of the entire path,
especially if say the path is dynamic.
That being said, in practice, systems
really try to avoid IP fragmentation.
And the reason is you suddenly take in one
packet and make it into multiple packets.
It's now the chances that any one of those
packets might be dropped goes up.
Let's say you know, one percent of all
packets are dropped, suddenly you're increasing
the probability that any one of
those three, and therefore, will be
dropped and therefore the whole original
packet will have to be lost.
IP doesn't support any reliability or
re-transmission of these fragments so if
one fragment is lost, generally you have
to re-transmit all of them that's up to a
higher layer.
So generally you wanna avoid IP
fragmentation.
So one interesting trick that our approach
to the TCP sometimes uses is to actually
choose a segment size to avoid
fragmentation.
Since TCP segments can be of any size that
TCP wants, what it does is it tries to
generate segments which will fit inside IP
packets and not fragment on the path to
destination.
And the way it can do this is by setting
the don't fragment bit.
And so say a TCP connection window opens
up, it can say choose, well, I'm gonna try
sending, let's just say, a standard
Ethernet frame of 1500 bytes.
I'm gonna set the, the don't fragment bit
and if it gets an ICMP error saying, oh,
you know, couldn't send this thing
couldn't, I had to fragment it and I
couldn't, then it says I'll try something
else.
There must be some smaller link.
Oh, I'll see if maybe there's a 512 byte
PPP link.
And there's a bunch of ways you can search
for this.
One is to do a binary search, that's
expensive.
You can also try common, try common sizes
like 1500 bytes.
There is an RFC that talks about the
options.
But this is an approach where TCP can
actually sense the
properties of the path for connection, and
based on that pick an optimal segment size
such that it doesn't have fragmentation,
but it's also able to minimize header
overhead.
It's, has as much payload per header,
given that it's minimizing the number of
segments that it sends.