So in this video, I want to talk about,
some more modern versions TCP.
Tcp Reno and New Reno. Where TCP Tahoe
solved the congestion control problem,
such that, TCP could operate, the internet
could work again.
It wasn't necessarily as high performance
as it could be.
In the sense that it was a bit more
conservative than it need to be.
And so, since then, there have been
improvements to TCP.
Although, still keeping the original
mechanisms of TCP Tahoe, to
have it send data more quickly and have
higher performance.
So, we are going to walk through two of
those editions.
One is something called TCP Reno and then
TCP New Reno.
So, if you recall for TCP Tahoe.
If
the protocol is running and you encounter
a time out or triple duplicate ACK which
implies that there's a lost packet.
You do three things.
You set your slow start threshold to be
the congestion window divided by two.
So it's determining when you're going to
enter the congestion avoidance state as
the congestion window grows again.
You set the congestion window to one and
you enter the slow start state.
The idea here is that you're sending
along, you're sending data.
I should say, here is the window size.
You're sending data,
Something happens,
There's an event.
You set your threshold to be half of your
original window size.
You set your congestion window to be one.
You enter slow start again, exponential
growth.
And then when you reach this threshold,
you do additive increase again.
So that's TCP Tahoe's behavior.
And so here's a picture just showing that
a little more clearly.
So here we start with a congestion window
of size one.
We're in the slow start state.
Then there's say a triple duplicate ACK,
or a timeout.
We set the congestion window to be size
one again.
We have a slow start threshold here, which
is half of this value.
Right, so this is X, this is X over two.
So we do exponential growth again until we
reach this point.
Which point now we're on congestion
avoidance.
Linear increase.
Here we have a timeout.
The window size is staying stable.
Boom.
Drop down to congestion window size one
again.
Slow start,
Congestion avoidance, time out, etc.
So we see this behavior, of whenever we
have a triple duplicate ACK or a time out,
we end up reducing the congestion window to
a size one.
Going through slow start.
And then entering congestion avoidance.
So TCP Reno generally behaves similar to
TCP Tahoe with one exception which is
that, on a time line, it behaves the same
way, that it sets this congestion window
to be size one and does slow start again.
The assumption here is hey, things have
gone very wrong if I have a timeout, and
so I'm just going to assume nothing about
the network and pretend as if things are
starting from the beginning.
What TCP Reno does differently is on a
triple duplicate ACK it assumes, look, a
segment was lost, but other segments are
arriving.
Chances are I'm close to what my speed
should be.
I don't need to drop my congestion window
to size one, instead I still set the
threshold to be congestion window divided
by two, as before.
But I set my congestion window itself to
congestion window divided by two.
So, this is called fast recovery.
Rather than entering slow start again, I
just halve my congestion window.
Then it adds another mechanism.
This, called fast retransmit.
Which it'll, won't wait for the timeout on
a triple duplicate ack.
It says look, I have a triple duplicate
ack.
It means that, that segment is really
likely to be lost.
So I'm just going to retransmit
immediately.
And what this behavior means is that, on a
triple duplicate ACK, TCP Reno
will stay in the congestion avoidance
isn't going to require logarithmic number of
steps to enter that state which means
that the window size is bigger.
Fast retransmit means its not going to
have top wait for a time up and so in theory
it is its not going to have a couple of
round trip time towards them ramping up
and so its overall throughput will be
higher.
And so what, this is a picture showing TCP
Reno behaves under similar
circumstances.
Here we see we start and a slow start
state.
Here, slow start.
Then we have a triple duplicate ACK .
And rather than drop down to a congestion
window of size one, it sets, if our
congestion window here was X, it sets the
congestion window to be X divided by two.
And since that is the slow start
threshold, this causes the protocol to re
enter congestion avoidance, to enter
congestion avoidance.
And here we see a triple duplicate ACK.
Do the fast re-transmit.
We get the acknowledgement.
We're growing the window again.
And here we have a, a timeout.
You know, in a timeout TCP Reno behaves in
the same way, in that it says, it says
something has gone drastically wrong.
I set my congestion window to be one.
And enter the slow start state again.
So here we have a slow start, congestion
avoidance, congestion avoidance, timeout
and then triple duplicate ACK.
This is how TCP Reno behaves.
So let's walk through that.
This is my sender.
Sends packet one.
I get an acknowledgment one.
I send two and three.
I get acknowledgments two and three.
I then send.
Four, five, six, seven.
And let's say that, packet four is lost.
Well, the receiver is still going to send
acknowledgments.
But in response to five, six and seven,
it's going to send ACK three.
ACK three, three times.
So triple duplicate ACK.
So at this point my congestion window is
one, here it was two, here it was four.
Now in receiving this triple duplicate
ACK, TCP Reno's going to set its
congestion window to be 2 Immediately
retransmit we transmit, packet four.
Right, fast re-transmit, so here's the
fast re-transmit.
No time out.
And hopefully we will get an ACK seven
which point now we have congestion window
size, of size two, and we'll send packets
eight and nine.
So TCP Reno significantly improves TCP's
throughput, so you don't have to enter the
slow-start state and drop your congestion
window to size one just when a single
segment is lost.
TCP New Reno improves things even a little
bit more.
Essentially, it behaves the same as Tahoe
and Reno in timeout.
When you're in a fast recovery state, it
does something a little fancy with your
congestion window.
When you enter fast recovery, so this is
when there's a triple duplicate ACK on
every duplicate ACK that you receive, you
inflate the congestion window by the
maximum segment size.
Then when the last packet that's
outstanding is acknowledged you return to
the congestion avoidance state.
You set your congestion window back to the
value set when entering fast recovery.
And essentially what this is going to do
is, if I have a large window of
outstanding packets, say, you know, I had
a very large window.
In this case, let's just say let's say I
have eight packets.
That's not a super large window, but for a
drawing it's reasonable.
And this packet here is lost.
Right, so let's call this packet x.
So this packet is lost.
Each of these packets are going to trigger
duplicate acknowledgements.
And, as now TCP Reno receives duplicate
acknowledgements, it's going to start
inflating its congestion window size.
And as it inflates the congestion window
size, what that's going to let it do is
start sending new packets.
The idea here is we have evidence that
packets are leaving the network, and so
it's Okay to send new packets.
We don't want to sent them too quickly
because clearly we're close to the
congestion point of the network, but
otherwise what happens if we do a fast
retransmit.
We essentially have to wait for an entire
RTT before we can send a new packet.
We have to do this new retransmission and
then we get the acknowledgment we can then
move the window forward.
And there is this whole RTT where
essentially TCP sits idle.
And you see that, in this example here
where gosh, we have the situation where
there are these long, there are these idle
periods waiting for the re-transmission.
And so essentially what this
tweak which I will walk through explicitly in a second
allows TCP New Reno to do is to start
sending out new packets while the fast
retransmit is in flight.
It starts inflating the congestion window
to be bigger so that even though this was
the last acknowledged packet, it can start
sending new packets.
But then once we get a proper
acknowledgement, like let's say we get an
acknowledgement for this segment here,
then it suddenly reduces the congestion
window size to the right size so it's not
like we've suddenly saturated the network.
So let's walk through what this looks
like.
So let's say we have a congestion window
of size...
Sixteen and we encounter a triple
duplicate ACK.
So, the rules mean we're going to set the
congestion window to be eight.
So at this point, we have a triple
duplicate ACK, the congestion window
becomes eight.
And we are going to do fast retransmit.
And so triple duplicate ACK comes in and we
send out fast retransmit.
, Meanwhile, while that fast retransmit
packet is outstanding, we're receiving
additional acknowledgements,
Right? the window size was sixteen and so
we had a triple duplicate ACK.
Essentially, we expect to receive order
sixteen, or fifteen duplicate ACKs.
And so, as those start streaming in, what
we're going to do is increase the
congestion window by one for each.
And so we count those, those three triple
duplicate.
So over this interval here, the congestion
window is going to increase +one for each
of those duplicate acknowledgements.
Right?
Which means it's going to increase up to
23.
So this might seem really big.
So we've inflated our congestion window
from 16 to 23.
But think about what this means in terms
of the sequence number space.
So we had.
This window of packets, right, and this
was the last acknowledged packet here.
Let's just call it packet one, right?
And we started and we have an outstanding
window of size sixteen, right.
So we can safely send from packet one to
sixteen.
So we've got that last acknowledgement for
one.
You know we could send sixteen everything
is some way one was acknowledged.
Allows us to send seventeen so everything
is good.
Now we have a triple duplicate ack and
we're not going to be able to send
anything past seventeen until the
congestion window grows beyond seventeen.
And so it's starting at one and the
congestion window has shrunk to eight and
this mean that the valid packets we're
allowed to send.
Are two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, and nine, right?
That's not very helpful.
And so, now, as these additional
acknowledgements come in, we're going to
start inflating this.
So we're going to allow ourselves to send
to ten, to eleven, to twelve, to thirteen,
to fourteen, et cetera, et cetera, et
cetera, until when we get say the eighth
duplicate acknowledgement, now suddenly.
We have increased our congestion window
size back up to sixteen which means that
well we could resend seventeen, and then
when we get the ninth we've increased it
to seventeen, which means that we can now
send packet eighteen.
And so, this will then increase up to
twenty three, and essentially what this
does, is its inflates the congestion
window, so we can send up to packet 24
Now if you look at this carefully, packets
seventeen, eighteen, nineteen, twenty, 21,
22, 23, 24, that's eight packets which is
equal to what the actual congestion window
size is.
It's the idea that by inflating in this
way given that we halved it, now we are
adding plus one.
The last half of acknowledgements that
arrive will allow us to clock out new
packets.
And so, essentially, then, and as soon as
the, the faste retransmit acknowledgement
comes in, we just reset everything.
Gosh, we're acknowledged.
Our condition will go a size eight.
We can start moving forward.
But essentially what this does is this
inflating of the window.
After a triple duplicate acknowledgement,
allows TCP New Reno to continue to send
data while the faster transmit is in
flight.
And the amount of data its going to send
is equal to, and it's clocked by, again,
acknowledgements coming in, so you know
packets are leaving the network, the
expected congestion window size for the
next round trip time.
Assuming that the fast retransmitted
packet is delivered successfully.
So that's TCP Reno and New Reno.
New Reno is generally used on many systems
today.
Or at least the basis for TCP today.
I'll talk a little bit more about more
advanced TCP that deals with some modern
network considerations.
But you know, a Linux system, or a Windows
systems, MacOS systems, the basic TCP
algorithm that's running is very similar
to New Reno.
It turns out that congestion control is a
really hard problem.
And it's one of the hardest problem for,
to build a robust network system.
The basic approach that you see, has been
adopted.
And which seems very, very powerful, and
very robust, is this idea of added
increase multiplicative decrease that you
increase a window additively.,
Right?
But then reduce it multiplicatively, so
you respond very quickly when things go
badly and carefully increase it.
And the trick is when you're doing this is
how to keep the pipe full and improve throughput.
So there's things like fast retransmit.
Don't wait for a timeout just to send
very, very resend quickly.
And also things like congestion window
inflation or gosh I don't want to waste a
whole round trip time waiting for the fast
retransmit acknowledgment.
I know stuff's leaving the network I'm
going to start sending out some new
packets.
I'll allow these packets, packets have
left the network.