The video included a quick worked example.
In case you found the example hard to follow,
in this short video I will explain the same
example in more detail, and ask a few more
questions about the same example.
“At the start of every second, a train of
100 bits arrive to a queue at rate 1000 bits/second.
The departure rate from the queue is 500 bits/second.
The queue is served bit-by-bit, and you can
assume the buffer size is infinite.
What is the average queue occupancy?”
The cumulative arrival and departure processes
will look like this. First, look at the cumulative
arrivals, A(t) shown in red. In the first
1/10th of a second, 100bits will arrive at
rate 1000bits/second. There are no more arrivals
until 1s, then a new 100bits arrive. Now let’s
look at the departure process D(t) shown in
green. As soon as the first train of bits
starts to arrive at rate 1000bits/second,
bits will start departing, because the question
says they are served bit-by-bit. If we had
to wait for a whole packet to arrive, then
the departure process would not start increasing
yet. The bits take 0.2 seconds to depart because
they depart at 500bits/second which is half
the rate at which new bits arrive. The queue
therefore builds up, with a peak after 0.1seconds.
To answer the question, let’s look at the
occupancy of the queue Q(t) as a function
of time. The queue occupancy is the vertical
distance between A(t) and D(t) – it’s
the number of bits that have arrived up until
this point, minus those that have departed.
During the first 0.1s the queue builds up
as new bits arrive, to a peak of 50bits. During
the first 0.2s the average occupancy is 25bits.
Then the queue drains from 0.1s to 0.2s until
it is empty and all the bits have departed.
The queue is empty for 0.8s then the same
process repeats.
We can immediately calculate the time average
occupancy of the queue. It spends 0.2s with
an average occupancy of 25b, then 0.8s with
an occupancy of zero. The time average is
therefore 5bits.
The second question is: What is the average
delay of a bit in the queue?
Let’s look at the evolution of A(t) and
D(t) again. The delay seen by a bit arriving
at time t is d(t), the horizontal distance
between the two lines.
The first bit arriving at time zero experiences
no delay. Whereas a bit arriving at 0.1s experiences
a delay of 0.1s. Notice that no more bits
arrive after 0.1s, so it makes no sense to
consider the delay of a bit arriving between
0.1s and 1.0s. We are conditioning the probability
on a bit arriving, which only happens in the
first 0.1 of every second.
Therefore, the average delay seen by a bit
arriving to the queue is simply 0.05s.
Staying with the same queue, the third question
is: If the trains of 100 bits arrived at random
intervals, one train per second on average,
would the average queue occupancy be the same,
lower or higher than in part (a)?
The time average occupancy will be Higher.
When two trains arrived deterministically
in part (a), they never overlapped and so
there were never bits from two trains in the
queue at the same time. But if they arrive
randomly, we might have bits from two or more
trains in the queue at the same time, pushing
up the occupancy, and hence the average occupancy.
This might be surprising. Let’s look at
an example to see why this is true.
Consider two cases.
Case 1: Assume the trains arrive randomly,
but no two trains ever overlap. The average
queue occupancy would be the same as before,
which was 5bits.
As soon as two trains overlap, even once,
the average will increase. To see why, consider
the example here. The red line shows the queue
occupancy of tone train which we assume arrives
at time 0. Let’s say the second train arrives
at time 0.1s just when the queue has 50bits
in it still from the 1st train. The queue
will keep growing because bits are arriving
twice as fast as they are leaving. The queue
won’t drain until time 0.4s. If this happened
every two seconds, the arrival rate would
be the same as before, but the time average
queue occupancy would now be as follows.
For 0.4s the time average occupancy is 50b,
then for 1.6s it is empty. TO get the time
average, we divide by two seconds. The time
average occupancy is 10bits, which is double
what it was before.
Why is that? It’s because the queue only
drains at rate 500bits/second and so not only
does it fill to twice as much as before, it
also takes twice as long to drain. The triangle
showing when the queue is non-empty has four
times the area as before.
The fourth part of the question is: If the
departing bits from the queue are fed into
a second, identical queue with the same departure
rate, what is the average occupancy of the
second queue?
The second queue will have bits arrive at
500bits/second and depart at 500bits/second.
In other words, it will never accumulate bits
and will always be empty.