So in this video I'm going to talk about
retransmission strategies for transport
protocols in order to achieve reliability,
in particular for sliding window
protocols.
The basic question is, we have with some
sliding window or reliable transport,
A window of packets that are in flight.
Say one, two, three, four.
The reason, cumulative acknowledgements and
so all we get is something back such as
ACK 1, ACK 2, ACK 3, ACK 4
It's just the last byte of successfully
received,
The last packet of those successfully
received.
We're maintaining our retransmission timer
for each of these packets based on when
they were sent.
And, essentially maintaining conservative
estimate of, if we haven't received and
acknowledgement for the packet by this
time, then this means that it is almost
certain that the packet was lost and so we
should transmit it.
And so the question is,
Given this set of parameters which are generally used
for reliable transport, how is the
protocol going to behave?
What it is its restransmisson strategy
going to look like? So you see that
there's essentially two strategies you end
up seeing, you end up, so set up emerging from
different protocols.
The first thing we go-back-n.
The way to think is go-back-n as a
very pessimistic approach or pessimistic
behavior, which is that if a single packet
is lost, then we are going to retransmit the
entire outstanding window of packets.
Go-back-n, so with a  window size of N we
lose a packet.
Some packet, we're going back N
transmission so we transmit all of them.
The second is selective repeat, the way to
think of it is optimistic.
So, go-back-n assumes that if one
packet is lost, all of them are lost in
the window.
So, selective repeat, assumes that if one
packet is lost, only that packet is lost.
So with selective repeat, if we lose a
packet, it's not acknowledged.
We'll retransmit that packet and only that
packet.
So, lets look at what go-back-n
appears like, what's the behavior that you
see?
So, let's say that we have a window of
size equal to four.
And so the sender sends packet one, two,
three, four and packet two is lost.
So here are our four transmissions.
Well, in response to packet one, the
receiver is going to send acknowledgement,
acknowledgement one.
But it's not going to send acknowledgement
two.
And so what will happen at some point
we're going to have retransmit timer go
off and then in the go back n protocol,
what the sender is going to do is it's
going to re-transmit the entire
outstanding window into some kind of
timing.
And so don't forget, and window is going
to include five because in response to
this act one, it can send five.
And so the transmitter seeing the packet
two was lost, it's going to assume that
the entire window is lost and retransmit
the entire window.
So, it's very conservative very, or very
pessimistic.
So, now let's see what a selective repeat
protocol will do.
So again, N = four,
We transmit one, two, three, four.
One, two, three, four.
Packet two is lost.
Packet one is acknowledged, which lets us
send five.
And the selective repeat protocol, the
transmitter is going to retransmit two and
then we'll continue execution and transmit
six, seven, eight, nine ....
So, retransmit only the packets that were
not acknowledged.
So one question that comes up, is why
given that selective repeat doesn't,
sends fewer, why would you ever want to do
go back n?
Well, there are a couple of reasons.
One is that selective repeat, if actually
all of those packets were lost, if packet
two, three, four, Are they packets two,
three, four, five were all lost,
In order to do each of this
retransmissions involves timers and
round-trip times, so it can be much
slower.
If there's a burst of losses, a selective
repeat protocol off and be slower to
recover.
It's supposed to go back in, which assume
that all the packets are lost and
retransmits all of them and it can't get
going faster.
And so as the trade-off here between sort
of the amount of data that you send, how
quickly you send it and then how much if
it's wasted versus the speed of recovery
from significant errors.
So let's walk through two example transport
protocols and their configuration and see
how they behave, what happens.
So, in this first one, our sender has a
window of size N and let's say that N=4
just like the prior examples.
And the receiver has a window of size one
so the receive window size is one.
So based on this, is the protocol going to
behave just go back N or selective repeat?
Well, so let's walk through what happens.
So the sender, let's say is going to send
one, two, three, four.
One, two, three, four.
And let's say that packet two is lost so
it doesn't arrive.
Well, the receiver is going to acknowledge
one.
Which we'll allow the center to send five.
But the receiver is not going to
acknowledge two.
Now at some point, 2's retransmission
timer is going to fire and I'll retransmit two
But the thing is, that because the
receiver has a receive window size of only
one, it has been unable to buffer packets
three, four and five.
And so when it receives packet two, it's
going to ACK two.
The sender has not received the
acknowledgment for three.
It's going to have to retransmit three.
And then the receiver can acknowledge
three.
At some point, the sender can then start
using it for a window again with the point
being that since this first two was lost,
three, four, and five couldn't be
buffered.
The fact that receiver has a window size
of only one, it's going to force the
sender to retransmit every single packet
in the window.
So we're going to see that this behaves as
go-back-n.
So let's see a second example.
So in this case the sender has a window
size of n and the receiver has a window
size of n and let's say that for both of
them just again for simplicity sake this
is of size four.
So, in this case for the protocol be
go-back-n or selective repeat.
And so, let's walk through what happens.
We have again one, two, three, four.
Two is lost so I get an acknowledgement for
two, for one, ACK one results in packet
five being sent.
Then at some point two's transmission timer
fires so, I resend two.
Now the receiver has been able to buffer
these packets because there is a window of
size n so it had three packets buffer.
It can then, so here it's buffer. It had
packets three, four, and five.
Packet two arrives.
It can then acknowledge five.
So it might be that the sender was a
little aggressive, maybe it did retransmit
three or four or something, but the point
is that it doesn't have to.
For this to operate correctly is say just
waited for the, those transmission timers
or did slowly transmissions, etcetera that
the sender is going to resend only packet
two.
Only the outstanding packet that was not
acknowledged, the rest of the buffered,
receiver, and so we see this behaves as
selective-repeat.
So, when you're implementing transmit
protocols, say if you're take, if you're
doing, you're doing lab two.
But, the only thing you want to think
about is how you handle retransmission.
So one of the really important things is
that you don't retransmit earlier than you
should by which I mean it's not okay to
say start a retransmit term based on
packet one or packet two and then when two
has retransmit timer fires, retransmit
entire window.
Because it could very would be that three,
four, and five have been correctly
received or assuming as it happened but
you're going to retransmit them anyway.
You're very aggressively putting
additional packets in the network here.
Inflating the number of packets that are
beyond your window size.
Three, four, and five could still be in
the network here.
You're putting additional copies of them.
So, in that way, you want to be careful
about the number of packets you put in
there. You have to be careful about
retransmission policy.
As we'll see, which you can see is that,
on one hand you can assume trying to be
very conservative.
And look, if one packet was lost, I'm
going to assume that the others are lost
and then I'm going to retransmit the
entire window with the go back N policy.
Now what will happen if say, your receiver
has a window size of only one or you can
maybe be a little bit slower and say look,
one pack was lost.
I'm going to wait for one trip time and
transmit with that.
See if I can get acknowledge and see where
the acknowledgement puts me and then
perhaps just do a selective repeat and
transmit only the packet that needs to be
transmitted.