So in this video, we'll talk about the
basics of network address translation and
how network address translator or
NAT works.
So if you go back to the end-to-end
principle.
There's this idea, this strong end-to-end
argument, that the networks job is to
transmit datagrams as efficiently and
flexibly as possible, everything else
should be done at the fringes.
So in this model, we'll have say two hosts
that have IP addresses and really all the
Internet should do, all that the set of
hosts and devices between these two nodes
should do, is forward and transmit their,
their datagrams.
Should, you know send it along some route,
through the Internet figure out the best
route.
And deliver it, deliver those packets
between these two hosts that's all the
networks should do.
You want all the intelligence the edges
because that's where the action is, that's
where you can add new things.
And when you start adding stuff in the
middle then you start introducing the
dependencies and complexities and make the
world generally a tougher place.
So network address translator
or NAT was first specified a good while
ago in RFC 1631.
And so, NATs are really interesting
example, a really compelling example of
how.
Putting something, putting some smarts
into the network can have some really,
really nice benefits..., in some ways,
have some really attractive benefits.
We're also introducing that complexity can
cause a lot of headaches.
So essentially what a network address
translator does is, it's some box that
sits between you and the Internet, like
say this host on the left, so here's our
NAT.
And this NAT has its own IP address, for
the public Internet, so let's just call
that IP address X.
And what happens is, what a NAT does, is
that when a packet comes from your
computer, from what's called its internal
address, or its internal interface,
internal.
What the NAT does, in that its going to
somewhere out on the broader Internet.
So the NAT has an internal and an external
interface.
The NAT will rewrite your packet so it
appears like it is coming from the NAT's
external interface.
And so if the NAT, lets say it has
internal interface I and external
interface X, well your packet might be
from 171.64.15.55.
The NAT will rewrite it to be coming from
IP address X.
So then the packet goes to this other
host.
It sees a packet from X.
Maybe it's a TCP connection request or
something like that.
And so we'll send the packet back.
to X, so the destination here, the source is
X.
Here the destination is X.
Then now, on receiving this packet, will
know to, that it was actually intended for
you, will re-translate it, re-write the
packet to being from to destination X to
being your destination and then, forward
it appropriately to its internal
interface.
So this just turns out to have a bunch of
really nice advantages.
For example, almost all wireless routers
today are basically all wireless home
routers today are NATs.
The idea is you connect your wireless
router to your Internet connection, the ISP
gives you a single IP address.
Lets just call it X, then internally the
NAT can give many machines behind it
different private IP addresses just local
IP addresses and translate all of them to
a single public IP address.
So its a way for a whole bunch of nodes to
share an IP address.
And this is what allows you to have say
ten machines in your house with a single
IP address.
It's a NAT.
A single public routable IP address.
The NATs IP address.
So then this provides some security
properties, where because your IP
addresses are hidden behind this NAT, it's
actually becomes very hard for adversaries
or attackers to start opening
connections to machines.
So it's a limited kind of firewall,
security protection.
So NATs are really, really attractive and
popular.
They give you a bunch of great advantages,
a great piece of functionality.
Now let me walk through a more concrete
example with my feature as exactly what's
happening when you sit behind a NAT.
So there's two hosts, A and B.
And they're both behind NATs.
And they, these NATs are on completely
different networks so one of them has this
IP address 128.34.22,8.
So the other NAT is 76.18.117.20.
So there is two people at home, different
ISPs.
So the first thing to note, is that the
NATs are giving these hosts behind them,
these private IP addresses, starting with
ten.
So if you try to send a packet to 10.x on
the on the Internet, it doesn't go
anywhere.
It's considered a private, local address.
It might go to, in fact, you have one, to
one of your private, local machines.
So that can share these IP addresses.
In fact, it's possible for a machine
behind that B, and the or behind the NAT
on the right and the machine behind the
NAT on the left, to have the same IP
address.
Because, that appears only valid within
their, their small domain.
So, what happens now when A wants to open
a connection to this SSH server, out of
the network.
So, it's trying to open a connection,
well, this going to result in TCP SYN
packet.
Now, when A sends the message, the source
address is going to be 10.0.0.101 and the
destination will be 18.181.0.31.
The source port it's going to be some port
that A has decided on, let's just say
5,000 for simplicity.
The destination port is going to be 22.
Now when this packet traverses the NAT,
the NAT is going to translate the network
address.
It's going to rewrite the network address.
So rather than coming from 10.0.0.101, the
packets going to be coming from
128.34.22.8.
The destination will remain the same, the
destination port will remain the same.
But it turns out the NAT also has to
rewrite the source port, because otherwise
what happens if two hosts behind the NAT
both decide to use port 5000?
You can't share port 5000.
So rewrite the source port to be something
like you know, 8035.
This packet then goes out over the
Internet, reaches the SSH server which
sees a request from 128.34.22.8 port 8035.
It'll generate, say, a TCP SYN-ACK in
response.
To this IP address and port, when the NAT
sees that the packet come back in it's
going to re-translate that 128.34.22.8,
8035 to 10.0.0.1.1:5000 and forward that packet
to A.
And so it sets up a mapping between these
(internal port, IP) pair and an (external port,
IP) pair.
Similarly, when host B sends the packet to
the SSH server.
The NAT is going to translate its IP
address and port to its own.
So B's IP address to its own, so what was
once 10.1.1.1.9 port let's say 13013 is going to become.
76.18.117.20
let's say a port 2009.
So then when the ssh servers sends the
TCP SYN-ACK back
You know send it to this (IP address, port)
pair, which the NAT can translate back to
the internal (IP address, port) pair and
deliver to node B.
So how does this work?
The NAT is magically setting up these
mapping you know.
How is it managing these mapping?
Well, turns out there's all kinds of
different ways NAT can operate and we'll
look at that in some future videos.
But the basic model is that the NAT
doesn't create a mapping generally until
it gets a request from inside.
So, here we have the NAT's internal.
Interface, and here we have its external
interface.
.
So generally speaking, when the NAT sees
packets.
Destined to the external, to nodes on the
external interface.
That is Internet at large, from nodes on
its internal interface.
In response to those packets, it might
generate a mapping.
So in this case, let's say A is trying to
open a packet to server S, port 22.
And so there's a packet coming in from
10.0.0.101.
I mean, let's say it's a TCP packet.
And this is port, again, let's say, 5000,
, and it's going to 18.181.0.31 port 22 .
Well, that's going to say, Look, I see a
packet that is trying to open up a
connection.
What I need to do is allocate.
For this particular (internal IP, port) pair
and (external IP, port) pair, so let's say
128.34.22.8 port 7,009.
So it's going to create a mapping from
this, 10.0.0.101, 5,000.
To 128.34.22.8: 7009.
And this is for TCP and TCP only.
So then, the packet will traverse, it'll
look up this mapping, it will translate
the packet, send the packet with the
external IP address port.
Then when a packet comes back from the
server, it's going to look up and say,
Aha, I received a packet on my external
interface.
I'm going to see if I've any mappings
which match it, based on the protocol, IP
address, and port.
And then if so, translate the packet and
rewrite it to the internal address and
port.
So, that's at a high level in terms of
there's all kind of variations and all
kinds of details which we'll go into in
future lectures.
But that's the basic model.
And the NAT is maintaining some state so it
can translate the packets.
And generally speaking, it sets up this
state in response to receiving a packet
from a node on the internal interface,
requesting, or that's sending packets to a
node outside.
And so when you connect over wireless to
your wireless router at home, this is
what's happening.
When you, say, look up on your
using your network control panel and
you'll see what your IP address is, you'll
see that it's almost certainly a local
private address either something in the
10. range or 192.168 and then when you're sending
packets out to say servers on the Internet
then that is translating them to it's own
public IP address and port.
And so for example, lets look at my, my
Imac, here in my office, so if I look at
my, IP address, so it turns out the
wireless, EN1 that's the wireless
interface.
You can see in fact, I have a private.
Ip address.
10.33.6.35.
So this does not go out over the Internet
at large.
This is a local private address within
Stanford.
And so, that IP address can't be you say,
you know, Google servers cannot send me a
packet at that IP address.
This means that I'm sitting behind a NAT.
In fact, if I type, you know, what's my
IP, into a Google server, it tells me that
my IP address is 171.66.168.122.
And so what's happening here is that, I
have a private IP address of.
10.33.6.35 on the internal interface of
the network address translation box.
And, the external interface of the network
address translator is 171.66.168.22.
So, when I issue a connection request to
Google servers, this is the IP address
they see.
And, they send packets back to this IP
address.
When the NAT receives those packets, then
translates them back to my own private
local IP address, forwards those packets
to the connection setup.
So these are everywhere and you should
probably try this at home.