In the next two videos, I'm going to be
telling you about clocks and clock
recovery.
Whenever we send data over a link for
example, an Ethernet link, we normally
assume a data rate like ten megabits per
second or a gigabit per second.
When we send it ten megabits per second,
we're assuming that each bit lasts 100
nanoseconds, or 10,000,000 of them per
second.
And at a gigabit per second, we're
assuming each bit lasts a nanosecond.
So there must be some notion of a clock
somewhere, the clock that was used by the
transmitter in order to send those bits in
the first place.
And the receiver needs to know that clock
as well, in order to be able to correctly
decode them.
The problem is that there is no universal
reference for a clock which is precisely
the same in two places.
So the clock that's used, or the frequency
that's used by the transmitter is not
precisely known to the receiver.
It has to figure it out and so in figure
out when one bit ends and an other bit
begins.
So in this video, I am going to be
describing what the general problem is,
How we encode clock information with the
data to make the life, make life easier
for the receiver,
And then how the receiver can extract the
clock and use it to transfer it into it's
own clock domain,
Its owned frequency of clock, and then use
it and manipulate it, as you would like
in, at the receiver.
So the outline of what we're going to be
seeing is this, I'm going to be describing
how data is transmitted using a clock, and
the receiver needs to, er, know when to
sample the incoming bits, in order to
recover them correctly.
We'll see this in the context of what's
called asychronise communication for short
messages, but then the more common case is
sychronise communication, that's whats
used in, ethernet, and, and, and systems
like that where the data, is encoded along
with the clock, making it easier for the
receiver to recover the clock, at the far
end, and then move it into it's own clock
domain.
When we transmit data,
We always send it using a clock.
That's because we want it to have a
particular frequency.
So for example here, I show a server A,
sending data.
And, I've sort of zoomed in on the final
stage of processing just before the data
goes out on the, out on the wire.
This is a flip flop which is, just nearly
timing the data according to the, to the,
to the outgoing clock which is here ten
megahertz.
In other words, there's a, 100 nanosecond
period to this clock.
So this is a clock that we might use for
sending a ten megabits per second.
When we want to receive that data at the
other end.
You know, ideally, there would be a second
wire coming from here that could be used
in order to clock the data in at the other
end.
So that this would come in as the data.
And then would go to the receiver at the
other end.
This would take to two wires. We'd have to
send both the data and the clock.
And in most cases, we can't afford to do
that.
It would be much more efficient if we
could just send one of them.
So on here, we would have the, if we were
to do this, we'd have the data.
That could be the sequence zero one zero
one, one and then zero, zero.
And then down here, would just be the
clock that we would use in order to be
able to encode it at one end and decode it
at the other.
We're going to be looking at a number of
different examples where the clock is not
sent.
There's no specific or separate clock line
and in fact this is how it's done in
practice.
There's no separate clock that's sent.
Everything has to be determined from the
signal itself.
To illustrate the problem, let me start
with an example.
Imagine that we have a clock here.
And this is the clock that is being used
by the transmitter in order clock the data
out onto the wire.
Okay? So I put guidelines here just to
help me draw that.
So this is the, the TX clock.
I'll write that as TXCLK.
The data that's being sent.
Let's say in this example. We're going to,
every time there's a downward transition
in the clock, we're going to change the
data that's, that's put on the wire.
So, for example, let's say that it started
out idle.
And then it went to A1.
And that it went for a one here.
And then it continued as a one in the data
down to here.
And then we wanted to send a zero.
And then a, and so on.
So the data that is being sent is zero
one, one zero one and then we're sending
another one again here.
And so on.
At the receiver, let's look at the
receiver's clock.
And let's assume that the receiver's clock
is, nominally running at the same
frequency.
Although we didn't get it exactly right
because we were generating it locally, and
we were using a different, oscillator, for
example, in order to generate that.
And, they were designed to be the same,
nominally.
But they're very slightly different.
And so, in this case, we're going to
assume that, that receiver clock is
operating just a tad slower.
So it may have its transition at the same
place at the beginning.
But because it's running a little bit
slower,
Its first transition is a little bit later
than this one and so its next transition
is a little bit later again, then again a
little later and then its going to get a
little later and eventually just because
its running a little bit slower, its going
to start falling behind and you can see
that by the time we get all the way over
to here its upward transition is about the
same time as the transmit clocks downward
transition, so it's about out by half a
phase.
I've exaggerated it here in practice it
would be much closer than this but I'm
just exaggerating to show you what's going
on.
Okay, now.
The data on the, on, when we were sending
it was being changed on the downward
transition, and it, it kind of makes sense
to, for the receiver to try and identify
the middle of the bit and sample the bit
in the middle, so, here and here, and
here, if it can, because this if furthest
away from the edges, and so the data is
going to be at it's most stable, so we're
looking to, looking to sample that in the
middle.
So, for example, if we started sampling
here, right at the beginning, from the
receiver, we would pre-accurately detect
that as a zero.
So we would see that as a zero and
everything would be good.
Now, we're going to sample it again here.
We're a little later than we would have
been, than, than, than we would have
liked, but we're still going to reliably
see that as a one.
So, things are good.
And it really, we're going to sample it
here, we're getting a bit close to that
edge, let's give ourselves the benefit of
the doubt and say that we just caught that
one there.
By the time we come over here and sample
again, what she's sampling right here and
we're going miss this zero completely, so
when we sample here, we're going to see a
one again.
So this zero that happened in, in the
middle, this zero that was sent here, we
didn't sample, there were no up arrows at
that bit period of the receiver, so we
didn't see it, we missed it completely.
So clearly our ability to detect this is
going to depend on a couple of things.
One is, how different are these clocks?
I really exaggerated the difference here
and practiced the, the very, very similar
within a fraction within a percent.
In fact, we usually use we usually use
units of parts per million, ppm, parts per
million.
So for example, if we say that a clock is
within what, plus or minus a 100 parts per
million, we mean it's within plus or minus
that would be 0.01%.
That's because that's ten to the minus ten
to the minus four.
So that would be a typical value.
In fact, you couldn't get clocks that are,
that are as much as, as close as 50 parts
per million.
Still, if we go over enough bits.
So if it's 100 parts per million, we would
have to go over about 10,000 bit times,
and we would actually have shifted by a
complete bit in either direction.
And we don't know whether the receiver is
running faster or slower than the
transmitter.
So we don't know whether we're going to
accidentally double sample a bit, or we're
going to miss a bit completely.
Generally speaking, though, they hold at a
fairly constant frequency.
In other words, if one is faster, it's
likely to stay faster for, for quite a
while.
They're not drifting very quickly,
relative to each another.
They may just have a fixed offset.
So here we see the problem where we
incorrectly decoded the data because we
didn't have the clock.
Now, in some cases, we, we can still
communicate, without, having to
explicitly, understand what the clock is,
or, or, or be able to recover it.
In, in what's called asynchronous
communication.
Although we don't use this for networks
like, ethernet, it's used by things like,
infrared, re-, remote control, for a tv or
for short communication, it's also used on
the, serial bus that's, used to connect
computers, although that's not very much
anymore.
So for very short communications, so long
as we know nominally, that the transmitter
and receiver clock are about the same, we
can, we can make this work.
So for example, imagine that we had a very
short packet here consisting of just seven
bits, at the beggining, It has this big
bit of a beginning which looks like it has
a bigger amplitude just to tell us that
this is the start of the packet, and
there's one at the end to tell us that
it's the end of the packet, so the start
bit and the stop bit.
Then we have the sequence 0110100, this is
just the data inside the, inside the
packet.
So the, the transmit clock, that's what
was used in order to encode this in the
first place.
That's, that's correctly, detecting the,
the middle of each of these bits.
011,
Right in the center of all those bits,
'because that's what the, was used to
transmit it in the first place.
And here might be the receive clock.
The receive clock here is running a little
slower than the transmit clock.
You can see that the, there's a slight gap
between here and here, and that gap is
going to grow as we go on, closer to the
end of the bit. So long as, before we get
to the end of the packet,
The receiver it can still correctly decode
the bits.
And here it's can, can correctly decode
that zero.
Then we're okay.
So how did all of this work?
Well, after the start bit, the receiver
said I'm going to start sampling half a
bit time later.
So it sees that start bit, it sees that
falling edge here, and then it times until
it samples, and then it correctly samples
the, the zero here.
And then it waits for another clock period
and then it samples again and it correctly
sample that one and so on, all the way to
the end.
You can see that if the packet was longer
because of this drift of the recieved
packet its getting later and later and
later, eventually we'll miss a bit.
So, so long as we can make sure that the
packet is not too long, in other words we
control P and if we know that the
tolerants between these two clocks, the
difference between them then knowing those
two numbers we can make sure we can
reliably decode the packet.
So for short packets this week works fine.
In practice though, this doesn't work very
well for long packets because we like P to
be thousands or hundreds of thousands of
bits, and we would have to make the
tolerance of the receive clock so tight
that this would not be practical to do in
a, in a real system.
So,
Asynchronous communications sometimes used
for links with short packets.
Infrared remote control, or serial links,
or, for example, those connecting to a,
directly to a printer, locally.
Okay.
So we've seen how data is transmitted
using a clock and we've seen that the
receiver needs to know when to sample the
arriving data, and we've also seen an
example of asynchronous communications.
Now we're going to go on to the real meat,
which is the synchronous communications,
which is what we use in practice.
Let me start with sort of a block diagram
of how the system might look.
Don't be intimidated, I'm going to go
through each of these pieces in turn, and
you're going to understand what each of
them is doing.
So the problem is different hosts and here
we have server A that's sending to the
router on the right.
Different hosts are using locally
generated clocks of not only the same
frequency, but slightly different.
So we have 10MHz plus or minus hundred
parts per million again this example here
is a ten mega bit per second link because
I am sending data using this 10MHz clock
and I am sending to the router, sending to
my first router, of course this could be
another host or an ethernet switch,
anything which is the other end of an
ethernet link.
When the data arrives,
Because I'm only sending one over one
piece of wire,
What the receiver is going to do is going
to try and figure out the clock that was
used by the sender.
And this is in what's called a clock
recovery unit, or a clock recovery
circuit.
These are special circuits that, that take
the incoming signal and determine the
clock that was used by the sender.
It does this by examining the frequency
and the phrase of the arriving bits.
So those bits that were, that were on the
wire, so it's going to look at the bits,
and say, huh, if I can actually detect
when there's a transition, then I can
actually determine what the frequency was.
And actually where one bit starts, and the
another bit, and that bit ends.
So it's able to recover this.
So while the bit mapping can be anything,
if there's a strong enough component in
the spectrum from the sender's clock of
what its frequency was, then its receiver
will find it and use it to sample the
bits.
There are many types of circuit that are
used for a clock recovery unit but the
most common one is called a phase locked
loop or a PLL.
Phase locked loop.
And the lay locked loops called DLL's,
they're kind of a digital equivalent.
Or they could actually be a very precise
filter.
There's something called a saw filter or
surface acoustic wave which is also used
as a clock recovery device.
In the next line, I'm going to tell you
about how we make life easier for this
clock recovery unit by encoding the,
encoding the, the clock and the data
together before we transmit it.
Let's go in and see what the other piece
are here.
So there's a flip flop that's used at the
receiver in order to clock that data in.
And you can see that let me just redraw
that.
Here's the flip flop and it's being
clocked using the senders clock.
So in other words, we've, we've figured
out what this clock was in the clock
recovery unit and we're using that to
clock here.
Even though we've used the sender's clock
in order to recover the data, eventually
we need to process it using a clock that's
been generated locally using an oscillator
that is, running inside the router.
So, it needs to be able to clock this in.
And this is why we say that the clock
that's once we've moved into the, into the
clock domain of the, the receiver, we call
this the receive clock domain.
So up until this point here, this
transition, this dotted line, we're using
the transmitters clock domain because
we've recovered the senders clock, and so
we're operating using its clock.
But the clock of the transmitter is not
much use to us as the receiver, if we're
wanting to process the data, in order to
do, calculate check sums, and re-transmit
the data according to our local, local
clock.
So we have to somehow move from one domain
to the other, and we have to do this very
carefully, so that we don't lose bits in
between.
So, once the data has been sampled by the
flip flop, it's placed into a small fifo.
And that's the fifo shown here.
And, this fifo is very critical to how the
whole system works.
The fifo is another special circuit to
help us take the bit from the sender's
clock domain into the reciever's clock
domain.
Why?
Because we need to get the bit into the
clock domain of the receiver so it can
process the packet using its own clock.
To do this, the bit is written into the
fifo, so it's written into the fifo here
using the transmitter's clock.
And then that it's read out of the fifo
using the receivers clock.
So the fifo is different from the ones we
used before.
Where we assumed that the clock is the
same on both sides.
This fifo was very carefully designed to
let us do this using two clocks.
Once the bit emerges on the other side, it
is no in the clock domain of the receiver
and we can safely process it using its
clock.
This fifo is called an elasticity buffer
and we call it an elasticity buffer
because it's taking up the slack between
the two clocks.
And we're going to see in a minute how
this is going to go up and down according
to the relative speeds of the two clocks.
And in a few minutes I'll explain how we
design the whole system so we never
overflow or underflow this elasticity
buffer.
But first, I'm going to describe how we
encode the signal in the first place, so
that the clock can be recovered by this
clock recovery unit.
If the clock was sent separately, as I
described in an example earlier,
As it would be on a circuit board of a
computer, or between different parts of a
circuit on a chip,
Life would be pretty simple.
We could simply use the clock to feed into
the flip flop, and capture the bits in the
same clock domain everywhere.
But if the clock is, is not sent, sent
separately, the data stream must have
sufficient transitions in it.
We must make sure there are enough
transitions in it, in order for the
receiver to determine the clock at the
other end.
Now, you might be looking at this and
saying, what if I was to send a stream of
all 1's, so that this actually was like
this.
It would have no transitions in it at all
and so the receiver wouldn't be able to
determine what the clock is.
So we need to prevent that from happening.
Likewise, if it was to send all 0's, there
would be no transitions.
Or if it was to send a signal that looked
like this that had the changed half as
often as the clock, then, we might be
confused and believe that the clock
frequency was half, when in fact it was.
So, we need to think about this carefully.
And the method that is typically used is
to encode the data, and when we send it in
order to make sure there are sufficient
transitions.
So I'm going to start by describing what
the original ten megabit per second
ethernet used.
It used something called Manchester
coding, or Manchester encoding.
Manchester coding is a very, very simple
mechanism.
It's, used occasionally these days, not as
much as it was, and we'll see why that is
in a minute, but, it's perhaps the
simplest one to understand.
Here at the top is the data that we want
to send.
So this is the 0111, sorry, sorry,
01101011, which is the data that we want
to send.
And the way that that's going to be
encoded before placing it onto the wire is
as follows.
We're going to look at the middle we're
going to look at the bit.
And make sure that there is a transition
during every bit time.
So this is, this signal here is the one
that's going to go onto the wire.
Whenever we see a zero, we're going to
have a downward transition.
Whenever we see a one, we're going to have
an upward transition.
So here we can see, one is encoded by an
upward transition, zero is decoded, is
encoded by a downward transition.
Okay, so this would be what would go on
the line and then to make it a continuous
signal we do this.
Now notice, I had to insert another
transition here because I got one followed
by one, so therefore I need to have a
downward transition.
And here I've got a one followed by a
zero, so I need to have a downward
transition here.
So this would be the sequence I would send
on the wire.
Then,
The clock that I would use at the far end
can be recovered by just looking for the
transitions.
See, I've got a transition here.
I've got a transition here, so whenever I
see a transition, I can be sure that, I
can use that to have a nice strong and
easy way to recover the clock.
And just make sure that I'm not confused,
I mustn't see this transition as,
representing another, another upbeat on
the clock at the other end.
But I can do that by just having a finely
tuned filter at the other end, because I
know that nominally, I'm looking for a ten
megabit per second clock.
And so, I'm, I'm not going to confuse it
with one that's running at twice the
speed.
So, by having a nice, healthy set of
transitions in the middle of the signal, I
can be sure that it's easy to recover it
at the other end.
So the advantages of this Manchester
encoding is it guarantees one transition
per bit period.
It has a second benefit, which is well, a
little bit more subtle.
It, it does something which is called
ensuring the DC balance.
If I send those as voltage levels on the
wire,
If that was zero and this was plus and
this was minus.
Oops, and this was minus, I'm actually
sending just as many,
Just as much, spending just as much of the
time above that wire above that line as I
am below it.
And so I'm making sure that I get DC
balance in the long term.
The benefit of this is that in order to be
able to correctly differentiate a one and
a zero at the other end, I just need to
set my threshold to be in the middle or
the average on the wire.
So that makes it a, for a very real,
viable and robust recovery of bits in the
far end.
There's a clear disadvantage of men-,
registering coding and that I'm inserting
more transitions than I actually need.
I'm doubling the bandwidth in the worst
case.
I'm doubling the bandwidth because by
having more transitions, if I was to send
a sequence of all 1s, I would actually
have a sequence of these, where I've got
twice as many transitions as I really
need.
So, by doubling the bandwidth I would have
a dominate frequency component with a
signal that is being increased.
If we're running over a cable and trying
to make it as fast as we can, this is a
problem.
We've now wasted some the precious
bandwidth on the, on the wire.
Let's look at what this what this spectrum
looks like.
This is the frequency spectrum for ten
megabits per second.
So, in other words, if we take it into a
spectrum analyzer, something that will
tell us the signal strength as a function
of this,, of the frequency and if we were
able to take the original bit sequence, we
would see something like this.
We would see,
At different frequencies,
So this frequency here is the 5MHz, which
is the average when I've got a sequence
of, of 0's and 1's but a random sequence
of 0's and 1's, I would see some frequency
component around here but it's not strong
enough to find it and lock onto it and
know that, that was the frequency of the
clock.
However, if I look at it with Manchester
encoding, I see what suddenly emerges is
this strong component at 10MHz..
Everything has been moved up in the
frequency, in the frequency band because
I've encoded it and then set in more
transitions.
So the spectrum itself is starting at five
megahertz roughly now, only a bit down
here for long sequences of 0s and 1s.
But I'm seeing that most of that spectrum
is now above 5MHz..
Makes it very easy for clock recovery,
because I just need to find this dominant
component, and then use it as my clock at
the far end.
So Manchester encoding it makes, makes it
nice easy, nice and easy.
As a second example, if I wanted to use
something that was a little bit more
efficient than Manchester encoding, I can
take successive numbers, successive blocks
of bits and include them in the way to
make sure I have got some transitions but
may be not twice as many as I had before.
This is, in this example I will describe
something called 4b, 5b encoding.
There are variance of this.
Ap 10b, 15b,
16b. 4b means its 4b of original data.
That I wanted to send.
And I'm going to encode that into a five
bit code.
So just as an example here, I took 0000
and I encoded it as 11110. So I'm
guaranteed if I send this on the wire of
11110,.
So this would be the 11110 and guarantee
that there is a downward transition during
that code.
This code has two transitions in it or
actually three from zero to one, one to
zero, and then from zero to one again.
This one has from one to zero, zero to
one.
So I can be sure always that there are
some transitions within that five bits.
If I know that at the far end then, that
there will be enough transitions then
whatever the data originally included,
I can make sure that I've got enough
transitions to be able to recover the
clock at the far end.
Why can I be sure that there are
transitions?
Well.
There are two to the four or sixteen data
codes, and there are two to the five or 32
codes that I'm going to put on to the
wire.
I'm just going to select those ones that
have enough transitions, so there are
twice as many to choose from.
I can always be sure to find a code that
has a transition in it, so I can be sure
that the outgoing data that I put under
the wire has enough transitions in it.
Comes in an overhead, it's, it's more
bound with efficient than Manchester
encoding but it has a 25% overhead.
But that's certainly much better than
having a double overhead.
I'm actually left with some extra codes.
And some people will, will use these for,
for some inbound control signals.
So, I actually end up with a sixteen codes
that I, that I didn't actually need,
because I've taken from four bits to five
bits.
Fewer transitions definitely make the
clock recovery harder, than for Manchester
encoding, but this has been around long
enough that people have developed clever
circuits, in order to be able to do this.
So, 4b, 5b, and variant of this, this
block coding is, is very commonly used
today.
So in summary,
I have a system that looks like this.
We've seen the, the clock that's being
used at the, here.
I've now got encoded data.
So this would be the encoded data that I'm
sending.
Could be 4B5B, or Manchester encoded.
Goes out over the link.
The clock recovery unit is going to
determine what the clock was that was used
at the sender, by examining the
transitions.
We'll use that to clock the data in, and
then it's going to put it into this
elasticity buffer right here.
In the next video, I'm going to be
describing how this, how this elasticity
buffer works and how we can size it
correctly.
But for now, we've seen how we send data
and how we can recover it.