In this video, you’re going to learn about
the service provided to applications by TCP
– the Transmission Control Protocol - which
is used by over 95% of Internet applications.
TCP is almost universally used because it
provides the reliable, end-to-end, bi directional
byte-stream service that almost all applications
want.
TCP is an example of the transport layer.
When an application calls TCP, it hands it
some bytes that it wants delivered to the
other end.
TCP places these bytes into a TCP Segment,
and then takes it from there.
TCP hands the segment to the IP layer, which
encapsulates it in an IP datagram. The IP
addresses are added.
The IP datagram is handed to the Link Layer,
which builds the link frame, adds the Link
address – for example, the Ethernet addresses
– and then sends it onto the wire.
When two applications use TCP, they establish
a two-way communication channel between the
TCP peers at both ends. First TCP establishes
a communication channel from A to B Then it
establishes a channel from B to A.
We call the two way communication a “connection”.
At both ends of the connection, TCP keeps
a state machine to keep track of how the connection
is doing. We’ll see how the state machine
works in a separate video.
The TCP connection is established using a
3-way handshake between hosts A and B.
First of all, Host A sends a message to B
indicating that the TCP layer at A wants to
establish a connection with the TCP layer
at B. The message is called a SYN message,
which is short for synchronize, because A
also sends along the base number it will use
to identify bytes in the byte stream. If it
sends “0” then the numbers will start
at zero. If it sends “1,000” then they
will start at 1,000.
B responds with what we call a SYN + ACK.
B signals an ACK because B is acknowledging
A’s request and agreeing to establish the
communication from A to B. The TCP layer at
B also sends a SYN back to A to indicate that
the TCP layer at B wants to establish a connection
with the TCP layer at A. It sends a number
too, indicating the starting number for the
byte stream.
Finally, A responds with an ACK to indicate
that it is accepting the request for communication
in the reverse direction. The connection is
now setup in both directions. They are now
ready to start sending data to each other.
The hosts send data to each other as if it
is from a continuous stream of bytes.
Assume time is increasing from left to right
and the stream of bytes next to A represents
the bytes it wants to send to B. The stream
of bytes might exist in advance – for example,
they are read from an html file describing
a static web page. Or it could be a stream
being generated on the fly – for example
from a video camera. Either way, TCP sees
it as a stream of bytes.
Data from the application on A is delivered
to the application at B. The TCP layers on
A and B work together to make sure the stream
of bytes is delivered correctly in order to
the application at B.
The stream of bytes is delivered by TCP segments.
A puts bytes from the stream into a TCP segment,
hands it to the IP layer which delivers it
to B.
The TCP layer at B extracts the bytes to recreate
the byte stream and delivers them to the application
at B.
In practice, the TCP segment may need to be
transmitted multiple times, in the case a
segment is dropped along the way, or if A
doesn’t receive an acknowledgment.
The TCP segment can be a small as 1 byte – for
example, if you are typing characters in an
ssh session, each character is sent one at
a time, rather than waiting for the whole
segment to fill up.
This isn’t very efficient when we have lots
of data to send; so we can fill the TCP segment
all the way up to the maximum IP datagram
size.
When A and B have finished sending data to
each other, they need to close the connection.
We say they “teardown” the connection,
which means they tell each other they are
closing the connection and both ends can clean
up the state associated with the state machine.
The TCP layer at Host A can close the connection
by sending a FIN message, which is short for
FINISH.
Host B acknowledges that A no longer has data
to send and stops looking for new data from
A. This closes down the data stream from A
to B. But B might still have new data to send
to A and is not ready to close down the channel
from B to A. So the message from B to A carrying
the ACK can also carry new data from B to
A. B can keep sending new data to A as long
as it needs to.
Sometime later B finishes sending data to
A, and now sends its own FIN to tell A they
can close the connection.
Host A replies by sending an ACK to acknowledge
that the connection is now closed. Because
both directions have finished, the connection
is now fully closed and the state can be safely
removed.
Here is a table summarizing the services provided
by TCP.
The first three are services TCP provides
to the application. As we just saw, it provides
a reliable stream of bytes between two applications.
It uses four mechanisms to make the communication
reliable – in other words, to make sure
the data is correctly delivered.
When a TCP layer receives data, it sends an
acknowledgment back to the sender to let it
know the data arrived correctly.
Checksums detect corrupted data. The TCP header
carries a checksum covering the header and
the data inside the segment. The checksum
is there to detect if the segment is corrupted
along the way, for example by a bit-error
on the wire or by a memory fault inside a
router.
Sequence numbers detect missing data. Every
segment’s header carries the sequence number
- in the stream of bytes – of the first
byte in the segment. For example, if the two
sides agree that the sequence numbers start
at 1,000 then the first segment will have
a sequence number of 1,000. If the segment
carries 500 bytes of data then the next segment
will carry the sequence number 1,500. If a
segment gets lost, then the sequence number
will be incorrect and the TCP layer knows
some data is missing. It is possible it will
show up later – perhaps it took a longer
path – or it might have gone missing, in
which case the sender will need to resend
the data.
Flow-control prevents overrunning the receiver.
If Host A is much faster than Host B then
it’s possible for Host A to overwhelm Host
B by sending data so fast that Host B can’t
keep up. TCP prevents this from happening
using something we call flow-control. In TCP,
the receiver keeps telling the sender if it
can keep sending; specifically, it tells the
sender how much room it has in its buffers
to accept new data. If Host B is falling behind,
the space drops – possibly all the way to
zero. When it has more room, it tells A and
it can send more data.
TCP delivers data to the application in the
right sequence; in other words, whatever sequence
the data was delivered from the application
to TCP at host A, this is the same order in
which it is sent from TCP to the application
at B. If segments arrive out of order, the
TCP layer re-sequences them to the correct
order, using the sequence number.
Finally, TCP provides a service to the whole
network by controlling congestion. TCP tries
to divide up the network capacity equally
among all the TCP connections using the network.
The congestion control mechanisms in TCP are
very complicated and we’ll devote the whole
of Unit 4 to studying congestion control.
The TCP Segment header is much longer and
more complicated than, say the IP and Ethernet
headers. That is because a TCP connection
is reliable – In order to make the communication
reliable, the two ends of the connection need
to exchange more information so they know
which bytes have arrived, which are missing,
and the status of the connection.
Here is a quick summary of the most important
fields in the TCP header. You don’t need
to remember the layout of the header, but
you should learn what each field does. If
you need a reference, I’d recommend Wikipedia
or the Kurose and Ross textbook.
The Destination port tells the TCP layer which
application the bytes should be delivered
to at the other end. When a new connection
starts up, the application tells TCP which
service to open a connection with. For example,
if TCP is carrying web data, it uses port
80, which is the port number for TCP. You’ll
learn more about port numbers later, but if
you are curious, you can look up the well
known port numbers at the IANA website. Search
for IANA port numbers. You’ll find thousands
of port numbers defined for different well
known services. For example, when we open
a connection to an ssh server, we use destination
port 22. For smtp (the simple mail transfer
protocol) we use port 23. Using a well known
port number lets Host B identify the application
it should establish the connection with.
The Source port tells the TCP layer at the
other end which port it should use to send
data back again. In our example, when Host
B replies to Host A, it should place Host
A’s source port number in the destination
port field, so that Host A’s TCP layer can
deliver the data to the correct application.
When a new connection starts, the initiator
of the connection – in our case Host A – generates
a unique source port number, so differentiate
the connection from any other connections
between Host A and B to the same service.
The Sequence number indicates the position
in the byte stream of the first byte in the
TCP Data field. For example, if the Initial
Sequence number is 1,000 and this is the first
segment, then the Sequence number is 1,000.
If the segment is 500 bytes long, then the
sequence number in the next segment will be
1,500 and so on.
The Acknowledgment sequence number tells the
other end which byte we are expecting next.
It also says that we have successfully received
every byte up until the one before this byte
number. For example, if the Acknowledgment
Sequence number is 751, it means we have received
every byte up to and including byte 750. Notice
that there are sequence numbers for both directions
in every segment. This way, TCP piggybacks
acknowledgments on the data segments traveling
in the other direction.
The 16 bit checksum is calculated over the
entire header and data, and helps the receiver
detect corrupt data. For example, bit errors
on the wire, or a faulty memory in a router.
You’ll learn more about error detection
and checksums in a later video.
The Header Length field tells us how long
the TCP header is. The TCP Options fields
are, well, optional. They carry extra, new
header fields that were thought of and added
after the TCP standard was created. The Header
Length field tells us how many option fields
are present. Usually there are none.
Finally, there are a bunch of Flags used to
signal information from one end of the connection
to the other. The ACK flag tells us that the
Acknowledgement sequence number is valid and
we are acknowledging all of the data up until
this point. The SYN flag tells us that we
are signalling a synchronize, which is part
of the 3way handshake to set up the connection.
And the FIN flag signals the closing of one
direction of the connection. Finally, the
PSH flag tells the TCP layer at the other
end to deliver the data immediately upon arrival,
rather than wait for more data. This is useful
for short segments carrying time critical
data, such as a key stroke. We don’t want
the TCP layer to wait to accumulate many keystrokes
before delivering them to the application.
A TCP connection is uniquely identified by
five pieces of information in the TCP and
IP headers.
The IP source and destination addresses uniquely
identify the end points, and the IP Protocol
ID for TCP tells us the connection is TCP.
The TCP source and destination ports identify
they application processes on the end hosts.
Together, at any instant, all 5 fields uniquely
identify the TCP connection Internet-wide.
Now, the unique ID only holds if a few things
hold. First, we need to make sure Host A – the
initiator of the connection - picks a unique
source port ID. We need to make sure it doesn’t
accidentally pick the same source port number
it is already using with another connection
to the same service on Host B. Host A uses
a simple method to minimize the chances: It
increments the source port number for every
new connection. The field is 16bits, so it
takes 64k new connections before the field
wraps round.
There is also a very slight danger that if
Host A suddenly creates a lot of new connections
to Host B it might still wrap around and try
to create two connections with the same global
ID. If this happened, the bytes from one connection
might become confused with the bytes from
another connection. This could happen, for
example, if a TCP segment somehow lived for
a long time in the network, stuck inside a
router buffer or circulating in a temporary
loop.
To reduce the chances of confusion, the TCP
connections initialize with a random initial
sequence number to refer to bytes in the byte
stream. While not totally fool proof, it does
reduce the chances of confusion. When Host
A initiates the connection to B, it includes
the initial sequence number if will use in
the stream of bytes from A to B. When B replies
and initiates the connection from B to A,
it supplies its own initial sequence number
for the stream of bytes from B to A.
And so to summarize how sequence numbers work…..
The sequence number in a segment from A to
B includes the sequence number of the first
byte, offset by the initial sequence number.
The acknowledgment sequence number in the
segment from B back to A tells us which byte
B is expecting next, offset by A’s initial
sequence number.
Let’s summarize how TCP port numbers work….
Imagine that Host B on the right offers two
services: A Web Server and a Mail Server.
When the Web client – for example a Chrome
browser on Host A – wants to request a page
from the Web server on B, it sends the data
to TCP.
We’ll assume TCP has already established
a connection with B, so now it just needs
to send the data. It creates a segment and
uses destination port 80 to tell B it is requesting
the data be sent to the web server.
Host A uses a locally generated source port
number for B to use when sending data and
acknowledgments back again.
As usual, the TCP segment is encapsulated
into an IP datagram and sent to B. The IP
+ TCP headers carry the unique ID of the TCP
connection.
When the IP datagram arrives at B, the TCP
segment is removed. The TCP layer sees that
the segment is for port 80 and sends the data
to the web server.
You’ll learn about other features of TCP
in upcoming videos.
You’ll learn about window-based flow control
and to stop us from overwhelming the receiver.
You’ll learn about retransmissions and timeouts
and different methods to accomplish it.
And you’ll learn about Congestion Control
in Unit 4.
In summary, TCP provides in-order, reliable
delivery of a stream of bytes between application
processes.