Nick:
So in this unit we're going to be learning
about network security. Usually when read
about the Internet and networks in the newspaper,
it's because of some security vulnerability
that's been exploited or found. Of course
we read about these exploits in software,
but sometimes you read about them at the infrastructure
itself and these are usually exposed because
an individual, a company, or a country is
attacking someone in order to discover or
tamper with their data. We're going to start
by learning about the types of attack that
are quite common. There are many ways to attack
a network, and you're going to be seeing a
collection of methods that work in a variety
of ways. The first and most common one is
to simply eavesdrop, or listen, on someone's
communication. In some networks, this is surprisingly
easy, and you're going to be surprised at
some of the methods that people use and can
be used, and we'll even demonstrate some of
these to you. You can either eavesdrop on
a broadcast network, like a wireless network,
or you can force the network to expose or
broadcast in a way that will make it easier
for you to hear. Another type of attack is
to masquerade or behave as if you're a piece
of the infrastructure that is providing information
back to a sending host. For example, you can
forge ARP responses, you can spoof the response
from a DHCP server or from a DNS server and
cause a client to a place other than where
it was thinking of sending it. So you can
either get the data redirected to you, or
you can look at it and pass it on, which is
often called a man-in-the-middle attack, or
you can make it impossible for the sender
to communicate with a particular part of the
network, and essentially censor or block a
part of the network. Sometimes you're actually
about to hijack an entire end host and masquerade
as an end host, and therefore completely terminate
the communication, for example to get someone's
credit card information when they're performing
an e-commerce transaction. Another thing that
you can do is prevent someone from being able
to communicate at all. This is usually called
a denial of service attack, by overwhelming
the sender, or overwhelming a piece of the
infrastructure, so that the communication
can no longer take place.
Phil:
So the Internet is dangerous. We're going
to learn the three principles that you can
actually use to secure your network despite
the fact that the Internet itself might be
insecure. First is confidentiality. This is
the idea that we'd like to be able to communicate
securely, that is hidden from everyone else,
despite the fact that they might be able to
see what we're saying. So if you have confidentiality,
then you can communicate with another party,
and other people can observe this communication,
but not be able to know what you're saying.
The second principle is integrity. So confidentially
let's us communicate without people knowing
what we're saying, but people can still meddle
with it. With integrity, we can be sure that
our communications aren't tampered with such
that the message that, say, Nick sent to me,
was actually the message that Nick sent to
me. It wasn't that somebody fussed with it
in between. The third principle is authenticity.
Can I actually be sure that the other party
I'm talking with is whom they say they are?
And it turns out there are some ways to do
this. But the basic techniques for both confidentiality,
and integrity, and authenticity, uses cryptography.
Mathematical tools, and secrecy and codes.
The idea is that if we use the right cryptographic
tools, then we can have secure communication,
even over an insecure network like the Internet.
And so you're going to learn about some basic
cryptographic tools, such as cryptographic
hashes, message authentication codes, symmetric
ciphers, public key cryptography, certificates
and signatures, which are all used in the
Internet today. And so by the end of this
unit, you should start to have a sense as
to how should secure your network going forward.