In this video I'm going to continue the
topic of the four layer internet model and
I'm going to tell you about the ICMP
service model. ICMP is the Internet Control
Message
Protocol and it is used to report errors and
diagnose problems with the network
layer. You'll recall that IP doesn't provide
any
guarantees about delivery, but it does help
and it'll prove to be a very valuable
tool to get some hints and some information
back from the layer, network
layer to tell us about when things are going
wrong.
There are three mechanisms that we use to
make the network layer work in the
internet. The first, we've already seen, is
the
internet protocol or IP. This creates IP datagrams,
and then
delivers them hop by hop from end to end.
The second are the routing tables sitting
inside the routers. There are algorithms that
run to populate
these router forwarding tables, so that the
routers know how to deliver them hop
by hop to the other end. The third mechanism
which is the purpose
for this video is the ICMP, or the internet
control message protocol.
ICMP helps communicate information about the
network layer between the end hosts
and the routers and I'm going to show you
a couple of examples of those in a minute.
It's typically used to report error conditions
and helps us diagnose problems,
figure out the path taken by packets and so
on.
Okay. ICMP runs above the network layer, and
so
strictly speaking it's a transport layer protocol.
When an end host or router want to report
an error using ICMP, it puts the
information that it wants to send back to
the source into an ICMP payload.
And hands it to IP, to be sent as a datagram.
Let's look at an example. As I said, ICMP
typically gets used as, as
a method for error reporting. And in fact
you've seen it if you've
ever seen the message destination network
unreachable.
Let me give an example. Imagine that I have
a web client running
as the application here. So I've got a an
HTTP or web client here
that's going to be accessing an HTTPserver
over here at B.
So as we've seen before, the application bytes
that for, for HTTP get put in to the
transport layer as usual and to TCP, comes
down to the network by it, goes out along
the link, comes up to the router along here.
Imagine that the address that is put inhere.
Is actually to a network that this router
has no information about in its forwarding
table. Now this will be a pretty bad situation,
because that router doesn't know how to forward
the packet to B.
But, if that happens, then the router will
send back a message, and so this will come
back down through the network, to A. And it
will say in it, destination network
unreachable. And that's simply saying that
it has no
means to deliver that packet to B, so it's
alerting A by sending that back.
And we'll see the format that it uses in a
moment.
So basically the ICMP service model is very,
very simple.
It allows it to send a reporting message,a
self-contained message reporting the
error. It's unreliable in the sense that it
sends
a simple datagram. It doesn't attempt to re-send
it, it
doesn't retain any state of the messages that
it sent.
It simply sends back a digest, giving an indication
of what the problem was.
And in fact how it actually works is, when
a message comes in - so for example, an IP
datagram. So here is my IP datagram.
Here is the header. Here is the payload or
the data portion of
my ip datagram, so this is my IP datagram.
Let's say this has just arrived, and in my
previous example, this has arrived from A
to the first router.
If the first router wants to send back an
ICMP message, what it does is it takes the
header. Now this header here has source address
A
and destination address B. And it will populate
this into, it will
place this into an ICMP message. So it will
take this header.
And put it into the ICMP message. So this
is my ICMP message.
And it will also take the first eight bytes
of the IP payload, and it'll put
this into the ICMP message. And then it marks
it with a type and a
code.And we'll see some examples of these
types
and codes in a moment. And then the whole
lot gets placed into a
new IP datagram. So this is the data of the
new IP
datagram. And this is gonna be sent back.
So. So this is the header.
And so the IP source, will be the router.
So I'll just put R for router and the IP
destination in my example will be A. It's
gonna send it back to A to tell it
that this was the, the error, this was the
type of error, this is how it figures out
what type of error it was. This was the data
associated with that
error. It's the IP datagram that was originally
causing the problem. That's all placed into
the data of the IP
datagram that goes back again to A. Let's
look at an example of some, some
particular ICMP message types. There are a
lot of message types.
This is just a, this is just a sampling of
them.
These are the six most important that we see.
And you don't need to remember the types or
the codes you'll find those in the
internet RFC792, and you can just look that
up online if you want.
These are the ones that are most commonly
used and I'll just go through examples.
We've already seen the network unreachable.
This was type three code zero. And there are
two other destination
unreachable ones. Host unreachable, that's
if an
Ip datagram gets to the last router, but then
the last router doesn't know where
the host is. Port unreachable means that
the port that's contained inside, or the protocol
ID that's inside the IP datagram,
it doesn't know what to do with it. It doesn't
recognize it at the other end.
We'll see how echo reply, echo request,and
ttl expired are used in a moment.
Okay. You've probably used the ping command
before. And ping is used just to test the
liveness
of, of another host. And it also checks that
we've got
connectivity to that host. So imagine that
we're sending a ping
message from A to B. So we're sitting at A
and we run the
command ping B.Right?
And you've probably done this. If you haven't
just try this on your
computer. Pick the, the name of a computer
like
www.stanford.edu and just type ping www.stanford.edu.
The ping application calls ICMP directly.
It sends a ICMP echo request.
And so that will be a message that goes into
the network.
So this is an ICMP. This is ICMP, and it's
a, happens to be a
message of type eight, code zero. If you look
on the table before, that is
actually a echo request. So this is my IP
datagram.
And it's gonna go off to B. As this goes through
the network, it's
gonna go across to B, we hope. Eventually
it'll reach B.
And then B is gonna see this, and whats B
is required to do is to send an echo
reply. So it will send back,
towards A, it will send the ICMP.
And the ICMP will be a, I think it was type
zero, code zero, which
was the echo reply. This gets placed into
an IP datagram.
So, this will all be placed into the IP datagram,
and it will be sent back to A.
Nice and simple. So, that's how ping works.
Now let's have a look at how traceroute works.
Traceroute is an application that tells us
the path that packets take through the
network and the routers that it visits along
the way.
You can try this by simply typing traceroute
and then the name of a web server or
some other server on the network into, into
your computer as I'm showing here.
Traceroute is gonna tell you not only the
path taken by the packets, but the
round trip delay to each of the routers along
the path.
So, traceroute uses ICMP in quite a clever
way.
So, the goal here of Traceroute is to find
the routers on the path from A to B.
So, it's trying to identify the two routers
along the path, and measure the
round trip time of packets from A to each
of those routers.
So traceroute does this by sending UDP messages.
And I'm first gonna describe what it does,
and then we'll see why it is that, that
works. So, A is gonna send a UDP message,
so it's
gonna send a UDP message. And that UDP message
is going to be sent,
doesn't actually matter what it contains,
but it will be encapsulated into an IP
datagram, for which the TTL, the Time To Live
field in the, the IP header, is, set
to, one. So this will be sent over the link
from A
to the first router, and as you recall the
router is required to decrement the TTL,
and then discard the packet if the TTL reaches
zero.
So it will set TTL equals zero, discard the
packet.
One more thing that the router is required
to do is to send back an ICMP message, so
an error reporting message back to A. And
it sends it back with a message of, of
I think it's type eleven ICMP. Okay.
So it's going to send back a type eleven message,
which is the TTL expired.
That's the, ICMP8 message, TTL expired. This
is gonna tell A.
And in order for that packet to reach A, it's
gonna take, just as before, it's
gonna take the IP header that was, the, the
one that's, that was sent.
It's going to take the first eight bytes of
the IP payload, and it's going to
populate that into a message along with this
ICMP, so, let's draw this like this.
So, this is going to be the ICMP message coming
in here.
This is going to be that digest of the original
IP message.
Going to put this into an IP datagram, and
it's going to send it back to A.
So when this reaches A, it's gonna know from
this message, there was a TTL
expired. And from this portion, from the payload
portion of the ICMP message, it's gonna know
aha, this came from a message I
originally have sent from A. It's gonna come
from the router, so the IP
source address of this datagram is going to
be the router, so I'll put that in as
R.So it knows that it was this router.
It could look up it's name. And now it knows
that the first hop router
is R. And by measuring the time that it took
from when it sent the original IP message
until it received this ICMP reply, it now
knows the round trip time to that router.
The next step is probably pretty obvious.
Next A is going to send a UDP message, put
into an IP datagram, and that is going to
have a TTL of two. Okay, so this is the IP
datagram that goes
out. So it'll go through to the first router,
that will decrement the TTL to one. Come through
to the second one, that will
decrement it to zero. And then this one will
send back an ICMP
message.So the datagram will look like this.
And I'll draw the IP datagram with the ICMP
message inside.
So this is the IP datagram. This is going
to be going to A, from,
let's call that R2. And inside is gonna be
the ICMP message.
So this is the ICMP message that it's carrying.
It's gonna say type eleven. Which was the
TTL expired.
And then it's gonna have the original IP header
plus eight bytes.
So that when it get's back to A, it knows
what message this was referring to, it can
measure the round trip time. Now it knows,
based on the message coming
from R2, it knows what, what this router is.
So you can look up its name, and now it knows
the round trip time to that router,
and it'll do this until eventually the message
finds its way to B.
The UDP message that it sends is using a port
number, which is a weird destination
port number, it deliberately picks one that
B is not going to know, so that B
will send back a message that says, and it's
going to be an ICMP message which is
port un-reachable. And so when it's send back
the port
unreachable, A knows, that, the message got,
the trace route made it all the way
to B, and knows that the trace route is complete.
So in summary, ICMP, the internet control
message protocol, provides information
about the network layer to end hosts and routers.
It sits above the IP layer and, therefore,
strictly speaking, it's a transport layer
mechanism. Although it's really there to serve
the
network layer. The commonly used tools ping
and trace
route both rely on ICMP, and I'd encourage
you to try both of them out and play with
them. They, they give you a huge amount of
information about reachability and paths through
the internet.
That's the end of this video.