It’s a dangerous world out there. We want
to keep our computer systems secure, but what
exactly does this mean? Every system and protocol
is different, but when talking about security,
we generally talk about three properties:
confidentiality, integrity, and availability.
Recall our threat model based on all of the
attacks we’ve covered. An adversary can
snoop on all of your traffic, suppress any
of your packets, replay packets, and even
generate new packets that seem to come from
your host and/or application.
To defends against this, we’re going to
use two approaches. The first, cryptography,
is a way to communicate securely end-to-end
despite the fact that the network inbetween
is insecure. Cryptography literally means
the study of codes. It’s a set of mathematical
tools focused on the idea of secrets and the
computational difficulty of understanding
data without the secret. Using cryptography
as a building block, it turns out that we
can actually build end-to-end secure communication
despite the fact that the adversary might
control and own the entire network. By secure,
I mean that the adversary can’t rewrite
our messages, generate new messages, or snoop
on our messages.
The second approach is to prevent an adversary
from blocking your messages. Even if two hosts
can communicate securely, an adversary could
prevent them from communicating at all. The
general approach for this is to design systems
to be scalable. Take, for example, DNS. The
fact that there are so many root servers,
some of which are highly replicated, means
that it’s very hard to launch a denial of
service against it. I’m not going to talk
much more about scalable system design -- it’s
a complex topic worthy of a course in and
of itself. Instead, I’m going to focus on
the networking part of the problem, secure
communication.
Cryptography is set of mathematical principles
and ideas for securing communication. The
most important thing to know about cryptography
is that it can be very subtle and details-oriented.
If there’s a single flaw in your system,
then it’s not secure. So just taking cryptography
and applying it without care is unlikely to
make your system secure. Instead of inventing
your new security system. it’s much, much
safer to use existing, tested, well-understood
ones. It’s often the case that ideas from
security are misused or misunderstood, such
as people thinking a message authentication
code, a security primitive, has the same error
detection properties as a CRC.
Cryptography can give us three valuable things.
The first is confidentiality. This is the
ability to communicate with another party
privately, such that no-one else can read
it. Cryptography provides confidentiality
through something called encryption.
The second is integrity. This is the ability
to know if our message has been tampered with.
There are many ways to provide integrity,
depending on the exact needs and the kind
of cryptography used. The three basic mechanisms,
which future videos will cover in depth, are
cryptographic hashes, cryptographic signatures,
and message authentication codes, or MACs.
Finally, there is authenticity. This is the
ability for the party to prove they are who
they say they are. The three basic mechanisms,
which future videos will cover in depth, are
certificates, message authentication codes,
and cryptographic signatures.
Again, I can’t stress it enough! Cryptography
can make your system secure, but only if you
use it carefully and correctly. It’s really
easy to make a mistake! Don’t trust systems
that seem to have just tacked security on
later and don’t think making a system secure
is easy.
The first property is confidentiality. The
idea is that two parties should be able to
exchange information secretly, so no-one else
can know what they’re sending even if they
can read the messages. This is really useful
if you want to send your credit card number.
A crypto system that has perfect confidentiality
is something called a one-time pad. The idea
is that you and I share a perfectly random
key of zeros and ones. No-one else has this
key, this one time pad. To send you a message,
I just XOR the message M with the key K, producing
a confidential message C. I then send C to
you. To reconstruct M, you XOR C with K.
A one-time pad is perfectly secure. If the
one-time pad is perfectly random, then given
any C, any M is equally likely. It’s also
very fast: all you have to do is XOR.
But it’s not very practical. K has to be
at least as long as M. If I want to exchange
100 megabytes with you, I need a 100 megabyte
K. So in practice, cryptosystems that provide
confidentiality try to provide algorithms
where we can exchange a much smaller K, say
128 bits, or 256 bits, such there are 2 to
the 128, or 2 to the 256, possible confidential
messages, possible Cs.
The second property is integrity. Integrity
is the ability to exchange messages and be
sure that they were not tampered with or changed.
For example, when I download software, I want
to know that it’s the real version and not
a hacked version that installs malware on
my machine.
Some forms of integrity also allow you to
know that the other party sent the message.
If the two of you share a secret key, then
there are forms of integrity which only someone
with the secret key can perform correctly.
Two very common forms of integrity are cryptographic
hashes and message authentication codes. Cryptographic
hashes are functions that turn arbitrary length
data into a fixed length hash, just like a
normal hash function. But cryptographic hashes
have the additional property that they are
*collision-resistant*. If I have a message
x with hash H of x, then it’s intractable
to find a message y, different from x, which
has the same hash. This means, for example,
if I know a cryptographic hash of a program
I want to download, then it’s intractable
for someone to hack the software in a way
that it has the same hash.
Message authentication codes, MACs, are like
cryptographic hashes, except they use a key
K to both generate and check the MAC. Anyone
can generate a cryptographic hash, but only
someone with K can compute the correct MAC.
With a MAC, it’s intractable to generate
the correct MAC of a message unless you have
the key K. So if we’ve exchange K beforehand,
and I receive a message with a correct MAC,
then I know that nobody tampered with the
message and you generated the MAC.
Finally, there’s authenticity. This is the
ability to verify someone is who they say
they are. For example, you receive a message
supposedly from the provost and want to be
sure the provost actually sent it. If you
and the provost have exchanged a secret key
before hand, you can do this with message
authentication codes. If you receive a message
that has a correct MAC computed with the secret
you’ve shared with the provost, I know that
the provost sent it. If you don’t have a
secret, then you can use a chain of trust.
If weyou trust one party, then that party
can vouch for someone else. This second party
can then vouch for a third party and so on.
So, for example, suppose we have some information
that lets us check Verisign’s authenticity.
Verisign can then vouch for Stanford, and
Stanford can vouch for the provost.
Finally, there’s how you design computer
systems for high availability, so they are
resistant to denial of service and distributed
denial of service attacks. There are tons
of kinds of attacks out there: replication
attacks, resource use attacks, ping attacks,
botnets attacks. Generally speaking, you can
either scale out your system so it distributes
the load and can handle it, or at some point
you can filter the traffic upstream. For example,
if someone is DDoSing your cable modem, you
could possibly contact your ISP to filter
out traffic coming at it.
So the three things that cryptography can
provide are confidentiality, integrity, and
authenticity. But once more: cryptography
can make your system secure, but only if you
use it carefully and correctly. Be careful!