Continuing on our theme of routing, in this
video, I'm going to tell you about a
distance vector protocol.
Distance vector protocol is a way in
which the, the routers maintain a vector
of their distances to a given, or to all
of the other routers, and then
iteratively, through a distributed
algorithm,
they converge on finding the shortest path
or the lowest cost spanning tree from them
to every other router.
And we're going to see a specific example
of this, what's known as the Bellman Ford
algorithm, which is the most commonly used
algorithm in these distance vector
protocols.
So, the particular problem we're going to
address is how can routers work together
to find the minimum cost spanning tree?
Here's an example that I've shown in green
here as the minimum cost spanning tree for
this particular graph.
Notice that this is equivalent to finding
the minimum cost spanning tree amongst
just the routers.
It didn't matter whether I included the
end hosts because really in the end, we're
just building the spanning tree amongst
the routers.
So, in the rest of the examples, I'm just
going to confine myself to that.
So now, let's look at the distributed
Bellman-Ford algorithm, And in this
example, we're going to use the case of
trying to find the minimum cost spanning
tree to R8.
Just to remind you in the previous slide,
this was the router in the bottom
right-hand corner.
So, this green spanning tree shown here is
the minimum cost spanning tree for
everybody
to reach R8.
So, remember that in general, all of
the routers are going to be building the
lowest cost spanning tree to reach all of
the other routers.
So, we're just taking one specific case
here of finding that minimum cost spanning
tree to r8.
In the Bellman Ford Algorithm, we're going
to assume that the routers know the cost
of the link to each of their neighbors so
that there is a metric and a cost
associated with using that link.
And we're going to assume that router R
sub i is going to maintain the value of
the cost to reach R8.
So, at any one instance, it's going to
keep a sense of its current lowest cost to
reach R sub eight, so router RA, it's
going to be C sub i.
So we're going to have a vector, C, which
is going to contain the seven costs of the
seven routers, R1 through R7, of their
current cost to reach R8, and this is the
the distance vector to reach R8.
Initially, the algorithm is going to set
this vector to all values of infinity.
And then, every T seconds, so starting
after the first t seconds, Ri is going to
send Ci to its neighbors.
In other words, each router is going to
send the cost to reach R8 to each of its
neighbors.
If Ri, at anytime, learns of a
lower-cost path, it's going to update its
value C sub i.
So if after t seconds it hears a
lower-cost path to reach R8, it's going to
update it's value and then we're going to
repeat and we're just going to keep
repeating forever.
Let's look at this is as, as, as how this
would work on a graph.
And remember, there's a natural extension
to calculate this for R1 through R7,
we just exchange all of the values.
I'm just showing you the one example here.
Now let's look at a concrete example, and
we're going to have a look at this
particular graph here, which I've
annotated with some costs.
They're different from the costs before.
It doesn't matter, what the particular values are, or
how they came about.  They could  represent the
delay of using a link, or the price of
using a link.
They're just values, and we're going to
try and find the minimum cost, spanning
tree using the Bellman Ford algorithm.
So, remember, in the Bellman Ford algorithm,
we start out with a distance vector to
reach R8, with all the values set to
infinity.
So R1 thinks it costs, it's infinite to
start with.
R2, and so on.
They all think that the cost is infinite
in order to reach R8.
Okay.
So, that's where we're going to begin.
And we're going to go through and see
waves of information propagating through
so that we can update these and steadily
converge on what the minimum cost spanning
tree is in order to reach r8.
So, in the next step, then information is
going to propagate outwards from r8.
So, this information here is going to tell
us in that first wave that r8 can be
reached in one hop from these routers.
R3 is going to learn that, it can get
there in four.
That's with the direct path.
R5 can get there in six.
R6 over here will learn that it can get
there in two, and R7 will learn that it
can get there in one.
So, there are the costs in that first step.
And so, R3 will update its own value,
four, six,
one, and two, respectively.
And now, they will advertise those values
on in the next round of the algorithm.
So, that information is going to propagate
out here into the, the next hop.
So, R4 is going to learn in
the next iteration of the algorithm that
it can get there, at a cost of two via R7.
It could get also get there at
a cost of six via R6, that's a higher
value so it's going to ignore that one.
R2 can get there at a cost of seven, six
plus one, so that's seven going via R5.
And R1 is going to learn that it can get
there at the cost eight via R3.
Okay, so it's tempting to think that we're
done at this point, because every router
has had a value, but of course, this is
going to keep going, because this
information is going to propagate further.
And the next time,
this news is going to propagate this way.
This news is gong to propagate this way.
This news is gong to propagate this way
and so on.
So, everyone is going to hear more values
in the next round.
Let me clear that to make a little bit
clearer and see what happens in the next
round.
So, this is the values  that I
just showed you.
Just as an example R1 had learned, if you
remember, that it can get to it can get to
r8 via r3 at a cost of eight.
So, it has that value eight going via r3,
for example.
Okay, so now, what happens?  You can see
that we've found out all of the two hop
information.
So this is really like the two hop
In the next iteration, we're going to find
out the three hop information.
Let's see what this three hop information
is.
Well, based on this, the ones that are
going to change, and I've shown you in red
here.
Let's focus on those.
R2.
Which previously thought that the lowest
cost path was  of cost seven, going via
R5.
It's going to learn about this three
hop path because R4 is going to advertise
to it, the value six.
And so, it's going to hear about this
value that it can get there at a cost of
six going via r4.
So, that's going to be its new value and
that's the one here.
Similarly, r5 is going to learn about
3-hop path which goes via r4.
It's going to learn about this one here.
So, previously, the lowest cost path was
of value six.  Now it's going to learn one
of cost four going via R4.
So, that's this entry here that it just
learned about.
So, the first 3-hop path that was actually
lower cost than the 2-hop path.
Let's see what happens in the next
iteration, In the next iteration of the
algorithm the news is spreading out further
to the four hop paths and then the four
hop paths, for example, R1 is going to
learn of the four hop path that goes one,
two, three, four, which is of cost seven,
because R2 will have propagated on the
information that it can get there at a
cost of six.
So, six plus one is seven so if it goes
via R2, it can get there at a cost of
seven so that's this one here.
R2 has just learned, in this next
hop, that there is an even better path.
And we can see this one here.
I'm going to draw this one in green, to
make it a little bit clearer, which goes
via here, and that is the cost one, two,
three, four, five.
So it's just learning that it can get
there at five, if it goes via R5.
All right, so the interesting thing here
is, that these two bits of information are
actually inconsistent, because the
algorithm hasn't converged.  The news of
this particular opportunity hasn't made it
to R1 yet.
So we'll see that happen in the next step.
In the next step, r1 is going to learn of
the newer value which is hat
it can reach it in the cost of six going
on this path here one, two, three, three,
four, five, six, the cost of six going via
R2.
Oops, I have a little bit of mistake
there.
Okay, that should be via r2.
So, now it appears that we're done.
How do we know that we're done?
Well, we can look at it and see that we
can't find any lower cost paths that tells
us that we're done.
But, you could also see that this will
finish, you can't go any further so long
as we've, we've explored the maximum hop
length in the network and the maximum hop
length here you can see that there's a
longer one that goes like this.
That's probably about the longest, so
that's one, two, three, four, five, six.
So, that will be another hop for
that information to propagate.
So, it's the longest loop free path.
We know that a path that has a
loop in it must have a higher cost, so
we're never going to pick that one.
So, as long as we have gone as many hops
as the longest loop free path, we know
that we'll finish.
The question is, how do we know that we'll
end up with a right answer?
In fact, there's a couple of questions
that are worth asking here.
The first one is, what is the maximum run
time of the algorithm?
I just told you that, it's going to be the
longest loop free path.
It's going to be the hop count of the
Will the algorithm always converge?
Intuitively, it's actually pretty clear
that it must converge, because we start
out with the values infinity, and we only
ever replace them with lower values, and
we keep reducing the value until the
algorithm has run.
So we only ever replace a value with a
lower cost value, and eventually we should
hear from all of our neighbors their
lowest cost path, and so eventually we
will reach the lowest value, and we will
converge.
So the algorithm will always converge.
It's the clever thing about this
algorithm.
So, what happens when link costs change?
Or when links and routers fail?
We'll see an example of that in a minute
when actually, things can go wrong when
that happens.
But in general, it will continue to
converge because, if something
fails, if a lower cost path should
suddenly appear, then it will find it and
start using it.
Things are a little bit more complicated
when things fail and there is no longer a
path to somewhere, and I'll show you an
example of this right now.
This is a well-known problem with the
Bellman-Ford Algorithm.
And, it's sometimes characterized as bad
news travels slowly.
Let's see what's going on
here.
We're going to look at this really simple
four-router network here that are all
connected in a line.
And the cost from one router to the next
is one.
So, a nice, simple, trivial example.
So, initially, everything is working fine.
We've converged on these values down here
at time zero.
We happen to know that we can get to R4.
So, this is all about your cost to reach
R4 in this case.
We know that R1 can get there at a cost of
three.
So that's its value, if it goes via R2.
R2 can get there at a cost of two, that's
this plus this, if it goes via R3.
R3 can get there in the cost of one and
it's directly connected to r4.
So, everything is good.
But then suddenly, the link from three to
four is going to break.
So, this link over here has broken.
What happens next?
Well.
What's going to happen is they're going to
keep advertising their costs.
R3 is going to start advertising, "hey, I
was under the impression that I could get
there with a cost of one before."
That's here.
"But I don't have that link anymore.
I know that, that link is broken.
But I did hear from R2 that R2 could get
there with a cost of two.
Now, I am one hop away from R2.
So therefore, I must be able to get there
at a cost of three, if I send my packets
to r2."
Clearly, this is wrong r3 is delusional,
we can't really do that.
But because it's, hearing this value
advertised to r2, that says, "if you send
packets to me, I'll deliver them to r4 at
a cost of two plus the cost from me to
you, and therefore, with an overall cost of three."
R1 doesn't know anything about the failure
yet.
Let's see what happens in the next step.
So, the question is, will it
eventually converge, and settle to
the correct value?
So in the next step.
Because r3 is now advertising its cost as
being three if it goes via r2.
That news is going to reach R2.
And r2 is going to say, "hey, you were
previously saying to me that it was a cost
of
one, now you're telling me, it's a cost of
three.
So therefore, it must be costing me four to
get there.
Its, your cost which was three that you
were advertising to me plus the one, so
it's costing me four to get there if I go
via R3.
And you can see what's going to happen.
They're going
to gradually keep feeding each other bad
information iteratively, and it's going to
increase at every step and this is just
going to spiral out of control.
So, in the next round.
R2 is going to say, "hey, you were
telling me that I can get there at four
plus the cost from me to you, that's five,
if I send packets to you."
And so, it goes to five and then, you know
it's going to go to six and so on.
And it's just going to keep increasing as
we go around.
This is known as the counting to infinity
problem.
Or bad news travels slowly.
There's a fairly simple fix to this, which
is, it seems a bit of a kludge.
But we could set infinity to be some small
number, and say, sixteen, and stop when
you get to a count of sixteen.
If you get to a count of sixteen, it
actually means that there's no path at
all.
There are various other
methods, one that's called split-horizon.
You'll find it described in textbooks.
Essentially, because R2 received the
lowest cost path from R3,
it does not advertise that cost to R3.
In other words, because R2 was originally
receiving that lowest cost path from R3,
it doesn't send those advertisements to R3
and so, R3 will never think that it can
reach R4 via R2.
So, that's one way.
Another one is called split-horizon with
poison reverse.
In this case, R2 will actively advertise
infinity to R3.
So, it says, because I heard the lowest
cost path from you, I'm going to actively
send you the value infinity so you will
absolutely never think that you can get
there via me.
So these are kind of fixes to what is
really an elegant algorithm, but which,
in practice, takes quite a few things
like this to make it work.
Let's take a look at Bellman Ford in
practice.
Bellman Ford is an example of a distance
vector algorithm.
In other words, there's a distance vector
that is maintained by all of the routers,
of the distance from them to every other
router, and then they iteratively converge
on the correct answer.
In other words, the correct minimum cost
distance.
This is an example therefore of a distance
vector algorithm, and forms the heart of
one of  the first routing protocols
used in the Internet called RIP.
RIP stood for the Routing Information
Protocol, and it was used very widely for
quite a long time.
And this was because, it requires very
little computation on the routers, it
could be calculated in a distributed way
requiring very little
computational burden on each of the
routers.
And we knew that it would eventually
converge.
With a few little fixes here like the
split horizon technique and preventing it
from counting to infinity.
Over time though, it was replaced by other
algorithms, other techniques that collect
together the entire state of the network
on each router and then, independently on
their own, calculate the minimum cost
spanning tree, so no longer a distributor.
But we'll see an example of that in
another video on Dijkstra's Shortest Path
First Algorithm.