Nick: The end-to-end principle holds a very
special place in the design of
the Internet. This is because it really refers
to two different principles: the
first deals with correctness. If you don’t
follow the end-to-end principe
when you design your networked system, then
chances are it has a flaw
and might transfer data incorrectly. The second,
which we call the “strong”
end-to-end principle, is much broader and
general.
Phil: So let’s say we want to transfer a
file from one computer to
another. Our application opens a connection
between A and B. It
reads a file on computer A and writes it to
the TCP connection. B
reads the data from the socket and writes
the data to a file on
computer B.
The network in this case does very little.
It just forwards packets
from A to B. A and B set up the connection,
and the application
reads and writes the data.
Phil: Why doesn’t the network do more? It
turns out there are a lot of things it could
do to make the
file transfer faster. The network could automatically
compress packets between A and B. If the file
is
plain English text, this could reduce the
transfer size tenfold. The network could reformat
or improve
requests. Let’s say that A wants to transfer
two files to B. The network could see this
and combine the
two transfers into a single request. It could
be that A’s file is already stored on another
computer, C,
that’s closer and faster to B than A is;
the network could transfer the file from C
rather than A.
Or the network could automatically add security,
encrypting the data so bad guys can’t read
the file. If
the network does this for us, then we don’t
have to worry about it in our application.
The network could add mobility support, so
that as computer A moves through a network,
routes
automatically update and packets continue
to flow to it. With this support, we could
even possibly
migrate connections across the network, moving
something like a Skype video stream from our
phone
to our laptop.
It turns out there are *many* things the network
could do to improve our application and make
designing it easier. But generally speaking,
it doesn’t. Why?
Nick: The reason is the end-to-end principle.
The end-to-end principle was first described
by
Saltzer, Reed and Clark in a 1984 paper. You’ll
meet David Clark later in the course when
he gives
a guest lecture. The end-to-end principle,
as they describe it is:
“The function in question can completely
and correctly be implemented only with the
knowledge
and help of the application standing at the
end points of the communication system. Therefore,
providing that questioned function as a feature
of the communication system itself is not
possible.
(Sometimes an incomplete version of the function
provided by the communication system may be
useful as a performance enhancement.) We call
this line of reasoning. . . “the end-to-end
argument.”
Put another way, the network could possibly
do all kinds of things to help. But that’s
all it can do
-- help. If the system is going to work correctly,
then the end points need to be responsible
for
making sure it does. Nobody else has the information
necessary to do this correctly. The network
can help you, but you can’t depend on it.
For example, if you want to be sure your application
is
secure, you need to have end-to-end security
implemented in the application. The network
might
add additional security, but end-to-end security
can only be correctly done by the application
itself. So making security a feature of the
network so that applications don’t have
to worry about it
is not possible.
Nick: Let’s go back to our example of transferring
a file between
two computers. It was this exact problem,
along with others, that
led Saltzer, Clark and Reed to formulate the
end-to-end argument.
You want to make sure the file arrives completely
and
uncorrupted. The file data is going to pass
through several
computers between the source and the destination.
So the file,
coming from source, passes through computers
C, D, and E before
arriving at destination.
Nick: Each link -- source to C, C to D, D
to E, and E to destination
-- has error detection. If a packet of data
is corrupted in
transmission, then the recipient can detect
this and reject the
packet. The sender will figure out the packet
didn’t arrive
successfully, for example through TCP acknowledgments,
and
resend it.
Now, one could say “Look, I know the packet
won’t be corrupted
on any link, because I have my checks. Since
it won’t be corrupted
on any link, it won’t be corrupted. Therefore,
if it arrives
successfully at destination, there’s no
corruption, and the file has
arrived successfully.” This is exactly what
some programmers at
MIT did. Since the network provided error
detection, they assumed
it would detect all errors.
Phil: This assumption turned out to be wrong,
and because of this
mistake the developers ended up losing a lot
of their source code.
This is what happened. One of the computers
in the transfer path,
let’s say computer D, had buggy memory,
such that sometimes
some bits would be flipped. D received packets
of data, checked
them, and found them correct.
Phil: It would then move them into main memory,
at which point they would become corrupted.
It would then forward the packet, but because
error detection occurs on the link, from the
link’s perspective the packet looked fine
and it would pass E’s check. The link error
detection
was designed for errors in *transmission*,
not errors in storage.
The only way to be sure the file arrives correctly
is to perform an end-to-end check. When the
source sends the file, it includes some error
detection information. When the destination
reassembles
the file, it checks whether the file, it its
entirety, has any errors. This is the only
way
one can be sure it arrived correctly. The
network can help, but it can’t be responsible
for
correctness.
As another concrete example, think of TCP.
TCP provides a service of a reliable byte
stream.
But the reliability isn’t perfect. There
is a chance that TCP delivers some bad data
to you, for
example because there’s a bug in your TCP
stack, or some error creeps in somewhere.
So while
it’s very *unlikely* TCP will give you corrupted
data, it might, and so you need to perform
an
end-to-end check on the data it sends. So
if you transfer a file with TCP, do an end-to-end
check that it arrived successfully. BitTorrent
does this, for example. It uses TCP to transfer
chunks, and after each chunk is complete it
checks that it arrived successfully using
a hash.
Phil: So let’s go back to TCP and reliability.
If you want end-to-end reliable data transfer,
then you need an end-to-end reliable
protocol like TCP. But following the end-to-end
argument, while you must have end-to-end functionality
for correctness, the
network can include an incomplete version
of the feature as a performance enhancement.
Wireless link layers provide such a performance
enhancement. Today, wired link layers are
highly, highly reliable (unless your
wire or connector is bad). But wireless ones
aren’t, for a lot of reasons. So while usually
99.999% of packets sent on a wired link
arrive successfully at the next hop, wireless
links can sometimes be more like 50% or 80%.
It turns out that TCP doesn’t work well
when you have low reliability. So wireless
link layers improve their reliability by
retransmitting at the link layer. When your
laptop sends a packet to an access point,
if the access point receives the packet it
immediately -- just a few microseconds later
-- sends a link layer acknowledgement to tell
your laptop the packet was received
successfully. If the laptop doesn’t receive
a link layer acknowledgment, it retransmits.
It does this several times. Using these linklayer
acknowledgements can boost a poor link, with
only 80% reliability, to 99% or higher. This
lets TCP work much better.
TCP will work correctly -- it will reliably
transfer data -- without this link layer help.
But the link layer help greatly improves
TCP’s performance.
So that’s the end-to-end principle. For
something to work correctly, it has to be
done end-to-end. You can do stuff in the middle
to help as performance improvements, but if
you don’t rely on end-to-end then at some
point it will break.
Nick: There’s a second version of the end-to-end
principle, described in the IETF request for
comments number 1958, “The Architectural
Principles of the
Internet.” We call it the “strong” end-to-end
principle. It says
“The network’s job is to transmit datagrams
as efficiently and flexibly as possible. Everything
else should be done at the fringes...”
This end-to-end principle is stronger than
the first one. The first one said that you
have to implement something end-to-end, at
the fringes, but that you
can also implement it in the middle for performance
improvements. This principle says to NOT implement
it in the middle. Only implement it at the
fringes.
The reasoning for the strong principle is
flexibility and simplicity. If the network
implements a piece of functionality to try
to help the endpoints, then it is
assuming what the endpoints do. For example,
when a wireless link layer uses retransmissions
to improve reliability so TCP can work better,
it’s assuming
that the increased latency of the retransmissions
is worth the reliability. This isn’t always
true. There are protocols other than TCP,
where reliability isn’t
important, which might rather send a new,
different, packet than retry sending an old
one. But because the link layer has incorporated
improved reliability,
these other protocols are stuck with it. This
can and does act as an impediment to innovation
and progress. As layers start to add optimizations
assuming
what the layers above and below them do, it
becomes harder and harder to redesign the
layers. In the case of WiFi, it’s a link
layer that assumes certain
behavior at the network and transport layers.
If you invent a new transport or network layer,
it’s likely going to assume how WiFi behaves
so it can perform
well. In this way the network design becomes
calcified and really hard to change.
In terms of long term design and network evolution,
the strong end-to-end argument is tremendously
valuable. The tension is that in terms of
short term
design and performance, network engineers
and operators often don’t follow it. So
over time the network performs better and
better but becomes harder
and harder to change.