Nick: So in this unit, we're going to be learning
about how to control congestion in networks.
You already know about something called flow
control. Flow control is when we try to prevent
a sender from overwhelming a receiver by the
receiver telling the sender to slow down.
Congestion control is essentially extending
that notion to the network as a whole. You
can imagine that if senders were to send too
many packets into the network, they're going
to overwhelm the network. The buffers of the
routers are going to fill up, the links are
going to overflow, and we're going to start
dropping packets. Clearly not a very good
thing to happen. So congestion control is
about preventing the senders from overwhelming
the network. So that leads us to ask how do
we do it? What do we want from a congestion
control mechanism? First, clearly, it needs
to prevent the overwhelming from happening.
And second, we generally want it to spread
the pain evenly. We want to make sure that
all of the flows that are being controlled,
are being controlled in a fair and equal way.
Phil: So one of the big questions that comes
up is we want to control congestion, but how
should we do it? Where should we do it? Should
we do it at the edge? Should we do it within
the network? Well if we follow the end-to-end
argument - the strong end-to-end argument,
it would say that we want the network to just
forward packets. We want the intelligence
to be at the edges. And so that's actually
in practice often what's done today. So in
this unit, we're going to talk about TCP and
how TCP controls congestion. It turns out
it's one of its most important features. That
a TCP sender, a TCP receiver, particularly
a sender, can control how many packets it
puts into a network, to make sure that it
doesn't overwhelm the network, it controls
the congestion. And so it's the end-to-end
approach, leaving the inside of the network
simple. And it turns out you can just do it
at the edge, and it turns out you can do it
very well. So TCP congestion control chose
to use a particular algorithm called additive
increase, multiplicitive decrease, or AIMD.
And it turns out that this algorithm has a
lot of really interesting properties, when
you actually look at how behaves in even very
large, complex networks with millions of flows
competing. It has some very nice stable properties
that allow it to control congestion well,
and also in a fair way.
Nick: It turns out it's such an important
idea, by many it's considered one of the crown
jewels of networking. It's one of the most
important intellectual ideas to have found
its way into the network. It's in TCP. It's
been in TCP now for about 25 years. And so
it's a very significant part of controlling
congestion in the Internet. So in this unit,
you're going to be learning about what congestion
control is, the kinds of properties that we
would like from a congestion control algorithm,
what the specific congestion control mechanisms
are that are used in TCP, the AIMD that Phil
just mentioned. And you're going to be learning
a lot of details about how that works, how
it's implemented in practice, how it works
in different scenarios, what happens when
you have one flow, what happens when you have
many flows. And you're going to be learning
a lot about not only what TCP is today, but
it's going to give you a lot of insight into
what TCP congestion control might become in
the future.