So in this unit where going to finally dig down below IP
and answer the question what is a link and
how they work. So, how does the link layer
work and what are issues that you encounter at the link layer.
So there are two basic things that this unit is going to cover.
The first: the fundamental principles of
communication
this is where the boundary of computer
science and networking with electrical
engineering
we're going to talk about things like signal
and noise
and how the signal to noise ratio, in fact,
determines what's the potential
bit rate capacity of a link. There's a
reason why today we don't have
100 terabit per second link layers
because of some of these
fundamental mathematical principles of
communication. So based on that, we're
going to look at things like
bit errors and how link layers recover from them.
Using coding,
Error correcting codes. So that
for example, you add a little bit of redundancy to your link layer frames
such that, if there are a few bit errors down at the physical and link layer,
you can recover from and still
receive the frame correctly. So the second thing
that we're going to learn about it this
in this unit are how these links are
actually built. You'll remember
from unit one that the
thin waste of IP allows many many physical layers
and link layers to operate underneath and still
use the
Interne Protocol and to tie them all together. So there are different categories of
physical links we're going to be talking
about two here, two that you'll be very
familiar with
already. There's wired links, for which the
dominant linking in use today is ethernet. So we'll learn
how ethernet works. The original version
Ethernet used a shared
cable and so needed a way to share
that cable
so we'll be learning about what's called the
CMSA/CD protocol
and medium access control mechanism  that allows us to share that physical cable.
but we'll learn also how ethernet works today,
which is to use switches, which you learned a  little bit about already
In the previous unit, how they learn addresses and
tables get populated. The second thing we'll be learning
under the links is wireless links. Now wireless is quite different
from wired. more than just a the fact
that it's broadcasted
into the air, there's many characteristics of wireless that make it fundamentally
different in the way that it works and we need to be mindful of these when making practical links
the first thing is
the signal itself and the channel can vary
it's not fixed over time
like it is in a wired link
where it always has the same capacity operating on the same link
The channel can fade, there can be
different types of interference signals can take different paths with different links
and interfere with itself and because it's broadcast
everybody can hear and so this introduces challenges as well
as well security challenges because
everybody can hear what we're saying
there's another problem that we'll learn about that's called the hidden terminal problem
this is when two clients that are communicating
Are both happily talking to an AP
you but they have no means to
communicate with each other
because they don't have any direct signal contact
there needs to be some extra level of
coordination in the network to make sure
that they don't interfere
with each other or at the access point. In addition to
learning about these different types
link we'll be learning about what are
the consequences of having
these different links and that is that different links can carry packets up to a different
maximum size
so-called maximum transmission unit. ethernet for
example
take packets up to 1500 bytes low other links
may take
packets only upto a certain length and so you
probably remember that mention IP
fragmentation
in the earlier parts of the class. This is necessary when you're
going from a link with a
large maximum transmission unit down to  a small one
that is not able to carry it the network will
fragment it
into a number of self contained fragmets that don't get put back together again
until they get to the end host which then reassembles the data and
hands it up to the next layer. so you learn how that works
what specific mechanisms are inside  IP to make that work.
The last thing we're going to be learning about is this really interesting tricky little detail
of the communication channel and that is that
when two hosts or two
ends of a link are communicating with each other they can't
possibly be using exactly the same
clock or have exactly the same frequency
exactly the same phase
two different places at the same
time so when a  sender is sending using one clock
which is potentially different from the one the
receiver is using. So,  somehow we need to
indicate to  the receiver what clock
rate and
frequency and phase that we were using in order for the far end to correctly decode the data
so we'll learn about encoding inorder to
recover the clock
and use it correctly at the far end