When we connect our computer to the
network today, we're usually using Wi-Fi
for wireless, or Ethernet for a wired
connection.
Ethernet is by far the most widely used
linked layer mechanism in the internet
today.
So, the linked layer covers how an end
host is connected to a router, how one
router is connected to the next.
And generally as we've seen, packets at
the IP layer are encapsulated into a
linked layer frame, most often Ethernet,
in order to be sent off to the first
router.
So, in this video and the next, I'm going
to be describing something called CSMA/CD
which is right at the heart of how
Ethernet works.
And was very much a part of the original
Ethernet.
And I'll be describing how Ethernet
started out,
Its evolution over the years.
And then how Ethernet switching became a
very common way to extend, extend the
scope of a, of a link to cover many, many
end hosts connected to a single router.
You'll often hear Ethernet referred to as
layer two, and this goes back to the seven
layer OSI model what we saw in an earlier
video.
Whereas, in the four layer internet model,
Ethernet is the lowest layer.
In the seven layer of OSI model, Ethernet
encompassed both, link and the physical
layers,
Both of the, the, the lower two.
So, Ethernet is often referred to as layer
two, because of the link.
The link really just covers the frame
format and the algorithm that decides when
a packet can be sent onto the wire.
And we're going to see that a little bit
later,
That's the CSMA/CD mechanism.
The physical layer covers things like the
connectors and the electrical signals that
are used on the wire.
Ethernet started out as a means to connect
multiple computers together on a single
cable.
That single cable was arranged as a long,
a long string or a bus, as shown here.
It was, in fact, a big, thick, yellow
cable that snaked around, either in the
walls, the ceiling, or under the floor.
And computers would be connected down into
it, and then they are all sharing access to
the same common wire.
And the idea was, that they would share it
in order to be able to send packets
between themselves.
But then only one packet would be allowed
onto the cable at a time because,
otherwise, it would collide or corrupt and
interfere with other packets.
So, this is what we call sharing a medium.
And, Ethernet is an example of when
multiple hosts share a common cable,
that's what we mean by medium.
So, to share the medium, we need to decide
who gets to send, and when.
Because if only one packet can be sent on
the medium at a time,
We need to decide when the medium becomes
free, who is it that gets to use it next?
Do they do it in round robin order?
Do they do it randomly?
Whoever gets to send first?
What is the mechanism for doing so?
And there's generally a class of what are
called medium access control protocols or
MAC protocols.
And these are the protocols or algorithms
for determining who gets to send next.
We're going to look at some examples.
But the one thing to note here is, you've
probably heard Ethernet addresses being
referred to as MAC addresses before.
And you may even see this written on the
bottom of your computer.
MAC stands for medium access control, even
though we'll see later, Ethernet doesn't
use this mechanism very much anymore.
That's just a vestige of, of the earlier
ten megabit per second version of
Ethernet.
Let's take a look at some examples of
medium access control protocols.
There actually been dozens or hundreds of
them described, published, and invented
over the years.
And many of them were standardized.
But, because many of them have gone out of
fashion, I'm really going to be focusing
on just one Ethernet or carrier sense,
multiple access with collision detection,
CSMA/CD, that's the one we're going to be
focusing on.
But, I just want to set it into context a
little bit.
So, there are MAC protocols which are
simple and random.
The simplest of which is something called
Aloha, that I will describe in a moment.
And, at the other extreme is a method
called Token Passing.
Let me describe roughly how these work.
Let me start with a simple and random
mechanisms.
A random access protocol is one where
every host can try to send at any time
that it has data to send.
It doesn't need to wait for some central
authority to give it permission or until
its turn comes around.
It just tries to send.
It might listen and, and, and see whether
anyone else is speaking or it just may go
right ahead.
So, it's random in the sense that it just
may start speaking at any time.
At the other extreme, deterministic
protocols like token passing have some
means to explicitly control who gets to go
next.
In other words, which hosts gets to send a
packet next.
The most common method is called token
passing in which a special packet, or a
token, is sent from one host to the next.
So, they might be arranged, for example,
in a ring.
And there will be a packet called the
token that goes around, this would be the
token packet. And when you hold the token,
you're allowed to send a packet.
So, it might then send a packet on to
another host.
So this would be the packet being sent.
And then, when it's finished sending the
packet, it then passes on the token to its
neighbor.
Who then gets the opportunity to send the
packet,
And then, will send the token on again.
So, the token will go around like the
conch shell in Lord of the Flies if you've
read that book.
Or in any mechanism where we have a round
robin opportunity to send.
And, the token is indicating who gets to
send next.
This gives every host the chance to send
in a deterministic order.
But it does require us to both generate
and maintain this token.
And it turns out that there are lots of
ways in which this mechanism can fail.
And, the token can get lost, or the token
can get duplicated.
And so, these have generally fallen out of
favor and being replaced by the simpler
Ethernet, Ethernet mechanism in which
every host just basically randomly sends.
But, we'll see how that's controlled using
this CSMA/CD mechanism in a moment.
So, generally speaking, random access
protocols are simple enough to implement.
Give really good performance when there are
a small number of senders sending data at
random times, but they work less well
under very heavy load because they can
spend a lot of time colliding with each
other and corrupting each other until they
figure out an opportunity to send.
So, when we're designing a MAC protocol or
choosing one,
Then we have some, we generally have some
goals in mind.
We would like to have high utilization of
the shared channel.
We'd like to make sure that most of the
time is spent sending data not trying to
recover from collisions, or when multiple
end hosts are talking at the same time.
We'd like it to be fair.
We'd like it to be fair in the sense that
everybody gets an equal opportunity to
send averaged over a long period.
We'd like it to be simple and low-cost to
implement so that it can be very widely
deployed.
And we'd like it to be robust to errors.
So, we'd like it that if a, an end host
fails, then the chances are it's not going
to bring the whole network down.
Let me start with an example.
And the example that I'm going to be using
is one of the earliest medium access
control protocols called the Aloha
Protocol that was used in the Aloha
Network in Hawaii.
So, here are the Hawaiian Islands.
Basically, there was a central station in
Oahu where Honolulu is.
And, then there were relays or, or end
attachments at radio transmitters on the
islands of Kauai, Molokai, Maui and
Hawaii.
And, every packet that was sent would be
sent from an end host into the central
station,
Which would then rebroadcast it out to
everybody.
And so, this was radio based, RF based.
There was no wire.
And so, the medium in this case was the
air.
The way that Aloha worked was, all hosts
would transmit on one frequency.
So, if a host has something to send, it
would send on, say, frequency zero.
This blue is just representing the channel
corresponding to frequency zero.
This would be sent up to the main relay
station or the, the central relay station
in, on Oahu.
And then, that would be retransmitted.
The packet data would be retransmitted out
over frequency one, a separate frequency.
So essentially, a separate orthogonal
channel that would then be repeated to all
end hosts.
So, we need a way to decide who can send
when.
And for this, we need a protocol that
everybody agrees upon so that the system
will work correctly.
And, the first Aloha network to use the
Aloha MAC protocol, which is very simple.
If you have data to send, transmit it.
If your transmission collides with
another, retry later.
That was it.
So, very simple. You send, and then if you
discover that it collided, then you would
retry it.
How would you know that it collided?
Well, you would listen,
You would send on frequency zero.
And you would listen on frequency one.
And if what came back was not a correct
copy of what you would sent on frequency
zero, you know it must have collided.
And therefore, you need to send again.
And you would retry at a later time.
Nice thing about the Aloha protocol was
it's very simple.
It's pretty robust against the failure of
an end host.
What do I mean by this?
Well, if an end host fails and just stops
sending, then the mechanism doesn't rely
on any end host being powered on or
correctly operating, because it'll just
stop sending packets.
There is a failure condition if it just
starts jabbering away, sending packets
that, that are meaningless, it can
actually bring down communication for
everyone else.
So, that's why we say that it's quite
robust against failure.
The protocol is distributed, it's
distributed in a sense that it's, it's
actually operating independently on all
the end host. So, they all independentely
decide for themselves.
Under low load when there are very few,
either very few hosts sending or they're
sending at a very low rate, they're
sending infrequently, we can expect the
delay to be small.
Nearly any host who has stated to send
will find that the, the channel is free
when it wants to send its packet. So, it's
very likely to get through the first time,
with very little trouble that doesn't have
to wait for some coordinating mechanism.
It just sends, discovers that it gets
through and that's great.
Under high load, a lot of time can be
wasted sending packets that collide.
Because under high load the chances are
that there are that there other hosts
wanting to send at the same time.
And so, as a consequence, generally
speaking, the Aloha protocol is thought to
have very low performance.
And, in fact, studies and, and theory, and
simulations have all suggested that on the
high load, you can show that the waste,
wasted time is so high, we can only
achieve about 20% throughput,
18%, in fact.
So, over 80% of the time is
spent on transmissions that collide under
very heavy load.
Clear, clearly, we need to improve
performance.
There were many, many papers in the 1970's
and 80's on this topic of how to improve
networks like this.
And the technique most widely adopted for
wired networks is called CSMA/CD and it was
used for, for Ethernet.
And, you can see some of the ideas here
for improving performance.
One is,
Instead of just going ahead and sending,
regardless of whether anyone else is
sending,
You can actually listen for activity
first.
This is the carrier sends part CSMA/CD.
So, you listen, first of all, to check
whether anyone else is sending before
sending a packet.
If they are, you wait. If they're not,
then probably your packet will get through
okay.
The next one is to try and detect
collisions quickly, and stop transmitting.
If you, if you take your time to detect
the collision or we wait until the packet
is over, then you've wasted all of that
time.
If you can detect it very, very quickly,
back off, and then try again later, then
you can improve the performance.
And the third one is, after there has been
a collision, pick a random waiting time
that is based on the load.
In other words,
Pick a random time before trying again.
If the load is high, then wait a long time
because that will give others the
opportunity to be able to send.
If the load is low, then wait a short time
because probably you'll get through
successfully next time.
If the load is high and you wait a short
time, the chances are you'll collide
again, and it will just be a wasted
opportunity.
This leads us then, naturally from that
simple Aloha mechanism to the very widely
used CSMA/CD protocol.
And this is how it works.
So, this is what was used for the original
ten megabit per second Ethernet.
So, all hosts can transmit and receive on
the one channel, which is this  wire
right here.
This is the shared medium.
Packets are a variable size of course.
When a host has a packet to transmit,
first of all it does carrier sense.
So, that's the CS of CSMA/CD.
It checks that, that the line is quiet
before transmitting.
So, it listens.
If the wire is quiet, then it says,
probably my packet will get through.
Then, if there is a collision, it will try
and detect it quickly.
It will detect the collision as soon as
possible.
If a collision is detected, it will stop
transmitting, wait a random time, and then
it'll go back to one again.
In other words, it will go back, listen
for whether the wire is, is quiet.
And then, try to transmit, and if there's
a collision it will keep doing that.
And it will keep doing that until it's
successful.
This random time is called a binary
exponential backoff.
And all that means is, as the number of
collisions increase for a given packet, it
will wait a longer time.
In other words, if there is,
If there are lots of collisions, it means
there's lots of other transmitters.
And therefore, I should try and hold off a
longer amount of time, in order to be able
to give everybody the opportunity to, to
send.
Let's look at how CSMA/CD works in
practice.
Let's say, that I have a packet at A that
wants to, at, wants to go to D.
So, it has the Ethernet address of D.
A will send the packet.
The bits, the packet will propagate down
the wire.
So, I'm going to draw it all the way along
the wire here with D in it as if it's
moving from left to, left to right.
It will propagate at the speed of light,
down the wire.
And then, it will come up into D, D will
recognize the Ethernet address.
And, the packet will be correctly
delivered.
That first bit, that very first bit of the
front of the packet will start out by
being put under the wire here.
And then, it will propragate along and it
will take it L over C.
If L is the length of the cable from A to
D.
It'll take L over C seconds to arrive.
D listens, hears the packet, and, and in
the meantime while that packet is coming
in, that, the, the wire is busy, so B, C,
and D will all hear the wire as busy and
won't try and send packets.
So, if they've got anything to send, they
will say, they'll do the carrier sends,
the step one. Say,
The network is busy.
I won't try and send now, I'll wait
until later.
Now, let's look at, at the condition of,
of what causes a collision in the network.
So, if A again, has a packet destined for
D, and D has a packet that is destined for
A, A will send its packet.
So, let's look at the first bit.
I'm just now going to talk in terms of the
first bit propagating down the wire from A
to D.
It'll take L over C seconds.
If that packet is going down the wire,
Here is the whole packet.
And D listens and says, aha, it's quiet
right now, because the first bit hasn't
arrived, and starts sending its packet.
And so, its packet is heading down this
direction, its first bit is going down
here.
And so, at some point, that, the front of
this packet will collide with the front of
this packet. And after that, they will
pass through each other, corrupting each
other, so that everyone that sees it,
first of all, C will see it, in this case,
so it will hear that there is a collision.
And the way that it detects the collision
is through a number of mechanisms.
One is it, it just starts to get garbled
messages.
It sees a very, a much larger number of
transitions, basically twice as many
transitions on the wire,
Or the main frequency component is
doubled,
Or the voltage level has been increased.
Any of these mechanisms can be used to
detect a collision.
As the, as the packet from D continues to
head towards A, that collision will soon
be noted at B when the front of the packet
gets to B.
And so, it will hear the collision.
And eventually, that packet will reach A,
and it will hear the collision.
And, of course, this packet hear will hit
D, and so it will hear the collision.
So, at all slightly different times, they
all hear the collision depending on the
particular time that the packets were
sent.
So, Carrier sense.
Listen, see whether the line is quiet,
send the packet, listen for the collision,
then back off.
The binary exponential back off is set so
that there's a good chance that they will
both back off by different amounts, and
therefore not collide next time they send.
CSMA/CD networks have a minimum
packet size requirement.
Let me explain why that is.
Going back to my example of when A and D
were sending packets to each other,
imagine now that A and D are sending
packets on this network, of length L, and
speed of propagation C.
Imagine that the, the first bit of the
packet from A,
So remember we have packet from
A to D.
And we have packets from D to A.
D listens, here the, hears that the wire
is quiet and at time zero.
So, this is going to be T equals zero.
The first bit of A, from A is going to
start propagating down here towards D.
Now, imagine that at A time, just a tiny,
tiny little bit, L/C - delta,
just a tiny time period before that first
bit reaches D. Host D decides that it's
going to send its packet.
It listens to the wire, says that it's
idle, and then starts to transmit its
packet.
So the, the packet almost immediately
collides.
And at time delta later,
The collision will be detected at D, and D
will stop transmitting
almost immediately.
Now, although D knows about the collision,
A doesn't know about the collision yet
because that information or that, that
collision has not propagated to A.
So that little fragment of what of D has
sent will propagate down here.
So, this is the collision propagating
down.
And so, eventually, the propagation, the,
the, the first bit will reach here.
If A is still sending the packet towards
D,
In other words, if it hasn't reached the
end of the packet yet, then A will detect
the collision as well.
And it will detect that collision after
L/C from when it started, and then
another L/C until the packet is
finished.
So, there's two L/C in, in the worse
case is the time from when A starts
sending a packet until it hears of the
collision.
If A had finished sending its packet by
the time the collision propagated to it,
A, wouldn't realize that the collision
took place.
And when it hears about the collision, it
wouldn't know what packet that caused the
collision.
Had it been its own packet, had it been a
packet from another host.
So, in order for a simple way for A to be
sure that it stops and realizes that there
was a collision and needs to back off and
re-transmit the packet,
One, one simple way to do this is to make
sure that A is sending its packet for at
least 2L over C.
In other words, in the worst case, it's
guaranteed to hear about the collision
before it stops transmitting the packet.
This means that we have a requirement of
P/R, the packet length divided by the
rate is greater than or equal to
2L over C.
This is a general requirement for CSMA/CD
networks in order to be able to detect a
collision while it's still transmitting a
packet.
Let's look at an example.
Imagine that I have a CSMA/CD network
which is running at a rate of ten megabits
per second.
And, let's say it's 10,000 meters long,
ten kilometers long.
It's a pretty big network.
And that the speed of propagation is two
times ten to the eight meters per second.
What we need, P over R is greater than or
equal to 2L over C.
So, we can say P must be greater than or
equal to two times L, ten to the four,
Times,
Well, I've just moved the, the R over onto
the other side.
So, ten to the seven, divided by two times
ten to the eight.
So, the two's are going to cancel, and I've
got eleven over eight is 1,000 bits.
So, what would tell me is that for a
CSMA/CD network to operate correctly at
that size and those rates, the minimum
size packet has to be a 1000 bits or about
128 bytes.
So, in summary, we've seen how medium
access control protocols are used starting
with Aloha,
A nice simple random access protocol.
And then, improved on its performance to
create CSMA/CD.
And, we saw that CSMA/CD is very simple,
Nice random access mechanism.
And, we learned that the minimum packet
size, P over R has to be greater than 2L
over C in order to be able to reliably
detect collisions before we finish
transmitting a packet.
In the next video, I'm going to be
explaining how CSMA/CD was used in the
original Ethernet.
And then, how Ethernet has evolved over
time.
And then, end with Ethernet switching.