LILA FISHER: Hi,
welcome to Edx.
I'm Lila Fisher, an Edx
fellow helping to put
together these courses.
As you know, our courses
are entirely online.
So before we start learning
about the subjects that
brought you here, let's learn
about the tools that you will
use to navigate through
the course material.
Let's start with what is on
your screen right now.
You are watching a video
of me talking.
You have several tools
associated with these videos.
Some of them are standard video
buttons, like the play
Pause Button on the
bottom left.
Like most video players, you can
see how far you are into
this particular video segment
and how long the entire video
segment is.
Something that you might
not be used to
is the speed option.
While you are going through the
videos, you can speed up
or slow down the video player
with these buttons.
Go ahead and try that now.
Make me talk faster
and slower.
If you ever get frustrated by
the pace of speech, you can
adjust it this way.
Another great feature is the
transcript on the side.
This will follow along with
everything that I am saying as
I am saying it, so you can
read along if you like.
You can also click on any of the
words, and you will notice
that the video jumps
to that word.
The video slider at the bottom
of the video will let you
navigate through the
video quickly.
If you ever find the transcript
distracting, you
can toggle the captioning button
in order to make it go
away or reappear.
Now that you know about the
video player, I want to point
out the sequence navigator.
Right now you're in a lecture
sequence, which interweaves
many videos and practice
exercises.
You can see how far you are in
a particular sequence by
observing which tab you're on.
You can navigate directly to
any video or exercise by
clicking on the appropriate
tab.
You can also progress to the
next element by pressing the
Arrow button, or by clicking
on the next tab.
Try that now.
The tutorial will continue
in the next video.