One-time pads are generally impractical. Instead,
what we want is a cryptosystem where we can
distribute a small key K, say 128 or 256 bits.
We somehow share this key beforehand, for
example over the phone, or write it down and
exchange it with a handshake. We then use
this K to encrypt a much larger message M.
We then call encrypt, E, passing the plaintext
message M and the key K, to produce the ciphertext
C.
Now, unlike a one-time pad, it might be there
is only one possible M that produces the ciphertext.
But, we believe it’s computationally intractable
to find this M. You could try all possible
keys, but decrypting with 2 to the 128, or
300 undecillion, keys, would take a very,
very long time. Suppose you it only takes
a single instruction to decrypt the message.
Let’s suppose your processor core is 4GHz.
And let’s suppose your computer has 4 billion
cores. Then it would take 4 billion of these
computers 31 years.
There are two kinds of symmetric ciphers:
stream and block.
Stream ciphers generate a pseudo-random pad,
a pseudo-random sequence of bits based on
the key. You then encrypt/ decrypt by XORing
with this stream, like a one-time pad. But
it is NOT a one-time pad! Immediately mistrust
anyone who says it is, they don’t know what
they’re talking about.
Generally speaking, stream ciphers have run
into lots of problems in practice. Problems
with stream ciphers typically stem from repetition.
If you re-use the same pseudorandom sequence
of bits (e.g., reuse the same key on two different
messages) then adversaries can launch attacks
like I showed with the two-time pad. The initial
WiFi encryption protocol, WEP, for example,
used a stream cipher. It was shown to be broken
in around 2001, when WiFi was starting to
take off, and replaced by WPA in 2003 and
WPA2 in 2004.
WPA2 uses something called a block cipher.
A block cipher operates on fixed sized blocks
of data, say 64 bits of 128 bits. A block
cipher maps a plaintext block to a ciphertext
block. There are many block ciphers. Today,
you should generally use AES, the Advanced
Encryption Standard.
I’m going to walk through the basics of
how one block cipher, Blowfish, works. But
be careful! I’m not explaining the algorithm
in its entirety. I’m just trying to give
you a feel for what a block cipher looks like
and how it works. I’m left out a lot of
details, which if you don’t pay attention
to, the cipher might not be secure. You should
rely on existing implementations and use suggestions.
Here are the basics of Blowfish. It uses something
called a Feistel network. A Fesitel network,
or a Feistel cipher, is one where encryption
and decryption use the same computational
structure. Specifically, decrypting in Blowfish
looks just like the inverse of encrypting,
except that the function F is different. So
to decrypt, you feed the ciphertext C in at
bottom, you reverse all the arrows, and the
cleartext M comes out at top.
To use Blowfish, you take the original key
and from it derive the function F and 18 subkeys,
P1 through P18. You take your plaintext block
of 64 bits and divide it into two parts, the
left half L0 and the right half R0. Both L0
and R0 are 32 bits long. You then processes
L0 and R0 through 16 iterations of the structure
on the left. You XOR the left hand value with
a key P. You pass this value through the function
F and XOR that with the right hand value.
The right hand value becomes the new left
hand value and vice versa. Then, in the final
step, you XOR the left hand value with P18
and the right hand value with P17. This produces
two 32-bit values, which you concatenate into
the ciphertext C.