Layering is a general and important principle
in the design of computer networks. You mostly
see its benefits: separation of concerns,
independent evolution, ease of adaptability
to future technologies. But it does sometimes
get in the way. TLS is used today for secure
web transactions over HTTPS. But it’s often
the case that a web server actually runs multiple
web sites through something called virtual
hosts. The domain names of all of the web
sites map to the same IP address, of the server.
Clients connect to all of them over port 80.
It’s not until the HTTP request comes in
that the web server process knows which site
the request is for. The Host: header field
of an HTTP request tells it. For example,
if you go to sing.stanford.edu and tinyos.stanford.edu,
they’re the same server. I can could configure
Apache so they serve up different web pages.
Apache would look inside the request, see
the Host: header, and chose which pages to
server based on that.
This can break TLS such that it can’t fully
work properly. How?
Does it break server authentication?
Does it break the key exchange?
Does it break randomness generation?
Does it break routing the handshake messages?
Or does it break premaster secret generation?
The answer is that it breaks server authentication.
The TLS handshake and secure session setup
occur before there is any application data.
As part of this exchange, the server needs
to provide a certificate that binds a public
key to a name. But it doesn’t know what
name to use. For example, my server can’t
tell whether a connection is coming in for
tinyos.stanford.edu or sing.stanford.edu.
So it doesn’t know whether to provide a
certificate for tinyos.stanford.edu or sing.stanford.edu.
In my case, I have a certificate that says
both, but if I wanted to add a new host name
to the server, say a new website named “www.networking-class.com”,
then TLS would throw an error.
The problem is that the session layer, layer
5, needs to know the host name that the client
is trying to contact. But that name is only
available in the application layer, layer
7. The client has translated the name to an
IP address, so a layer 3 name. So here’s
an example of layers, encapsulation of functionality,
causing a conflict and getting in our way.