Nick: In this unit you will learn a lot about
packet switching – it is quite an intense
unit and your head might be spinning with
packets by the end of it. But that’s why
we have videos! You can cover the material
at your own pace and review it several times.
Phil: We will start out with a leisurely look
at why the Internet – and almost all modern
networks – are built on a foundation of
packet switching. Packet switching is simple
in the sense that each packet is a self-contained
unit of data that carries information necessary
for it to reach its destination. Packet switching
is efficient in the sense that it keeps a
link busy whenever there is work to be done,
rather than have dedicated capacity reserved
for each user or application.
Nick: After a leisurely introduction to packet
switching, we will dive deeply into some of
the consequences. We will take a journey that
includes more math than you will see in any
other unit of this course. The math might
seem daunting at first, but it’s actually
quite simple. Once you learn the math, so
many other details or complex questions become
really easy to answer and understand. For
example, you will learn why two packets traveling
between the same two end hosts might encounter
a different delay. While the time they spend
traversing each link is the same, the packets
might take different paths and experience
different queueing delays in the router buffers.
Phil: Make sure you fully understand the three
main components of packet delay: the packetization
delay, the propagation delay, and the queueing
delay; and that you understand the physical
processes that cause them. By the end of this
unit you will be able to answer questions
like: “How long does it take for a packet
to get from here to London?” or “How many
packets can I fit in space between the moon
and Mars?”. You’ll understand why routers
have buffers, and how queueing delay leads
to uncertainty about when packets will arrive.
For most applications, this isn’t an issue.
But for real time streaming applications,
like Skype and YouTube, they need to playback
smooth, hiccup-free audio and video to the
user, and so they need to absorb the variation
in delay across the Internet. You’ll learn
how playback buffers are designed.
Nick: Finally, you’ll learn about how packet
switches work in practice. At the end of the
unit you’ll also be able to answer the question:
“How does an Internet router actually work?”,
and “How is it different from an Ethernet
switch?”. “How does a router arrange its
lookup tables?” and so on. It’s quite
a whistle-stop tour of packet switching, and
by the end of the unit you should have a good
intuition for how packet switching works in
the Internet.