Let’s look at the first of three properties
that cryptography can provide: confidentiality,
or secrecy.
The basic way you achieve confidentiality
is through encryption. Because cryptography
has a firm mathematical basis, and because
it’s important to be precise given the dangers
of using it haphazardly, I’m going to introduce
some terms.
I’m going to start with symmetric encryption.
In symmetric encryption, two parties share
some secret key K. So let’s suppose we have
a message M, we want to transmit confidentially,
and the key K. M is called the plaintext,
or cleartext. It’s the thing we want to
keep secret. To encrypt, we call a function
E, passing the message M and the key K. This
produces a ciphertext C. If our encryption
algorithm is secure, then it’s intractable
for someone to figure out the cleartext from
the ciphertext unless they have the key. So
we can transfer C over the network, adversaries
can look at it, but they can’t read the
original message M.
To decrypt the cipher text, we call the decrypt
function D, also passing the key K. This returns
the original cleartext M. The goal is that
you can only decrypt the message, or learn
anything about it, if you have the right K.
Of course someone could try every K, so you
pick a key big enough that exhaustively searching
the space is intractable. For example, make
the key 128 or 256 bits.
Because E and D take the same key K, we call
this symmetric or shared key encryption. There
are other cryptosystems that don’t use symmetric
keys, we’ll cover them later. Examples of
symmetric encryption algorithms are AES, Blowfish,
DES, and RC4.
A
one-time pad is a perfectly secret but generally
impractical encryption algorithm. We generate
a perfectly random stream of bits as our key
K. The sender and receiver somehow exchange
this key securely beforehand. For example,
through a handshake and a USB drive. To encrypt,
we XOR our message M with the key K. To decrypt,
we XOR our ciphertext C with the key K.
This algorithm is “perfectly” secure in
that if we have the ciphertext but not the
key, then any M is equally likely. Furthermore,
it’s really fast. All we have to do is XOR
the messages.
So if you’re a super-secret spy who has
to send a short message, one-time pads are
great. But not so in general practice. The
problem with one-time pads is that your key
K is the same size as the message M. To send
a gigabyte of data, you need a gigabyte- long
key. This is not practical. We’d like to
be able to send small keys that encrypt large
amounts of data yet are still intractable
to crack.