This video digs into the details of what
actually a DNS query response series looks
like.
So, as soon as you know what resource
records are and what their structure is
and the high level view of this idea to
the client issuing a recursive query which
is then non recursively issued to other
servers in the network.
And by details, I mean, that this is high
level, there's this idea I issue a
recursive query COUGH and then this
results in resolver issuing a series of
non recursive queries to give me my final
answer of what the address record of
www.stanford.edu is.
But what are the, what are the actual
contents of these queries? What are the
actual contents of the responses and what
is the information that each of these
servers has to know?
So, this matter, this is really important
when you are actually setting up a name,
name system,
when you are actually setting up a domain and
need to configure name servers in network
such that you would be able to actually ask
questions and people are able to access
their machines and their names.
So, the big challenge, one of the big
challenges comes from this concept of
traversing zones.
So at some point, my name server has a
root cache file.
So, this just gives some IP addresses of
root servers.
And this is the bootstrapping process.
If I just have those IP addresses, then
from there, I can get TLD, TLD name server
addresses from there,
I can get domain name server addresses,
and sub-domains,
Etc. So,
At a high level it sort of makes sense,
Oh, I asked about edu, I asked about
Stanford.
But there turned out to be a couple of
tricks.
So,
Think about an NS record.
So, if you recall, a name server record, if I
ask for what the name server is of a
domain, the nameserver record contains a
host name.
So, for example, if I ask what is the name
server of stanford.edu, the answer is a
host name.
So, here let's dig for the nameserver of
stanford.edu.
And the answer is, we get four answers,
these host names,
Avallone.stanford.edu,
argis.stanfor.edu,
atalante.stanford.edu, and
aerathea.stanford.edu
But the problem is these are all names in
Stanford.
How can we get the address of these name
servers unless we know the IP address of
these name servers?
These are the servers we would ask for
what those names are.
So, there's this chicken and egg problem.
How do we get started?
Given that we're being given host names.
and so, the solution to this and the name
system, of the domain name system is
something called the glue record.
And what this is, is that when, say,
Stanford goes to the edu servers and says,
hey,
These are the name servers for Stanford.
It gives them not only NS records
specifying the names of the servers but
also associated A records. And these are
glue records because it means the edu
servers are going to serve up address
records, A records for stanford.edu,
Only for the name servers of stanford.edu,
but nonetheless,,they they are serving A
records for stanford.edu,
Right?
And so, we go back to this example,
Alright?
We can see that on one hand, I'm asking,
what are the name servers of stanford.edu?
But the additional section then, also
gives me address records for them, and
these address records are stored within
the edu name servers.
So, let me just walk through an example of
this.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to look
up www.scs.stanford.edu assuming there's
no cache.
I'm going to explicitly walk through this
series of queries that would be issued.
The way I'm going to do that is with this
norec option, which means do not ask a
recursive query.
And so, as the first step, lets dig.
So, this is going to, I'm going to contact
one of the root servers to the A root
servers.
And say, hey who do I talk to for
edu? Because it's non-recursive.
And I get a response which says, here are
some of the servers to use.
So, let's say, here's the, the A edu
servers.
And these are the main servers that you
can use...okay So, I am going to use the A
edu, server.
And I'm going to say, hey,
Whom shall I ask about stanford.edu?
And it's going to tell me to ask
argus.stanford.edu. As you can see,
it's also getting me the A records the A
record for argus so I actually have an IP
address to ask.
Then I'm going to ask argis, hey, whom
would I ask about www.scs.stanford?
And Argus is going to answer, oh, you
should ask ns1.fs.net.
And, or you can also ask
mission.scs.stanford.edu.
Oh, and here's the address record for
And so, in its response, I now know the IP
address to contact and I can put that
record into my cache.
And so, if I then do
mission.scs.stanford.edu, I'm going to get
the A record.
In fact, that mission.scs.stanford.edu
does gave me the A the record for, for
www.scs.stanford.edu, time to leave is
3600, and IP address of 171.66.3.9. So, on
record that we saw briefly, besides an A
record and NS record, there is something
called the CNAME record, a canonical name.
What the canonical name record tells you
in DNS is that a name is an alias.
So as we saw before, if you dig
www.stanford.edu, you'll see that that's
actually an alias for another name say,
www-v6.stanford.edu.
And so, if there's a CNAME record for a
name, there can't be any other records for
the name.
It's telling you, oh, this is just a
pointer.
And so often, what will happen is that if
you ask a query about a canonical name, it
will tell you, oh,
Sorry, for and alias name, they will tell
you this is an alias for this canonical
name then here are the records you want
for the canonical name.
So, for example, if you dig
www.stanford.edu, it will tell you the
canonical name is this other name oh, and
here is the A record for that other name.
Another kind of DNS record, and this one
is really valuable is, they're all really
valuable, is what's called an MX record.
So, mail exchange record.
And it tells you what's the mail server
for a domain.
So, for example, there's no host,
scs.stanford.edu,
You can't ping it, try it. But you can
send e-mail to scs.stanford.edu.
People have e-mail addresses of that
domain.
And so, what this is, is that, there is an
MX record for scs.stanford.edu that says,
oh, if you want to send mail to this
domain, this is the server you should talk
to.
And further more, an MX record causes A
record processing.
So, if I say, hey, what is the MX record,
then it will say, oh, this is the name of
the server for the mail and here is the A
record for that server.
So, for example, let's dig
mx.scs.stanford.edu.
You know,.and And we'll see, okay, answer
section.
The MX record for scs.stanford.edu,
The TTL, 3600, its internet is
market4.scs.stanford.edu.
Furthermore, the address record for
market4.scs.stanford.edu is 171.66.3.10.
And this ten is a preference value, it
tells you if there's maybe different
servers that you want which one is best.
So there, we can request the MX record.
So, this starts to get a little funny. So,
what happens if the male server name
doesn't have an A record?
So, let's try digging this bad MX.
So, let's do dig MX, add
mx.scs.stanford.edu, okay.
And it's going to say, well, bad MX is
cs144.scs.stanford.edu but now, we don't
have an A record of it.
But this is weird.
Why don't we have an A record for
Cs144.scs.stanford.edu? That's a valid
host name but for some reason, the name
servers not able to give us an A record.
So, if we look up, let's just dig
cs144.scs.stanford.edu,.
If we look up here, it turns out that
cs144.stanford.edu is a CNAME for
www.cs.stanford.edu..
So, it's actually an alias for this.
And this is where you get one of those
interesting edge cases in protocols, these
things were the way it's designed,
It turns out there's some implications
which you maybe didn't foresee which
actually, you know, I mean, kind of maybe
a good idea.
The point is that your MX record isn't
something which people are looking at.
It's something which just machines use so
you shouldn't have it be pointing at aliases.
If you're pointing at aliases then you're
forcing another level of indirection in
the DNS hierarchy which isn't helpful
given that it's just machines, it's not
people.
So recall, when you look up an MX record,
you'll also get processing for the
associated A records, but cs144 does not
have an A record,
It has a CNAME record and the fact that it
has a CNAME record means it cannot have
any other record.
And so, there's this approach where, if
you point your MX record at an alias, it
forces people to lookup.
And so, there is, it's sort of this way to
create a negative incentive for you to do
that.
And so, here's this interaction, which
means two different kinds of records, with
their process which is, in a way, to kind
of construct this system to be more
efficient.
So, in addition to A records, Quad A
records, NS records, MX records, and CNAME
records, there are all kinds of other
records.
There are Start of Authority records,
which give you information about the
actual caching of DNS information.
There's something called a Text record,
which is a way to put arbitrary text, so
you can associate arbitrary text with a
name.
This is a great way for extensions.
People have explored all kinds of new
services using Text records.
It allows you to play with something in
the operating, working internet and then,
maybe transition to a new kind of specific
record.
There also things called pointer records,
which do the reverse mapping.
You look up a pointer record for an
address and it'll give you a name if one
exists or if it knows of it.
And then, as we've see before, there were
called quad A records, or IPv6 address
records.
They have full 128 bit IPV6 addresses in
them.
And so, those are the nitty-gritty details
of DNS, the information that is cached,
how to use glue records to stitch together
zones and some of the different kinds of
records that you have besides just simple
NS and A records.