In the last video, I explained how
additive-increase/multiplicative-decrease
could be used to modulate the window size
in the sliding window protocol.
For example, for modulating a TCP flow.
And I explained how the, the window size
is essentially varying to probe how much
capacity the network has for additional
bytes to be placed into it.
Now, in the case of a single flow,
This is, this is interesting when, we're
looking at a router with, one predominant
flow.
So, for example, in a home network, we're
probably, at any one time, there's one
dominant network flow for, for example,
for streaming video or downloading a
webpage.
But out in the wilds of the Internet, it's
very common for a router to have many,
many, many flows passing through it at the
same time.
So, in this video, we're going to look at
the multiple flow case.
As an example, a backbone router in the
backbone of the Internet,
It'd be pretty common for it to have ten
or even 50,000 flows passing through it at
any one time.
And there, we could expect the dynamics to
be very different indeed.
So if we look at that if we look at that
case.
So for example, if we look at the case
again of a source and a destination
sending packets through a packet buffer,
in this particular case the bottleneck
link is the one on the right again, and so
packets will tend to accumulate in that
router.
Here I show any one source and we saw the
dynamics before where we have a handful of
packets corresponding to the those in the
window that could not be placed onto the
links.
But in the backbone of the Internet we
might see thousands and thousands of
packets.
It's not uncommon for a router buffer to
be able to, to hold hundreds of thousands
of packets, and they will come from many,
many different flows.
I've tried to represent that here with
different colors.
I didn't have enough colors to show all
the different flows that, that, that would
make up the, the buffer at any one time.
But you can see immediately that the
packets belonging to any one individual
flow are only going to make up a small
fraction of the occupancy of the buffer.
So each one of them will be going through
that window, changing and they will all be
doing that independently of each other.
And occasionally one of them will
experience a, a packet drop and so it will
go back again and then, it might go for a
long period without actually seeing a
drop, while somebody else sees it, another
flow sees a drop and it will back down and
so they will all be expanding and
contracting somewhat independently of each
other.
The more flows there are,
The more independent they will be, and the
more steady the occupancy of the queue
will be for anyone over the load in the
network.
So the consequence of this is that the
occupancy of the buffer is more determined
by the overall load than the dynamics of
the individual windows.
And so that occupancy tends to be pretty
constant, pretty steady.
And it's quite reasonable to think of the
RTT, the round trip time, as being quite
constant when there are many flows.
So just to contrast the single flow case
with the multiple, multiple flow case that
we saw before, the window size in red, the
buffer occupancy, and the RTT, because
they are so strongly related is the dotted
line, and they move in lockstep.
And as we saw before, they, they, the, the
rate will tend to be, will tend to be
constant.
Because W of T and the RTT, which is also
varying with time, will be moving in
lockstep and thefore, the rate is
constant.
If we look at the multiple flow case,
because of this aggregation of many, many
flows, and the packets of many flows into
the router buffer.
Each one of them making a small,
representing a small change in variation
in the occupancy of the queue.
The buffer occupancy in the RTT tends to
be much smoother.
And is representative of the
overall load of the network.
So there are many fewer perturbations in the
occupancy of the buffer.
If we zoom in on any one individual flow,
as I've done here in red, then you can see
that it will still go through this
additive increase and multiplicative
decrease, but the drops will, will happen
at more random times, than with the single
flow, because it really depends on who,
which flow encounters the drop and backs
off, and they all do it at, at different
times.
So, as a consequence, the RTT is staying
pretty constant and so the rate will be
proportional to the window size.
So, the rate will W of T over RTT, RTT
will now be pretty much constant.
So the rate will be a function of windows
size.
So the rate will move according to that
sawtooth.
You may have noticed that the shape of the
sawtooth has changed in, in, in, in a
different way and that is that the,
When I was drawing this before for a
single flow, you can see it's curved,
It's not straight, whereas for multiple
floors it's, I drew it as a straight line
and that's for a reason.
When we have only got one flow,
The way in which the RTT will increase
each time we place more buffer, packets in
the buffer, it will increase in the
following ways.
Always the horizontal, the horizontal step
here will, will increase by RTT each time
and then it will go up by one, go by RTT,
and then it will go up by one and so on.
But the RTT itself is increasing,
So the step is getting longer and longer,
hence the curve,
Whereas down here the RTT is constant, and
so each step is the same size, so it will
be RTT in the horizontal direction one on
the vertical direction, RTT one RTT.
And so, it'll be a straight line when it's
smoothed out.
So this equation here tells us that the
rate is, proportional to the window size.
Notice that it also tells us it's
inversely proportional to RTT.
It's worth asking, what actually is the
relationship between the rate, RTT, and
the drop probability in the network.
So in the next, in the next slide, I'm
going to explain the relationship between
them by offering you a sort of a simple
geometric model to start with and then
explaining how this fits, in the, fits
with practice.
Here is our familiar AIMD model.
The sawtooth that's going through the
additive increase, multi, additive
increase up here, and then the
multiplicative decrease, and I'm showing
here the drops taking place at each of the
peaks.
These were the drops that led to the
halving of the window size.
So we're not going to worry about, how we
know that the drops took place or how long
it takes us to find out.
We're just going to assume that every time
there's a drop, we halve the window size
and see if we can figure out a function
for the rate of the flow, as a function of
the drop probability and the RTT.
So the first thing to note, is there is
one drop every time we send this number of
bytes, because this represents the, the
area under that line, represents the bytes
integrated over time.
The width here is W max over two times
RTT,
Remember RTT we are going to assume is a
constant because there are many flows in
the network.
And so if we find this area A, and one
over that will tell us the, the, that for
every drop that we take, that's how many
bytes we had that we had sent. So we
will do that in a moment.
And then from there, we are going to try
and deduce the rate as a function of the
drop probability.
So let's work though this.
From the sawtooth, we know that, what the
area A is.
The packet drop rate is going to be one
for every I, A bytes that we send, where A
is just simply three over eight times W
max squared.
Three-eighths because the horizontal
distance down here,
The distance here is Wmax over two because
it's just a square.
That's the number of RTTs times RTT, so
that's the time because each step is of
RTT wide.
So the area is three-eighths of W, Wmax
squared.
So therefore the throughput is A, that's
the number of bytes that we send,
Divided by the time that it took us to
send it, which is the width.
Because we know A is a function of P, we
can substitute P into the equation, and we
end up with a rate equation that looks
like this.
Root three over two times one over RTT
times the square root of P.
So look at that for a moment.
It's more than just an equation.
It tells us something about the property
of AIMD.
It tells us first that the rate that a
flow experiences is proportional to one
over its RTT.
In other words, the bigger the RTT, the
lower the rate.
You think about that for a moment.
It means that when we're communicating
with a server that's further away, we can
expect a lower rate.
This is not really the probability that we
want from a congesting control algorithm.
We don't necessarily want to penalize
flows that are further away.
And so, this is generally considered a
weakness or a, a poor characteristic of
AIMD.
The second thing to notice is that it's
quite sensitive to the drop probability,
one over square root of p.
So we look at the equation in a little bit
more detail.
First of all, it tells us that, it appears
to tell us that, not only if we double the
RTT, we halve the rate.
But also, as the RTT tends to zero,
doesn't that mean that the rate tends to
infinity?
That can't be the case.
Well, of course, the rate is the, the, the
minimum of this value and the link speed.
So it can't possibly exceed the link
speed.
So at some point, with a very small RTT,
the, the, the rate will actually be
determined by the speed of the link.
Also, it appears to say, as the,
Drop probability goes to zero, the rate
will go to infinity.
If you think about it, this is, is
actually true, this is actually correct
because in the sawtooth,
If the probability of drop is tending to
zero it means that there aren't any drops
in the window size.
In other words we were able to increase
the window size without limit.
We were able to put more and more bytes or
packets into the network without there
ever being a drop.
Well, if that was the case it means that
we've continued to increase the rate and
we've encountered no drops, it means that
we haven't found the upper limit yet.
So in fact, this is this is correct.
So in practice, there will always be some
drops, there must be some drops for the
mechanism to work and for the rates to be
controlled.
It also tells us what the what the
sensitivity is to the, the drop
probability.
So for example, we can rewrite this
equation here by saying that if you wanted
to understand the ratio of two rates,
Say R1 and R2 as a function of the drop
probability, we can say that the
relationship between them is P.
The square root of P2 over P1.
That's simply by taking two values for R
and P.
If we keep the RTT constant, then the
ratio of those would be the square root of
P2 over P1.
So if we were to increase the,
probability,
Let's say that, the drop probability,
increased from one percent to four%.
Then it tells us that the, the ratio of
the rates would be 2x.
In other words, we would, by increasing
the probability, by a factor of four, we
would have the rate.
What this tells us is that, that AIMD is
quite sensitive to the drop probability.
So we want to make sure that our networks
don't encounter too high of  a drop
probability.
So what have we learned here?
We've learnt that TCP, which uses AIMD, is
going to be very sensitive to the drop
probability, very sensitive to the RTT.
Other observations that we can make about
the multiple flow cases,
As before, the window is going to contract
and expand according to the AIMD
equations.
And it's doing this just before as to
probe how many bytes it can place into the
pipe.
How many, how many bytes can the pipe hold
overall including the buffer?
The bottleneck is going to contain packets
belonging to many, many different flows,
Thousands, tens of thousands, or even
hundreds of thousands of different flows.
And ascending rate is going to vary with
window size,
Unlike before, when it tended to stay
constant.
Aimd is very sensitive to the loss rate.
We saw one over the square root of P.
And AMD, AIMD is going to penalize flows
that have long RTTs.
What this means is that the, it can take a
very long time to climb back up that
additive increase for long RTTs.
So it's very high, it takes them a long
time to regain their rate after they have
a drop.
So, we've now learned about the AIMD
process and, we're going to find out that
this is underlying.
It's one of the main mechanisms that
underlies the TCP congestion control
mechanisms.
There are quite a few other mechanisms
that we're going to be learning about over
the next few videos.
Aimd is one of them.
There's also the question of how we detect
drops quickly?
How we react to those drops?
How do we get into the AIMD process in the
first place?
And, we'll see that there are lots of
tricks in the TCP toolbox.
And there are many variations of TCP that
have evolved over the years to turn it
into an extremely effective mechanism.