The HyperText Transfer Protocol, or HTTP,
is a cornerstone of the
modern Internet. Originally intended to transfer
documents, it’s
now used for so much more, such as streaming
media from
companies like Netflix and applications through
scripts that your
browser downloads and runs. In this segment
I’ll explain the basic
conceptual model behind HTTP, something called
representational
state transfer, or REST. I’ll also explain
some of the early
challenges HTTP encountered in version 1.0,
released in 1995,
which were fixed in version 1.1, released
in 1997. HTTP has
remained mostly unchanged for fifteen years
since. In 2009,
Google proposed a new protocol, called SPDY,
spelled S P D Y,
which is the basis for a new HTTP/2.0 standard.
I
HTTP stands for HyperText Transfer Protocol
-- so what’s HyperText? HyperText is a document
format that lets you include formatting
and content information in a document. Whenever
you download a web page, you’re downloading
a hypertext document. Unlike
many other document formats, like Microsoft
Word or PDF, hypertext is all ASCII text.
If you look at a document, there generally
speaking aren’t any characters your regular
text editor can’t display.
So let’s take as an example this excerpt
from the Wikipedia page on HTTP’s history.
It has the word “History” is a larger
font, some
links, shown as blue, an embedded image, and
a few other nice bits of formatting, such
as the line under history, that make it easier
to read.
Under the covers, the document looks like
this: this is the hypertext my browser downloaded
to display this section. All of the
formatting information is inside angle brackets.
This less-than, H2, greater than, for example,
means this is a heading, so should be
displayed bigger. You can see the word “History”
outside any such formatting information -- the
word History on this snippet is
displayed as a header, as you can see. So
at a basic level, a hypertext document is
just a text document, which your browser
displays based on these special formatting
controls, called tags. A hypertext link, for
example, is just a formatting tag that says
“the
stuff inside this tag, if clicked, should
load this URL.” The tag that does this is
the A tag -- see this example here of an A
tag for the
HTTP V0.9 link on line 227. When you click
on that link, it takes you to this URL: http://www.w3.org/pub/”
etc.
But there’s one way in which a hypertext
document is more than just formatting. With
hypertext, you can embed
documents, or files, inside other files. The
simplest example of this on this wikipedia
page is the image. The bits
of the image aren’t stored in this hypertext
document. That wouldn’t be human readable
ASCII text. Instead,
there’s a way to, in a hypertext document,
say “load this other document and put it
here.” Take a look at line 220
-- you’ll see an image, or IMG tag. The
IMG tag says “load the image from this URL
and display it here.” When
your browser loads the hypertext for the wikipedia
page, it sees tags like this one and automatically
requests the
files they reference. So when you load the
page your browser automatically requests the
image and displays it.
There are all kinds of resources besides images
that a web page can reference: other pages,
style sheets,
scripts, fonts, and more. Let’s look at
an example: I’m going to request the web
page for the New York Times
and use my browser’s developer tools to
see all of the requests this results in. As
you can see, it requests
something on the order of 20 documents, ranging
from hypertext to images to ads.
This turns out to be a really important property
of hypertext: requesting one document can
lead to to request
more documents.
In HTTP, a client opens a TCP connection to
a server and sends commands to it. The most
common
command is GET, which requests a page. HTTP
was designed to be a document-centric way
for programs
to communicate. For example, if I type http://www.stanford.edu/
in my browser, the browser opens a
connection to the server www.stanford.edu
and sends a GET request for the root page
of the site. The
server receives the request, checks if it’s
valid and the user can access that page, and
sends a response.
The response has a numeric code associated
with it. For example, if the server sends
a 200 OK response
to a GET, this means that the request was
accepted and the rest of the response has
the document data. In
the example of the www.stanford.edu web page,
a 200 OK response would include the HyperText
that
describes the main Stanford page. There are
other kinds of requests, such as PUT, DELETE,
and INFO, as
well as other responses such as 400 Bad Request.
Like hypertext itself, HTTP is all in ASCII
text: it’s human readable. For example,
the beginning of a GET
request for the New York Times looks like
this: GET / HTTP/1.1. The beginning of a response
to a
successful request looks like this: HTTP/1.1
200 OK.
But the basic model is simple: client sends
a request by writing to the connection, the
server reads the
request, processes it, and writes a response
to the connection, which the client then reads.
The data the
client reads might cause it to then issue
more GET requests.
If some of these documents are on other servers,
then the web
browser opens connections to them and issues
GET requests. So let’s
say in this case the client requests a page
from server A. The
hypertext references an image which is on
server B. The client opens
a connection to server B and requests the
image. This happens pretty
often with ad networks. The New York Times
page, for example, has
some ads from Google embedded on it. So the
New York Times page
tells your browser to contact a Google server
to load a small document
with some ads on it. The Google server serves
hypertext for the ads. It
might also be that the New York Times serves
its images from a
different machine than its hypertext, so your
client opens a connection
to its image server and requests the banner
saying “New York Times.”
Here’s a sample URL for requesting a web
page. This URL has a lot of information in
it. The first part,
http:// tells a program what application level
protocol is being used. This tells the transport
layer what
TCP port to connect to. In the case of http://,
this means your program knows to use HTTP
and to
connect over TCP port 80. So this specifies
a transport layer identifier.
The second part, sing.stanford.edu, tells
your program what computer to contact. So
it’s a network
layer identifier. Combined together, http://sing.stanford.edu
tells your browser to open a TCP
connection to port 80 on the computer sing.stanford.edu.
Using something called DNS, which we’ll
cover later, your computer can translate sing.stanford.edu
into an IP address.
The third part, fullduplex/index.html, tells
your HTTP client what document to request.
While http: says
*which* application protocol to use, fullduplex/index.html
provides information for that application
protocol.
So together, these three parts tell my client
“request fullduplex/index.html from the
IP address for
sing.stanford.edu using HTTP by opening a
connection to TCP port 80.”
This is what an HTTP request looks like. The
first line, ASCII text, says the method, such
as GET, the
URL for the method, and the version of HTTP
being used. The white boxes represent spaces.
So
there’s a space between method and URL as
well as a space between URL and version. The
left arrow
means carriage return -- a way to say to go
to the beginning of the line, and the down
arrow means
newline, a way to say to go to a new line.
So, for example, in my prior example of requesting
this URL,
the method will be GET, the URL will be fullduplex/index.html,
and the version will be most likely HTTP/
1.1.
After this first line, the request itself,
there’s zero or more headers. There’s
one header per line. Each
header line starts with the header field name,
followed by the value.
After the headers, there’s an empty line.
Followed by the body of the message.
Wait -- why might a request have a body? What’s
the body of a request? In the case of the
GET
method, to request a page, the body is empty.
But HTTP supports other methods, such as POST,
which
sends data, for example when you fill out
a form and submit it. POST requests often
have a body.
So let’s see what this looks like. I’m
going to request http://sing.stanford.edu/
fullduplex/index.html. This is a web page
some of my now-graduated Ph.D.
students wrote to describe some neat research
they did in wireless networks.
I open up the developer tools in Firefox,
which lets me see the requests and
responses. You can see there’s a GET for
fullduplex/index.html, HTTP/1.1,
followed by a bunch of headers.
One header that’s important for this request
is “If-Modified-Since.” This is a
way for the client to tell the server to only
give it the document if it’s been
modified since that time. If the document
has been modified since that
timestamp, the server responds with a 200
OK with a new copy of the
document. Otherwise it responds with a 304
Not Modified. This header is
useful when your client caches pages, which
most web browsers do. Rather
than transfer the same document again, the
client can tell the server to
transfer it conditionally. If the server responds
with a 304, the client can just
use its cached copy.
An HTTP response looks similar. The first
line has the HTTP version, the status code,
and the
phrase associated with that status code. Such
as 200 OK or 404 Not Found. There’s then
zero or
more headers, a blank line, and the body of
the response.
Let’s see what the response to my GET request
looks like. It’s a 304 -- this web page
has not been
modified since my browser put it in its cache.
Now if I clear my browser cache, and request
the
page again, the request doesn’t have a Modified-Since
header and so the response is a 200 OK.
The developer tools on Firefox let you see
the request/response pair but not their actual
formats.
For that, I’ll do something much simpler.
I’ll use the telnet program to connect to
a web server.
Telnet opens a TCP connection: it writes what
you type to the socket and prints out what
it reads.
So I’ll telnet to sing.stanford.edu port
80 and type GET /fullduplex/index.html HTTP/1.0.
A lot of HTML comes back. If I scroll to the
top, I can see the HTTP response, 200 OK,
with a
bunch of headers, a newline, then the body,
the HTML of the page. The Content-Length header
tells me how long the body is.
HTTP is a cornerstone protocol of the modern
Internet. While it
was originally document-centric, designed
to fetch pages and
documents, today it’s used for much more.
A document, for
example, can be a script that your browser
executes as part of an
application. The basic model, however, of
requesting URLs and
receiving responses, still holds. One nice
thing about HTTP is that
it’s human readable text. You can type an
HTTP request and read
the response, as you saw me do by telnetting
to port 80. I
encourage you to play around a bit, use the
developer tools in
your browser to see what’s requested, and
learn more about the
details of the protocol.
So that’s the basics of the protocol. Request,
response. HTTP/1.0
was very simple. A client wanting to request
a document opens a
connection. It sends a GET request. The server
responds with a
status code, such as 200 OK, the document,
and closes the
connection once the response is complete.
If the client wants to
request a second document, it must open a
second connection.
When the web was mostly text, with maybe an
image or two, this
approach worked just fine. People hand-wrote
their web pages,
putting in all of the formatting.
So let's walk through how long this takes.
Let's make some simplifying assumptions. The
latency
between the client and server is 50 milliseconds.
An HTTP request is a full TCP segment. A
response is 2 full segments, so the size of
a small initial slow start congestion window.
That way we
don't have to worry about window sizes, etc.
The packetization delay of a full segment
is 10ms. So
the packetization delay of a request is 10
milliseconds and a reply is 20 milliseconds.
Let's finally
assume that TCP segments with no data, such
as the three-way handshake and ACK packets,
have
a packetization delay of zero. Finally, we
can have up to 4 open connections.
So let's walk through how long this takes.
Let's make some simplifying assumptions. The
web server
can respond immediately, there’s no processing
delay. The latency between the client and
server is
50 milliseconds. An HTTP request is a full
TCP segment. A response is 2 full segments,
so the size
of a small initial slow start congestion window.
That way we don't have to worry about window
sizes,
etc. The packetization delay of a full segment
is 10ms. So the total packetization delay
of a request
is 10 milliseconds and a reply is 20 milliseconds.
You can assume that the links are full duplex,
such
that a node can simultaneously receive and
transmit on the same link. This means the
packetization
delay of a request does not affect the packetization
delay of a response. Let's finally assume
that
TCP segments with no data, such as the three-way
handshake and ACK packets, have a
packetization delay of zero. Finally, we can
have up to 4 open connections.
Let’s consider a first case. We want to
load a single page. How long will this take?
First, there’s the latency of sending a
SYN, so 50ms. There’s the latency of the
SYN-ACK, so
another 50ms. On receiving the SYN/ACK, the
client can send the ACK of the three way handshake,
followed by the request. The request has a
packetization delay of 10ms, so this takes
60ms. The
server then needs to send the response back.
The packetization delay of the response is
20ms, so
this step is 70ms.
So the total delay is 50 milliseconds plus
50 milliseconds plus 60 milliseconds plus
70 milliseconds,
or 230 milliseconds.
Let’s look at a more complex example. There’s
a page that loads 5 images.
We can break this into two steps. In the first
step, the client requests the page. In the
second step, it
uses 2 connections to request the images.
The first step will take the same length as
our single page example. There’s 100 millisecond
for the
setup, then 130 milliseconds for the request
and response.
The second step is a bit trickier. Remember,
while we have separate TCP connections, they
are
sharing the same link. This means that the
packetization delay of one request affects
the other.
Setting up the two connections will take 100
milliseconds. But how long will it take for
the two
request/responses to complete?