So in this video I'm going to give you a
brief overview of the TCP header.
If you want more information, there's of
course tons of documentation online but
this is just a brief summary of what, the
fields and the header and their meaning.
Standard TCP header is twenty bytes long.
So you can see here that there are five
rows of four octets each.
Additionally, you can have options after
the TCP header, I'm not going to any of
those now.
The basic TCP header you're seeing most
connections is twenty bytes long.
So the first two fields in TCP are the
source port and destination port.
Each of these are sixteen bits or two
octets, so talk about connecting to the
web port, port 80, that's the destination
port say of 80.
The next two fields are the TCP sequence
numbers. So this denote from the source of
this packet to its destination. What is
the sequence number of the data contained
in this segment, as well as what is the
acknowledgment number from that endpoint?
So for example, I have, if I want to
acknowledge that I received up to byte
5000 and then, this is sequence number
4000, then as I said, I will send sequence
number 4000 acknowledgment number 5000 The
sequence number denotes what the sequence
number of the first byte of the data
region, which follows the segment header.
So, if I had a sequence number of 4000 and
there were 500 bytes of data, then this
would mean byte 4000 to 4499. Now, the
acknowledgment number acknowledges the
last byte received plus one.
And, so if I were to send the segment 4000
to 4499 and the other side received it, it
would have send an acknowledgment number
of 4,500 That is in TCP, the ACK is
not for the last byte received but that
plus one.
What is the next bytes that is needed?
So when we talk about TCP ACK packets,
what these are, is they're TCP segments
that have no data.
All they're doing is counting the
acknowledgment numbers for it.
This happens, if say traffic is
unidirectional.
Sending lots of data in one direction, but
there isn't data coming back.
If the flow is bidirectional, then these
acknowledgment numbers are just going to
be added or padded on to, not padded, but
incorporated into the data segments as
they're being sent.
So after the sequence number and
acknowledgment numbers, we have a bunch of
fields. Let's start with the checksum.
So the checksum is computed over the TCP
pseudo header, which is the TCP header, as
well as some of the IP header.
This way you add a little bit resilience
for the IP header with the IP addresses,
et cetera.
So the checksum covers the pseudo header,
the TCP header, and then the data within
the TCP segment.
And so, the checksum, actually in someway
stretches before the packet to the pseudo
header filled in from the IP header and
stretches to the end of the segment.
Simple ones compliment checksum.
The window field is the flow control
window.
It tells the endpoint, so the flow control
window or the window flow within a packet
is telling the other endpoint how much
receive buffer space its sender has.
So if you say, say a window of 20,000,
that means that there cannot be more than
20,000 outstanding on acknowledged bytes
in this connection, in that direction.
So, these bits here, U, A, P, R, S, and F
are control bits.
So, let's start with some of the less,
less common one.
So there's U which is the urgent bit.
That means that this data is particularly
urgent.
So hey, let's, let's get to the
application quickly.
Then there's P which is the push pit.
So, the push pit says hey, please push
this data to the receiving application.
So the other four bits,
There's the ACK bit, the reset bit, the
SYN bit, and the FIN bit.
So, the ACK bit here, this bit is set to
one, if the acknowledgment number field is
valid.
So, the ACK bit is generally set to one
for every single segment except for the
first one that initiates the connection.
Because, when you initiate a connection,
you don't know what the other side's sequence
number is,
You can't acknowledge anything, so the ACK
bit is not set.
So we talk about TCP set up, say the first
packet sent does not have the ACK bit set
but all other packets in the connection
towards termination have the ACK bit set.
The SYN and FIN bits are used to set up
and tear down connections accordingly or,
or respectively.
So the SYN bit says, hey, this is my
starting sequence number, please
syncronize to this number. And so when you
first open a connection you sent a packet
with the ACK bit not set but with the
SYN bits set and then the sequence number.
And you're telling the end point I would
like to synchronize you to this sequence
number which represents my first byte of
data.
The other side can then respond and say,
alright I'm going to acknowledge that
sequence number and send you one of mine.
In this case both of these fields are
valid.
To which then you can respond and say
okay, I'm going to acknowledge your
sequence number.
Now it's synchronizing.
Both know when the byte start.
So one of the things that you can imagine I
could always just start my sequence number
at zero for every connection for both
direction but it turn out to be real
security problems are doing that.
That means people can guess what your
sequence number is.
They could start interspersing packets.
Generally seems a bad idea.
Also because if you have lots of short
lived connections, these packets with
similar sequence numbers can be long lived
with the network and you want to be able
to filter them out.
So, the F is for FIN This is for tearing
down a connection so when you set the FIN
bit, you're telling the other side I have
no more data to send.
And so often they exchange as you send the
FIN, they acknowledge the FIN, they send
later UF with new more data send and you
acknowledge that FIN.
The final bit is R, the Reset bit, which
says we need to reset the connection.
Something wrong has gone on.
So, if the urgent bit is set, then this
urgent pointer points where in the segment
that Urgent data is.
Finally we have the offset field.
So, the offset field is needed because
it's possible for TCP to have options and
you don't know from this header
necessarily where the options are.
So, what the offset tells you is what
offset within the segment does data
begin.
So, if you have options then the offset
tells you the size of those options and
your TCP stack knows to look inside there
for options.
Are the options are patterned to be four
bytes or four octets wide.
So that's the basic TCP header where the
source and destination ports.
The sequence numbers, both for the data
and then for the acknowledgements of the
data that you've received.
The offset field to tell you where data
begins.
The urgent and push bits for urgent data
or data you want to push the application.
The acknowledgement bit indicating the
acknowledgement number is valid.
The SYN bit for synchronizing the sequence
number.
The FIN bit for tearing down a connection
saying that this, there's no more data to
send.
The reset bit for resetting a connection.
The window for flow control.
Checksum for making sure that there are no
errors in the data.
An urgent point for the urgent bit and
then options.