So, in this video about the physical
error, we're going to talk about bit
errors and coding.
A way to introduce some redundancy of the
data is that you can protect yourself
against bit errors.
So recall, that the Shannon limit, the
capacity of a communication channel is
determined by the bandwidth and then the
base two log of one + the signal to noise
ratio.
And so basically, what this means is that
in practice the available data rate
possible data rate is bounded by this
signal to noise ratio, so if your signal
is stronger you can send data faster, if
the noise in your circuits is lower, you
can send data faster.
So, the importance is that this is a
theoretical limit.
Just because we know we can't do better
doesn't mean we know how to get there.
In fact, few systems today can actually
get there.
We are getting close but it doesn't
actually say how do it just that
it's impossible to do better.
So often for a variety of reasons, your
bandwidth is typically fixed. Say, if,
you, are, are, operating in some
unlicensed spectrum, like you're WiFi or
something, the FCC says, hey you can't do
more than this, you can't use more than
this bandwidth.
And so often what systems are trying to
do, is, improve the signal to noise ratio.
But basically what it means, that if your
signal strength is higher, then you can
transmit data faster.
You can either transmit symbols shorter,
you can transmit them for shorter periods
of time, or you can put more bits per
symbol, you can make your actual
constellation denser, the IQ
constellation.
See here we are transmitting this perfect
black signal.
But the problem is that.
This perfect wave, because there's noise
on the receiver, just in the hardware, what
we receive, is closer to this red signal,
all this noise introduced, and so let's
take a step back and think what does that
means, how would that appear to a
receiver?
So let's go back, to this sixteen QAM
constellation I showed you when talking
about IQ modulation and signal modulation.
So this is the constellation used in HSPDA
3G data standard. As you recall we have
these sixteen points, with different INQ
values. Well so if there's no noise in the
system, then when a signal arrives it's
going to be exactly on one of these
points.
But in practice it's not, that there's
some noise that the systems introduced,
and so let's pretend for example that we
have some low noise receptions, such that the
signal strength is much higher than the
noise, then well rather than seeing this
exact point here, we'r going to see
something like this.
The noise is going to cause the signal to
jitter around a bit, but it's still pretty
clear, from the constellation, that it's
this symbol.
Similarly if we were trying to receive in
this symbol, while there is some noise,
But because the signal is much stronger
than the noise, these little jitters
aren't very big and it's clear that it's
this symbol.
But now what happens if we're in a higher
noise environment.?
What that means is rather than the signal,
the received signal of what we are going
to observe being like this,
It might be like this,
Where the noise causes the received signal
to have all kinds of different phases and
amplitudes than we expect,
Because of the noise in this system.
And fundamentally, this means that
there'll be some points in which we get.
You make the wrong conclusion about what
this symbol is.
So in these cases, for example, what we
thought we receive, what we were trying to
receive, 0000, our system might think it
was 0011 or 0001, or 1000, or 0100.
So this is how bits are sure
introduced.
It's when your constellation,
It's when the signal to noise ratio is
such that some of the symbols are,
Misrecorded or misunderstood.
And you can imagine if we had, had a sparser
constellation, like let's say we only had
two points, here and here.
Then this degree of noise would've been
fine, it wouldn't have caused us to jump
all the way from here over on to this
side.
But for this particular density of
constellation the noise was great enough
to introduce some bit errors.
And so it turns out that there's a really
deep theory on exactly how this works and
what's possible and what bit error rates
are and you can say given for a given
modulation scheme and a signal to noise
ratio you can just analytically compute
what your expected bit error rate is.
There's some mathematical assumptions that
are made but this is the bedrock
assumption the bedrock principles of rf
communication theory that served us so
well.
What's important here is the bit error
rate can become arbitrarily low, but it
never reaches zero The way noise behaves,
it's possible, although very rare, you
might have this huge spike in noise just
for a moment.
It happens to be, at that point, a whole
bunch of things happen at once.
And so the bit error rate never reaches
zero and, what this turns out in practice
is that.
In general, sending packets just as raw
bits, like say picking, your constilation,
such that you have the right number of
bits per symbol and then just directly
translating from bits in a packet into
bits in symbols turns out to rarely be
the, most efficient way to use the
channel, just because thers, this non zero
small probability to get bit error.
But the issues is of course that if you
want to make that probability very, very
low, low enough that it's unlikely that
any bit will be in error, well then, due
to the way this works, you're going to be
doing much better than you do in general,
by optimizing for this very rare case of
tiny spike, which might occur in any of
the bits you're say, you know, 12,000 bit
long or 1500 byte packet.
Many of the, the bits in terms that the,
the actual symbol intrem that constelation
are doing just absolutely great, but
you've, sort of, over protected for this
one outlier.
And so in practice, if you just directly
map your bits to the symbols, your system
is going to operate well, well, below the
capacity, well, well below the Shannon
limit.
And so, in practice what you do with the
physical layer is you take, say here are
bits,
So let's say we have a message that says
hello.
So, H, E, L, L, O, question, O, O comma,
which are these ASCII values, maps to
these bits.
Here are our packet, here's our packet
data.
Then do is transform this packet data
into.
Symbols, with some amount of redundancy,
so some amount of error correcting codes.
So the packet will actually get a little
longer, in terms of, the, number of, bits
we're sending at the physical layer.
So here say we have, 48 bits.
And we might send, in terms of symbols
say, 60 bits.
So there's twelve extra bits.
We arranged this into something called
coding so that if a couple of those bits
are wrong, we can recover from that and
still get the original 48 bits.
So even if there are a couple of,
Couple of jitters in here, we'll still
receive the packet and be able to recover
the data just fine.
And so this is coding, it's the idea of
adding a little bit of redundancy at the
physical layer, you can do it anywhere,
but it's almost always done in the
physical layer, so the coding is not a
physical layer specific idea but to
improve your link layer throughput.
By adding a bit of redundancy you can
protect from a few bit errors or so with your
expected rate of bit errors are and this will
, in aggregate, although you're making it a
bit longer will improve the throughput of
the system. This is true both in theory
and in practice.
So turns this off and use this coding
gain, which is the ratio of bits to link
layer to the bits of the physical layer.
So, if you hear somebody type, let's say,
one-half code, what that means is that if
I have a packet that's n bits long at the
link layer, I turn it into 2n bits at the
physical layer,
Or a three four code is each three bit. So
3n bits become 4n bits at the physical
layer.
So we have this redundancy you can
correct against some bit errors.
So here's an example of a very, this is a
very, very simple wireless physical layer
802.15.4 also called Zigs.
Also, it's used in ZigBee.
802.15.4 uses quadrature
phase-shift-keying and so, each one, each
actual transmitted symbol has two bits and
what 802.15.4 does is it combines two of
these QPSA, QPSK symbols into a 4-bit
symbol.
So it's what he calls these four bit
symbols.
There are sixteen of them to the fourth.
And each one then maps to 32 QPSK chips.
So, so here are symbols at the link layer
and here are symbols at the physical
layer.
And so we take say, four bits of the link
layer and turn it into 32 bits at the
physical layer which is sixteen QPSK
symbols.
And so, if I say I want to transmit a
packet that has 0001, then actually it's
transmits the physical layer is this
sequence of bits in terms of QPSK symbols.
So we can then figure out, what's the data
rate?
Or, what's the symbol rate?
What's going on with k-, with 802.15.4?
So, it turns out the bit rate at the link
layer is a h-, 250 kilobits per second.
The coding rate.
You have sixteen chips of two bits, that's
32 bits.
Is that the physical layer becomes four
bytes at the link layer.
So we have, what is a one-eighth code.
Four physical layer bits become one linked
layer bit.
Although they're in clusters of four and
32.
So based on this, if we are transmitting
250 kilobits per second at the link layer
and we have a one-eighth code, how many
symbols are we transmitting per second?
How quickly is 802.15.4 modulating the
signal?
Well, each of the symbols has two bits,
right, this is one-eighth code and so one
way to look at it is that the physical
layer, right, we're transmitting eight
that bits per second, so 8250.
250 kilobits per second which is equal to
two megabits per second.
At the physical layer, since each symboled
physical layer has, two bits, this means
that, 802.15.4 transmits one million
symbols per second, or in other ways, each
symbol is one microsecond.
Let's look at a, a more modern or, sorry,
a more advanced physical layers.
This is what 802.11n.
Very, a reasonably recent WiFi standard
uses.
So most, you know, WiFi stuff you buy
today is a 802.11n.
And so it turns out, there's all these
different schemes it can use but here's
just a subset of them.
And so you can see for these eight, use a
bunch of different modulations,
Bpsk, Binary Pahse of King, Quadrata Phase
Shift King, sixteen, sixteen QAM, 64 QAM.
Different coding gains, so one-half,
one-half three-fourths one-half 5/6ths.
And from that you can then figure out,
given the data rate.
Here's the actual data rate in megabits
per second.
Here are the different data rates of this
physical layer support.
So for example, if you're using MCX, index
seven is your sort of determination of the
standard of the, of what the coding system
is.
We can get up to a 150 megabits per
second, and that's if you're using a
64-QAM constellation with a five six
coding.
As you notice here that there's these
different channels?
Right, remember that the, the data that we
get, is also not only the signal to noise
ratio, but is also based on the channel.
And so here with twenty megahertz versus a
40 megahertz channel, you can see, with
the 40 megahertz channel we're a little
better than twice as fast.
The reason why we're a little better is
cause these time values are fixed.
And so.
These things are fixed, so we can do a
little bit better than half if there were
no time values you'd be directly, half,
Plus there's also some guards. But so you
can do generally double the channel,
you're just about doubling, the
throughput.
So an overview.
We want to talk about chips which are down
at the physical layer, the representation
signal of the physical layer, versus bits,
which is the representation at the link
layers.
The link layer has a whole bunch of bits
and then pass them down to the physical
layer, they're turned into chips.
Now physical layer has to deal with noise.
It's an actual physical medium, noise from
the hardware circuits, from the
environment, etc.
This can cause chip errors.
If you have a denser modulation.
Then you can have higher throughput,
because you represent more bits per
symbol.
But a denser modulation is less robust
to noise because of the distance between
the different symbols.
So a sparser modulation has fewer errors.
So big tensions what exactly is the
modulation used?
We saw an 802.11n, there's a bunch of
different modulations that are used.
Four different signal to noise ratios,
which give you different actual
throughputs.
So the.
How do you translate between these
link layer bits and physical layer bits?
It turns out just a one to one mapping is
rarely a good idea.
It might be the most efficient in terms of
just raw bits.
But, the problem is that the probability
of bit errors mean you want some
redundancy.
It's rarely going to let you get close to
the Shannon capacity.
So you talk about something called a
coding gain, which is the layer two to
layer one ratio.
And because layer one will represent each
bit at the, at the link layer, with more
than one bit at, its bit layer, you can
recover from some chip errors.
So we saw one example 802.11 n, where
you see anything from a one-half coding
gain to a five-sixths coding gain.
Under all kinds of different
constellations, ranging from BPSK, Binary
Phase Shift King, to 64 QAM, 64 Quatra
Amplitude Modulation.