When we read about computer networks in the
newspaper, it’s often because they have
been attacked or compromised. Almost every
week we read about hackers breaking in and
walking off with millions of credit card numbers
and other private data, perhaps following
a phishing attack or by exploiting some other
vulnerability to access a supposedly private
network. Or we read about a new worm that
Is designed to take over computers turning
them into botnets, such as the infamous Code
Red and Slammer worms of the early 2000s.
Botnets are armies of infected computers,
controlled by a master, that are commonly
used to send SPAM. While SPAM levels appear
to be dropping slightly, reports suggest that
between 75% and 95% of emails sent every day
are SPAM, adding up to hundreds of millions
of emails per day. Worms are also sent by
one government to attack another. For example
when the 2010 Stuxnet worm – which is widely
believed to have been created by the US and
Israel - to attack centrifuges used for processing
nuclear material in Iran.
In this video we’ll look at some of the
ways a network can be compromised by an attacker,
and I’ll explain the security characteristics
we want from a network.
Let’s start by exploring the different ways
a communication can be compromised.
The first and simplest method is for an attacker
to Eavesdrop on someone’s else’s private
communication . This means passively sniffing
and recording network data. Or it could mean
listening to the metadata, such as noting
that a connection has been made, without necessarily
recording the data in the connection. Connection
metadata was made infamous recently when the
NSA acknowledged recording information about
calls and connections made, without – suuposedly
- recording the contents.
There are many ways to tap a network. For
example, at the physical layer an attacker
might passively tap an electrical or optical
cable. Or – as you have seen before – we
can listen-in to WiFi because the packets
are broadcast for everyone to hear. A third
way is for an attacker to persuade a router
to duplicate and forward copies of packets.
In each case, the attacker can use standard
tools such as wireshark to decode the protocols
and understand the user’s data.
A second type of compromise is when an attacker
modifies, deletes or inserts data as it passes
through the network. In other words, they
are actively tampering with our data by Changing
the contents of the packets, redirecting packets
to a different, rogue server without us knowing,
or taking over control of our end host. This
might happen by persuading us to download
malware based on a phishing attack, or by
exploiting a vulnerability in our computer
or the way we communicate. For example, later,
we’ll see how it is possible to hijack an
ongoing TCP connection without either end
knowing.
Finally, an attacker might just want to prevent
us from communicating. This kind of attack
is usually called a denial of service attack.
Sometimes these attacks are performed by swamping
servers or entire networks by generating billions
of messages from different botnets spread
around the Internet. We’ll learn more about
Denial of Service attacks in a later video.
Let’s take a look at an example.
Imagine that Alice is making a purchase online
from an e-commerce site. She is using her
laptop, connected to her local WiFi access
point, then over the Internet to Amazon.com.
She browses the site and makes her credit-card
purchase using vanilla http. Unfortunately,
what she doesn’t know is the bad guy Attacker
is listening in to what she is doing.
There are a few ways the Attacker can eavesdrop.
For example, by simply listening or sniffing
the WiFi packets broadcast into the air. Anyone
with a laptop and the Wireshark tool can listen
to packets in the air and – if they are
not encrypted – decode their contents. Alternatively,
the attacker can eavesdrop on the physical
wire, by placing a passive detector to pick
up small electromagnetic signals that leak
from the cable. Or the attacker might insert
an electrical connection onto the wire. If
the attacker is eavesdropping on a long haul
link in the Internet backbone, they are more
likely to be tapping into an optical fiber.
This can be done by placing a device called
an optical coupler which diverts a small fraction
of the optical signal onto a second optical
fiber which can then be listened to and decoded.
An attacker without physical access might
manage to subvert the switches and routers
along the path, tricking one of them into
duplicating data and forwarding it to the
attacker’s computer. This can be done by
remotely subverting Ethernet, IP or DNS traffic.
We’ll see examples of all three later. Or
the attacker might manage to break into the
router console and take over the router completely.
In our example, if the attacker successfully
eavesdrops on the clear http communication,
he or she can learn Alice’s private data,
such as her credit card number and her home
address.
In a later video we’ll learn more about
https prevents this from happening in practice.
If the attacker is able to insert herself
into the middle of the communication, between
Alice and Amazon.com, then the Attacker can
terminate the http connection in the middle,
pretending to be Amazon to Alice, and pretending
to be Alice to Amazon. The Attacker could
simply pass through the data, recording it
without changing it. Or the Attacker could
alter the data, for example to modify the
shipping address, causing the purchased items
to be delivered to the Attacker instead of
Alice. So called Man in the Middle attacks
are very hard to detect, because both parties
can think they are talking to a legitimate
end host.
A third line of attack is to redirect the
traffic away from the server without Alice
realizing that she is not actually talking
to Amazon. If the Attacker is able to fool
a router to forward packets destined to Amazon.com
to the Attacker instead, then the Attacker
can respond and pretend to be Amazon. Or the
Attacker might fool Alice’s DNS server into
returning the Attacker’s IP adddress when
Alice is trying to lookup Amazon’s IP address.
In each case, Alice can be forced to browse
the Attacker’s website and be encouraged
to enter her credit card information.
Clearly Alice is not happy and would like
her communication to be more secure. In general,
when we say we want secure communications
over the Internet we are saying that we want:
Secrecy/confidentiality: We don’t want anyone
to listen-in to our communication. For this,
we use encryption and we will describe how
it works in one of the upcoming videos.
Integrity – We don’t want our messages
to be altered in transit. The most common
way to prove that a message has not been tampered
with is to attach what is called a message
authentication code, or MAC. MACs are based
on encryption as well, coupled with calculating
a hash over the transmitted message. WE’ll
study message authentication codes in an upcoming
video.
Authentication – We often want to confirm
the identity of the other party we are communicating
with. In our example, Alice wants to know
that she is really talking to Amazon – who
she trusts – before entering her credit
card details. In a later video we will study
digital signatures and certificates that help
us ensure that we are really communicating
with who we think we are.
Finally, we want: Uninterrupted communication
– We don’t want someone to prevent us
from communicating. You may have heard of
denial of service attacks where an attacker
floods a network or a set of servers to prevent
them from working properly. We will study
denial of service attacks shortly.
And so in the next few videos we will study
different types of attack
Eavesdropping.
Redirecting Ethernet, IP and DNS traffic.
Hijacking a running TCP connection.
Denial of service.