Another kind of IP address is  internet
protocol version six, or IPv6.
So recall the purpose of the IPv4 address
originally was to allow you to stitch
multiple different networks together so
provide this globally unique
identifier which would be usable across
many different networks.
But some of the problems that's emerged,
especially recently,
Is that the IPv4 address space has
only 32 bits.
That's only 2^32 IPv4 addresses
or approximately four billion.
This seemed tremendous at the time back
when the internet was 60 nodes.
But today its actually a limiting factor.
Generally for a variety of reasons on any
kind of numbering scheme like this, you
look at telephone numbers etc or.
Utilization never going to be 100%.
So in fact utilization of the IPv4 address
space is around 35%.
Only 35% of the IPv4 addresses are active
at anytime.
The challenge there is that if you don't
have an IPv4 address, then there's, you
know, there isn't way to communicate with
IPV4.
You need an IPv4 address to have
IPv4 communication.
The other side needs an address to send an
IP packet to.
And so realizing there is possibly this
shortness, this scarcity of IPV4 addresses
plus a couple a sort of crufty things
people saw in IPv4.
Work started on a new version of the
Internet protocol in 1994 called IPv6 or
Internet protocol version six.
The basic protocol for IPv6 was published
in 1998, RFC2460.
And then there was a lull for a good
while, but still we think in 1998, this is
just before.
One year before the
first dot com boom and bubble.
The Internet's taking off, but by no means
is the IPv4 address space close to
exhaustion.
So there's a lull of work,
But there was an increased interest, and
in, around the 2003, 2006 time frame.
People started to get a better handle as
to, what were the challenges in IPv4
networks.
What's important, what's not.
How should we use IPV6 addresses based on,
current work utilization and, and designs.
And so today, there's actually a hard push
within the IETF as well as, several
governments to adopt IPv6.
You can imagine, especially countries or
regions where growth of connectivity is
very large,
Say in China, there, the scarcity of IPv4
addresses, is perhaps a greater concern.
So, there's a big push today to get IPv6 deployed and in use in the
internet as a whole.
So what does an IPv6 address look like?
So, IPv6,
Rather than being limited to two to the
32, has a 128 bits of address.
So this is absolutely enormous.
2^128.
So approximately 3.4  10^38
addresses.
This means that you could have 21 IPv6
addresses per square inch of the world's
surface.
So, at least with the idea that an IPv6
address is going to name a device.
As long as we have fewer than 21, devices
per square inch, we'll be able to hold up
at least, on the Earth.
Of course, it might well be that these
addresses are used for more than that.
But, but still.
And generally speaking an IPv6 address is
separated into two parts.
There's the sub net prefect, the sub net
prefix which is same length n and the
interface ID within that subnet.
128 minus n bits long, so think of this
similarly to a CIDR or address, or a CIDR
class.
Where you have the net mask describing
what's the network identifier and then the
set of nodes within that.
Now, you don't really want to write 128
bit addresses as, sixteen, little octets.
Plus, often, they have big regions of
zeroes, and repetitions.
And so, IPv6 addresses are written
differently than IPv4.
Where IPv4 is written as a simple, series
of, period delimited, integer values.
IPv6 address are written in hexadecimal as
eight blocks of sixteen bits.
So here's sixteen bits.
This is two, hexadecimal.
There's two zeroes, 01.
And here's the second.
This is, there's a leadings here at zero.
It's just been highlighted 0470806D1:
:nine If you have a long run of zeroes,
you can omit a single one of those with
colon, colon.
So this is really saying is, here's our
first block, here's our second block.
Here's our third block, here's our fourth
block, this is our eighth block.
The fifth, sixth, and seventh are all
equal to zero.
Alright.
So if I were to write this address out
fully you'ld see 2001:470:
806D:1:0:0:0:9
And there's a prefix length here of 64,
saying that the subnet is 64.
The last 64 bits denote the actual address
of the node, which in this case is this.
You can also, if you want to use an IPv6
address in http, in a URL, in your web
browser, you can do it by putting it into
brackets.
So this says, to contact this node.
This IPv6 address port 80 in
the URL. And it's also possible if you
want to write the low 32 bits like IPv4,
that's an IPv4 address.
Just because that's one way to make IPv4
addresses addressable fromfrom IPv6.
If you have a leading 96.
Bits, didn't do anything, this is an IPv4
address, and you stick the IPv4 address at
the end.
So we have these enormous 128 bit
addresses,
Which allow us to add many more devices to
the Internet.
So, how do you assign them?
Currently say you look at IPv4 you have
IANA and ICANN and RIRs handing out slash
eights and the RIRs take the slash eights,
the blocks of sixteen million addresses
and distribute them to companies or
organizations or whatever is, is asked.
As it turns out that actually how you
assign IPv6 addresses has gone through a
couple of iterations as people have gained
better experience and refinement.
So for example, the first RFC on this, RFC
3177, said that generally want to give
people /48.
Sometimes you'll want to give them a slash
64.
Very, very rarely, give them a /128.
Alright?
So this would be that we have, 48bits
identifying the network.
80bits which they can use for the
interface ID.
Sometimes we've got 64 where then, 64
denotes the interface ID, and occasionally
we have just essentially the single
128-bit.
So you're giving just one address to
somebody.
RFC6177, after many years of experience said
this isn't a great idea.
So, you want to give out at least /64's,
which I mean, you don't want the 64 to be
any higher than that.
You do not want to be giving out 128, so
give out 64's, or maybe 60's even, you
know, or 56's as needed. The observation
is that 48 is a lot, much more than almost
anyone needs.
And there are lots of cases where people
need more than one 64, and so you can
allocate it.
And then kind of like how IPv4, when you
go to a regional internet registry.
And you ask them for a block of addresses.
They're going to ask you how many.
And they're going to make a decision as to
whether or not.
If you ask, say, for a /, Say you ask for
a /23.
They're going to decide whether you really
need, that number of addresses.
In this case 512 addresses.
And in the same way today RIR's can decide
on the allocation sizes used.
Do you get a 64, do you get a 60, do you
get a 56, etc. Great, we have this way of
distributing
IPv6 addresses.
So how do we actually get an IPv6 address?
So if you look at something like DHCP,
You know, you basically need to ask for an
IPv4 address,
And it's independent of anything else.
But the IPv6 address space is so much
larger.
It might be, you could do something a lot
simpler and just simplify the
configuration devices.
And exactly what it does.
So it turns out that if you have a /64
subnet.
That is, you know, your organization has a
/64.
So a 64-bit sub-net network identifier,
you can then automatically generate your
own IPv6 address, just from this subnet
identifier.
It turns out that Ethernet cards which is
basically what
almost everybody uses today, Ethernet
devices are a 48-bit.
They have a 48-bit unique identifier.
It's their layer 2 address that identifies the
actual device.
It's specified manufacturing, it's baked
into the card.
Often you can reprogram it but it's baked
And so the Ethernet address looks
something like this where there's a
manufacturer code.
It's saying oh, this was made, say by
Apple, or was made by Dell, or was made by
Oracle or made by HP, or Cisco.
So these codes are what an organization
gives out, and then when an organization,
you know,
Needs a code, you can then use the lower,
24 bits to basically produce sixteen
million devices with that code.
If it needs a new code, it gets a new code.
And the zero here is to denote just for
unicast MAC address, G is zero, and there's a
unicast packet address.
And so what you do is, you take this
Ethernet address, this 48-bit Ethernet
unique identifier, and you perform a
transformation.
You basically add some 1's in, in the
middle you flip the zero.
and you add
FFFE, so F-F-F-E into the middle.
And you're going to get a 64-bit,
identifier.
So now if I know my organization's 64-bit
subnet ID, let's just say it's X.
And I know my Ethernet address from my
hardware card, which is say Y.
I can then take Y put it through this
function and now my IPv6
addresses, just this first 64 bits then
these latter 64 bits.
And so this is specified in RFC 4291.
And so here's an example of how you have
what is a large address space.
And that, the size of the address space
being 128 bits actually gives you a great
deal of flexibility in terms of assigning
addresses.
So for example, one thing you could point
out is, every single ethernet device has
these same two bytes in it.
You're not, you're not going to reuse them
so in some ways that's flexible because
it's nice if we want to do something
besides Ethernet.
We know as long as we don't match these
bits then we can generate an IPv6 address
which will not collide with Ethernet
device.
But essentially just that tremendous
plentitude of addresses gives us a bunch
of flexibility and can simplify management
can simplify configuration.
So in that way IPv6 is really nice.