Encryption provides confidentiality. But we
also need integrity. Fo a system to be secure,
we need to know that a message was actually
generated by someone else and no-one has modified
it. For example, suppose we want a secure
file system protocol. Without integrity, an
adversary could append garbage data to writes,
or potentially create new write commands with
garbage data.
The basic point is that secrecy is not enough.
Encryption can prevent someone from reading
our messages, but it doesn’t protect them
from tampering.
The second property of secure systems, besides
confidentiality, is integrity. Integrity algorithms
let you know for sure that a message was generated
by someone with the key. So assuming the key
is secret, you can be assured it came from
a specific program, host, et cetera. This
is really useful. For example, with integrity
you can know that a routing vector actually
came from the node it’s supposedly from,
an an adversary isn’t trying to trick you
to route traffic through them. You can know
that the person who’s making a bid in an
auction actually made that bid. And you can
know, if you receive a message to terminate
a connection, or a bad message that might
cause you to terminate the connection, that
the message actually came from the other endpoint
and isn’t someone trying to shut down the
connection on you.
Generally speaking, integrity usually comes
first. There are lots of cases where you want
integrity but confidentiality isn’t that
important, but it’s rare that you want confidentiality
but not integrity.
Cryptographic hashes and message authentication
codes are two major integrity primitives.
Cryptographic hashes let you safely determine
that data hasn’t been modified. Anyone can
generate a cryptographic hash. They require
no key. It’s a hash function with some special
properties. Cryptographic hashes are useful
for storing data. You can be sure no-one has
tampered with the data. And since no key is
needed, anyone can check that the data hasn’t
been tampered with.
Message authentication codes, or MACs, are
a second way to verify that data hasn’t
been modified. They have all of the integrity
properties that cryptographic hashes do. But
they have the additional property that they
ensure that the person who generated the MAC
has a key. Only somone else with the same
key can check that the MAC is correct. So
message authentication codes are useful in
networks. If you send a message with a MAC
appended to it, the receiver, if they have
the corresponding key, can check that the
message they receive is the message you sent,
and that you sent it, since you had to have
the key to generate the MAC. In that way,
MACs also provide authentication, hence their
name.
A cryptographic hash is a hash function with
some special properties. Like an ordinary
hash function, a cryptographic hash produces
a fixed length output from an arbitrary length
input. For example, I can compute a 256 bit
hash from a gigabyte of data. They’re generally
really fast to compute, faster than the network.
Cryptographic hashes, like normal hash functions,
typically work by performing a single scan
over the data and performing some mathematical
operations based on each byte or word. That
way you don’t have to keep the entire data
in memory at once, you can just stream through
it.
Cryptographic hashes provide the property
that they are *collision resistant*. What
this means is that if I have some data x and
a hash H(x), then it is intractable to generate
a y such that hash of y is equal to hash of
x. Of course, there are many such collisions.
Let’s say that I have a 256 bit cryptographic
hash. There are 2 to the 256 different values.
Let’s say that I’m hashing 1 gigabyte
of data. Well, there are 2 to the 30 bits,
so 2 to the 2 to the 30 different blocks of
data, but only two the 256 different hashes.
While such collisions exist, they are very
difficult to find, such that people spend
years trying to do so and don’t. You can’t
just try two to the 128 different data blocks.
This is a very deep idea: make sure you understand
it. Given a hash value H, it is intractable
to generate a piece of data that has that
hash value. This seems very simple, but it
is amazingly powerful. Given a hash value
H, it is intractable to generate a piece of
data that has that hash value.
If you need to use a hash function, use SHA-256
or SHA-512. These are the SHA-2 (secure hash
algorithm 2) algorithm with either 256 or
512 bit hashes. SHA-1 is nearly broken today.
There’s also SHA-3, which the National Institute
of Standards and Technology selected in October
2012 to be an alternative hash to SHA-2 which
is just as strong but based on different mathematical
principles. That way, if there’s something
wrong with SHA-2 we’ll have an already vetted
algorithm to fall back on.
Now, SHA-2 was designed by the National Security
Agency, or NSA, and published in 2001. Given
all of the recent press on the NSA trying
to build back doors, you might think there’s
one in SHA-2. But chances are there aren’t.
It’s been around for over a decade, and
was vetted in a public process. Anyone who’s
anyone in cryptography and security has taken
a look, and it seems fine. Breaking SHA-2
would be the equivalent of developing Einstein’s
theory of relativity in physics. SHA-3 was
designed by a group of security researchers
and won a competition sponsored by NIST to
for the new SHA-3.
Cryptographic hashes have this nice property
that a small hash uniquely describes a large
piece of data. The basic approach is this.
Take your file, and compute its hash, store
this as h1. Later, compute the hash on the
file again. Let’s call this hash value h2.
If the new value doesn’t match the old one,
then something has changed in the file. If
the two are equal then you know the file hasn’t
been tampered with, because someone couldn’t
generate a few file, or change the existing
file, so that it has the same hash value.
So something you sometimes see when you download
software is someone publishes the hash of
the software along side with the program.
You can then check that what you’ve downloaded
is what they produced, and so nobody has inserted
malware into the distribution after it was
released.
One neat way you can use hashes is something
called a Merkle hash tree. So by themselves,
cryptograph hashes just tell you if the data
has been modified. If I have a huge file,
I can tell it’s been modified, but not where.
If you build a Merkle tree, you can tell what
part of the file has been modified. You hash
small blocks of the file, then create a tree
of hashes, like shown here. If the top-level
hash differs, then you know the files differ.
You can then walk down the trees and in a
logarithmic number of steps figure out what
part of the files differ. So if someone has
tampered with your file, you can see if it’s
because someone truncated it by accident or
inserted malicious ode.
Cryptographic hashes are very useful and tell
you nobody has modified the data, but they
don’t require a secret. Anyone can generate
a cryptographic hash. Message authentication
codes, though, want to provide authenticity
as well. You want to be sure that the program
that generated the MAC has a secret.
Building message authentication codes is easy
once we have cryptographic hashes. All we
need to do is incorporate the secret into
the hash. We can define a message authentication
code algorithm, HMAC, which takes a key K
and a message M. All it does is prepend the
key to the message and compute a hash over
that data. We can then send just the message
and the MAC. To check the message authentication
code, the receiver prepends the key, and computes
the MAC. They know only someone with the key
could produce the MAC.
So, it’s simple: we have a cryptographically
strong MAC!
WRONG!
Recall that hash functions work by iterating
over the data. For most hash functions, this
means you incorporate the new data into the
existing hash value. Put another way, the
hash value is the intermediate state of the
computation. This means that if I see message
M has a certain MAC, then I can append some
data to M, making M-prime, and compute the
MAC for M-prime.
So, as it always seems with security, the
simple approach doesn’t work and has vulnerabilities.
We need to do something smarter.
Luckily, that smarter approach is not much
more complex. Here’s the right way to compute
a message authentication code. Take your key
K, and XOR it with an inner pad, say 0x36
repeated 64 times. Take a hash of this inner
key K, prepended to the message. Then, compute
an outer key by XORing K with a different,
outer pad, say 0x5c repeated 64 times. Hash
this outer key and the result of the inner
hash.
So why doesn’t the previous attack work?
Well, let’s suppose your attacker appends
some information to M. They don’t know K.
The MAC, however, is made up of the hash of
M, not M itself. So appending data to M will
result in a completely different hash value.
The intermediate state of the computation,
leaked in the previous approach, is hidden
through the inner hash.
So this is how MACs are generally computed
today. You take a cryptographic hash of a
transformation of the key and the message,
then a cryptographic hash of a different transformation
of the key and that hash.
So one final problem. Let’s say you want
both confidentiality and integrity. Should
you encrypt the MAC, or MAC the encrypted
data?
The answer is the latter. MAC the encrypted
data. There are some cases where encrypting
the MAC is not always secure. So always MAC
encrypted data.