In the following video I'm going to demo how
an attacker can masquerade as a DHCP server,
forcing Alice's machine to be incorrectly
configured.
In the example, she's going to be forced to
use a rogue DNS server, taking her to the
wrong IP addresses for web servers she's trying
to access.
In our demo, three hosts are connected to
switch “s1”. Host H1 is Alice’s machine,
which is running a good DHCP client. Host
“dhcp” runs a good dhcp server. The DHCP
server configures Alice’s machine to use
the a Good DNS server. Host “evil” is
run by Eve the Attacker, and runs a rogue
DHCP server, a rogue DNS server and a rogue
web server.
Initially, we will assume the Eve has not
started her attack, and we’ll see a Mininet
demo of the Good DHCP server correctly configuring
Alice’s machine, so that she can access
the Internet just fine.
Then, we’ll see what happens if Eve’s
machine masquerades as the local DHCP server,
replying faster than the Good DHCP server.
Eve will configure Alice’s machine to use
the Rogue DNS server, directing Eve’s web
traffic to Eve’s web server as well.
Let’s see what happens….
The demonstration shows how simple a DHCP
attack is, if the Attacker has access to the
local network, and can install a rogue dhcp
client close to the victim.
The demo I’m going to show you runs in the
Mininet emulation system, which means you
can easily and safely run it yourself on your
own computer, and I’ll tell you shortly
how you can do that. It also means the same
code can easily be replicated into a real
network. The demo was created by Bob Lantz,
at the Open Networking Lab in Palo Alto.
H1 runs a dhcp client and is initially configured
correctly by a nearby host running a good
dhcp server for the local network. "evil"
is run by Eve the Attacker and runs a rogue
DHCP server. The host "dhcp" is connected
to s1 via a 500ms link, to delay its dhcp
responses to Alice. We need the delay to be
sure Alice will hear the evil DHCP responses
before the good ones.
H1 runs a DHCP client, and is initially configured
correctly by a nearby host running a good
DHCP server for the local network. Evil is
run by Eve the attacker, and runs a rogue
DHCP server. The DHCP server host is connected
to S1 via a 500ms link, to delay its DHCP
responses to Alice. We need the delay to be
sure Alice will hear the evil DHCP responses
before the good ones.
Alice uses host "h1" to browse the web using
her Firefox browser.
As we can see, she can successfully reach
the Stanford website. Her computer, h1, runs
a dhcp client to configure her IP address,
the address of her local router and her DNS
server. If we use the dig command to look
up another name like amazon.com, we can see
that the DNS server, in this case a public
DNS server run by Google at IP address 8.8.8.8
is responding to the query with Amazon’s
IP addresses, and the site loads as expected
in Firefox.
Eve the Attacker starts three processes on
the evil host: A rogue DHCP server, a rogue
DNS server and a web server. Eve is going
to force all Alice's web accesses to go to
Eve's web server instead. Every so often,
our dhcp client is required to renew the lease
on its IP address. In wireshark we can see
that when h1 issues a DHCP discover, the good
DHCP server at 10.0.0.50 responds with an
offer that contains the address of the legitimate
DNS server at 8.8.8.8, but (unfortunately)
Alice’s machine hears the offer from the
rogue DHCP server first and accepts it. She
is now in trouble. Alice’s machine now uses
Eve’s rogue DNS server, also at 10.0.0.66.
I should clarify that our demo requires a
subtle refinement. In practice, when a host
renews the lease of its IP address, it usually
sends a DHCP request message to the same DHCP
server as before. Not the DHCP discover message
it sends here. If it sends a DHCP request
to the same server as before, it would not
listed to Eve's reply. In our demo, we forced
Alice to send the DHCP discover message, so
she will see responses from both the good
DHCP server and Eve's rogue DHCP server. In
practice, Alice's machine will send the DHCP
discover message when joining a new network,
or when moving to a new wifi access point.
When Alice’s browser asks for the IP address
of google.com, the rogue DNS server tells
Alice’s machine to use Eve’s web server
instead.
When she revisits amazon.com, most of the
correct site appears since Firefox has cached
the DNS results, but as soon as Firefox does
a *new* DNS lookup, which we can force by
pressing shift-refresh, she is given the IP
address of Eve’s rogue web server instead.
If she visits a new site like yahoo.com, then
she will also end up at the rogue site. You
can imagine many bad things Eve could do.
She could simply deny or block access to particular
web sites for Alice. Or she could copy the
look and feel of those websites Alice visits,
and masquerade as an ecommerce site, forcing
Alice to reveal her credit card or other personal
information. Or she could simply sit as a
transparent proxy watching and recording all
Alice's traffic.
When we switch off the DNS server and evil
dhcp client, Alice will eventually go back
to using the correct, local dhcp server. The
first time she revisits the same web site,
her browser (in this case, Firefox) might
have cached the bad DNS lookup and still try
and go to the evil web server. But eventually,
Alice's host will start using the correct
DNS server and her network will start working
correctly again.
The video shows just how easy it is to attack
a network, if you have local access to the
network and can intercept and beat the DHCP
traffic flowing in the network, then you can
install a DNS server. You can then install
and redirect traffic to your own web server
or any other type of traffic. Very easy if
you have access to the local network. If you
want to run this demo for yourself, then you
can just download the script below, at the
URL on the screen, http://mininet.org/teaching
and then run it in a Mininet instance.