In the last video, I told you how we can
use the
additive-increase, multiplicative-decrease
method to modulate the size of the TCP
sliding window,
And therefore, control the number of bytes
that are outstanding in the network.
If we want to increase the, the number of
bytes that are outstanding, we might
contribute to more congestion.
If there is congestion and we want to
reduce it, then we might reduce the number
of outstanding bytes,
In other words, reduce the window size.
So using this window size modulation, we
can vary the number of outstanding bytes
and therefore affect or control the amount
of congestion in the network.
Notice this has been done by the end host
only, without any explicit support from
the network.
In order to understand how AIMD works and
then later how TCP congestion control
works,
We're going to start by looking in some
detail at how AIMD works with a single
flow.
If we can understand how it works with a
single flow, then we have a chance of
understanding how it works in a more
complicated network with many, many flows
through a router at the same time.
So, we saw before, AIMD works as follows.
Each time a packet is received okay, we
increase the window by one over W.
Therefore, once we've received the whole
window's worth of packets, the window size
will be increased by one.
Every time a packet is dropped, we're
going to decrease the window size
multiplicatively. We're going to reduce it
by a factor of two and this is the
dynamics that we saw before.
Now let's, look at an animation of the
AIMD process working in practice.
We're going to take a good look at this
animation of a single AIMD flow over a
single bottleneck link.
If we look on the, let me explain what's
going with the figure.
The congestion window size, W, is shown on
the graph down here varying as a function
of time.
So this is cwnd,
The congestion window, and this is the same
as the value here at the source.
So this is the source, this is the
destination, and this is the router in
between.
The router has a buffer and it's going to
buffer packets that are waiting to go onto
the egress link.
The egress link is this one here and this
is the bottleneck link between the source
and the destination.
This link here on the left is running
faster than the link on, on the right,
Which is why every now and again there is
a buildup of packets in this buffer
because they're arriving faster than they
are departing.
The reason that the packets look littler
on the left than they do on the right is
just supposed to represent the fact that
the link on the left is running faster
than the one on the right.
And although, it's at a higher data rate,
and so the packetization delay is, is
shorter and so the packets appear a little
bit shorter on the left.
So packets are going to flow from the
source to the destination, they're the blue
ones, and then for each packet, there is
an acknowledgement coming back to the
source, that's what the red ones are at
the top.
And you can see that the arrival of the
acknowledgements is clocking the, the
transmission of the next packet.
So we often say that an algorithm like
this is self-clocking and we'll see later
the TCP is self-clocking.
The packets are triggered by an
acknowledgement coming back.
Okay, now that I've explained this, I'm
going to restart it so that we can look at
some of the, some of the dynamics.
I'm actually going to give you our URL to
this same animation so you can play around
with this on, on your own time.
So starting again.
We can see that the, that the window size
here is telling us how many packets there
can be outstanding in the network.
And I like to think of it as, that there's
a kind of a bag that is representing the
network as a whole and, we're trying to
figure out how big that bag is.
How many packets can we put into that bag
before they overflow and drop
on the floor?
And I find this a useful way to think
about AIMD.
So, we're basically trying to figure out
where those packets can be and how many
there can be in the link.
And really there's only a couple of two or
three different places that they can be.
First of all, the packets can be on this
link here, on this fixed,
This fixed capacity pipe.
There are a certain number of packets that
we could fit onto that end of
that pipe.
There are a certain number that we could
put here and there are a certain number
that are represented by the
acknowledgements coming in the opposite
direction.
So all of those are fixed.
The only variable portion is how many that
we have currently got in the buffer, in
the middle.
So it's like a concertina.
There's this concertina, to start
with, that concertina is closed and we're
putting the packets into the network and
then as we, as we fill up the links after
the links are full, the only place they
can go is into the buffer, and the buffer
will absorb.
For every extra window, every extra time
that we open the window, we are
essentially putting an extra packet into
that packet buffer.
So initially, when the window is at its
minimum value,
All the links are full, but the buffer is
empty.
If we increase the window by size one, The
links are full, so it can't be placed into
the, into the link.
The only place that it can be placed is
into the buffer.
So the buffer will increase by one.
If we then increase the window by one
again, it'll go into the buffer.
Increase it by one again, it'll go into
the buffer.
Eventually, the buffer overflows.
We drop a packet, and then the AIMD
rules are that we drop the outstanding
window size by half. Eventually the buffer
will go empty again, and then we start
again.
So really, all we're doing by changing the
window size is modulating the occupancy of
the buffer at the bottleneck.
If we look here on the simulation, we can
see that, we can see that happening.
So, right now, the window size is nine, so
that we will see at any instant, there are
nine packets and acknowledgements
outstanding in the network.
But because the links are full, this
outgoing link here is full, our bottleneck
link is full,
The only place that those packets can go
once we increase the window size, is here.
So we filled it up.
Any additional ones are inside the buffer.
And every now and again you'll see that
we're received a full window's worth and
then we increase the, there we go, we will
increase the windows size by one.
It's currently at thirteen.
In a moment it will increase to fourteen.
And every time we increase the window size
the buffer will have one more packet in
it.
And down here, you can see that, every
time we, we receive a full window's worth,
It will actually go up by one and
therefore, that's how the window is going
to evolve over time.
So we're almost getting to the point where
the buffer is full.
We got to a point where, the, the window
is sixteen.
And.
At the moment, the rate at which packets
are coming in is exactly matching the rate
at which they're going out.
In a moment, we're going to actually put
one extra packet into the network and you
see it got dropped.
And the knowledge of that drop is
propagating through the network.
It will now go onto the outgoing link.
It will come back, actually through the
absence of an acknowledgement, but that
doesn't matter.
And so, therefore, the window size will be
halved,
So that's what's going on over here.
The buffer will have,
Will drain because we're only allowed to
have half as many outstanding packets in
the network,
Therefore we stop sending.
The, the buffer drained, because it drains
at the full rate and then we start the
whole process off again.
The first thing I want you to notice is
that the outgoing link is kept busy all
the time,
100% of the time, even though this window
process is concertinaing, it's going full
up and then full down, when we have a
drop, full up and then full down.
So even though this window is going
through this sawtooth motion, the egress,
the bottleneck link in the network is
staying busy all the time.
In other words, the rate at which packets
are being sent is staying constant and
this is a really important property of
AIMD, particularly with a single link.
It's not really adjusting the rate.
It's actually effecting the number of
packets that can be outstanding in, in the
network.
And this subtle distinction will become
very important in a moment when I tell you
a little more about the dynamics of, of
AIMD.
And then it'll help us understand what's
going on when there are multiple flows in
the network.
To increase our understanding of what's
going on, let's look at the dynamics of
that single flow.
This is from a simulation in a well known
network simulator called NS, of a single
TCP flow over a bottle neck link.
The graph at the top here is telling us
the evolution of the congestion window or
cwnd like we had before,
That's the red one. the green one is the
RTT, the round trip time.
This red line here is the utilization of
the bottle neck link.
In other words, how busy is that
bottleneck link kept.
And down here is the occupancy of the
buffer and we can see that evolving.
So it's very similar to the simulation
that we, that we just saw, the animation
that we, that we just saw.
So notice that the, the congestion window
is moving in this beautiful sawtooth, but
because every time we put one more packet
into the network, we increase the
occupancy of the buffer.
So every time we increase W, the only
place that an extra packet can go is in
the buffer.
So it's going to move in perfect lock step
with, with cwnd.
But because we are increasing the
occupancy of the buffer we are
increasing the delay the packets
experience as they go through the network.
So therefore, the RTT, the round trip
time, is also going and following the
same, exactly the same shape.
So, cwnd and the RTT actually follow the
same shape.
The consequence of this is, that the
sending rate for a single flow, which we
can define to be the number of, number of
bytes that we send in one window,
divided by the round trip time.
Because the round trip time is varying
with the window size, W over RTT is
actually going to be a constant.
This is actually going to be a constant.
Why is that?
The reason that it's constant is because W
and RTT are moving in lockstep.
They're essentially the same.
And we saw that in the animation.
The egress link was kept busy at all, all
times.
So, we're not really modulating the rate,
in fact we don't want to modulate the rate
when everything is constant and we've only
got a single flow.
We want to keep the outgoing link busy.
All that the window is doing is probing to
see how big the bag is, how many more
bytes we can put into the network without
it overflowing.
And it's constantly probing and changing
that, that window size, just in case the
conditions change and the, the capacity
increases, and therefore, there's more
room in the bag to put more packets.
Just to just to, to label the point a
little,
The window size is going to move like
this.
RTT will move like this in lock-step and
so this rate is a constant.
So, from this we can also make another
observation and that is how big should the
buffer be so that the whole system will
behave correctly.
So we saw last time that the buffer
occupancy was moving in lock-step with a
window size process.
This, this picture down here is
essentially the same as our animation.
A bottleneck link over here,
A link here with a faster rate, the router
buffer between A and B.
So if we would to, to, to look at that
again in, in a simulation,
And look at the, the behavior.
The graph on the, graphs on the left are
the same as the ones we saw before.
And in this case the buffer occupancy
equals RTT times C.
In other words, it's just enough to hold
enough packets that will fit
into the, the, the round trip when the
buffer is empty.
If we were to make the buffer a little bit
smaller, and that's what we're doing here,
So the buffer is smaller,
Then, what happens is, that the buffer,
after it's, after there's been a drop,
which is taking place here.
When the window size decreases and is
halved according to the AIMD rules, the
buffer will fall because we have fewer
outstanding bytes in the, in the network.
Therefore, the source will stop sending
packets, the buffer will drain, but it's
draining and empty for some period.
So if the router buffer is empty, it means
the egress link, our bottleneck link, our
precious resource, is actually not being
used, and so the utilization will drop
from a 100% during that time.
So if we want to prevent this from
happening and have a 100% at all times, we
need to make sure that this doesn't
happen.
Therefore, we need to make sure that the
buffer never goes empty and we need a
behavior like this, from which we need a
buffer of RTT times C.
Now why it's specifically RTT times C,
you'll see in a problem set a little bit
later.
But the basic intuition is, that the
buffer occupancy, the size of the buffer,
Must, from the peak to the trough, must be
the same as the distance from the peak to
the trough here, to be able to ride out
the time when the window size is halved,
and we have fewer outstanding packets
placed into the network.
And that distance there turns out to be
RTT times C and we'll see that later in a
problem set.
Let's summarize what we've learned for a
single flow.
The window is going to, to expand and
contract according to AIMD, the
additive-increase/multiplicative-decrease,
which is going to modulate the size of the
TCP sliding window in order to determine
how many outstanding bytes there can be in
the network.
Essentially, we're probing how many by,
bytes that the pipe can hold from end to
end.
And we're constantly be going to be
probing by changing the size of that
window.
We're going to carefully increase it, see
how much space there is.
If we find that we overfill it, we're
going to drop back down again, and then
we're going to keep trying to probe it to
see if there's more capacity that's
available.
So, we're going to tentatively, additively
increase and then if we find that we've
got into trouble, we're going to very
quickly in a very responsive way, drop
back down again to be able to reduce the
number of outstanding bytes in the network
as quickly as we can.
So the sawtooth, sawtooth is actually the
stable operating point of TCP.
There's nothing out of control just cause
it's oscillating.
It's exactly the behavior that we want
under a stable operating condition.
And, the sending rate is, in fact,
constant, so long as we have enough
buffers in the network, which is RTT times
C.
So these are all the observations for a
single flow.
In the next video, we're going to see how
things are a little bit different when we
have many flows in the network.