This video is a continuation of our first
video on how packet switches work.
In the first video we saw that there are
two basic operations to a packet switch.
First, packet addresses have to be looked
up into a forwarding table, and then the
packet has to be switched or
transferred to the correct output port so
that it can be sent on to the correct
outgoing link.
In the last video we saw how addresses are
looked up in tables for Ethernet switches
and internet routers.
And in this video I'm gonna explain how
packets are switched to the correct egress
port.
I'm gonna look at a number of different
techniques.
Output queuing, input queuing, and virtual
output queues.
And, and we'll see and get a sense for how
these packet switches are actually built.
I wanna start with the sort of the basic
vanilla switch, which is the one I showed
you before.
We have the address look up on the left
over here.
And then on the this is the forwarding
table where we look up the addresses.
And then we have the, the packet queuing
logic.
And then the buffer memory where the
packets are held during times of
congestion.
When packets arrive, here are three
packets arriving with different egress
Ports, indicated by the color of the
header of the packet.
So the red one at the top is going to the
red port over here, the one in the middle.
So when these packets traverse the back
plane we see that the blue one is able to
go to its output.
One of the red ones can be delivered
immediately, and the other one is held in
the output queue, waiting for its turn.
So as soon as the first two have left,
this one can then depart in FIFO order.
We often refer to a switch like this as an
output-queued switch, because the queues
are out the output.
And this has a certain ramification for
the, for the performance of the switch.
Let's take a look at that, When we have
packets arriving, it's possible in the
worst case that all the packets coming in
at the same time from the outside will be
wanting to go to the same output queue,
let's say this one here.
So if we have N ports each running at rate
R and there are, let's say there are N of
them.
Then in the worst case we could actually
have a writing rate of n times r into this
output queue.
Similarly and we always have a reading
rate from this queue of rate r.
So we, so we say in the output queue
switch that this memory run an aggregate a
total rate of up to n plus one times r.
The somewhat annoying thing, or
frustrating thing about this is that long
term, it can't possibly be the case that
we're writing into this quet rate N times
R, the system could not sustain that.
This only really works if some mechanism
is in play like congestion control to hold
the average rate of writing into this queue at
no more than one R.
So it feels as though the maximum rate
that we should is two times R.
That was what we would strive for.
Unfortunately your paying this penalty of
N.
And N could be a large number.
It could be hundreds or even thousands.
So this memory has to run much faster.
output queued, output queued switches are  said to be
limited by this problem.
That they have to have memories that run
very, very fast.
And it becomes quite a challenge when
building scalable output queued switches to find or, or
use memories, or create a memory
hierarchy, that will run fast enough.
One obvious way to solve this problem is
to move the queues from the output over to
the input.
Let's take a look at what happens when we
do this.
For obvious reasons we'll call this input
queued packet switch.
Now the queues where packets will be held
are at the input side of the switch.
The advantage of this will perhaps be
obvious in a moment, if we consider
packets arriving to the switch.
Same pattern as before; two reds, one
blue.
In this case what we would do is all of
the packets would come through the switch.
Only one of them needs to be held.
That's the one down here waiting for it's
turn to go across the switch.
And that's because it's output line is
busy and there's no cue at the output to
hold it.
So we hold it back at the input and then
later when its turn comes it can depart
just like it would for an output cue.
So it's shown on the face of it, the good
news is that things look like they work
the same.
And the better news is that the buffer
memory here is now only has to accept one
packet.
At the most one packet.
From the ingress, at a time, and has to
only send one packet into the switch in a
packet time.
It's speed is being reduced from n+1 times
R, just down to minimum in our goal,
which was two times R.
So, a factor of almost n, reduction.
So, this makes a huge difference.
And, for this reason people often say that
input queued switches are much more scalable,
indeed quite a few big switches are made
this way, but with the caveat, and there
is a problem that we are gonna discuss, we
are gonna have take a look at right now.
In an input queued switch the problems is
something called head of line blocking.
And this problem is something that you'll
see in many contexts.
I want to explain it here, so you'll
recognize it when you see it in other
environments.
Let me go through an example.
These are three inputs, representing the
inputs of the switch.
So these are the input buffers.
I've taken away everything else on the, on
the switch, just to make it a little bit
clearer.
And we're gonna see packets arrive to
these.
Here they are.
The red one's going to the red output.
Black ones to the black output, green ones
to the green output, and imagine that you
have the task of deciding which switch,
which packets to go and you look at the
packets at the head of line, of this, and
you see that they're red.
Problem is, that you can only send one of
them at a time.
And so in this particular instance we'd
only be able to send the red ones.
Even though there are green and black
packets in the system that could go to
these unused outputs.
Because we've arranged everything as a single cue we
get this head of line blocking affect.
Natural solution to this, which is pretty
widely used is something called Virtual
output queues, where each input maintains a
separate queue for each output.
So in this case, we have a three by three
switch, so this queue here is a FIFO queue of
packets waiting to go to output one, the
red output, for output two and for output
three.
So when packets arrive, here are the same
set of packets arriving as before, but now
they get pre-classified and placed into a
queue corresponding to the output they're
going to.
That's why we call them virtual output
queues, it's a queue of packets going to
all going to the same output.
The good news now is that because each
queue holds packets going to the same
output, no packet can be held up by a
packet ahead of it going to a different
output.
So it can't be held up because it's head
of line is blocked by someone who is
stuck.
So now, the we can look at this and say
aha!
We have visibility into all of the head of
line packets, and we can deliver all three
in one go, and therefore get a higher
instantaneous throughput.
It's an obvious solution, it can be a
little tricky to implement in practice,
but the nice thing is that it overcomes
this head of line blocking entirely.
So the good news overall is we've reduced
the
speed of the queues to two times R, speed of
the memories because remember, we can only
have one packet come in at a time and only
one packet depart at a time.
And, we are able to sustain the same
throughput performance as before.
Just to look at this on a graph, we often
see graphs that look like this.
This is a plot of the delay or the average
delay that a packet would experience as a
function of the load, this is basically
how busy the ingress lines are.
The best that any queuing system can
achieve is this line here and this
corresponds to a system in which, as the
load approaches 100 percent the delay
increases, well the average delay
increases and is asymptotic to a 100 percent
In fact, this is what we will see in a
output-queued switch.
An output-queued switch is perfect in the
sense that you can't achieve a higher
throughput, or you can't achieve a lower
average delay.
Let's take a look at the main properties
of output queued switches first we say they
are work conserving.
Work conserving means that an output line
is never idle when there is a packet in
the system waiting to go to it.
That means there is blocking internally
preventing a packet getting to that line,
whenever that line is idle there is no
packet in the system waiting for it.
As a consequence, throughput is maximized,
because you cannot have a higher
throughput than keeping all the lines
busy, whenever there's a packet available
for them.
And the expected delay is minimized cuz
we're always doing useful work delivering
packets onto the outgoing line.
Just to recap the performance that we
suffer from with head of the line
blocking.
This was our perfect output queued switch, on the
right.
This nice performance here with head of
line blocking it's a well known result
that the throughput can be reduced in other words
this asymptote when things fall apart gets
reduced to two minus the square root of
two or approximately 58%.
So we lose almost half of the performance
of the system as a consequence of this
head of line blocking.
The actual number will vary depending on
the particular
arrival pattern, but in general, it's
pretty bad news.
But if we use virtual output queues this
58 percent gets pushed back up again to
the full, full 100 percent of the system.
It doesn't entirely match the output
queue, switch the asymptote will still be
100 percent over, over here.
Actually with, virtual output queues the,
the delay will be slightly higher.
But the asymptote is 200%.
I'd like to say a few last words about
virtual output queues.
Virtual output queues are actually used
very widely.
And you may even have noticed them when
driving on the street.
So, in the US where we drive on the right
it's very common to have a left hand turn
lane like the one that's shown here.
This is to hold cars that are arriving and
that are blocked because of cars coming
the other way.
So, these ones are blocked, and can't turn
left until there's nothing coming the
other way.
However, cars in this lane here can keep
going straight on or can turn
right
They are not held up or blocked, because
of a packet ahead of it, going to an
output, that in this case over here, which
is temporarily unavailable.
So  in countries where you
drive on the, on the left hand side, then
the right hand turn lane is quite common
as well.
So next time you're driving and you see
one of these, just remember, this is
virtual output queuing.
So in summary, we've seen the packet
switches perform two basic operations.
They look up addresses in a forwarding
table.
We saw examples of that in the last video
for Ethernet switches and for internet
routers.
And they also, once they've decided where
a packet is going, they have to switch it.
They have to deliver it to the correct
egress port so it can go under the correct
output link.
The simplest and slowest switches use
output queuing because this maximizes the
throughput and minimizes the expected
delay of packets whereas more scalable
switches often use input queues with
virtual output queues to maximize the
throughput.
That's the end of this video.