Here’s a quiz. For this quiz, assume there
is no other
documentation of the TCP finite state machine,
so there’s no
supporting textual description which defines
other state
transitions.
In the first question, suppose the finite
state machine starts
in the closed state. Then a user program calls
listen on the
socket. The socket receives a SYN message,
but before any
other event arrives the user program calls
closed. What state
will the socket be in?
In the second question, suppose the finite
state machine
starts in the closed state. Then a user program
calls connect
and before any other event arrives the user
program calls
close. What state will the socket be in?