So in this video, I'm going to dig into
the details of AA211, or WiFi.
What it's packet formats look like, how it
used different, how it used different
media access control algorithms, and sort
of an overview of WiFi itself.
So recall when we were talking about
physical layers, and coding, and different
modulation schemes that something like
802.11n has a whole bunch of different
speeds it can operate at.
So here's just a limited set of very,
actually a reasonably small subset of the
ways in which an 802.11n link can work.
And so there's a thing NCS index, this is
actually a field in the packet, and it
tells you for the data portion of a
packet,
How that data portion is modulated and how
it's coded.
And so in practice, 802.11N is used in
everything from Binary Phase Shift Keying
up to 64 Quadrature Ought Amplitude
Modulation, with coding schemes from
one-half to 5/6ths.
And this means that the actual range of
data speeds that you see for an 802.11N
link, which is going to adapt based on the
observed signal to noise ratio is from,
and this is just a subset.
Actually, it goes faster as we'll see in
the future video on MIMO.
From 6.5 Mb/s to a 150 Mb/s.
And this is a factor of, you know, over
twenty difference between the speeds.
And so, WiFi 802.11n is able to, depending
on what the spectrum is like, depending on
what the timing is like, is able to adapt
across a huge range of speeds.
So it can adapt its length based on the
channel conditions.
Compare this to a wired system, where
because the signal-to-noise ratio is fixed
based on the medium.
You just have a fixed speed that you can
operate at, which is the fastest speed the
other side can do.
So you imagine this is kind of a
challenge.
Which is that WiFi depending on the
signal-to-noise ratio that it oberves the
channel conditions, wants to be able to
operate this huge range of bit rates.
And so how does this work?
This is not occurring at the physical and
link layer.
And so what happens is, this is what the
802.11b physical layer looks like.
So here, there's this physical layer
header which starts with some
synchronization bits.
This is what allows the other side to
detect oh, this is actually a Wi-Fi
signal, this isn't just junk.
So there's this series of synchronization
bits, followed by sixteen bits that denote
okay, it's no longer synchronization.
This is what's called the SFD, or Starter
Frame Delimiter.
So there's this particular sequence of
bits you expect.
Then there's the start of frame delimiter,
denoting that the synchronization is
over.'Cause it might be, you started, say,
in the middle of the synchronization, you
don't know when it's going to end.
And then after that, there's a series of
48 bits denoting the signal, the service,
the length, and the CRC of this physical
layer chunk.
All of this is being scrambled by the
physical layer using forward error
correction, coding, interleaving, all
those kinds of techniques that'll be
robust to bit errors.
Now, of course, you need to get this in
its entirety before you can start, let's
say, pulling the link from, apart, because
you just need to say, know what the length
is.
So that's the physical layer.
Then in the link frame, we have a whole
bunch of fields.
There's the frame control field, this
gives you sort of control information
about the frame, what it's like.
There's duration, this tells you how long
this packet or things about it are going
to take.
This is really important if say, the data
rate is higher than you can demodulate,
like you don't have a high enough signal
to noise ratio.
So this duration is sent, you know how
long this packet or this exchange is going
to be.
It's a way to tell the nodes, hey, this is
how long it's going to take.
There can be up to four addresses embedded
in the header.
Often you just have a two addressing mode.
Oh, there's the source and there's the
destination but there's other things you
can do.
Say you want to bridge across networks
etcetera.
There's a sequence number then, there's
the network data, what's coming in from
network layer, and then finally, a frame
check sequence.
So think of this like a CRC, it's a 4-byte
frame check sequence.
So let's look at these first two fields,
the frame control and duration.
Now what these are used for, as I was
saying, is the duration field tells
listeners other nodes that can hear the
packet and also the recipient how long
this packet or packet exchange is going to
take.
And that way, even if they can't
understand those packets'cuz they're too
fast, they know how long it's going to
take, and they can use this for something
called virtual carrier sense.
The idea here is a call that, in the
CSMACA algorithm, a node will count down
while the channel is busy.
Now it could detect the channel is busy
directly by listening.
Or it could detect the channel is busy
virtually by being told that it is.
So this duration field, for example, is
what a CTS packet uses to tell nodes
around it.
Hey, clear to send.
I you know, you're channel was busy for
this long because I'm going to be
receiving something, and so you shouldn't
transmit.
So another thing the 802 eleven header can
do is essentially virtualize a link.
So think, we have these three addresses.
So I'm not going to go to the fourth one,
let's just consider these three.
So this is the case where, if I want to
have an AP.
Act more like a switch, say, than an
independent link layered device to which a
packet is destined.
So in this case, I can tell, hey, I'd like
to send, this is, you know I'd like to
send a packet from outer one.
Two adder two, via adder three.
This a way of telling the AP, a-ha, I
would like to send a package to this other
link letter address through you.
So you can sort of virtualize that link of
the access point.
And so give the nodes that are connected
wirelessly, virtual access to the wired
network sitting behind the AP.
So one of the things we saw in RTS/CTS
is that depending on the speed that
you use RTS/CTS, these control packets
could have a significant overhead, up to
25% at eleven megabits for 802.11b.
And this all comes down to the fact that
because 802.11 has this huge range of
bit rates, but it needs to be backwards
compatible, this means that, say these,
this physical region, the physical frame
header.
Needs to be comprehensible why everyone
listening, so I can't, if I'm a
transmitter, I can't transmit the physical
header at my full speed.
So if I'm operating at 1Mb/s or 600Mb/s,
I still need to transmit this
header at the same speed so that everyone
can understand it.
Same with things like the duration field.
And so the way to think about this is
that:
Because the slowest link is say, 1 Mb/s,
I need to transmit
this that everyone operating perhaps even
at 1Mb/s can understand it.
Then the data region may, maybe will save
you 600 Mb/s, so tiny,
tiny, tiny.
But, this original, this initial control
sequence is still going to remain the same
length.
So in practice what this means is that, as
Wi-Fi speeds get faster and faster and
faster,
Right?
So you can imagine, if I have a slow
speed, then the data, this is at 1Mb/s
so this is slow.
Here's control.
Here's data.
The control is small compared to the data.
But as I make the data region faster and
faster, there's data, which is faster
control or faster.
.
It can be, in fact, that the control,
here's data, here's control.
Can be the dominant duration of the
packet.
These bits are sent so slowly compared to
the data region, the network layer, that
all my airtime is consumed by these
control headers.
And some people at Microsoft Research have
done some analysis of this and have shown
that, look when you're operating up to 600Mb/s
at some of the fastest
802.11 speed, 802.11n we can do today.
This control sequence is 92% of your
airtime.
That is, you're only spending
eight percent of your time actually
sending data.
So you can imagine, even if you double
your data rate, you're not going to
actually double your throughput because
you're going to go from consuming
eight percent of the time to four percent
of the time.
It's still then 96% of your autonomy
consumed with control traffic.
And so, there's this diminishing return.
So, 802.11 is the basic MAC format.
It's designed to work on top of many
physical layers, many modulations, many
speeds.
But part of that is that it needs to have
backwards compatibility.
So rather than say, talk about the number
of bytes that this packet is going to
last, you talk about how long this
packet's going to last in time.
So that even if you don't know what the
modulation scheme is, because it's some
future version of wi-fi that your device
doesn't talk, it knows how long the packet
will be.
Mac control things like the control
descent packet.
Are done in terms of durations.
There's this duration field where it can
say, hey.
The channel run mean needs to be clear for
this number of microseconds.
It also allows you to virtualize a link,
right, by embedding additional addresses.
That you can actually bridge between the
wired and the wireless Ethernet.
And so, while you read all those about
faster and faster WiFi in a 600Mb/s,
in practice, it's not actually
getting that fast.
And, the reason being that, these
controlled headers that are needed for
backward compatibility and for
interoperability just end up consuming all
of your air time.
As, the actual observed data throughput on
a 600 Mb/s Wi-Fi link is
far, far, far below 600 Mb/s,
probably closer to at most 50 Mb/s.