In this segment, I’m going to cover one
very important optimization
that occurred in HTTP/1.1, something called
the Keep Alive
header.
HTTP is a basic request, response protocol.
HTTP/1.0 was
very simple. A client wanting to request a
document opens a
connection. It sends a GET request. The server
responds
with a status code, such as 200 OK, the document,
and
closes the connection once the response is
complete. If the
client wants to request a second document,
it must open a
second connection.
When the web was mostly text, with maybe an
image or two,
this approach worked just fine. People hand-wrote
their web
pages, putting in all of the formatting.
So the approach that HTTP/1.0 uses can be
really wasteful.
Clients spend a lot of time opening connections.
Furthermore, the TCP congestion control window
doesn’t
get a chance to grow, since each connection
has a new
window.
HTTP solved this problem by adding a few headers
to
requests and responses. A request can include
a Connection
header, which tells the server whether it
would like the
connection to be kept open after the response
or closed.
The server can do whatever it wants, but the
client can give
a hint. For example, if you’re requesting
a basic text file,
there’s no reason to keep the connection
open, as the text
file won’t reference other things to load.
A response includes a Connection header, which
tells the
client what the server decided to do. If it
decided to keep-
alive the connection, then the keep-alive
header tells the
client for how long. Now, the client can send
further
requests on the same connection. It can also
open more
connections, if it wants, but it doesn’t
have to.
So how big a deal is this? Let’s consider
a more realistic case than before, where the
packetization delay is only 1 millisecond
and the page loads 11 images. Browsers today
usually
have more than 2 open connections, but they
also load more than 11 images, we’ll just
keep
these numbers small for simplicity. We’re
going to use the same analysis we used when
looking
at HTTP/1.0 in the HTTP/1.0 video.
The slow start window is big enough so we
will never hit congestion control.
For HTTP/1.0, this will take 1,421 milliseconds.
There are seven rounds. In the first round,
we
request a page. This takes 203 milliseconds.
In the next 6 rounds, we request 2 images
each. Except for the last round, where we
only download one image.
Each round takes 203 milliseconds. So the
total time is 203 milliseconds plus 1218 milliseconds,
for 1.421 seconds.
For HTTP/1.1, this will take 326 milliseconds!
We setup the connection, that takes 100
milliseconds. Requesting the page takes another
103 milliseconds. Requesting the 11 images,
however, only takes 123 milliseconds! That’s
51 milliseconds for the first request, and
milliseconds for the 11 responses, 50 milliseconds
of latency plus 22 milliseconds of
packetization delay. It’s over four times
faster, because we can send these requests
back-to-
back in a single connection and don’t have
to open new connections.
HTTP/1.1 has been around for a while, since
1997 or so. Very recently, Google has developed
a new protocol, called SPDY,
that improves on HTTP. It does things like
allow request pipelining. One issue HTTP sometimes
runs into is that the order in
which a client requests resources is the same
that the server responds. This can be a problem
if some resources require a lot
of processing. Say you have a dynamically
generated web page through something like
Ruby on Rails or Django. Your
database is overloaded, so it takes a while
to generate the page. But most of the resources
are just images that can be send
quickly. If the client requested the slow
page first, it won’t receive any of the
images until after it receives the page. It
would
be nice if the server could respond in a different
order, and say start sending the images while
the page is being generated.
SPDY also removes redundant headers. Open
up Wireshark and look at some HTTP requests
and responses. Very often,
there’s a lot of redundant information in
each response and request. If you could just
set some parameters (such as browser
type) for the duration of the session, rather
than send it each time, that would speed things
up.
SPDY has been in use for a while, and it’s
becoming the basis of HTTP/2.0. In a few years,
I suspect most sites will be using
HTTP/2.0 because of the speed benefits it
will bring, especially for mobile devices.