In this video you are going to learn about
the second transport layer UDP, the User Datagram
Protocol. UDP is used by applications that
don’t need the guaranteed delivery service
of TCP, either because the application handles
retransmissions in its own private way, or
because the application just doesn’t need
reliable delivery. UDP is much much simpler
than TCP, which is why this video is much
shorter. All UDP does is take application
data and create a UDP datagram, then hands
it to the network layer. The UDP datagram
identifies the application that the data should
be sent to at the other end. That’s about
it.
As we have come to expect, the UDP datagram
is encapsulated inside the data field of the
IP datagram.
UDP provides a very simple service, as should
be clear from the small number of fields in
the UDP header.
Unlike TCP that has over ten header fields,
UDP has just four.
1. The source port indicates which application
the data comes from. If the far end replies,
it will send a datagram with this port number
as the destination so it can find its way
back to the correct application.
2. The destination port indicates which application
the data should be delivered to at the other
end host. The port numbers in UDP serve the
same purpose as in TCP - they direct incoming
packets to the correct application process.
3. The 16-bit Length field specifies the length
of the whole UDP datagram – header plus
data – in bytes. The value must be at least
8 bytes, because that is the length of the
UDP header.
4. The UDP checksum is optional when using
IPv4. If the sender doesn’t include a checksum,
the field is filled with all zeroes. If a
UDP checksum is used, then it is calculated
over the UDP header and data.
In fact, the UDP checksum calculation also
includes a portion of the IPv4 header as well,
as shown here. The calculation includes the
IP source and destination addresses and the
protocol ID which has the value of 17 and
tells us that the IP datagram carries UDP
data. You might be wondering why the UDP checksum
includes part of the IP header – doesn’t
that violate the clean separation of layers?
Yes, it does. The rationale for violating
the layering principle and using information
from the layer below is that it allows the
UDP layer to detect datagrams that were delivered
to the wrong destination.
In summary, the UDP header is small, because
the service it offers the application is very
simple. It provides a simple message protocol
for sending data from an application on one
host that may or may not be delivered to an
application on a remote host.
Port numbers in UDP work the same way as in
TCP.
If process 1 on Host A has data to send to
process 1 on Host B that uses port 177, the
data is placed into a new UDP datagram with
destination port 177. Host A adds its own
source port number so any replies can be sent
to Process 1 on Host A.
The datagram is encapsulated in an IP datagram
and sent to Host B.
Host B removes the UDP datagram and directs
the data to Process 1.
It is useful to think of UDP as merely a Demultiplexing
mechanism to divide up the stream of UDP datagrams
and send them to the correct process. In fact,
some people call it the User Demultiplexing
Protcol for this reason --- it is essentially
all UDP does.
To sum up UDP’s Service Model, we say that
it has the following three properties shown
in the table.
First, it provides a connectionless datagram
service. No connection is established, because
none is needed – all of the information
is self-contained in the datagram. It means
packets may show up in an any order, so if
the application cares about in order delivery,
it will need to resequence the data itself.
UDP is an unreliable delivery service. It
doesn’t send any acknowledgments to let
us know data reached the other end. It has
no mechanism to detect missing datagrams.
If an entire datagram is dropped along the
way, UDP will not inform the application,
and it will not ask the source to resend the
datagram. However, the application might choose
to ask for the data again by itself, essentially
building a retransmission mechanism on top
of UDP. Early versions of NFS, the network
file system did exactly this. They decided
they didn’t want to use the sliding window
used by TCP, so they created their own inside
the application.
UDP should sound very much like the service
provided by the IP layer. That’s because
UDP is offering little more than a simple
wrapper on top of the IP layer, with the means
to direct the arriving data to the correct
application at the other end.
So why do we have UDP? It is used by applications
that don’t need reliable delivery, such
as simple request-response applications. DNS
– the domain name system used by the Internet
to turn a hostname into an IP address uses
UDP because the request is fully contained
in one UDP datagram. You’ll learn how DNS
works later, but for now you just need to
know that if we send a DNS request containing
a hostname, the DNS server will respond with
an IP address we can use to send IP datagrams
to the host. If the request is successful,
then using UDP is lightweight and fast – there
is no need to setup a connection before making
the query. If the request is unsuccessful,
it simply times out and is resent. This makes
DNS simple and fast most of the time. The
DHCP or Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
also uses UDP. DHCP helps a new host find
out its IP address when it joins a network.
Your laptop probably uses DHCP when it connects
to WiFi. We’ll learn more about DHCP later,
but it’s enough to know here that DHCP is
also a request-response application making
a single, self-contained request in one UDP
datagram. The Network Time Protocol or NTP
also uses UDP for the same reason.
Some applications use UDP because they have
their own special needs for retransmission,
congestion control, in-sequence delivery.
A few real-time streaming audio and video
services use UDP. This is much less common
that it used to be, because most video and
audio streams of http today, which uses TCP
instead of UDP.
In summary, UDP provides a simpler, datagram
delivery service between application processes.