So, this video is about how to read an
RFC, or Request for Comments.
The standard document in the IETF of the
Internet.
So, reading RFCs is critical.
If you want to get a deeper understanding
of how the Internet works, how its
protocols are specified. But, there are
documents that's evolved over several
decade to have certain instructions and
approaches,
And this video is going to explain what
that looks like and why.
There's actually an RFC, or Request for
Comments 2555 which describes the history
of RFC survey.
Historical retrospective of the first one.
First RFC, RFC one was entitled, Host
Software.
And, this quote from RFC one talks about
where that name came from.
The idea that these documents aren't
statements of control, or assertion of
control would rather part of a dialogue.
And while RFCs today are a bit more formal
that this first one, some thoughts on how
to structure host software, that still
remains. There's nobody who enforces RFCs,
rather there are statements of a group of
people about what you need to do to
inter-operate.
You can always do the right things that
don't follow RFCs, but if you want to
inter-operate, this is what you do need to
do.
So, over time, RFCs came to have, have
come to have a standardized format.
So there's the structure of the document,
well, concerns of intellectual property,
and also specific terms that RFC has used.
Often you see them in, in capital words
that have very, capital letters have very
specific meaning, are all defined in RFC
2119.
Modern RFCs for example, always have, or
are required to have two sections.
security considerations, and
considerations for IANA.
So, security has obvious reasons.
Iana is if this RFC, it needs new value
registries, say, protocol fields, whether
it allocates fields in, in other
protocols.
Now, one thing that often a first time
reader doesn't quite realize, and it can
be a bit confusing, is that there are
actually multiple types of RFCs.
And they actually have different meanings
in very different implications towards the
standards process of the Internet.
So, for example, there are proposed
standards, standards track, informational,
experimental, and best current practice.
And the way to think of those serves as a
spectrum of whether or not this is an idea
a couple of people have proposed, say,
experimental. Or whether or not it's a
specification or it's simply some valuable
information that's, an informational RFC
can be not a protocol but rather some
valuable information for the community.
Then, you have proposed standards.
So, here's something which a group of
people believe should become a common
standard of the, of the Internet, and then
standards track.
And the transition between proposed
standards and standards track or standards
track is further along the process towards
becoming a really stable standard of the
Internet, has to do with how many
implementations there are, whether they
can inter-operate, and there's some formal
process for making that transition.
There are also RFCs that are best current
practice which state, based on the current
knowledge today, these are the things that
you really want to do, best practice, best
practices.
So, for example, there are best current
practices about how to implement TCP and
its congestion control algorithms.
So,
That's what an RFC looks like.
This is the basic process that an RFC
takes, or document takes to run RFC.
This is a bit simplified and this is
actually my personal experience when
working on the RFC for this algorithm or
they came out of my research trickle.
So, generally, what happens is that the
document starts as a draft.
And so, when you see documents in the ITF
named draft, they are not RFCs, they are
not formal documents.
Instead, there are works in progress and
correspondingly, they actually time out
so people don't update the draft.
Eventually, it disappears off the IETF
servers.
And so, you start with a draft, I mean,
you know, it said draft-levis.
This means that this is a personal draft,
it's a private, it's a personal submission
that somebody, just a person or maybe a
few people, are suggesting this document
is might be of interest to the Internet.
And then, there's some information, in
this case, Levis, that's me.
Roll was the IETF working group, that was
the draft is being proposed for, the
routing over on low power and lossy
links, and then the descriptive name,
trickle, the trickle algorithm, and then a
number.
So, this is version zero of this
draft, so the first version of it.
Then, you can submit that to a working
group for some consideration, discussion.
Maybe it iterates a couple of times, you
make some improvements, some
modifications, and the numbers increment,
so trickle-00, trickle-01, trickle-02.
Then, at some point, the chair of the working
group can say, or ask the working group,
Do we think that this is something which
should become a working group work item?
That is this, is this a document or an
idea or a protocol which the working group
thinks is part of it's charter and should
make more formal.
When it becomes a working group document,
then the name changes from draft to
someone's name, draft-levis to draft-ietf,
to show that this is now a document under
the full auspices of a working group.
And you can see then it's still the roll
working group.
At this point, the version number resets
to zero,
Zero. Then, it goes through revisions, you
present it at working group meetings.
You get feedback, comments on the mailing
lists, questions, concerns.
The document iterates over versions, 01,
02, 03.
At some point, the working group chair,
one of the working group chairs, they
decide that the document is ready for
publication.
And so, the working group chair can say
say, look, I feel that this document has
gone through a lot of revision.
We agree, it seems like it's a good
position.
It's something that's part of the working
group's work.
We want to make this an RFC.
At that point, there's a last call issued.
First, the working group, and then to the
IETF.
So, the working group has given a chance,
a trade to respond any final comments to
improve the document, after which, then,
it's given a last call to the entire IETF.
Anyone can comment on it, and suggest
things to improve it.
After it's passed to those last calls,
that is, all of the issues which people
have seen have been addressed to the
satisfaction of the working group chair,
It goes to the IESG, the steering group,
the Internet Enduring Steering Group which
has representatives from all of the major
areas of the Internet.
And so, you have both tremendous depth.
People, or say, experts in transport,
experts in real time application
infrastructure. But then, because it's all
of the experts, there is also a tremendous
breadth.
Everything from the network, to
operations, to, to transport.
It's the IESG reviews it,
Gets feedback, it gives comment.
Sometimes they refuse to publish it as an
RFC.
They say that this is not, this has
subsequent issues that we see you need to
completely rework it. But, if things go
well, they actually gives you comments,
they address these comments and then, they
document it approved, approved as an RFC
or Request for Comments.
So, as described in RFC 2119, there are
certain terms which are used in RFCs which
have a very specific meanings with respect
to interoperability and proposed
standards.
And so, these are those terms and there,
when they're used, they are used in all
caps.
And so, the first is most required and
shall.
If you see these terms used in RFC, then
this is an absolute requirement.
If a protocol or implementation does not
follow this statement, then it is not it
does not follow the RFC, it is not
compliant.
Then, there should recommended. And so
the, should recommended it, or things you
really generally want to do.
It's really advised that you do it, but
it's understood that there might be times
when you don't, for whatever reason.
And so, the, the terminology that's used
in 2119 is that you really should
understand the implications of not doing
this if you're going to choose to not do
it.
And then finally, there's may optional.
And so, this is totally up to you, you can
do it, you cannot do it. It is not
required interoperability in anyway.
And so, when you read an RFC, it's
important to see these terms and how
they're used, and then understand what the
RFC is really saying you have to do to be
compliant.
So, I thought, as an example, we could
walk through RFC 5681.
This is TCP congestion control.
As you can see, it's standards track, so
this is pretty well along.
And it's written back in 2009 by a bunch
of folks or, bigwigs in the internet.
And so, one thing you can see is in fact,
the history of this document in terms of
drafts, so it's draft-ietf, and it went
through all of this revisions and you can
see what the revisions are.
The earlier revisions that this what, this
obsoletes is 2581.
And so, this particular IETF draft went
through seven revisions before becoming an
RFC.
So, let's go back to the RFC.
So, as you can see, there's an abstract or
stating what it's about, other copyright
notes for intellectual property some
background.
It defines a bunch of terms which are used
in this. But, if we jump forward, so here,
say in section three, it's defining the
congestion control algorithms of TCP.
So it'll start, congestion avoidance,
fast retransmit and faster recovery.
And so, you know, for example, one of the
first requirements this document states is
that it's okay for TCP sender to send more
slowly than what these algorithm say in
order, in order to back off more
aggressively to congestion.
But, it must not be more aggressive.
That these, what this document describes
are, is going to be upper bounds of what
TCP should do.
They should never send faster than this
because they do so might cause a problem.
So then, here's another specification.
It says, the initial value of the
congestion window.
So, when you start a TCP connection, what
the congestion window initial window is,
It must be set following these are
parameters.
So, basically, if you have large segment
sizes, then it should be two segments.
If you have medium sized segments, it can
be up to three segments and if you have a
small segments, it can be up to four
segments.
And this statement is, if you want to
follow TCP congestion control properly,
here's what your initial segment size can be, the
initial congestion window size.
So, those are examples of must and must
nots.
Here's an example of a should.
So, this ssthresh is saying, what is the
initial slow start threshold.
The initial threshold at which we're going
to transition from slow start to
congestion avoidance.
And so, this document says, it's the
initial value should be very, very high.
So, I choose to do slow start until you
essentially get a loss, and then you drop
into congestion avoidance.
However,
You know, it can be smaller if you'd like.
And so, it should be set arbitrarily high.
But, if you cannot set it arbitrarily high,
you should understand whatever the
implications of what will happen if you do
this.
Finally, here is an example of in fact, a
may, a should, and a must not.
So, it's talking about when is TCP is in
congestion avoidance and it's incrementing
its congestion window.
It says, oh, you may increment congestion
window by certain number of bytes, but you
don't have to, you could just not if you
want to. You could not increase it.
But it should increment it once per RTT,
by this equation, equation, and it must
not increment it more than this amount.
So, that's basically saying, hey, here is
the upper bound, and you should not ever
do it more than that upper bound, but you
generally want to follow this equation,
you should follow this equation.
So, all this aside,
Remember, so, this document is saying
something about how large the congestion,
how large the initial window size should
be.
It must be this number of segments, two
segments for a large size, three for
medium size, four for small segments.
But remember,
This is just an RFC, right?
There's, you can say that somebody isn't
compliant but they, nobody is going to
enforce it.
In fact,
If you look at this webpage here, there is
this really interesting blog post
about two years ago about how Google and
Microsoft are, were not following this
RFC.
So, if you want, you can look this up.
This is Ben Strong's blog. If you search
for "Google Microsoft congestion window
cheat".
And essentially, what he found is that,
when you first connect to Google or
Microsoft sites,
Their initial window is much, is
significantly larger than two.
That is they will send you more than two
segments, essentially, so they can send
you their whole webpage in just one round
trip time and not having to wait for the
congestion window to increase.
And so, he walks through and come, all the
experimental evidence that he gathered,
and he shows that these guys were not
following the rules.
And there has been a discussion in the IETF
about, maybe we need to increase these
sizes.
Networks are getting faster. But the point
here being that, just because it's written
in an RFC, that says you must do
something, doesn't necessarily mean that
everyone always does.