the answer to case 1 is 90 milliseconds. The
setup is 20 milliseconds the ack request is
25 milliseconds and the response is 30 milliseconds.
So 95 milliseconds total.
The answer to case 2 is 380 milliseconds.
It takes 95 milliseconds to load the intial
page. It then takes 95 milliseconds to load
image one. When Image one finishes,image 3
starts.
Meanwhile, image two is already in flight
so thats 95 milliseconds.
When image 3 completes, that's another 95
milliseconds, since image 2 has already completed.
Image 4 is in flight.
It takes a final 95 milliseconds for image
5, for a total of 380 milliseconds.
Let's take a look at this pictorially, to
see what's happening. This picture starts
after the first initial page request.
It's showing what happens as the client request
images.
So we start at 95 milliseconds. There's a
pair of SYN SYN/ACKs as the two connections
start their three-way handshake.
So 40 milliseconds later, at 135 milliseconds,
the client sends request 1 at 135 milliseconds,
and request 2 at 140 milliseconds.
Request 1 arrives at the server at 165 milliseconds.
20 milliseconds of latency and 5 milliseconds
of pavketization delay.
The server starts sending the response. It's
sent one segment of the response, 1a, when
the second request arrives.
The response segments for the second request
are enqueued and sent after response 1b.
Response 1b arrives at the client at 190 milliseconds.
At this point, the client opens a new connection
through a three-way handshake, but note how
long this took.
The client is requesting the third image at
190 milliseconds, 95 milliseconds after the
first request started.
because the second request is going in parallel,
the client doesn't have to wait for it to
complete before starting the request.
It will start the fifth request immediately
after the third one completes.
So these three rounds take on 95 milliseconds
each. If we had requested six images, then
the final round would take 105 milliseconds.
Look at this figure carefully, until you understand
what's going on.
As requests are delayed going out from queueing,
they delay responses. As responses delay going
out from queueing, they delay further requests.
Over time, this causes the requests and responses
to naturally space themselves out, reducing
queueing delay.
And because we have multiple operations in
parallel, they can mask each other's latencies.
If you look at these numbers and think about
them a bit, you should see that requesting
multiple resources in parallel doesn't take
much longer than requesting a single resource.
There's additional packetization delay, but
on most networks today, packetization delay
is a tiny fraction of the overall time.
A single request can't fill the network capacity,
but many requests might be able to.
HTTP only allows a single connection per request
though.