In the next few videos, we're going to
look at a number of different ways that packets can
be routed across a network.
In this video, I'm going to start with
some of the basic concepts and principles
of routing, regardless of whether we're
routing packets based on the layer three,
or IP addresses, or if we're using the
Ethernet address, and, and Ethernet
switches.
The basic problem that we're trying to
solve when routing packets, is how should
packets be routed from A to B.
Should the packet be picked up by the end
host A, over here, by the network in the
middle, or by some other entity?
So, what, what path should they pick?
And, what are the most important metrics
for them to consider?
Should they take the shortest path?
The least congested path?
A randomly picked path?
The safest and most reliable path?
Does it matter?
So, in the next few minutes, we're going
to look through at some different
techniques and some different metrics for
solving this basic problems.
So, we're going to look at a number of
different approaches.
Flooding, source routing, forwarding
table, and spanning tree.
We will at some metrics and then, I'll
describe what the shortest path spanning
tree is and that describes some other
types of routing, multipath and multicast.
Flooding is perhaps the simplest way to
make sure at least one copy of a packet is
delivered to every destination in the
network and therefore to the
destination that its wanting to go to.
With flooding, each router is going to
forward the packet to every interface.
So, if A is sending a packet, and let's
say that its sending it to B, so it has B's address in it.
When it reaches the first router, it's
going to send it out of every interface
except the one through which it arrived.
That's going to happen on the next router
as well, so it'll send it out of these
interfaces.
It will come down to this one here, which
will send it out here and here, then it'll
go out from here, and then it'll go from
this one out of here.
But it'll also go in this direction.
And it'll come back around here, and come
back around here and you could see, very
quickly, that there's a loop that's going
to form in the middle with the packet
going round and round and round forever.
But, we can be sure in this case, because
every packet will be delivered at least
once to every leaf.
It will therefore reach every destination.
And if it contains B's address, which it
does, then we can be sure that B can find
the packet or receive the packet by simply
filtering on packets matching its address.
This is clearly very inefficient.
All packets are going to cross every link,
potentially multiple times.
And packets are going to loop forever.
Therefore, it's common to use a hop count
or a time to live field like we do in, in
IP to start packets looping forever.
But at least, we can be sure that packets
are going to reach their eventual
destination, we can be absolutely sure of
that.
So, flooding is nice and simple.
It requires no state in the routers.
It doesn't, it doesn't require any
understanding by A of the topology of the
network.
So, it's very, very simple.
But because it's so inefficient, it's
really only used at times and instances
when we know nothing about the topology,
or we can't trust our knowledge of it, and
we need to be able to reach every node.
So, we'll see a couple of examples of this
later, particularly at times of
transition, when we're not quite sure
what's going on.
So, in summary.
It's inefficient in link usage, packets
going to loop forever, and it's used when
we don't know or can't trust the topology.
Now, let's look at another method called
source routing.
Source routing is when the source
populates the packet with the sequence of
hops that it will visit along its path.
So, if we give names to these routers,
let's call them R1, R2, R3, R4, R5, and
R6.
And so, if A is sending to B, with source
routing, it might, for example, put in the
header, R1, R3, R6 to indicate that it
wants the packet to go through that
sequence, before it gets to B.
So, that would just say, go to R1 first,
go to R3, R6, and then to B.
I just happen to draw them in the order in
which they will be visited.
That's going to depend on the way in which
we use source routing.
We'll see that a little bit later.
But it hits specifically here, A knows the
topology, it knows the order in which it
wants the routers to be visited, and it's
giving the final destination to make sure
that it works, and reaches B.
Likewise, with flooding, the routers need
no forwarding tables to be populated in
advance.
All the decision-making is made by the end
host.
So, this is actually a pretty good example of the
end-to-end principle in action.
The function is implemented at the end
host, A is the one that knew the route and
so it picked this as the path that would
be taken.
And this way, we can make sure it's done
correctly.
But it's a lot of work for the end host,
and packets are a variable length and
might carry a lot of addresses.
So, on the face of it, it's kind of a good
scheme but clearly, we would like to do
something that was a little less
heavyweight on the end host.
So, it's an end-to-end solution and no
support needed from the network.
Packet carries a variable and maybe long
list of addresses, and hosts must know the
topology and choose the route, and this is
used when the end host wants to control
the route.
So now, let's look at the, the method that
we already know is used by the Internet,
and the, this is in, this is when we
actually have a forwarding table that's
used throughout the network to route the
packets hop by hop.
And as you know already, I'll go through
this fairly quickly, if we're sending a
packet from A to B along this particular
path, S1, S2, S4, and then to B.
But the forwarding table case, we use a
forwarding table at each hop in order to
decide where the packet will go next and we've seen as example before.
You can really think of this as a, an
optimization.
It's an optimization in the sense that
although we could correctly have the
behavior work by populating the packets
with the, with the route using source
routing, we have decided to have the
network take on these functions to
optimize it because it's such a common
function, common to everybody that's using
the network.
So, it's an optimization in the sense that
the network is going to handle the hop by
hop routing on behalf of everybody.
It does require a population of the
forwarding table so we need a way to
populate these forwarding tables.
And we're going to see in, in, in, in the
next few videos, various ways in which we
can populate this table.
So, from here on, we're going to be making
the assumption that we're using forwarding
tables.
And that, the, the, that we need some
method in order to populate this table, in
order to decide how the routing will take
place.
We have put destination state in the
network, because we are going, each of
the, of the destinations, we're going to
have, to have a next hop address, populated
in the table although we don't
necessarily have to have a flow state.
Any flows in the network that are heading
towards the same destination could all use
the same entries.
When populating the forwarding tables with
entries, it's often the goal to create
what we call the spanning tree and we're
going to see many examples of this.
Spanning tree is spanning in the sense
that it reaches all the leaves and it's a
tree, in a sense that it has no loops.
So, we want to make sure that we can reach
every destination or every source can
reach a particular destination, and we
want to make sure that there are no loops.
Let me give you an example of this.
Imagine that we want to create the
spanning tree that A, B, C, and D, the
host at the top, will use in order to send
packets to X, the destination at the
bottom.
So, A, its packet could follow this path,
B's might follow this path, C's might
follow this path, and D's might follow
that path.
So, you can see I've created a tree with
the root at X and it's spanning all of the
sources that might send to it.
So, tree in the sense that it has no
loops.
This would be implemented by populating
the routing, the forwarding table at R1
with the entry, if I want to go to X, then
I go to R3 as my next hop.
That's, that's telling it what to do here.
Likewise, at R3, we would have an entry
that said, if I want to go to, to X, then
I will go directly to X.
Similarly, over here in R4, I will say, if
I'm going to go to X, then I will go there
via R7.
So, the spanning tree is used in order to
create the routing entries so that we can
populate the forwarding tables and
therefore route paths along that spanning
tree.
When calculating the spanning tree, we
need to know what our objective is, or
what our metrics of success are.
How do we know, amongst all of the
possible spanning trees, which one we're
going to pick?
So, this is going to depend on what our
metric is.
So, let's look at some, some choices that
we might have.
We might choose to pick the spanning tree
that minimizes the distance.
This could be the geographic distance or
the, minimize the length of the links
between the source and the destination.
So, for example, noticing that this link
along here is long, we might, we might
decide that this path is actually
geographically shorter than this one down
here, and therefore prefer it.
We might also choose the one with the
minimum hop count.
So, the example I showed you before was
generally following the shortest hop
count.
So, for example, D would take this path
here, because it's the shortest number of
hops.
It will also be the one that minimizes
delay.
I've got no way of telling directly from
the graph what will minimize the delay but
that might be something that I can measure
in the recent past, what have been the
lengths that have experienced the
minimum delay and therefore, give
preference to those.
I might go and use the ones that maximize
the throughput, that maybe the least
congested or the path that is least
loaded, or it may be the most reliable
path, the one that in the recent past has
failed the least often.
That may be my metric.
It could also be the lowest cost path.
I may have a price or a cost associated
with using any one link, and I want to
minimize it.
Or it could be the most secure path, the
one that most recently has, had the, the
fewest security attacks, or it might be
one over which I have a virtual private
network running, and so on.
There are many, many metrics that I could
use.
Or, in fact, I could actually use a
combination of any of those.
So, typically, how we, how we do this, is
we start by creating a, an annotated graph
with whatever cost metric we've chosen,
and I could have picked any of those ones.
So, we can represent our metric as a cost
for using a link.
So, this is a, a, a set of costs that I
made up, just as an example.
In general, the cost might be different in
each direction, just because of the
congestion maybe more in one direction, or
the throughput may be different, but for
ease of drawing, I'm going to show one
number per link here.
So, one natural choice is to try to find
the spanning tree from every host to x and
I might try to find the one that is
minimizing the cost.
In which case, I'm going to call it the
minimum cost spanning tree.
In this example, the, the solution is
fairly obvious.
Let's have a look at what, what that would
be.
So, coming to X, if I'm coming from B,
then the minimum cost is going to be to
take that path here because that has the
cost of four.
When I'm going from C, the minimum cost is
going to be this one here, which has a
cost of five, three + two.
Coming from D, it's pretty easy.
It's going to be down here.
A is a little bit more subtle.
It's not the one down here.
The lowest cost one is the one that goes
this way, which has a cost of five.
So, there's my minimum cost spanning tree.
And here's an example of that drawn out.
So, in this case, it's very simple to
calculate it, what we need is a method
that will work in much more complicated
networks.
For example, this one.
This is clearly way beyond something a
human could do in their head.
This is a picture of the topology map for
the backbone of the internet.
Well, I can't do this in my head, maybe
you can.
So, we need automated algorithms to
calculate the route and put the necessary
forwarding entries into the forwarding
tables in the routers.
So, to calculate the routes, the routers are
going to exchange information with each
other about the current topology as they
know it.
This is the job of what we call the, the
routing algorithm or the routing protocol.
In some cases, the algorithm to calculate
the route is wrapped in with the exchange
of the state itself.
In another case, it's that separate.
We're going to look at examples of both.
Going back to our outline, we've got down
to the, the shortest path spanning tree.
We're going to be looking at several
examples of this over the next few videos.
I just want to finish up by telling you
about two other types of, of routing that
are commonly used.
The first one is multipath.
So far we've assumed that all the packets
to, to a given destination are going to
follow the same path, in particular, the
shortest path spanning tree.
The downside of the shortest path spanning
tree is that some links can become very
popular.
We saw that we had a path that went down
here before, and a path that went down
here.
You can see that this whole are here is
going to become quite popular, and could
become congested.
So, it means that we might need to keep
adapting the algorithm.
An alternative would be, instead of
adapting the algorithm is to, from the
beginnings, spread all of the traffic of
all, over all of the links.
So, this is quite different from the
shortest path spanning tree.
This might be a, a case where we send some
of the packets from A to X this way and we
might choose to send some of them this way
and we might choose to send some of them
this way, then we might choose to send
some of them this way.
This is called multipath where we are
spreading the packets to a destination
over multiple paths.
Essentially, when load balancing traffic
over some or possibly all of the paths,
we're going to see the details later but
for now, it's enough to know that, that it
might look something like what I, what I
just drew.
So, in principle, it's okay for packets to
take
different length paths and to get
disordered.
So, it might be that in the example I had
here, that a packet taking this path here
might get there much sooner than taking
this path here.
And therefore, get new sequence relative
to it.
Now, the Internet makes no promise of
in-sequence delivery.
That's the job of TCP, to put them back in
the right order.
But we're going to see later that in
practice, it's, it's common to make sure
that packets within a given application
flow don't get missequenced just to make
life a bit easier for TCP.
But this is just really an optimization in
the network.
So, multipath is when we spread the
packets over multiple links, in order to
spread the load as evenly as we can across
the network.
Another type of routing, another method is
called multicast.
So far, we have assumed that all packets
are going to a single destination,
something we call unicast.
For example, the packets in the last few
examples I've shown are going from A to X as
a single packet.
In some applications, an end host might
want to send packets to a set of hosts.
For example, A might want, might want to
send packets to, a, a single packet that
gets delivered to B, C, and X maybe, but
not D.
Applications that might want to do this
could be like a broadcast TV or a radio
station where currently, B, C, and X are
listening to a TV station being broadcast
from A.
It could be automatic updates to a large
number of hosts, for example, a car
company updating its inventory every night
to all of its dealerships.
Or it could be stock prices being updated
in the trading room where you want
everybody to receive the update very,
very, at the same time.
So, while we can obviously send each
packet one at a time to its destination,
that would be fine.
And you could send individual packets to
B, C, and X.
It's natural to ask if the network can
help.
Whether it can and whether it should do
the replication for us.
So, for example, A could send a single
packet, it could come down until it
reaches B and then, it could be
replicated, one packet going this way and
one packet going this way and another
packet going on to C, and so on, at every
branching point within the network.
So now, we send one packet and it's
delivered to everybody.
And we're using the graph structure of the
network to do the replication for us.
So, notice that in order to send for A to
B, c, and x, I've essentially drawn a
spanning tree.
And this is actually going to prove to be
quite interesting later.
I've got a spanning tree across the set of
destinations, and we're going to see some
examples of how this works later.
It's enough for us to know right now that
just, that this is a one way of routing
packets.
And we'll see later how this is done
specifically in the Internet.
So, in summary, there are several ways to
route packets across a network, starting
with the simplest method, flooding.
So, in practice, we use routing algorithms
or also known as routing protocols to
calculate the routes and populate the
forwarding tables.
Often, the algorithms calculate the
minimum cost spanning tree to the
destination and we're going to see lots of
examples of that soon.
Other types of routing include multipath
to spread traffic overlinks and multicast
to deliver the, to multiple end hosts.
That's the end of this video.