So in this video, I'm going to talk with
the details of how a NAT operates.
And that is the rules and recommendations
that are given in terms of NAT behavior
for handling both incoming and outgoing
connections, possible packets that
traverse, as well as how a NAT responds
when it's not acting as a NAT.
Recall that a NAT, a network address
translation box will set up mappings from
internal IP address port pairs for
transport protocols to external IP address
port pairs.
So here, we have a NAT whose external IP
address is 128.34.22.8.
And so, that's an internal interface and
an external interface.
To the external world, this NAT appears as
128.34.22.8,
To the internal world, it has another IP
address,
Say, 10.0.0.1.
Now, host A, can, by issuing, by sending a
TCP connection open
SYN message to server S on port 80.
Then that will observe that, will
translate host A's internal address and
port 10.0.0.101, 4512, to the external
address in port 128.34.22.8.
And it's going to assign an external port,
in this case 6641, for this mapping. I'll
set up this mapping.
So, one question you can ask is that, if
some arbitrary packet comes into the NAT,
how should the NAT respond?
So now, if the NAT is,  starts
receiving TCP packets from 128.34.22.8,
Sorry, packets to 128.34.22.8:6641, It
should translate them, that's what the
mapping says.
Now, it might have restrictions on that
based on whether it's  cone, port
restricted, et cetera.
But generally speaking, packets which
match this will traverse.
But what happens if it receives a packet
destined to it's external address, so,
128.34.22.8:55127.
What should that do?
Well, in the end, the NAT is itself an IP
device,
And the fact that some of its ports happen
to result in translation is independent of
the fact and how it would respond.
So imagine that there are no port mapping
set up that, there are no internal nodes
to the NAT, that nobody had opened any
connections.
How would the NAT respond if you tried to
open a connection to it?
In this case, it responds as it always
would.
So for this particular case, it might do a
connection refuse, like a reset packet.
Or, you know, depending on what message,
what packet comes in, it could send an
ICMP error.
And so, generally speaking, the NAT
behaves like a normal IP device or an IP
router with the exception of, when packets
come to the internal, the external
interface that have a mapping or when
packets traverse from the internal
interface and generate a mapping.
So besides that, if you imagine, if you
had no such A or B or any node behind it,
then that behaved just like a normal IP,
Inter, IP device.
So for example, many NATs, such as your
home router,
In fact, run a web server on port 80.
So if you have a home wireless router, it
runs a web server in port 80 which is what
lets you configure it.
Or sometimes it's not port 80 but some
other port.
But the idea that the NAT itself can
respond to connections,
Whether they'd be for a web management
interface or for other services.
That's a perfectly reasonable and
allowed behavior.
So one question that comes up was, we have
a NAT, is what causes you to set up these
mappings?
So you can imagine in the case of UDP .
This is generally when a packet comes from
the internal interface going to something
external.
The NAT sets up a mapping, mapping that IP
address port to an external IP address
port.
Of course the NAT needs to be careful
about these allocations so that it's not
reusing them.
TCP,
Well, if you see a TCP SYN then your node may
set up a mapping or, you know, you could
even be a little more a little more con, a
little more liberal, and say, look,
If we see any TCP packets coming from
inside, then we assume there should be a
mapping and just set up the mapping.
There's of course, a question, then, this
is how you create mappings when you tear
them down.
Well, UDP, since there is no control
sequence,
Generally, these are on a time out.
The mappings are torn down on a timeout.
You do need to reclaim them, otherwise you
could run out of external ports to use.
TCP, well, if you see a, a proper FIN,
packets change to tear down the
connection, then you know that you can,
garbage collect the conection state, the,
intern, the mapping, a little more
quickly.
Of course, there are some edge cases here.
You need to be sure it actually was
discarded.
You want to be sure you don't enter some
state where it's possible to lose data.
So turns out there are RFCs that go into
detail on exactly how NAT should behave
and these behavior recommendations came
out after, you know, almost a decade of
experience with these devices and how they
can possibly disrupt applications through
strange behavior.
So there were some early documents that
tried to, that tried to state based on you
know, somebody went out and actually Colin
Jennings, went out basically to Fry's
Electronics and bought you know, 25
different NAT boxes and just measured them
and saw what they did and they did all
kinds of crazy things.
So based on that, and based on application
behavior, the ITF came up with a pair of
recommendations,
One for UDP one for TCP.
There's also, you know, for other, other
behavioral recommendations on how NATs
should behave,
So UPD is specified in RFC4787.
So here's, RFC 4787.
As you can see, it's a best common
practices, number 127.
Best current practice.
And so generally speaking, these documents
have, there's stuff about terminology.
They have, a set of behavioral
recommendations.
So,
Here, for example is recommendation one or
requirement one.
A NAT must have an end point
independent mapping behavior.
So, what this means, is that if we were to
turn to the terminologies to describe
NATs, what this essentially is saying in
terms of that classification terminology,
if you were to read through the details of
the document, is that NATs cannot be
symmetric.
In that, the mapping a NAT creates,
between, for UDP, between an
internal IP address port, and an external
IP address port must be independent of
what the end point is.
It can't be a symmetric NAT where it
sets up a new mapping for every external,
IP address and port,
Because of all the ways in that, that,
that tends to break applications.
So here's a, a second recommendation.
Here's a recommendation that NATs have an
IP address pooling behavior of paired.
So this is for NATs that happen to
actually have multiple external addresses
and the idea is, hey, if we can, then,
Can I, UDP packets coming from the same
internal IP address, should appear to have
the same external IP address.
So here's the third here's the third, som
s-, recommendation, that requirement.
Which is, has to do with how ports are
assigned.
So it turns out historically, ports zero
to 1023 were considered system services.
So these were ports which only
administrators or super-users could bind
to, basically the root on Unix systems.
So that's why you see things like HTTP,
SMTP, they're all running on the low port
numbers as opposed to lots of
applications, stuff like Bit Torrent or
Skype which are on high port numbers and
that's a historical artifact but there are
some, sort of,
assumptions that applications
have made historically, based on this.
And so what one of this requirement says,
is just to kind of say, we don't break
things.
That if the internal port is between zero
and 1023, then the external port should be
between zero and 1023.
And the opposite is also true, that if
it's not, if it's in 1024 to
Then the external should be between
So I'm not going to go through all of
these requirements,
What's nice actually, as you read through
these documents, is it really gives you a
sense of all of the different kinds of
application expectations that there are.
What's nice is that there are these
justifications.
It'll even explain, hey, there are
applications that make these assumptions,
or protocols that make these assumptions.
And therefore, the NAT needs to do this so
it doesn't break those applications.
Gives you just this nice,
Sort of a couple of points of interesting
protocol approaches that happen on the
internet.
Now the TCP requirements are specified in
RFC5382.
And so we can see the, the first,
requirement for TCP NAT behaviour is very
similar to UDP.
This end point independent mapping.
Symmetric NATs are really bad, they break
all kinds of things.
So never build a symmetric NAT.
So that's requirement number one.
But unlike UDP, TCP has connections, and
so, and connection set up.
And so there are a couple of requirements
that come out for TCP that aren't present
in UDP.
For example, and this one's kind of
interesting, is requirement two.
A NAT must support all valid sequences of
TCP packets for connections initiated both
internally as well as externally when the
connection's permitted by the NAT and the
basic point here is this, this sub point
A,
That a NAT must handle TCP simultaneous
open.
So this gets back to the case we talked
about, NAT hole-punching, where it can be
that two nodes behind NATs, say, A and B
They want to open connections to one
another.
They want to open a connection through the
NAT, so what they do is they talk to some
external server, and there are servers
that, provide this abstraction, things
like, ICE, that allow them basically to do
some query responses to figure out what
kind of NAT they're behind, and also to
figure out what the external IP address
and port is associated with their local IP
address and port.
So based on this, both A and B can figure
out, given their internal address and
port, what's the external address and
port.
They somehow exchange this information
through a rendezvous service,
And then both A and B simultaneously
try to open TCP connections to one
another.
Now, it could be that, you know, these
connections, these connections are there
or that this state is there.
But the basic point is that, it can very
well be that, B sends a SYN which sets up
the state,
And that SYN reaches A before A has set up
its translation state and so the SYN is not
going to transverse.
However, the state now exists on B.
So B now has a translation entry.
Now A then opens a connection back and its
SYN does traverse this translation and now
A can open a connection on B.
But the thing is that this is a
simultaneous open.
B has sent a SYN and the SYN is
outstanding.
In terms of the TCP state diagram, it's,
it's already sent a SYN.
So this is the simultaneous open when A
and B sends SYNs to each other at the same
time.
So, for peer-to-peer applications,
where A and B want to open in connection
directly to one another, it's important
that a NAT allow this kind of TCP open.
That it's not just that, aha, we don't
support simultaneous open and so,
therefore, we're not going to allow this
SYN to traverse because that's an
incoming SYN.
That if you have a mapping, the incoming
SYN must be able to traverse,
That's what here, requirement two is
saying.
But even more generally, it's saying that,
Look, TCP has a state diagram, and that
you're supposed to be able to traverse
this state diagram to open a connection
anyway that you want and then NAT should
not restrict that.
That is that NAT should not be
somehow limiting the, limit the TCP
implementation options.
So here, requirement three, states that it
should have an end point independent
filtering behavior.
So this is basically, this is, back to the
terminology.
We talked about classification of NATs.
This means a full cone NAT.
That it's recommended that NATs, in terms
of TCP be full cone.
And again, like the UDP, recommendations,
each of these behavioral recommendations,
each of these has a justification.
And so, it can be really, sort of, very,
very, sort of, insightful and illuminating
to read through and what are the kinds of
applications,
What are the, sort of the edge cases that
can make, that NATs can break?
And see a lot of them relate to
peer-to-peer, in particular, voice over
IP.
All these kinds of applications where NATs
work fine when simply you have a client
behind the NAT, opening a conn, connection
to a server.
But anything peer-to-peer, where things
behind NATs want to open connections to
one another, you have to, have an
intelligent behavior on the NAT,
otherwise you can break those
applications.
So this one requirement four, is kind of,
of an interesting edge case which is that,
so, a NAT must not respond to an unsolicited
inbound SYN for at least six seconds.
So, here's the, here's the case why this
is important.
Again, let's go to this example.
We have A and B that are both behind NATs
and they're trying to do a simultaneous
open.
Now, it turns out that A ends up sending
its simultaneous open well before B does,
Such that its SYN arrives before B has
tried to open, its, its connection to A.
So if B's NAT responds with responds to
this an, you know, unsolicited in bound
SYN by saying you know?
Sorry, connection refused.
Or by, you saying ICPM, ICPM error,
whatever it wants to do,
Depending on the circumstances.
The problem, then, is that this might come
back to the NAT.
It caused them not to tear down the state.
And then, when B tries to do it's own
simultaneous open, so here be the error.
If B tries to do its own simultaneous
open, that state is now torn down and
that's going to fail.
And so the idea here is that if B has to
wait at least six seconds, the assumtion
is that B and A, if they're doing
simultaneous open, are going to try to do
so within six seconds of each other,
That's what it sort of means,
simultaneously.
And so, the NAT will wait before issuing
that, response, such that B has a chance
to do its own open, which could then set
up a state for A.
Note that in the second sentence, if
during this interval, the NAT receives and
translates an outbound SYN, it must
suddenly drop the original the original
unsolicited inbound SYN.
So in this case you know, inbound SYN came
in, it was unsolicited,
But then, suddenly, something showed that
maybe it was solicited.
You should just drop it.
You shouldn't issue an error.
You can ask the question as to whether or
not you should have it traverse the NAT.
That'd be another approach.
I actually went back and looked through
some of the archives and this just seemed
to work pretty well.
The mailing list archives about this
discussion.
This seemed to work pretty well.
It means the NAT doesn't have to buffer these
SYNs.
It, it solves the problem, and serve as
the least complicated answer.
So that's just a brief overview of
some of the internals in NATs and their
policies and the algorithms that they use
and some of the rules that there are for
their behavior to allow applications to
work.
If this is something that's interesting, I
totally recommend, reading these RFCs in a
bit more detail.
Especially, because they give these really
nice descriptions as to why these
behaviors exist.
Particularly for peer-to-peer applications