So in this video, I'm going to talk about
CSMA/CA.
Carrier Sense Multiple Access Collision
Avoidance.
A MAC protocol or MAC algorithm used in
wireless networks.
So for a wireless network to be able to
detect that there's a collision, it needs
to know whether or not a packet collided,
or whether it was delivered successfully.
So, because in a wireless network due to
signal strength attenuation, you can't
detect that there was a collision at a
receiver because you can't observe the
receiver directly.
You need some feedback from the receiver
as to what's happened.
And so the way this is commonly achieved
is with link layer acknowledgments.
And the idea is that if A is transmitting
a packet, a data packet, to B, if B
successfully receives this packet, then
what it does, is it sends an
acknowledgment back.
This acknowledgment packet could be
very, very short.
It's occurring at the link layer.
It doesn't go across multiple hops in the
network.
It's directly, say, using a wireless
Ethernet between A and B.
And so the advantage of this is if A
starts transmitting, say, a data packet to
B, but at the same time, C transmits a
data packet and the two collide.
Then B will not send that acknowledgement,
it doesn't successfully receive either
packets, sends no acknowledgement, A knows
that it might need to re-transmit, that it
should possibly re-transmit.
Of course you can have collusion on ACKs,
ACKs aren't perfect, so  it  can be that A, does
some unnecessary re-transmissions but
generally speaking A needs some feedback
from B to know whether or not the data was
delivered successfully.
If these were very, very uncommon.
Right?
So in the same way, the same wire
Ethernet.
Where it's possible, it's very uncommon
that a packet doesn't collide and yet
doesn't arrive successfully.
Then you might not need an
acknowledgement.
But the fact that wireless, the signal
strength changes so much over time.
That data, data errors are common, means
that you want to have some positive
feedback.
So using link layer acknowledgments.
This is how CSMA/CA works.
So the idea is you start off with some
initial random back off.
It can be very small, say, if the
channel's idle.
You sense the local channel.
And you transmit after the back off.
So the basic idea here is, listen, if the
channels idle, then transmit.
If you don't hear the packet
acknowledged, if you don't hear an
acknowledgement, then back off again and
retry it.
So, transmit again.
If you hear the packet acknowledged, then
you can send the next packet.
This is the basic CSMA, carrier sense
multiple access, CA, collision avoidance
algorithm.
And it's collision avoidance because you
do just back off again.
So, let's look at this more concretely.
What is 802.11?
It's a wi-fi.
What does it do?
So, 802.11 has two modes.
One is CSMA/CA.
Er, it has many modes, but the common mode
that everybody uses today is CSMA/CA.
It also has another mode common,
reasonably common, called request to send,
clear to send, which we'll talk about in a
future video.
But here, let's talk about CSMA/CA.
So the basic approach is that you pick an
initial wait period, T.
This often starts off as being very small.
And what the transmitter does is it
periodically checks the channel.
If the channel is idle on all those
checks, it decrements T, so it's counting
down T.
So T represents the amount of idle time
the transmitter wants to hear before it'll
transmit.
So in T which is zero, it tries to
If it hears an acknowledgement, then it
accepts the next packet for transmission.
All's good.
If it doesn't hear an acknowledgement, it
doubles T.
So it'll exponentially back off, longer
and longer.
If T grows to be larger than some large T
value, then it just drops the packet.
Rather than waiting or blocking on a given
packet, it'll just drop that packet and
try to go on to the next one.
And so here's a little, little walk
through.
So here's our sender S, and it picks an
initial T value here.
T, the channel here is busy so it's not
decrementing T.
It starts decrementing T.
T becomes zero here.
And so it transmits, it transmits this
packet.
Unfortunately, it doesn't hear an
acknowledgement so it picks a new T, which
is.
In a range twice as large as the original
t.
It decrements that T, there are periods of
busy-ness, there are period of idleness
and then finally T decrements, let's call
this T2, and finally T2 decrements to zero.
It transmits here is an acknowledgement.
Great.
It goes on to the next packet transmission
with the initial small T value as the back
off.
So CSMA works, CSMA/CA works pretty well,
but it has a bunch of problems which
really do occur in practice.
So the first one is something called
hidden terminals and so this occurs when,
Say we have this node B in the middle,
like this could be, say, your access
point.
And you have two nodes, A and C, who both
want to transmit to the access point.
So the basic problem with CSMA/CA is that a
transmitter is listening as to whether the
channel is idle at it.
When really what it cares about is whether
the channel's idle at the receiver.
It could be that the receiver is hearing
something, and so it can't hear the
transmitter's packet, but the transmitter
can't tell because it can't hear what's
happening at the receiver.
It wants to sense the receiver's state, but
can actually only sense its own.
And so a hidden terminal is when two
nodes, say A and C, both try to transmit.
To, a receiver, or it can be even to an
adjecnt receivers.
And the receivers can hear both of them,
so B can hear both A and C, but A and C
cannot hear each other.
So A, is hidden to C, and C is hidden to A.
And so A starts transmitting, B starts
receiving the packet, C doesn't hear it,
so C says, aha, I think the channel's
clear, it transmits.
B hears C and A's packets.
There's a collision.
B hears nothing.
Both are lost.
This is something which CSMA/CA can't
solve.
Because you're sensing locally, but you
want to be sensing what's happening at the
receiver.
So you can imagine that this happens a lot
in AP networks.
So, the second problem is what's called an
exposed terminal.
And this is kind of the reverse of a
hidden terminal.
So imagine this case where B wants to
transmit a packet to A, and C wants to
transmit a packet to D.
But now A can't hear C, right.
So A can't hear C.
What's going to happen?
B starts transmitting to A.
All is good, A is receiving the packet.
Now C wants to transmit to D.
D can't hear B.
And this is fine.
D is absolutely capable to receive a
packet from C while B is transmitting.
But C senses its local channel, and it
hears, aha, wait, wait, B is transmitting.
I can't transmit.
And so it doesn't transmit, and so C is
exposed to B.
And so.
Whereas a hidden terminal is a case where
someone transmits when they shouldn't, an
exposed terminal is when someone doesn't
transmit when they could.
So the third problem that occurs, in
CSMA/CA, or, even in just wireless networks
in general, is that, let's say we have our
nodes A and B.
And A transmits a packet to B, but there's
no acknowledgement.
So is this because there was a collision?
That is there is some other node C
transmitting at the same time and that
interfered?
Or is this because suddenly the channel
between A and B became very poor, the
signal to noise ratio went down, it's a
weak signal like say, you know somebody,
some person walked between the two.
Problem is, A can't tell.
It doesn't know whether or not this was,
this loss was due to a collision or just
poor signal.
And you can imagine, it might want to
respond differently.
Because a collision is going to want to
back off.
Because, it doesn't want to contend with
the channel.
But, if it was due to low SNR, then it
wants to perhaps reduce it's bit rate,
transmit slower so it can support more bit
errors due to the, the lower signal
strength.
And so there's often this issue.
And people are starting to solve this
problem now and figure it out.
But, where A tries to transmit to B.
It's loss due to collision.
A interprets that has being a low SNR so
it starts transmitting a slower bit-rate.
Which then means its packets are longer
which increases the chance of collisions
or it transmits to B.
It thinks that it's because it's due to a
collision.
So it backs off more, when really if it
just transmitted again immediately, it
would have been fine.
And so in a standard CSMA, a simple CSMA
algorithm distinguishing these two is
really, really hard.
Nevertheless, because it's so simple, and
when there isn't a tremendous contention,
when you do a good SNR, CSMA works pretty
well.
CDMA/CA is the general MAc protocol you
see used, say, in WiFi networks today.