Nick: In this unit you learned how to answer
the following question.
How should packets from A reach B? Or in the
multicast case how should packets from A reach
B, C and perhaps other end hosts too?
We started by studying four basic approaches
used when routing unicast packets from one
end host to another.
First, we can flood packets over every link
in the network. When a packet arrives to a
router, it is replicated to all of the interfaces
except the one it arrived on. This guarantees
that a packet will eventually traverse every
link, and will therefore reach any (and every)
end host in the network. It is clearly very
inefficient and expensive, and needs to be
coupled with a mechanism to prevent packets
from looping forever. Flooding is used during
times of uncertainty, when the topology is
changing and we have no other way to be sure
we can reach every other host. For example,
when OSPF routers are exchanging link state,
they flood the link state packets throughout
the OSPF domain, so the topology is known
to every router even when it has changed.
Second, we can use source routing. In source
routing, the source host puts into the header
of every packet a list of hops the packet
should traverse through the network. Clearly
this is possible if the end host knows the
entire topology. Source routing means we don’t
need to exchange routing table information
in the network – the routers don’t need
to contain a forwarding table at all. In fact,
arguably, source routing is very much in keeping
with the strong end to end principle – we
shouldn’t burden the network with having
to know all the paths. But in practice, source
routing is rarely used for a number of reasons.
The biggest reason is security: Network operators
don’t like source routing because it requires
them to expose the full topology of their
network and open it up so end hosts can send
packets wherever they want. The Internet designers
felt it was a worthwhile optimization for
the routers to maintain a forwarding table,
to avoid having to distribute full up-to-date
topology information to all the end hosts.
Third, the routers can contain forwarding
tables. Rather than relying on the source
to provide the routing information, the forwarding
table in the router contains the address of
the destination, and an indication of which
interface to exit the router in order to move
on step closer to the destination. Today,
all Ethernet switches and Internet routers
use forwarding tables. The job of the routing
algorithm is to populate the forwarding tables.
Finally, you learned how unicast routing algorithms
usually build a spanning tree, with the destination
at the root of the tree. It is a tree because
we don’t want loops. It is spanning, because
it provides a way for all source end hosts
to reach a destination. Generally speaking,
routing algorithms used in the Internet – such
as OSPF and RIP – populate the forwarding
tables so as to create a spanning tree across
the network. Usually, the spanning tree we
build is a minimum cost spanning tree, where
we are trying to minimize the hop count, delay
or distance traveled by packets.
Phil: You learned about two algorithms widely
used to build the forwarding tables in routers.
The first is the Bellman-Ford algorithm, which
is usually referred to as a distance vector
algorithm. Each router constructs a vector
of distances from itself to every other router
in the network. In successive steps, the routers
exchange their vectors so as to find the neighbor
that is closest to each destination. After
a number of iterations – equal to no more
than the longest loop free path in the topology
– the algorithm will settle on a set of
forwarding tables in each router that tells
it how to route packets along the shortest
path to every destination. The Bellman Ford
algorithm was the basis for RIP – the Routing
Information Protocol – which was the first
widely used routing algorithm in the Internet.
The good thing about RIP is that its algorithm
is distributed – the routers work together
to build a complete set of forwarding tables.
This was important in the early days of the
Internet when the routers were assumed to
have very little computing power. However,
RIP has many problems trying to converge on
the right answer when the network topology
is changing. We saw examples of the so-called
“counting to infinity” problem in which
bad news travels slowly, and methods such
as “poison reverse” to try and overcome
it. Today, RIP is rarely used, and has been
mostly replaced by OSPF and an algorithm called
IS-IS.
OSPF is based on the second algorithm, Dijkstra’s
shortest path first algorithm. Dijkstra’s
algorithm assumes that every router has the
computational power to construct its own routing
table, if it is given a complete topology.
The routers learn the topology by exchanging
link-state information – basically a binary
indication of which links are present and
working. Once they have the topology, every
router sets about calculating its own local
forwarding tables so as to reach every end
host in the network. Dijkstra’s algorithm
is deceptively simple and fast. As a result,
OSPF is very widely used in enterprises and
college campuses today.
In addition to RIP and OSPF, we studied four
other aspects of routing.
You learned how the Internet uses hierarchical
routing to break routing down into more manageable,
locally controlled problems. Each autonomous
system, or AS, chooses an intra-domain routing
algorithm to route packets inside its AS–
for example, Stanford uses OSPF on campus.
Every AS is required to use BGP in order to
exchange routing information with other AS’s
in the Internet.
BGP is the only sanctioned way to exchange
routing information between autonomous systems
in the Internet today. Basically, every AS
advertises to its neighbors the path packets
will take to reach every prefix in the Internet.
The path is the set of AS’s the packet will
pass through along the way. We learned how
every BGP router can use a locally-defined
policy to decide which route advertisement
to accept and use to route packets.
You also learned briefly about multicast routing.
Multicast routing is an optimization added
to a network to avoid the source having to
send a packet multiple times to a set of destinations.
Multicast was all the rage in the 1990s because
it was thought that many applications, such
as Internet TV, would use multicast delivery.
Although many multicast routing algorithms
were invented and standardized – as you
learned in the video – they are not widely
used today. This is because most big applications
and services – such as video streaming–
offer us the convenience of streaming us what
we want, when we want, using a single unicast
connection. Most of the time, there are too
few people watching the same video at the
same time for it to be worth supporting the
optimization in the network.
Finally, you learned about the spanning tree
protocol. This isn’t actually an Internet
routing mechanism per-se, because it is a
mechanism used by Ethernet networks to avoid
creating loops. The spanning tree protocol
allows a set of switches to construct a single
spanning tree, with one switch at the root,
in order to prevent packets looping in the
network.