Nick:
In this unit, you learned about the Transport
Layer. Specifically, you learned about the
three most important Transport layers in use
today. The first, TCP –or the Transmission
Control Protocol - is used by over 95% of
Internet applications. TCP is almost universally
used because it provides the reliable, end-to-end,
bi directional byte-stream service that almost
all applications desire. Most of the videos
In this unit were about TCP. You learned how
we detect that a packet was not delivered
or was corrupted along the way, and you leaned
about the mechanisms TCP uses to successfully
retransmit data until it is correctly delivered.
We spent 3 videos exploring different methods
for reliably delivering data across the unreliable
Internet.
The second transport layer we studied is UDP,
or the User Datagram Protocol. UDP is used
by applications that don’t need the guaranteed
delivery service of TCP, either because the
application handles retransmissions in its
own private way, or because the application
just doesn’t need reliable delivery. All
UDP does is take application data and create
a UDP datagram. The UDP datagram identifies
the application that the data should be sent
to at the other end. That’s about it. Although
very few applications use UDP, we saw examples
of DNS and DHCP which are both simple request-response
query protocols.
The third transport layer we studied is ICMP,
or Internet Control Message Protocol. ICMP’s
main job is to send feedback if things are
going wrong. For example, if a router receives
an IP datagram but doesn’t know where to
send it next, then it sends an ICMP message
back to the source to let it know. ICMP is
very useful for understanding why end to end
communications are not working properly.
Finally, you learned about one of the most
important overarching Architectural Principles
that guided the design of the internet, and
continues to guides our thinking today. It
is called the “End to End Principle”.
We learned about two versions of the End to
End principle: The milder version says that
there are some functions that can only be
correctly implemented at the edges or fringe
of the network; these clearly need to be implemented
there. End to end reliable file transfer and
security are two examples. It is OK to help
these features by adding functions to the
network, but these can only help, not replace
the end to end functionality. The second,
stronger version of the End to End Principle
says that if we can implement a function at
the end hosts, then we should. The basic idea
is that the network should be kept simple,
streamlined with as few features to go wrong,
slow things down or require upgrading. It
assumes that the end hosts are quite intelligent
– such as a laptop or smartphone – and
can implement many of the features needed
by the application.
Phil:
In this unit you studied five main topics
1. Three widely used transport layers. TCP
for reliable delivery of a byte stream between
applications, UDP as an unreliable delivery
of datagrams between applications, and ICMP
as a way to detect when things go wrong.
2. How TCP works, with a particular emphasis
on how it reliably delivers bytes between
two applications. You learned how data errors
and missing packets are detected, and how
packets are retransmitted as well as several
different retransmission strategies, including
selective repeat and go back N. You learned
about how the basic TCP mechanism uses Go
Back N and keeps track of the outstanding
unacknowledged bytes using a sliding window.
You also learned about the TCP state machine
that keeps track of the current status of
the TCP connection.
3. How UDP works and why it is used by a small
number of applications.
4. How ICMP works and how it helps us detect
when communications go wrong, and to monitor
the performance of the route between two end
hosts.
5. You learned about the End to End Principle,
which is an important overarching principle
used in the design of the Internet and many
other communication systems. Throughout this
class – and after you go out into the world
to use your new networking expertize – you’ll
find many people talking about this principle
to help guide their design decisions.
Phil:
You should now have a good understanding of
the three different Transport Layers.
You should understand different retransmission
strategies and why TCP uses a “Sliding Window”.
You should know why TCP uses connections,
how they are established and how they are
maintained by a state machine.
You should be able to explain the End to End
Principle.