Nick: Introduction to Computer Networks teaches
you the basic principles of computer networks.
Philip Levis – glance – and I will teach
these principles using the Internet as an
example.
Phil: So you’ll learn the principles of
networks as well as how the Internet works
and why. So Nick, why should students take
this class?
ニck: Well, first off, the Internet was invented
here at Stanford! Well, partially invented
here – many people contributed a lot. And
it’s the greatest invention of our times.
You’re watching this video over the Internet.
And I don’t think its growth in importance
is slowing down. In ten years it’s going
to be even more important.
Phil: I totally agree! The Internet today
is more than just Facebook. It’s changing
main street in small towns, as services like
Amazon grow. It’s changing politics through
services like Twitter and events such the
Arab Spring. It’s changing education through
videos like this. It is transforming society,
and it’s exciting to live through that transformation.
We grew up just as the Internet was starting
to take off – I still remember the first
time I used a web browser in 1995, the summer
before I went to college. I realized the world
was going to change. I just didn’t know
by how much.
Nick: We’re teaching the class using a flipped
classroom. The reference material is in videos
such as this one, which we’ve recorded and
you’ll watch before class. The class meets
three times a week. Once a week, on Mondays,
we’ll have an in-class exercise, such as
using a software tool to map out Stanford’s
network. On Wednesdays we have guest lectures,
including one from David Clark, the Chief
Protocol Architect of the Internet when it
was first designed in the 1970s, as well as
lectures from Netflix, a member of the Internet
Architecture Board, Google, and more.
Phil: These lectures will give you examples
of how the principles and ideas you’re learning
in the class are applied outside of academia.
They’ll also introduce a lot of interesting
problems and challenges the Internet and its
users face today.
Phil: On Fridays, we split the class in two
so Nick and I can hold section meetings to
get to know you better. We’ll alternate
which half of the class we meet with so you’ll
see each of us five times. We’re using section
as an opportunity to ask and discuss some
open ended questions about the Internet. For
example, in one section I’ll present how
BitCoin works to start a discussion on its
technical, economic, legal, and political
implications.
Nick: The in-class exercises on Monday and
guest lectures on Wednesday are required.
The Friday section is optional.
Nick: Phil and I both enjoy teaching this
class because we both research networked systems
and so spend a lot of time thinking about
them. We enjoy teaching new students each
year about them, and hope that some of our
enthusiasm and excitement can rub off!