So NATs provide a really useful service.
They allow you to share an IP address
among many hosts, which is real useful
today, given that IP addresses are
becoming more scarce.
They also can provide some other useful
services, such as a limited degree of
security and firewalling.
So there are a lot of implications to what
happens when you're behind the NAT.
So this video is going to go into what
some of those implications are and how
some modern applications today try to deal
with them when there are obstructions.
So the first implication to applications of
a network address translator is that,
generally speaking incoming connections
you can't have an incoming connection.
So we saw this back when we talked about
Skype.
What happens is when you want to open a
call to somebody who's behind a NAT, you
can't directly open a TPC connection to
them,
Because there's no mapping on this.
So let's walk through how that works.
So here, we have an SSH server, or we have
a server sitting behind a NAT, here's
server A.
And it has, and so it happens to be
running an SSH server on port22, and it
has, you know, opened a connection to this
server S.
It's browsing the web, you know, it does a
web connection.
This is great.
So now, what happens when host B wants to
open an SSH connection to host A?
.
Well, the problem is, it's going to be
sending a packet to this NAT and whatever
happens, somehow this packet needs to be
translated to be going to 10.0.0.101:22,
but there's no mapping for that.
Ssh is a server.
It doesn't issue connection requests out.
It receives connection requests and so the
NAT has no mapping.
And so, because there's no mapping, to
10.0.0.101:22, B effectively can't open an
SSH connection.
Alright, the NAT allows connections out,
it does not allow connections in,
And so this poses all kinds of
complications for applications.
Where, you know, what happens if, say, I'm
running Skype and I would like to make a
phone call, if the other node's behind the
NAT, I can't open a connection to that
node.
And so, it really restricts the kinds of
services that you can deploy and, you have
to jump through a bunch of hoops in order
to make applications work when they're
sitting behind NATs.
But so, this is the number one implication
of sitting behind the NAT, to an
application, which is that, essentially,
if you're behind the NAT, generally
speaking, other nodes, unless you
coordinate very carefully, and I'll show
some ways you can do it, you can't open,
nobody can open a connection to you.
So the first approach, and, talked about
this briefly, in the Skype lecture before,
is something called connection reversal.
So imagine that A is sitting behind a NAT,
and B wants to open a connection to A.
Well, B can't, because the NAT has no
mapping, these packets will pass up, you
know, bounce off, you get ICMP errors.
And so, what you can do, is have some kind
of reversal service or some kind of
rendezvous service, where both A and B are
connected to the rendezvous service.
And when B wants to open a connection to
A, what it actually sends is it sends a
request, hey, A, I want a connection.
The rendezvous service can forward this
request on, then A can open a connection
to B,
So this is called connection reversal.
Because B wants to open a connection to A,
but because it can't, because of the NAT,
So instead you reverse the connection and
have A open a connection to B.
And to do this, you need some kind of
rendezvous service so that the two can
communicate, by they both open outgoing
connections to the rendezvous service, and
then, requests are forwarded in that way.
So this is for example one of the things
that Skype does.
So another approach, and this is also
some, this is also what Skype does, is if
both hosts are behind a NAT, well, this
means that neither of them can directly
open a connection to the other.
Both cases, the connection request will
fail.
There's no mapping on the NAT, generally
speaking, and so it fails.
So instead you usually have both of them
connect to some relay R,
And then the relay R forwards traffic
between those two connections.
So, data that streams in from A's
connection that R receives, then forwards
to the connection to B,
Data that comes in from B's connection, R
receives and forwards to A.
But here's an example of suddenly this is
no longer end to end.
We've now introduced this additional host
in the center and who knows what could go
wrong.
So certainly, if you're doing this, it's
good to encrypt your traffic, unless,
unless you trust the relay.
But this is a way that if both hosts got
a NAT, they can still open connections to
one another, admittedly, through a third
host that is and does have a publicly
routed IP address, and which is not
sitting behind a NAT.
So that's sort of some basic things that
you can just say at the TCP level and
etcetera.
It turns out that if you really need to
open up direct connections, there are more
aggressive and tricky things you can do.
One of which is called NAT hole-punching.
And so, the basic idea here is that we
have these two clients that are sitting
behind that, it's client A and client B,
And they want to open up direct
connections to one another or a direct
connection between each other.
They don't want to go through some
external rendezvous service or relay.
And so what they do, is they first talk
with some external server to figure out
what, you know, use some service over
here,
To figure out what their external address
and ports are.
So client B says, aha,
If I send you packets, say, from UDP Port,
6000,
The server will then report back with a
message saying, aha,
Well, these packets you're sending,
I see them coming from 76.18.117.20:9091.
So the client B knows that 10.1.1.9:6000
appears externally to the world as
76.18.17.20:9091, And A does the same
thing.
So it'll find out that, you know, it's
packets look like 34.22.8:30005 or so.
So now, in these cases, both clients A and
B have sent packets over the NAT from this
internal address port pair to this ex, to
an external IP address, and port.
And the NATs have created mappings,
So they have mappings internally,
For this internal address port.
And let's just say that they're full cone
NATs just for simplicity sake.
This means that these mappings are now
active on the NATs,
And so it's possible now, if communicating
with the server client B can ask the
server, hey, what's client A's public IP
address and port?
Based on that, the server could say, oh,
well it's 128.34.22.8:30005.
And client B could send traffic to that,
Public IP address and port pair, and it
could diverse the NAT mapping.
Right.
Similarly, A could ask the server, hey,
what's B's I, public IP address and port
pair, then send traffic to
76.18.17.20:9091 and have it traverse the
mapping and go to client B.
This is assuming that those mappings are
full cone.
These are full cone NATs.
Let's say that they're not full cone NATs.
Well, it turns out you can still do some
tricks,
Where the server can tell client A and
client B again what the public IP address
port pairs are of the other clients and
then the clients can try sending traffic
to each other simultaneously.
And so client B will start sending traffic
to 128.34.22.8:30005 from it's port 6000.
Simultaneously, client A will start
sending traffic to 76.18.17.20:9091 from
it's IP address and port.
And what's going to happen is that, if we
say, had a restricted cone NAT or even a
port restricted NAT, when those packets,
those, outgoing packets traverse the NAT,
The NAT is going to set up a mapping.
It's going to say, aha, I see that you
client A, are sending traffic to this
external IP address and port.
I'll create a mapping for you so things
are translated properly.
Similarly, this NAT on the right, it's
going to when client B sends the traffic.
And so by knowing what the external
address and ports are of the other side,
they can force the NAT to set up a
mapping.
So one question is, is there a kind of NAT
or what kinds of NATs would this not work
for this model where client A and client B
simultaneously send traffic to the
external IP address and port that map to
internal IP address and port issues
clients, which were determined earlier by
communicating with the server.
So given we have this, this different
kinds of NAT's, is there a kind of NAT for
which this would not work?
So it turns out this will work for full
cone NATs, because the mappings will work
fine even if the, the, source IP address
and port are different.
It will work for, restricted cone NAT,
because again, we've set up these mappings
which will include the external IP address
of the other NAT.
It'll work for port restricted NATs,
because again, these packets will be
coming from the right UDP ports.
The one class of NAT it won't work for is
a symmetric NAT,
Because when these clients talk to the
server to figure out their IP address and
port, their external ones,
That mapping won't hold when they start
talking to another NAT.
So, just because the server port 30,005,
When client A then tries to send traffic
to the NAT on the right, the, this the NAT
is not going to reuse port 30005.
It's going to allocate a new external port
and so it won't work.
So this is one reason why symmetric NATs
are really frowned upon in the Interent
today.
So we've talked about implications of NATS
to applications and how they have to do
things to set up mappings, or either use
relays or rendezvous services.
So there's another, perhaps even deeper
implication of NATs which is to transport.
So if you think for a second, for a NAT to
set up a mapping, it needs to know what
the transport,
Protocol is.
It needs to know the transport protocol's
header.
So, for example, when it sets up a UDP or
TCP mapping, the NAT needs to know that
this is a TCP segment, this is a UDP
segment, this is where the port number is
in that segment. This is what I need to
rewrite, rhis is where checksums are calculated.
And without that, it can't do it.
So if you deploy, if you say, write a new
transport protocol, use the transport
protocol identifier in an IP packet,
And you try to get it to traverse a NAT, a
NAT will discard it.
It doesn't know the target format.
And so in this way,
You can't really deploy a new transport
protocol on the internet today.
So, there's a chicken and egg problem,
where the people developing that software
and maintaining the NAT software will not
add support for a new transport protocol
until it's very, very popular,
But it won't become very popular until it
works across NATs.
And so, there's this, sort of debate and
philosophical discussion, right, until the
early you know, mid 2000s about how NATs
mean that were basically stuck with TCP,
UDP, and ICMP, right, to have an
application work for real on the internet
at large, it has to use one of those three
transport protocols.
And, so, really, with NATs today, we're
not going to see any new transport
protocols from the Internet.
And, so, this leads to this really big
philosophical debate especially occurring
as nats deployed in the early 2000s.
About, on one hand, nats are astoundingly
useful.
You can reuse addresses.
For security, you know, if I am sitting
behind a NAT, and I happen to have some
vulnerable open ports,
Say, on my Linux machine or my Windows
machine.
Since there's no mapping,
Attackers from outside of the broad
internet can't, can't compromise me,
Right?
So, gives this very simple, I mean, very
sledgehammery but, but very [laugh]
effective just for end users security,
right and not opening connections can be
good.
But, there's also a, they're also
tremendously painful, especially before
NAT started to have standard behavior,
developing applications is really hard.
Imagine, if somebody calls you and says,
hey, your application doesn't work, you
know, sometimes the connection drops.
And it could be something like, it happens
to be that it's when their client is
transitioning from one server to another.
And the NAT is using a symmetric, is a
symmetric NAT, such that the ports are
being reallocated and the connection
breaks.
Really hard to debug.
And so one example, there's this really
famous example is this thing called Speak
Freely, which is this pre-Skype Voice over
IP.
And, basically the guy said, hey I'm going
to stop developing Speak Freely because,
you know, it just doesn't work under NATs
and there's no way to make them work at
NATs.
This was before people figured out all the
hole punching and before the behavior
standard have to do so.
And so, there's this huge philosophical
debate.
NATs good, NATs bad, they break the end
to end argument, but really, it's really.
It's very interesting, but turns out to be
pointless.
I mean, NATs are here to stay.
They're deployed.
They'll always be deployed.
Their advantages, generally, are
considered to outweigh, the disadvantages.
People are going to deploy them, they want
them to work, and you have to work around
them.
But so, what this means is that we in sort
of historically talk about the Internet as
having a narrow waisted IP.
There is a single unifying protocol which
then allows you to have many transfer
protocols above, many link protocols
below, but NATs have changed that.
And so really,
In a practical sense, the new hourglass
includes not only layer three, but also
layer four, because for practical
concerns, we're not going to see new
transport protocols implemented or
deployed.
You can build protocols on top of UDP, and
that's generally what's done today.
Since UDP just provides a nice datagram
service rather than using a transport
identifier at three, at layer three, You
use a port, at layer four.
But this is the world as it is, that now
the new hourglass of the Internet because
the network address translation.
Is IP, then with ICMP, TCP, and UDP, so
you can see how this technology.
Actually cause an architectural shift
within the Internet within the past
decade.