In the last video I told you about
different types of congestion.
The different time scales it can occur at
and what some of the consequences might
be.
We then looked a little bit about the
little bit at the characteristics of
congestion control algorithms that we
might like to try and design.
So we said we wanted high throughput,
We wanted them to be fair amongst the
flows competing for the bottle neck links.
We wanted the control of congestion to be
distributed so that it can scale.
In this video we're going to start looking
at basic approaches to controlling
congestion.
We're going to consider whether the
congestion control should take place in
the network with specific support of the
routers or whether it should be done at
the end host.
And then I'm going to tell you a little
bit about how TCP does it.
We're going to start with the basic
mechanism called AIMD or additive increase
multiplicative decrease and we're going to
study how that works over the next couple
of videos before we look in more detail at
how TCP congestion control really works in
practice.
So I'm going to start with the
consideration of where to put congestion
control.
But you may have already been wondering
why it is that we can't simply use fair
queueing.
Notice that we've already seen a way to
give everyone a fair share of the outgoing
link, by simply decomposing the output
buffer into per flow queues as I've shown
here.
So that I've got multiple flows going
through the network.
Then each flow would be placed into its
own queue.
And then we use a fair-queuing scheduler
to divide-up that egress rate.
Let's say R.
Amongst all of the flows that are
contending for it.
And so if they're all wanting to send at
rate greater than R over two, then they
would each receive R over two, because
that's what affects queueing scheduler
would do.
And in fat,
This will give us a, not only a fair
behavior, it will actually give us the
maxmin fair at every link across the
flows, it'll give us good throughput
whenever there is work to be done.
It will always keep the outgoing line
busy, we say it's more conserving.
So it'll give good throughput on each of
the links.
So, what's wrong with this basic
mechanism?
Well, the first thing is, that, that it
isn't responsive.
It's simply going to divide up the links,
but there's nothing here that will tell
the sources the rate at which they should
send, or give them any indication of how
many packets they should send.
In fact, if they do send, so if these are
each trying to send a, the full blast
rate, so if there are packets coming in
from all directions, trying to, trying to
use these links, then packets will simply
be dropped onto the floor as the buffers
overflow.
We'll end up used, wasting a lot of the
upstream bandwidth.
Delivering packets over links that
eventually get dropped downstream.
So we need a way of signaling back to the
sources, to say give them some indication
of the rate at which they should send or
the number of outstanding packets that
they can have in the network.
So in network based congestion control
there is explicit feedback that comes from
the routers to indicate congestion in the
network.
So for example if I have a source A and a
destination B and then some routers in
between with some links like this.
Let's imagine there are some flows in the
network that are coming in from different
directions going through this router
causing some congestion to take place
right here.
One thing that we can do is if there is
congestion is to try and signal back to A
some signal.
To say there is congestion in the network
you need to reduce the number of packets
that you have outstanding or reduce the
rate at which you send them.
And so the question is, what would we
send?
And how would we get it back to, to A.
We could for example say I'm dropping a
packet or it could a indication of the
occupancy of the buffer, or it could mark
we just crushed some threshold and so
we're, we're getting more congested.
Any of these would be examples of, of, of
congestion.
Another one might be that the outgoing
link has a certain amount of capacity left
over and as, as the capacity gets used up
we send a signal back to say how much of
that capacity is available or it could be
a function of all of the signal that I've
that I've just mentioned.
So the next question is, how do we get
that signal back, and how many bits do we
use to represent it?
If we're sending back the whole queue
occupancy, we'd really like to be able to
send, send a, sizable integer value, to
indicate what the current occupancy is.
That would take a lot of bits, and it
might be complicated.
So in practice, generally, people look for
schemes that use, one, or a couple of
bits, to signal back to the source.
And then the next question is, how do you
get them back to the source?
There's no point in creating a whole
packet, just to send it back to the source
if we can piggyback, on, packets that are
already going by.
So it's fairly common, to use packets, for
example, if, there, if there's a TCP
packet that's coming through, or some kind
of, 2-way communication, to piggyback onto
packets going in one direction, such that
they get sent back in the
acknowledgements, and, and, and eventually
get back to the source.
There's one particular technique that's
called ECN, or explicit congestion
notification, in which the
routers indicate whether they have, have
some degree of congestion, for example,
crossing a threshold.
They then mark bits in packets going
towards the destination, which then copies
those bits back into the acknowledgements
going in the other direction.
The original scheme that was designed to
work somewhat like this was called decbit
that was proposed more than twenty
years ago as a single bit mechanism to
signal to the source to slow down.
So.
Nice advantage of a scheme like this is,
it's simple to understand.
We can see that the signal will directly
control the behavior of the source.
It should be pretty responsive to change,
because we can detect the, the onset of
congestion in the, in the network and be
able to tell the source.
It's distributed in the sense that the
signal is coming back from all of the
routers in the network, and it only
affects the source, and so the source can
make up its decision, make its, make up
its mind how it will process that signal.
And it can be made to be maxmin fair.
So, it can be made to be fair.
But for example, measure the rate of each
flow through the router and pass back the
maxmin fair allocation for each flow.
There are other ways that are simpler for
example using fair queuing as I described
before.
So, network-based could certainly
work.
On the other hand.
It's worth asking the question, of,
whether we actually need, the network, to
provide any congestion notification.
In other words, can we, support congestion
control, without any support from the
network, at all, merely by implementing a
mechanism at the end hosts, where it's
just going to simply observe the network
behavior.
So going to the example that I had before,
if I have end hosts A and B, and then
routers in between.
If I'm able to observe behavior of the
network.
Such that it's enough to be able to decide
at what rate I send or how many
outstanding packets I have in the network
then perhaps we can implement a congestion
control mechanism this way.
This is nice because if it doesn't depend
on the behavior of the routers or it
doesn't behave on them sending specific
information back, we can evolve and adapt
it over time without having to change the
network in between.
We're going to see that TCP does this.
TCP actually does congestion control
purely at the end host by observing the
network behavior.
What it's going to do is, if packets are
dropped along the way.
It's going to observe this through either
a timeout or it will see a sequence of
acknowledgments that are all the same
coming back because the data was missing
and so B is going to keep acknowledging an
earlier piece of data, which it can
interpret as, as data missing and
therefore needing to retransmit it.
So if there's been data that's dropped A
could interpret this as congestion and
then slow down the rate or have a fewer
number of outstanding packets so that it
will reduce the congestion in the network.
So basically A is going to observe, it's
going to act a little bit like it's
observing the behavior in the network and
seeing what happens in terms of timeouts
and duplicate acknowledgments and anything
that indicates a drop.
It could also see an increase in delay or
variance, any of the things that would
indicate to it that congestion is
occurring so that it could change it's
behavior accordingly.
In TCP's case, it actually has to do this
because IP offers no support by default.
IP offers no indication of congestion in
the network.
So when TCP was first conceived, it was
actually by necessity that it would that
it would control congestion this way.
So let me give you a quick introduction to
TCP congestion control.
TCP implements congestion control at the
end host because the network provides  no
support.
It reacts to events observable at the end
host.
In particular it's going to use packet
loss or if it believes that there were
packets that were dropped.
It's going to exploit TCP's sliding
window, that we use for flow control and
retransmissions.
It's going to exploit the fact that that's
there, and it's going to overload it with
a means to control congestion.
And I'm going to be explaining that
shortly.
And the way it's going to do this, is it's
going to try and figure out how many
packets.
It can safely have outstanding in the
network at any time.
And this is a important concept.
Let me repeat it, it's going to try and
figure out how many packets it can safely
have outstanding in the network at any
time.
Now we're familiar with this already with
a sliding window used in TCP, and this
just a reminder of how the sliding window
works.
Recall that the window is sliding over a
stream of bytes, so this is the underlying
steam of bytes that we're sending.
And that is increasing to the right, so
byte zero was somewhere over here.
And the window is telling us data that has
that has been acknowledged.
So this is earlier data which has been
fully acknowledged.
This is outstanding data that is being
sent, but not yet acknowledged.
This is data that's okay to send.
In other words, it's data that we perhaps
haven't sent yet but because it's inside
the window, we're allowed to send it if we
want.
And then there is data that is not okay to
send yet because it's ahead of the window.
The window hasn't slid, over the top of
this yet, because we're still waiting for,
outstanding acknowledgements over here.
Okay, so the sliding window tells us not
only which bytes can be outstanding, but
also how many bytes.
That's the window size and you will recall
that the, the receiver is going to send
back information about what is called the
receive window to tell us how many bytes
we can have outstanding such that
we don't overrun the receiver.
And we're going to see in a minute that
we're going to reuse that mechanism in a
different way at the sender.
But just to give a rough idea of what's
going on.
With the TCP sliding window, here is a
view on a timeline of what's taking place
when packets are sent and received, and
it's going to give us a feeling for how
this is going to work.
So A is allowed to send up to a window's
worth of data and have it outstanding
before it reads, receives any
acknowledgements.
So here is that window of, of data.
And when those, when those packets are
sent, of course each one of them is going
to lead to an acknowledgement.
So sometime later, we are going to get
the, the acknowledgements and then we're
going to send the next window's worth of
data.
So if the round trip time is much bigger
than the window size.
In other words, the time is much bigger
than the amount of data it takes to fill
that pipe.
Then there will be this big delay in
between and TCP will basically move
forward by sending a window in a burst.
Pausing and waiting for acknowledgements.
Sending a window in a burst, having a
pause and then just repeating like that.
So that's in this particular case.
Now let's consider a different case.
And that is when the round trip time equals
the window size.
In other words, the window is exactly able
to fill up the pipe.
The number of outstanding packets that
we're allowed to have in the network
precisely fills the pipe.
In this particular case, the first
acknowledgement will come back just after
the last packet is being sent.
And so, we're able to send in a continuous
stream.
And so there are no pauses.
Therefore we're using the network more
fully then in this case when we've got
this idle time.
So this gives us a hint as to our ability
to keep the network full.
Some people would interpret this as a rate
because it's the window size divided by
the round trip time.
And we're going to look, we're going to
consider that a little bit later.
So that's the basic idea of how this is
going to work.
More specifically.
With TCP congesting control.
TCP is going to vary the number of
outstanding packets in the network by
varying the window size.
And it's going to set the window size,
instead of just being the advertised
window which is what it used
before, which came from the receiver to
stop overwhelming the receiver.
It's also going to take into consideration
something called the congestion window.
This is something which is calculated at
the source.
So the advertise window comes from the
receiver, and at the source, or the
transmitter, it's going to calculate the
congestion window, that's often
abbreviated to CWND.
C, W, N, D stands for congestion window.
And then it will take whichever is the
smaller value.
In other words, if the network is
congested, then it's going to use CWND,
and if the network is not congested, then
it will be dominated by the receive
window, the one advertised by the
receiver.
So the next question to ask is, okay, how
do we decide the value for CWND?
How will we going to use CWND in order to
change the window size to control
congestion in the network?
And the scheme that we're going to use is
called AIMD.
And this is a sort of a classic technique
in, in networking that's used for
controlling congestion in a TCP network.
Alright, and, and it could be used in any
network that uses sliding windows.
AIMD stands for additive increase and
multiplicative decrease.
Let's start with the additive increase.
The way the window size is going to evolve
is as follows, or, or rather CWND.
If every time a packet is received
correctly by the sender it's going to
increase the window size, in fact CWND,
By one over W.
What this means is that every time a
complete window's worth of data has been
accepted, has been correctly received and
acknowledged, then the sender is going to
increase its window size by one.
It will increase it by 1/W for every
packet, because there are W packets, then
by the end of the window it will have
increased it by one.
So this is the additive increase.
It's going to slowly increase when things
are going well.
If things are going badly and packets are
dropped, then it's going to use this as a
signal of congestion.
And if that happens it's going to reduce
the CWND by a factor of two.
It's going to halve it.
What this will look like is, if we draw
the window as a function of time.
So this will be the CWND as a function
of time.
It's going to start by increasing.
Every time we have a success.
And then when we have a drop.
So here is the drop taking place here.
It's going to drop down.
To halve its, half of its value.
So if this is the peak value then this
value down here would be, that would be
peak over two.
And then it's going to start increasing
again and increasing, increasing until it
has another drop.
And then it's going to increase again, and
increase again.
And it could go up to a higher value
because now the network may be allowed
more outstanding packets, come down to a
different value, and then go up.
And then there might be another drop.
So it isn't always going to go in this
nice neat symmetrical Sawtooth.
This is where the drops are taking place.
And it's halving at each case.
So here is the additive increase, here is
the multiplicative decrease.
The additive increase, the multiplicative
decrease.
This is often referred to as the TCP
Sawtooth or the AIMD Sawtooth.
Just because of its shape.
If we zoom in, let's take a closer look at
what's going on at each step.
So let's take a closer look at what's
going on here.
This is actually proceeding by going in
steps.
Remember it's going in steps such that
every packet time, it's going to increase
by 1/W.
And I'm going to simplify that by saying
every RTT.
This horizontal dimension is time.
It's going to increase by one.
The window sizes are going to increase by
one.
Because every time we've acknowledged a
complete pack-, window's worth of data,
it's going to increase the window size by
one.
So it's going to go forward in the steps
of RTT along the horizontal part of the
stair, then it's going to by one, then RTT
and so on.
So this leads to what's often called the
AIMD Sawtooth, or the TCP Sawtooth that
can look like this.
This is an evolution of CWND.
Remember that's the congestion window as a
function of time.
So here was the additive increase, we had
a drop, we dropped down to half the value,
we had an additive increase, we dropped
down because of a drop that took place
here.
And then we go up again through the
additive increase and you can see here the
available window size, in other words the
amount of data that the, that the source
can have outstanding in the network is
varying presumably because the network
conditions are changing.
There are other flows in the network or
maybe even the capacity of the links is
changing.
Maybe they're wireless links for example.
So in summary, we have choice when we're
implementing a congestion control
algorithm.
We can im, implement it in the network, or
we can implement it at the end host.
TCP controls congestion from the end host,
because IP offers it no support by
default, so it gives it no signals or
indication of congestion, other than
dropping packets.
So it merely reacts to events that are
observable at the end host, in particular,
packet loss.
It exploits TCP's sliding window and it's,
that's used for flow control and it's
going to overload that sliding window by
changing the window size to try and
control congestion.
It tries to figure out how many packets it
can safely have outstanding in the network
at one time.
And it's going to vary that window size
according to the additive increase
multiplicative decrease algorithm.
And we're going to be studying that more
in the next two videos.