So in this video about the physical layer,
we're going to talk about two things.
First, capacity, that is how you determine
how many bits per second a given physical
layer can support.
And then modulation, how is it you
represent these bits on the medium itself.
So it turns out that there's a theoretical
limit on how much information a given
channel can carry.
Well, in this case, a channel means a
medium in which you're putting your
information.
This channel could be, say a wire or
wireless.
It could be sound waves,
Whatever you want.
It's just a term that's used to talk about
the way in which the information is being
communicated.
And says, this limit is called the, the
Shannon limit, after Claude Shannon who
established it.
And so, it turns out that if you look at
a given communication channel and under, a
certain set of assumptions that often
hold pretty well.
This is a very good approximation because
you could good sense as to, to, what's,
what's possible.
The channel capacity or the number of bits
per second you can send over a given
channel is B
Log2 (1 + the signal to noise ratio), where B is the bandwidth
of your communication, that is with the
range of frequencies you can use.
That's assuming that we're doing things
with basically sinusoidal waves etcetera.
S is the signal strength, so how strong is
the signal when it arrives at the receiver
and N is the noise.
So any receiver is going to have some kind
of noise, in the same way that when you
are listening, you might think you hear
sounds but there are sounds that are too
faint for you to hear. And it's because those
sounds are essentially below the noise
sensitivity of your ears.
Or in the same way if there is a white
noise generator in the room, it can make
it harder to hear things because there is
this noise.
And so, all communication devices have
noise.
Often it's just due to thermal properties
of the hardware.
There are just stray electrons from thermal
effects that introduce some noise into the
system.
It's a big thing in engineering on how do
you bring the noise down?
And so what the, the basic point here is
that, the amount that we can send is
proportional to the amount of bandwidth we
have, like how large a chunk of
frequencies we can use and then the signal
to noise ratio.
Now, if we want a higher signal to noise
ratio, it's just the Signal divided by the noise.
It requires either you have lower noise,
that can be really expensive it's you
know, harder to make hardware with, with
lower noise or a stronger signal requires
that the signal be louder.
This for example, why when you have more
bars on your phone it goes faster because
the data rate is
faster because the signal to noise ratio is higher.
And turns out that building hardware for
very high bandwidth, so signals that have
a tremendous bandwidth, is actually really
hard.
All these complications come into play.
So it's not like you can just easily build
a communication system with arbitrary
channel capacity.
There are all these engineering things
which come into play, which is why we
don't suddenly see you know, a terabit
Ethernet.
But some fundamentals, we're talking about
the capacity of a channel, we are talking about
bandwidth and signal to noise. The way to
think about this is and this is how we
generally represent signals is in terms of
analog signals, so think sinusoids.
And so when we are talking about
sinusoidal waves here's a simple, here's a
simple one here, there are a couple of
properties we care about that I'm going to
talk about in the rest of this and some
future videos.
The first is the amplitude of the wave.
So this is,
So the amplitude denotes the actual, one
way to think of it is that how loud it is,
the signal strength, loudness.
Signal strength .
Second property is the wavelength, so how
long is one of these waves?
So the speed of light is approximately,
so C, is
approximately one foot per nanosecond,
that's a good, rough rule of thumb.
And so one billion
feet per second.
And so if for example, I'm sending a
signal whose wavelength is one foot, this
would mean that it has a, wave length of
one foot, since the wave is traveling,
one billion feet per second and this
means that there must be one billion waves
per second.
It's because there's, this waves traveling
at a billion feet per second, the wave
length is a foot, must have a billion
waves per second.
So this gives me the frequency, so how
many waves do I expect a second, so
1 billion per second turns out to be one
gigahertz.
So one gigahertz wave, in this is
electromagnetics, this is light.
just at lower frequencies.
A 1-foot, a 1-gigahertz signal is, has a
wavelength of about a foot.
So, WiFi today, for example, operates at
2.4 gigahertz,
Around five gigahertz So, these have wavelengths
of approximately five inches and, you
know, 2.4 inches.
So here I'm talking about the frequency,
the wave length of a given wave the
amplitude of a given wave, but it turns
out that when we send signals you don't
use a single frequency, we actually use a
range of frequencies.
It's the bandwidth is the size of the
frequency ranges we use. For example, if
you look at one WiFi standard 802.11b,
it's an older one, it's going to, we use
as a common example because it's one of
the simpler ones since it's older. in
802.11b, if you, those of you who've used
it, you have to select a channel, so
channels one through eleven.
Often people use one, six, and eleven.
Each of these channels is twenty megahertz
wide,
And so when you look at a frequency amount
for 802.11b.
You can see that all these channels, and
here's one, and here's eleven, and they
take up about twenty megahertz of the
frequency range, like so.
And so you actually use a range of
frequencies, and I'll show you sort of why
this happens and how this happens.
So finally there's what we call phase.
And so this is actually the timing of the
waves within a wavelength.
So here we have, here's a wave which is at
this particular phase, where the peak is
occurring here.
So let's call this t0. It's of course,
possible to send this exact same wave,
but, at a different phase.
For example, we could send it like this.
It's the same wave, but its phase is, its
phase is offset by one half, of, the
wavelength, and therefore, 180 degrees.
And so, it turns out that things we do to
control, as we'll see in a second, that we
do to control waves, that we do to send
signals involve changing the amplitude of
waves, changing the frequency of waves, as
well as changing the phase of these waves.
But fundamentally, these waves are what's
going on underneath in the system.
So, given that we are using waves, there's
a whole bunch of ways we can represent
bits.
There's, this one is the simplest way is,
let me call it amplitude shift keying or
ASK.
What's this, this process is called
modulation.
How do I take a signal or take a
particular bit of piece of data and then
modulate my waves to represent that
signal?
So, here I'll try to represent that data.
How I modulate the signal to represent the
data?
So, here for example, I have an amplitude
shift keying where one has a small
amplitude sorry, zero has a smaller
amplitude and one has a larger amplitude.
So if I want to send a zero, I send a
smaller wave, and I want to send a one, I
send this larger wave.
Another approach that you can use is
something called frequency shift keying
where you use two separate frequencies and
so here's a one and here's a zero.
The zero happens to be the higher
frequency,
The one is the lower frequency.
And then as I want to send out of stream
of 0s and 1s, I just move these
frequencies back and forth.
Oh, I'm sending one, one, one, so it's
longer, longer, longer then zero, zero,
zero, shorter, shorter, shorter.
The other side can decode these and then
figure out what bits are being sent.
So amplitude shift keying turns out to be
very, it's very commonly used especially
in wired networks.
And the reason is that when you have a
wire, your medium is controlled.
The signal, you put it on one side, it
decreases a little bit on the other side,
but not by very much.
Wires do not have a lot of resistance,
That's why we use them to, to carry power.
And so, amplitude shift keying is commonly
used in wired systems.
Just because it's very simple,
And it, it works great.
So, most common wired Ethernet today uses
amplitude shift keying.
For example 100BASE-T and 1000BASE-T,
This is a 100 megabit and gigabit ethernet
use what's called PAM-5, which means five
levels of amplitude modulation.
They're called pulses, because you're
sending pulses at these different
amplitudes.
So think of these basically as voltages
-two -one, zero, +one, +two.
And so, you're sending these different
voltages along the wire.
It turns out, ten base, a 10GBASE-T or ten
gigabit ethernet, more like the sort of upcoming
standards people are adopting needs to use
more levels of amplitudes in order to get
all of its data through.
And so, it uses PAM-16, so, it's sixteen
levels rather than five.
So another form of modulation that's very
popular, is what's called phase shift
keying.
So, unlike amplitude shift keying where we are
adjusting amplitude of the waves, or frequency
shift keying where we are using different
frequencies, the phase shift keying uses
the phase of the waves.
So, here for example, let's say zero, this
is the phase of zero degrees, but then to
send a one, as you can see, my phase is
reversed. This is a phase of 180 degrees
right or -180 degrees, the two are the
same.
Here I send the zero again, I start
sending at a phase of zero degrees again.
So, phase shift keying is really useful
when your channel, when your medium is
such that you can have significant
variations in signal strength.
So amplitude shift keying, you need to got
to figure out all the different amplitudes
are, so in the amplitudes when the actual
attenuation with signal strength is stable
like in a wire, that's great.
But, for example in wireless situations,
amplitude is a bit harder. Phase
can be much easier.
So situations where phase shift keying is used
are, I'd say, DSL, Digital Subscriber
Lines, you'll have better along long
phones lines, where there could be weather
and wire shaking, and bad connections, but
really long wires. Cable modems, right,
that are stretching out through an entire
neighborhood, wireless systems, these all
use phase shift keying.
On some, they also use amplitude but
they, unlike, you know, wired Ethernet,
all these systems use phase.
And so one kind of phase shift keying is
binary phase shift keying or BPSK.
And so basically you have two phases zero,
zero degrees and pi or a 180 degrees.
And so I can now prior picture, you're
either sending something at this phase,
let's say that's zero or you're sending it
at this phase,
Which is say 180 degrees, this is 180
degrees,
Pi.
That's, this is zero, zero.
So example, BPSK is used in 802.11b, an
older WiFi standard, at low speeds,
One megabit and two megabit per second.
There is also a Quadrature phase shift
keying, QPSK.
Where now we have four phases.
You can imagine just as we have zero and
180 degrees, in QPSK we have zero, 90
degrees, 180 degrees, 270 or zero, pi/2,
pi, 3pi/2 radians and degrees
respectively.
So, it turns out QPSK is also used in this
older WiFi standard, 802.11b, it is used
at the higher speeds,
5.5 megabits per second and eleven
megabits per second.
Now one thing you should come out from
this is that the reason why we might use
QPSK versus BPSK or PAM-16 rather than
PAM-5.
Is that for a given signal we're sending, we
can send more information.
Sor example, BPSK, each wave we send
carries one bit of information. Is it zero
or pi?
In contrast for QPSK, each symbol that we
send on the waves,
Each little chunk of data we're sending on
the physical layer contains two bits.
Is it zero, pi over two, pi, or three pi
over two?
So we can represent those as 00, 01, 10,
11.
It's not actually how it's done, but the
idea is actually, by having these denser
representation you're sending more
information per unit time.
Now, one reason that phase keying is very
popular is actually as it turns out, it's
very easy to shift phase.
So for example here, if I just have a
carrier wave at, say zero degrees, and
another carrier wave, you know, at -90
degrees.
Then any linear combination of these two
allows me to create any intermediate
frequencies.
So for example here, if I combine zero
degrees to -90 degrees just add these two
waves up, I'll get something at
minus 45 degrees.
That's if its a, you know, sort of one to
one equality. If for example instead I did
0.5,1,
Then we'd have something a little closer
to, to the zero degrees right, assuming
that this is the -90 degrees and this is
the zero degrees.
Okay? Similarly if I did rather than 1,1
if I did -1, 1, so this is -90
degrees this is zero degrees, then what
we'd see is rather than a wave between
these two the wave would be,
The wave would be here.
Right? It would be at +45 degrees with
this setting.
And so just from these two things you can
combine and create any intermediate
frequency you want which turns out to be
really useful in hardware.
And in fact that is exactly how hardware
does it using something called I/Q
Modulation.
So I means the in-phase component so it's
zero degrees.
Q is the quadrature component at -90
degrees. This is just complex way of
saying hey if we want to create any,
Any phase between zero and I'm going to
say 300 and, you know, zero and basically
-zero wrapping around,
We can just combine these I and q with
some linear factor and get that.
So for example let's look at those two
thing, two things we had, BPSK AND QPSK, so
BPSK has two phases zero and a 180
degrees.
What are the I/Q value's of those?
Well, so for zero degrees, it's going to
be 1,0.
Right?
For a 180 degrees, well, that's the
opposite of zero.
Right?
If you would think about it, you know, on
the unit circle, say here is zero, here is
180 degrees.
So just as we have +1 and here we're
going to have -1, So -1, 0.
For QPSK, we have four phases, let's say
zero, 270, 180, and 90.
So, again, zero is going to be 1, 0.
But now, 270, alright, 270 is down here.
Right? 270 is down here, right? So here is
-90/ 270.
Right?
So, 270 is going to be 0, 1.
180 is going to be just like in BPSK,
-1, 0 and 90 is going to be 0,
-1.
And so we can, just by changing the
scaling factors of the I and the Q, create
any phase we want of a signal.
That's exactly kind of how it looks like
in hardware, is that we have these IQ
values coming in,
These digital values.
Then we have these two carrier
frequencies, and we had, adding them up to
come out in RF, since then this is what comes out
of the antenna.
This is actually how you build the
hardware, this IQ, this IQ values.
But what's really available, and the
reason why I am going into them, but I/Q
constellations is that they actually lend
themselves for really, really simple and
easy to understand graphical
representation of whats going on down at the
physical layer.
And so the way to think of it, is if we take
these IQ values and we represent them on
an 2D grid, right, we can use what's
called a /Q Constellation, this 2D plot.
In this case, in these 2D plots, the angle
of your vector, represents the phase of
the signal, right like here say we have 45
degrees, right here we have 135 degrees.
And then the length of this vector
represents the amplitude of this signal.
So, if we look at something like on-off
keying where you either send something or
it's silent,
We see here's an amplitude of one,
amplitude of zero.
There's our on-off keying.
Right? There's no shift in phase.
Amplitiude shift keying, where we have two
different amplitudes used.
See, here's a one and here's a zero.
We're just changing the amplitudes.
We're not actually changing the phase,
we're just changing the value of i.
Bpsk, remember there are two phases zero
and 180, hence that's what we see here. So
here is 180 to say represent the one and
here's zero, say to represent the zero.
Qpsk, also has four, has four points with
these four different phases.
I could've also,  rotated them and
say drawn them like this, but still easier
to see them when they're these four
corners like this.
This is a way to represent what the
wireless signal is.
It's a nice pictorial representation, we
start talking about signal or noise and
those ratios will start, things will start
to make a little more sense, will be
really clear depiction of what's
happening.
And so just recall, we can represent any
intermediate phase from this zero and -90,
There's just some linear combination with
those two.
Now, at some point, at the link layer, we
have bits.
Bits are coming in.
We have some packet, you know, from the
network layer, and we have some frame at
the link layer with some bits in it,
Zero, one, one, zero, zero, one, one,
organized into bytes, into octets,
however.
But down to physical layer, we don't
necessarily, can't necessarily transmit a
whole byte,
It might be that we can only transmit a
couple bits at, at a time.
And so in the physical layer, we talk
about symbols.
And a symbol is the unit of, is the unit
of transfer that the physical layer can
provide.
So often, we talk about things at the link
layer,
We talk about, oh, we add a byte,
But that might not be the boundary down at
the physical layer.
The reasons is we sort, is what I talked
about before, a symbol can contain more
than one bit.
So BPSK has one bit per symbol, there's
two phases.
Qpsk has four phases, has two bits per
symbol.
But then you also get situations like,
like a PAM5 that's used in a 100 megabit
and one gigabit Ethernet on a Cat-5 cable
where there are these five voltage levels.
There are five different symbols that you
can use, and that doesn't necessarily map
perfectly, to, a number of bits, right,
five symbols, is just over two bits.
It's as important to realize that,
although, I'll put the link layer even
past down to the physical layer sequence
of bits, there's this transformation that
occurs turning that sequence of bits into
a sequence of symbols, down at the
physical layer.
So finally I talked about amplitude
keying, I've talked about phase keying.
There's this approach you use today, it's
very, very common, you see it in almost
all modern communication systems, it's
called QAM which really stands for,
Quadrature Amplitude Modulation, or
basically, this means phase and amplitude
keying at the same time.
And so, whereas ASK, amplitude shift
keying is only the amplitude, and phase
shift keying is only the phase, in QAM we
use both.
So to give you an example, the way this is
originally talked about,
Say sixteen QAM means that we have sixteen
different symbols, and so we can
represent, for each symbol we can
represent four bits.
256 QAM means there's 256 different
symbols which means we can represent for
each symbol we can represent eight bits.
And so returning to the IQ plot, or the
modulation plot.
Here is what sixteen QAM looks like.
So this is the constellation, the I/Q
constellation used in HSPDA, which is a 3G
data standard.
And so, as you can see there are these
values from three, three to -three, -three
and they map to different bits.
And so, here I've shown in gray the I and
Q values, right, so here's an I of three a
Q of one, I of three Q of three, I of -one
Q of three, Q of one, sorry. And then what
the represented bits are above the
physical layer.
And so here's an example I/Q constellation
for sixteen QAM, and as we can see, it's
adjusting not only the amplitude, that is
the length of the vector, coming out of
the, the origin, but also the phase, which
is the orientation of the vector coming
out, of the origin.
So here's an example, I/Q constellation,
used in modern 3G systems, sixteen QAM,
sixteen different symbols, and here's how,
bits mapped to these symbols.
So for example, if I wanted to send, 1011
1001,
I would send 1011,
So it sends this first.
Right.
This will be the first symbol that I send,
number one.
Then 1001, I would send this symbol,
Second. And so if we're to go down and dig
into and see what's happening down in the
physical layer, we're going to see a
signal transmitted, with a phase, of,
what's essentially, 135 degrees, right,
this is, 135 degrees, and an amplitude of,
let's, say of x, then the next symbol, is
going to be,
With this angle, right, with this phase,
which is, you know, approximately, let's
say, 105 degrees and a slightly smaller
amplitude.
And it's slightly smaller amplitude,
right, because this vector is longer.
And that's what you actually see in terms
of the waves in the physical layer.
So what's used today?
Well ASK, amplitude shift keying is
basically all the wired Ethernet uses amplitude
shift keying.
Its very rare for communication systems to
use frequency shift keying.
There are some examples like the National
Weather Services Weatheradio and Bluetooth
actually uses it in some forms.
Binary phase shift keying is used
basically by all the WiFi standards, abgn,
its also used in WiMax.
Quadrature Phase Shift Keying is used in WiFi,
there's low power wireless, liked Zigbee,
called 802.15.4.
3G, LTE, WiMAX, 16-QAM, is used in
wifi, as well as these data standards for,
cellular phones, for mobile phone, mobile
telephony.
64 QAM is used in WiFi, so it's LTE and
WiMAX.
And so, as you can see, that, there are
these, the, the older, that the more
modern standards are the ones using the
denser constellation, because people have
made things go faster and faster.
So here's an overview, there are many
different ways, that you can take your
bits, and then represent them, in terms
of, a physical medium, convert them into
voltages, phases, frequencies, etcetera.
Wired Ethernet and wired systems often use
amplitude to represent signals.
Whereas Most technologies today like
wireless technologies or things that are
over less controlled media like cable
modems, DSl.
Use phase shift keying or a combination of
phase and amplitude called QAM, quadrature
amplitude modulation.
And one of the key things you can
represent a QAM symbol, in fact, any of
these as a linear combination of two
things,
That the, the in-phase component I at zero
degrees and a quadrature component q at
-90 degrees.
This is actually how, how circuits do it
today and what's really nice is that it
gives you a very good pictorial
representation of what the signal looks
like, and how it's controlled, and how
it's modulated, and how those map to bits.