This video is going to dig into the
details of TCP connection setup and
teardown.
This is a deeper look than sort of, the
initial service model we presented.
Looking at a couple of edge cases and the
entire TCP state diagram.
So, we're going to look at 3-way
handshake, something called simultaneous
open which turns out to be really
important today in peer to peer
applications, and actually show the full
TCP state machine for connection setup and
teardown.
So, the high level problem here is, if we
want to communicate reliably, it turns out
it's very helpful to have state on one or
both ends of the connection.
You can, in fact, turn, turns out you can
communicate reliably with having something
stateless on one end or the other, but
it's much less efficient.
Having a little bit of state is great,
it'll make you have much better
throughput, etc..
But, if we have this state, there's this
problem of, how do we set up that state?
What is it?
So, connection establishment.
But then, also, given the state's going to
us to take, take up RAM in your machine,
when can you tear it down?
When is, can you, sort of, garbage collect
this state, and reuse it?
So, for example, the memory structures
using for your TCP connection, the buffers
are also the port numbers that you used.
So, there are these problems of connection
establishment and teardown.
So, here's the standard TCP header with
its standard twenty byte payload, and then
options.
So, for connection set up, as we've seen
before, there are four parts of the header
that are used.
The sequence number, the acknowledgment
number, the ACK bit and the SYN bit. So,
here, I'm going to walk through the 3-way
handshake in a little bit more detail as
to what happens in the packets that are
exchanged.
So, recall in the standard 3-way handshake
model, we have an active opener and a
passive opener.
The passive opener is sitting, listening,
waiting for a connection request, such as
a web server.
The active opener is the one who initiates
the request, the request to start the
connection.
So, in the first step, the active opener
sends a TCP segment with the SYN bit set
to indicate that its synchronizing the
passive side to the beginning of its stream
it saying what is the first sequence
number of my stream?
And so, let's call it S sub a. So, you do
this rather than just say assume zero for
a bunch of reasons.
Number one, it's very helpful to randomize
your starting sequence number for security
reasons.
It means that people can't guess where
your stream starts and try to insert data
on you.
Also, it's useful if there happen to be
old packets flying around the internet,
which sometimes happens, you get
tremendous delays somewhere.
If you randomize your starting sequence
number, then it becomes very unlikely that
some random segment, or perhaps a
corrupted segment is going to overlap your
own sequence window.
So, the active side sends a SYN saying,
This is my starting sequence number, S sub
a.
The passive side responds, also with the
SYN saying, okay, that's, I'm going to
synchronize you.
My starting sequence number is let's say,
S sub p, for passive. But, I'm also going
to set the ACK bit which means that the
acknowledgement sequence number in the
packet is valid.
And I'm going to ACK S(a+1).
Recall that a node acknowledges not the
last byte received, but rather the first
byte that hasn't been received.
So, by sending ACK S(a+1), the passive
side has acknowledged that it has received
the SYN which is effectively by S sub a.
The active side then responds.
It doesn't need to send the SYN because it's
synchronized.
So, it sends a packet with sequence number
S(p+1), that's commonly what's used.
and ACK S, I'm sorry,
It sends the packet with S(a+1) and ACK
S(p+1)
And, so now, it's acknowledging saying, I
have received your SYN and I'm
acknowledging that.
Now, this initial packet, the sequence
number is S(a+1) but it tends to be of
zero length.
So, if there were a byte in the packet, it
would be Sa(a+1) but it's not, and this
is of length zero.
This is a, just a, a simple control
packet.
And so, there's a sequence number of which
the bytes would start, but there are no
bytes.
So, that's the basic connection setup.
SYN, SYN ACK, ACK, A, A + one, P, P + one,
and then an empty segment just for
connection establishment.
So, turns out TCP also supports another
way of opening connections, one that's called
simultaneous open, which I said is used a
lot, as you'll see later, in the course in
peer to peer applications to reverse
things called network address translation
boxes.
And so, the way simultaneous open works is
this happens if both the active, if the
two sides, we call them active and passive
but now they're really both active,
Both know each other's port numbers.
So, the node on the left knows that the
port that the node on the right is issuing
a connection request from, the node on the
right knows the same for the node on the
left.
And so, they're using the correct port
numbers.
And they do this, they negotiate this, say,
beforehand.
So, what happens with simultaneous open is
both sides send SYNs at the same time.
And so, here the one on the left sends a
SYN. Let's call this S sub a again. But,
at the same time, then on the right sends
a SYN S sub p.
Well then, on the left, responds and it
sends SYN S sub a,
Ack S sub p + one.
Similarly, the one on the right responds
with SYN S sub p, ACK S sub a + one. At
this point, we have now established the
connection. Both sides are synchronized we
know the starting sequence numbers
that acknowledged that. but note that this
takes four messages rather than three.
So, let's see this just a standard 3-way
handshake and practice.
So, here I've opened up Wireshark, filtering
on port 80 and a certain IP address.
And so, I'm just going to telnet to a port
80 on that host and we'll see the SYN, SYN
ACK, ACK set up.
And so, there it is.
So, here's the first packet sent from my
host to the destination.
And we see that it's an HTTP port 80 SYN
sequence number zero.
And there's no ACK sent,
There's no ACK bit.
And so, the acknowledgement field's
invalid, so it's not displayed.
Now, it turns out the sequence in this
packet isn't actually zero.
What tools like Wireshark do, just to make
things easier to read is they use relative
sequence numbers.
They show you what the sequence number is
relative to the beginning of the stream.
And since were just starting the stream,
we see sequence number zero.
We dig inside the packet, down here at the
bottom we see.
Wireshark tells you, sequence number zero
relative sequence number.
And if we then look at the actual field,
it's ccbd1dbb.
And so, it's much larger than zero.
Now, we do then see is for the second
packet that's acknowledging this.
It's going to acknowledge with ccbd1dbc.
Here again, it's using relative ACK
numbers but that's what we see,
Ccbd1dbc.
And, it's also sending a, a SYN, so here's
the SYN ACK.
And so, the sequence number again, a
relative sequence number of zero but it's
341135ae. So, this is from my host to the
server.
This is server back or the SYN ACK.
Then, my host responds with an ACK. And
so, you can see sequence number one.
Acknowledgment number one, so it's
acknowledging the SYN that was sent from
the server and it gives a sequence
number one but it's a length of zero.
And so, it's saying a-ha, you know, I,
this packet contains the stream starting
at byte one, but there's nothing in it so
there's actually no data yet.
So, there we see a simple 3-way
handshake..so So now, let's look at a TCP
connection when there is data, so we're
going to see the SYN, SYN ACK, and then
some data communication.
So, we do the same thing as before except
this time rather than tellnetting to port
80 where there's no data transferred, I'm
just going to do a standard web, web
request to port 80. And so, here we
see a TCP connection.
And so, here we have the SYN, SYN ACK,
Ack. Now, the connection has been
established and then data transmission
starts.
And so, here's a packet shown as HTTP.
And if we look inside,
This particular TCP segment, see sequence
number one, just the start of the data
stream.
Length 474, so this particular chunk of
data was 474 bytes long.
So, the next sequence number would be 475,
still ACK one.
And so, there's the data that we're
sending a request to the web
server,
Then the web server responds. And it
responds with ACK 475,
Right? So, the next byte it will expect is
475 but sequence number one.
So, this is just length zero, this ACK, it
has no data in it.
This is what we call sort of just ACK
packet.
And so, it has no TCP segment data, but
it's acknowledging the data that is
received.
The next packet, though, from the server
actually has data in it.
So, you can see here, length 1448,
but sequence number one.
So, it's one  to 1449.
And here's the next TCP segment. And then
we see here, putting that together,
there's the HTTP response which is put
together. And so, there we see the
connection establishment and now the
sequence and acknowledged number of spaces
are walking forward according to the data
communication.
So, next we're going to look at how TCP
tears down a connection. Like a, a
connection setup, the uses the sequence
number, acknowledgement number fields. But
unlike connection setup which use the
synchronization bit to synchronize
sequence numbers, connection teardown uses
the FIN bits to denote there's no more
data to send, so it uses the ACK in FIN
bits.
And so, when TCP sends a packet with the
FIN bit.
What this means is that, that sender has
no more data to send,
This is the end of the stream.
This is causing you to say, call close or
shut down, in the application.
But, TCP connections, like most reliable
connections, are bidirectional.
And so, it's not until both sides have
nothing to send that you actually
terminate the connection because it could
be one side is done but the other side has
more to send.
And so, it's not until both sides have,
have FINed and you've acknowledged those
that you can tear things down.
So, a typical teardown exchange looks like
this where we say, if A and B who are
communicating, and A closes first.
And so, it sends a packet with a FIN bit
with sequence number S sub A and
acknowledging S sub B.
B then sends a packet to aknowledge this
FIN, so ACK S sub A + one.
Then, at some point later, B decides it
needs to close it's side of the connection
so it sends a FIN, sequence number S sub B
Acknowledgment S sub one is still
acknowledging Sa + one, which then A
responds saying, I'll acknowledge Sb +
one.
So, FIN like SYN represents of the last
byte of the connection.
The way that you, like SYN represents the
first byte, the way you acknowledge by is
acknowledging plus one with FIN, you
acknowledge you receive it by
acknowledging plus one.
Of course, you, you can have also
simultaneous close, where they send the
FINs in parallel and the same exchange
occurs.
Great. So now, we've exchanged these
messages and we've acknowledged them.
When can we actually tear down the
connection?
When can we actually delete the state?
When can we reuse the ports?
This turns out to be nontrivial.
You can't do it immediately.
So, for example, what happens if this
final ACK is lost in the network?
So, I've sent FIN, then I receive a FIN
then I ACK it,
I can't immediately teardown my connection
because, what happens if that ACK is lost?
The other side's never going to hear it.
It's never going to know whether the
connection was, torn down.
Another issue is it could be that we do a
FIN, FIN ACK, and an acknowledgement
teardown and then the same port pair, the
same port pair is used immediately for a
new connection.
We want to make sure that we don't, by
accident, then corrupt the data because
the sequence number of spaces overlap.
So, the solution is used is the active closer
goes to something called, time wait.
And what this means is that, if I'm the
person who sends the FIN first, then, once
the connection is torn down, I have to
wait a little while before I can reuse my
state.
And so, you keep the socket around for
two, what's, sort of the maximum segment
lifetimes.
So, two times what you expect to be the
longest time, segments might live in the
network which is on the order of a, say a
minute or so.
So, this approach of two maximum segment
lifetimes can pose problems with servers.
In particular, if I have a server and it
has tons and tons of sockets which is in
this time wait state, this can slow things
down, the server, when closing first.
There are tricks.
You can send a reset, delete the socket,
you can set an option to make the, the
linger time to be zero.
Another issue is the OS might not let you
reuse a port because it's still in use.
There is an option you can do called
SOREUSEADDR that'll let you to rebind a
port number.
So, this is useful if say, you're just
de-bugging something and gosh, I don't
want to have to wait two hours just
because I happened to have FINed in this
order.
So, let's see what a connection teardown
looks like.
So, here's a basic connection set up, SYN,
SYN ACK, ACK, and then here's the
teardown.
So, because we are, are exchanging
data, we have acknowledgement  bit set.
So, here's the FIN,
Here's the initial FIN from my host when I
close the connection.
And so, it sets the FIN bit ACK one
sequence number one, ACK one.
Then, the server, in response, is also,
closing, so it sends a FIN sequence number
one, ACK two.
So, it's acknowledging my FIN.
And then, my host responds with an ACK,
for that FIN sequence number two, ACK two.
So, here's a simple 3-way handshake for
tearing down the connection.
FIN,
Acknowledging some prior data,
Acknowledging the FIN, sending your own
FIN, and then acknowledging the FIN.
So now, if we put all of this together, we
can see what the full TCP finite state
machine looks like.
And so, this something you're going to
come across many, many times.
This is well-established finite state
machine that really sort of, lays the
ground for how you want to set up reliable
connections.
And so, I'm going to walk through it.
It looks pretty complicated when you first
see but it's because there are a couple of
cases.
And actually, given what we've presented
before, it should all, all be pretty
simple.
So first, we're starting in the close
state.
So, this is when there are no connections
open, you know, I'm just sitting there.
My application's now tried to open a
connection.
So then, the first transition here to the
listen state,
This is the passive opener.
This is a server.
Server's listening to connections.
So, you can see, the action is listen and
there's no packets exchanged.
If you close it, you then return to the
close state.
So, that is if I'm listening for
connections, I hear nothing and return to
the closed state.
The other transition out of the closed
state is the active open. So, here's the
connect. And connect causes a SYN packet
to be sent so this is step one of the
3-way handshake..
So, you send a SYN and you're now in the
SYN send state, SYN send state, this is
the active side.
These red lines are showing the active
opener of the 3-way connection. So, SYN
sent.
Then, if you receive a SYN in ACK, so this
is the stage two.. You send an ACK, and
now the connection's established.
So, this path here,
This is the active opener.
Now, let's watch the passive opener.
The passive opener is in the listen state,
and it receives a SYN from an active
opener. In response, it sends a SYN ACK
enters the SYN receive state.
Then, if it receives an acknowledgement
for it's SYN in stage three on the 3-way
handshake, a reflection of this step here,
then the connection has been established.
Now, if you're in the listen state, it's
possible that you can also call send to
them results in sending a SYN message. or
you can also, in that way you are then
going to, even though, you're in listen
state, you can actively open and active an
open state.
So now, there's one more path here which I
mentioned, the 4-way simultaneous open,
Which is this.
And so, this is when both sides have sent
SYN.
So, we're just looking at one side of the
connection.
And in response to a SYN, you get a SYN
from the other side.
And so, this is the two SYNs crossing.
So, in response you send SYN + ACK, SYN
received, then you ACK.
And so, there's the four messages.
Each has sent a SYN,
Each had received a SYN,
And then received the SYN and sent a
SYN/ACK and there is an ACK data exchange can
occur.
So now we are in the established state.
Now, of course, you can always transition
out. In fact, it closes and resets.
So now, at this point, we've gone through
connection establishment.
Now, we're going to go into connection
teardown.
And so, there are two cases here.
One is that, if we're the active closer
here we call close that results in a FIN
message being sent,
A FIN, packet with a FIN bit.
We now enter a FIN wait one.
The other is, if we receive a FIN, then we
acknowledge it.
And we're now on the passive close state
with the other side is closed, and then we
call, when we actually call close,
We'll send FIN, send the last ACK and be
closed.
And so, here in closed wait we're still
allowed to send data right until we call
close.
This is the other side is closed but we
haven't.
So now, when close is called, we're in the
FIN one state and there's a bunch of
transitions out of that.
One is that, we receive a FIN. So, we've
sent a FIN, received a FIN.
So, this is the example I showed with the
TCP teardown. So, we've sent a FIN, we've
received a FIN, we acknowledge it.
We're now in the closing state, we then
transition to time wait.
Another is that we receive a FIN plus an
ACK.
So, we can just acknowledge that and enter
time wait.
Final one is that, we receive an ACK, but
no FIN.
So, this is, we have closed our side of
the connection, but the other side hasn't.
And so it's sort of this state here is
correlated with this state here.
Then, when we do receive the FIN, we
acknowledge it into the time wait state.
And then, we have the time out before we
can actually close and recover the state.
So, you can ask, what's the difference
between this transition to closing and
time wait?
The reason is that this transition to
closing is when the two FINs pass each
other.
So, I send a FIN,
The other side sends me a FIN,
But hasn't acknowledged my FIN.
This is the difference between FIN/ACK and
FIN + ACK/ACK. And so, then I wait for
that FIN to be acknowledged, and then
transition to time wait.
So, this is the full TCP finite
state machine.
It looks really complicated.
I mean, it does have, one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten,
eleven, twelve states.
But when you realize it breaks down into
these two parts, connection establishment,
connection tear down, and really there's
just a bunch of different possible ways
that FINs can be exchanged, it's actually
not that complicated.
So, I encourage you to open up Wireshark
and just open up a couple of web
connections to see what, what's happening
with your TCP connections, and you'll be
able to see how those different
connections are traversing this finite
state machine.