So in this video, I'm going to talk about
"request to send/clear to send" a wireless
media access control algorithm.
So "request to send/clear to send" or
RTS/CTS, uses a short sequence of control
packets to determine whether or not it's
safe to transmit data.
So I'm showing three nodes, A, B, and C
where A can hear B, and B can hear C,
etcetera but A and C cannot hear each
other.
And so, in an RTS/CTS exchange, rather
than just immediately send the data packet
to be like you do in, say, CSMA/CA, A can
just transmit.
Instead, the first step, is that A sends
what's called a request to send packet or
RTS.
That's a short control packet and it asks
B, can I send you a packet of this
duration, say.
If B successfully receives the RTS, and it
believes that it's possible for it to
receive for example, it doesn't think
anyone else can be transmitting nearby,
then it can respond with a clear to send,
a CTS.
And it can tell A, you are clear to send
for this period of time.
And the key thing here is that C can
overhear this clear to send packet, and
know, that B is going to be receiving
data.
Because B know that B's going to be
receiving data, it knows it shouldn't
transmit during that time.
And so this clear to send can prevent C
from transmitting, and therefore prevent,
in theory, the hidden terminal problem
that we see in CSMA/CA networks.
So next, A sends the data.
Followed
by B sending an acknowledgement back.
So this is the basic RTS/CTS exchange.
An RTS followed by CTS followed by data,
followed by an ACK.
Now, of course, if A sends an RTS to B and
doesn't hear a clear to send, then it can
always retry later.
There, there are the standard backoff
approaches.
You'd see, for example,
exponential backoff that you see in data
transmissions in CSMA/CA.
So the point here, is it's not that
RTS/CTS has a lower probability of, say,
the hidden terminal problem.
But rather, what it's doing is it's
pushing that problem to the control packet
exchange.
For example, it could very well be that R,
that A, A and C try to simultaneously
transmit an RTS .
And that causes a collision, but this
won't appear as a data packet loss from A
to B.
Instead you'll cause just additional RTS
packets.
So RTS/CTS is pushing losses and
collisions to the control packet exchange.
So let's go back to the problems with
CSMA/CA. Hidden terminals, exposed
terminals, and collision or low SNR.
So you can ask, one by one, whether or not
RTS/CTS helps or solves these problems.
So first, hidden terminals.
RTS/CTS can't solve this problem.
It's always possible for example that RTSes
arent heard, CTSes aren't heard, that for
example we have B sending a CTS to A, but
some other node is transmitting, and so C
ends up not hearing it.
So it's possible the hidden terminals will
occur.
But, RTS/CTS greatly reduces them by
having this clear to send packet and
clearing the channel around the receiver.
So for the most part it doesn't solve it,
but it greatly helps.
So how about exposed terminals?
So recall, exposed terminals are when we
have a node here, let's say C.
So B wants to transmit to A.
C wants to transmit to D and C won't
transmit, because it hears B transmitting.
So in theory it's very well possible that
C could transmit to D.
So B is going to send an RTS.
Then there will be a CTS.
C doesn't hear the, the RTS, doesn't hear
the CTS, so it knows it can transmit.
But in practice, this doesn't really work.
The reason being that C doesn't want to
transmit to D because A is going to send
an acknowledgement.
And so generally, RTS/CTS won't really
help you with exposed terminals.
So how about collision or low SNR?
Well given that RTS CTS can reduce
collisions hidden terminals it can help
with this collision of low SNR in a sense
of when data losses do occur, its more
likely that their low SNR, there is
probability that their collision is lower.
It can't solve the problem, but it can
help.
So given that RTS/CTS can help, and it can
prevent you know, really help with hidden
terminal problems, which is pretty common,
especially, you know, in heavily used
networks, why don't we use it?
Why is it that most WiFi systems today use
CSMA/CA?
So the reason is overhead.
So recall, we have this packet exchange.
We have an RTS, then we have a CTS.
The question is how long does this packets
take.
Well, there are little control packets but
still just the way WiFi for example works
is that these control packets actually
have to take a significant amount of time.
The reason being that, unlike a data
packet which you can send at a really high
speed just to the destination knowing that
it's going to have a high signal to noise
ratio so you can use dense constellation
and you can send it really, really fast.
These control packets need to be heard by
everyone, so they always have to be sent
at a very low speed.
So, you know, wireless, may
have many different speeds and you always have to send
these control packets at the lowest speed.
And so, if you look, let's say, this is
just, this is some data a student of mine
collected just using 802.11b, so it has
four speeds one, two, 5.5 and eleven
megabits per second.
And this was the observed throughput in
of data, so this is throughput observed up at the
network layers here is exchanging these
frames.
And so you see, if you're exchanging data
frames at one megabit per
second, this small control exchange is not
a big deal; it's just four%.
Because these control packets, the actual
data packets themselves are being sent in
one megabits, these control packets are
small.
But as the data rate goes up, if the data
packets get shorter and shorter in time,
because they're faster and faster, the
overhead goes up.
These small control packets become a
larger and larger fraction of the air
time.
Point of which if you're transmitting at
eleven megabits per second, you can get
about 5.89 megabits per second out of
CSMA.
About 4.42 out of RTS/CTS.
There's a 25% overhead.
So you're reducing the throughput of your
network by a quarter using RTS/CTS.
And so if you don't have collisions, if
you're not having hidden terminals because
your network is idle, you're taking a big
hit.
So when I approach people, what we talk
about is that if you see very few losses,
things are working great, you use CSMA.
But then, if you start seeing collision,
you start seeing losses, then switch over
to RTS/CTS to get better arbitration.
So there's been some research on this.
But, generally speaking, people often just
use CSMA.