The 4-layer model of the Internet takes a
stream of data from the application layer.
The transport layer breaks this stream into
segments of data that it reliably delivers
to an application running on another computer.
The transport layer sends these segments as
network layer packets, which the network layer
delivers to the other computer. Let’s see
what that looks like in practice, the actual
packets that a web browser and server send
and receive.
First, let’s look at the transport layer.
Almost all web traffic is over TCP, the Transport
Control Protocol. In its typical operation,
there’s a client and a server. A server
listens for connection requests. To open a
connection, a client issues a connection request,
which the server responds to. I won’t go
into the details of exactly how this works,
but it turns out this exchange takes three
messages, something called the “three way
handshake.”
The first step of handshake is when the client
sends a “synchronize” message to the server,
often called a SYN. The second step is when
the server responds with a “synchronize”
message that also acknowledges the clients
“synchronize”, or a “synchronize and
acknowledge message”, often called a SYN-ACK.
The third and final step is when the client
responds by acknowledging the server’s synchronize,
often called an ACK. So often the three way
handshake is described as “synchronize,
synchronize and acknowledge, acknowledge”,
or “SYN, SYN-ACK, ACK”.
Recall that the network layer is responsible
for delivering packets to computers, but the
transport layer is responsible for delivering
data to applications. From the perspective
of the network layer, packets sent to different
applications on the same computer look the
same. This means that to open a TCP stream
to another program, we need two addresses.
The first, an Internet Protocol address, is
the address the network layer uses to deliver
packets to the computer. The second, the TCP
port, tells the computer’s software which
application to deliver data to. Web servers
usually run on TCP port 80. So when we open
a connection to a web server, we send IP packets
to the computer running the web server whose
destination address is that computer’s IP
address. Those IP packets have TCP segments
whose destination port is 80.
But how do those IP packets get to their destination?
We don’t have a direct wire connecting my
client to the server. Instead, my client is
connected to an intermediate computer, a router.
This router is itself connected to other routers.
IP packets between the client and server take
many “hops,” where a hop is a link connecting
two routers. For example, since my client
is on a WiFi network, the first hop is wireless
to the WiFi access point. The access point
has a wired connection to the broader Internet,
so it forwards my client’s packets along
this wired hop.
A router can have many links connecting it.
As each packet arrives, a router decides which
of its links to send it out on. Routers have
IP addresses, so it’s also the case that
it might not forward a packet but rather deliver
it to its own software. For example, when
you log into a router using TCP, the IP packets
are destined to the router’s own IP address.
How does a router make this decision? It does
so through something called a forwarding table,
shown here on the right. A forwarding table
consists of a set of IP address patterns and
the link to send across for each pattern.
When a packet arrives, the router checks which
forwarding table entry’s pattern best matches
the packet. It forwards the packet along that
entry’s link. Generally, “best” means
the most specific match. I’ll describe how
this matching works in more detail in the
video on longest prefix match. But in this
simple example let’s just consider the default
route, the first entry in the table above.
The default route is the least specific route
-- it matches every IP address. If, when a
packet arrives, there isn’t a more specific
route than the default route, the router will
just use the default one.
The default route is especially useful in
edge networks. Say, for example, you’re
Stanford University and have a router connecting
you to the larger Internet. Your router will
have many specific routes for the IP addresses
of Stanford’s network: “send packets to
the engineering school over this link”,
“send packets to the library over that link.”
But if the destination IP address isn’t
Stanford’s, then the router should send
it out to the larger Internet.
So now let’s look at some IP packets in
a real network. I’m going to request a web
page from www.brown.edu and use a tool called
Wireshark to show you all of the packets.
We’ll see how my web browser opens a TCP
connection to the Brown web server using a
three way handshake of SYN, SYN-ACK, ACK,
then starts issuing HTTP GET requests which
the server responds to with data. Once we’ve
seen the exchange of packets between my client
and the Brown University web server, I’ll
use another tool, called traceroute, to observe
the path that these packets take through the
Internet.
So first I’ll start up wireshark. Because
my computer is using many network applications
and sending lots of different packets, I’m
going to tell wireshark to only display packets
that are TCP segments to the Brown server
using port 80. This way we’ll only see the
web traffic I’m generating. I’m also going
to tell Wireshark to listen on en1, which
is the name my Mac gives to my WiFi link layer.
As you can see, I have many link layers available,
but let’s just look at en1 since that’s
how I’m connected to the Internet.
Next I’ll open my web browser and request
the web page for Brown University’s Computer
Science department. This is where I went as
an undergraduate and so I like to keep up
with news on the department. You can see in
wireshark that loading this page involved
sending and receiving a lot of packets! Wireshark
shows me the timestamp of each packet, the
source IP address, the destination IP address,
what protocol it uses, its length, and further
information. Look at this first packet. It’s
from my computer, whose address is 192.168.0.106,
to the Brown CS web server, whose address
is 128.148.32.12. It’s going to TCP port
80 -- the HyperText Transport Protocol port
on the server, which we can see from the > http
field in the Info column. The packets is SYN
packets -- the first step of the three way
handshake.
Look at the first three packets. The first
is a SYN packet from my computer to the web
server. The second is a SYN-ACK packet from
the web server back to my computer. The third
is an ACK from my computer back to the web
server. This is the three way handshake! Now
the two computers can exchange data, and you
can see that the first data packet is an HTTP
request -- my computer sends a GET request
to the web server. The response to this GET
request is three packets -- wireshark shows
the response when it receives the third one,
shown in the line whose info is HTTP/1.1 200
OK. So here we can see how my requesting a
web page from Brown’s Computer Science server
creates a TCP connection through the three
IP packets for the 3-way handshake, then more
packets for the HTTP request and response.
This is how the network looks like to the
end hosts, the computers, as they exchange
packets at the network layer. But what does
it look like inside the network layer? What
hops do these packets take? To see this, I’m
going to use a second tool, traceroute. Traceroute
shows you the hops that packets to a destination
take. So we can type traceroute www.cs.brown.edu
to see the path through the Internet. I’ll
add the -w flag, which specifies a timeout,
with a timeout of 1 second.
The first hop the packets take is to my wireless
router, whose IP address is 192.168.0.1. As
you can see from the next hop, I’m at home
-- I have a cable modem and my Internet provider
is Astound. After this packets take another
hop to a router with IP address 74.14.0.3.
The hop after that is a router in San Francisco,
California, then several routers in San Jose,
sjc for above.net and sanjose1 for level3.net.
After sanjose1.level3.net, the packets are
across the United States in New York! They
go through a series of routers in New York
-- ebr, csw, ebr, then, on hop 13, to Boston.
Boston is very close to Providence, where
Brown is. After oshean.org that we see three
stars -- this means there’s a router that
won’t tell traceroute about itself. The
stars are traceroute’s way to show it waited
for a reply but the replied timed out. On
hop 20 we see a router in Brown’s CS department.
After that, everything is hidden -- Brown’s
CS department doesn’t want you to be able
to see what the inside of its network looks
like.
Because we couldn’t see the path end with
Brown’s web server, let’s try another
one: the Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence
Lab (CSAIL) at MIT. We can see that packets
take the same path to Boston, until hop 15.
The path to Brown goes to oshean at hop 15,
while the path to MIT continues in level3‘s
network. On the path to www.csail.mit.edu
only two routers are hidden, the 13th and
19th hops. We can see that www.csail.mit.edu
is also named akron.csail.mit.edu and, after
22 hops, packets from my computer reach MIT’s
web server. Look at the time values -- the
time for my packet to reach the MIT web server
and its response to return to me -- there
and back, the round-trip time -- is under
90 milliseconds, or less than an eye blink.
We’ve now seen the life of a packet, starting
as an application-level client web request
and taking nearly 20 hops through the Internet
to reach its destination. For me, this is
one of the best things about teaching this
course. Everything we present is something
that you and I interact with every day -- even
just in the space of watching one video! It’s
easy to see the principles and ideas in practice,
and with a few simple tools you can inspect
the Internet in operation, in real time!