So in this video I'm going to talk about
two additional mechanisms that TCP Tahoe
introduced to control congestion.
Better RTT or round trip time estimation,
and self-clocking.
To recall,  TCP Tahoe introduced three
basic mechanisms that allowed it to tame
congestion and essentially allow the
Internet to work again.
The prior video talked about, congestion
window and this idea of the slow start,
and congestion avoidance states.
Now, let's talk about the second
mechanism, timeout estimation.
So it turns out that estimating your round
trip time is really critical for
retransmissions and for time outs.
If your round trip time is estimated to be
too short, that is you estimate it to be
shorter than what it is, then this means
that you're going to waste capacity.
You are going to think that the packet
wasn't successfully received when it has
been and retransmit unnecessarily.
This is then going to trigger slow start.
This is really bad in the sense of I have
a nice window size, I'm sending data, but
my RTT estimates are too short.
I'm now entering slow start unnecessarily.
Now if the RTT estimation is too long,
that's also a problem because it could be
that, really I could've retransmitted a
long time ago.
The packet didn't get there.
But say, let's say I estimated an RTT of
five minutes when it's only a couple
hundred milliseconds, your protocol's
going to sit there dead for five minutes
before it issues a time out and tries to
do a retransmission.
So this is fine, but the real challenge is
that especially on the Internet, we've
seen the packet switching.
Rtt can be highly dynamic.
Furthermore, it can vary significantly
with load.
Even as you are starting to send things
faster, you can change your own RTT even
if the rest of the world remains the same.
And so how do you estimate RTT very
inexpensively, very quickly given these
constraints?
So before TCP Tahoe, there was a very
simple mechanism, which is that.
R is your RTT estimate.
And you'll just initialize it to something
reasonable.
Okay, we'll guess like five hundred
milliseconds or something.
Then you're generating a measurement for
the most recently acked data packets.
You say, okay, I sent packet five at this
time.
I now got the ack at, you know, time plus
57 milliseconds, or say, 200 milliseconds,
and then I'm going to estimate, and will
be, you know, 57 or 200 milliseconds.
I then maintain an exponentially weighted
moving average.
So alpha r + 1- alpha m.
So this is basically saying, take my
existing estimate, and incorporate some
fraction of my new estimate.
So if, say, let's just say r is equal to
100 milliseconds.
And my measurement is equal to 80
milliseconds.
And alpha, which are the weighting of
history to the present sample.
Let's just say, alpha is equal to .9.
So I'm going to weight history a lot, this
way this will smooth out noise.
Then the new r is going to be 0.9
Times 100 milliseconds, plus 0.1.
Times 80 milliseconds, 98 milliseconds.
And so this one sample, 80 milliseconds,
is going to, should go one-tenth of the
way between r and m.
So you can imagine a lower alpha value
means that you're going to weight the
current measurements more, versus a higher
alpha value, weigh the history more.
Then, your timeout is based on this
factor, beta R, and beta was two.
And so if you see that the, you don't get
an acknowledgement for twice your average,
then you assume there's a timeout, and
then you trigger a timeout.
So this seems like a totally reasonable
algorithm.
You know, at first blush.
So what's the problem?
It turns out that the problem is that the
fact that R is a certain value should not
say anything about what the distribution of
RTT values is like.
So one way to imagine is, let's say, you
know, here's a graph.
And I'm looking at a distribution of the
round trip times of packets.
They're not constant.
They're varying over time.
Well, in some cases, I might have, here's
my, my average.
Let's call it A.
I might have a distribution like this.
All right.
Where in fact, if I were to look at 2A,
that less than 0.0001% of packets take
that long.
At which point, beta, a beta of two is a
tremendously conservative estimate.
But, it could also be  a slightly
different case, where here, let's just say
I have a another link or another path
which is B, where my distribution looks
more like this.
Where if I look at 2b.
Some, say, twenty percent of packets tend to
have an RTT of that law.
Depending on the dynamics of the network.
You can have very distributions of RTTs.
And this approach didn't keep that in
mind.
And so, for tcp connections that had very,
very tight distributions, beta is way too
conservative.
And you end up being idle when you don't
need to be.
The estimate's too large an RTT but
when the, when the RTT has a very broad
distribution of beta
equals two.
Is far too aggressive and you end
retransmitting unnecessarily.
So TCP Tahoe, solved this problem by
essentially including the notion of the
variance of the RTT in its estimates.
And so this is the algorithm that, that
was proposed and which is used.
And essentially, what you're going to do
is, just like before, you're doing an
exponentially weighted moving average.
You have this RTT estimate, and what
you're doing is also measuring your error
in the estimate.
And so given I have this estimate R, and I
have a measurement M, I measure the error
to be M minus R.
And I multiply it by this gain factor, and
because these terms I'm essentially
multiplying by minus R, so there's the
alpha factor that we saw in the prior
approach.
And then we measure the variance.
And so the variance is again,  the weighted
average of the gain factor of the error
minus the variance.
But the, so the basic idea here is we're
measuring not only an exponentially
weighted moving average of R.
But we're also measuring an exponentially
weighted moving average of the variance
over time.
And then our timeout is equal to the
average plus four times the variance,
where beta is four.
So this way, if we have, as before, if we
have a very tight distribution, then, with
a variance, like this, then we're going to
time out when the packet, when the
variance is just, when you have a, a
packet that's just four times the variance
out.
Similarly, if you have a very broad
distribution,
Your variance is going to be way out here.
Then you'll end up timing out when the
variance, when the, when it's four times
that value.
And so, it's very it's very likely that
the packet was actually lost.
In a case of tremendous congestion, you're
not getting, estimates, you know, nothing
is happening, you exponentially increase,
this timeout.
So here are two graphs from Van Jacobson's
paper, which show the performance of this
RTT estimation.
And so what the,
The faint line on the bottom shows is the
actual measured RTTs as packets from
acknowledgements.
And the solid line above shows the time
out estimate for the TCP algorithm.
And so the idea is that in a perfect world
that the time out would, would.
Perfectly mirror this, such that, gosh, we
didn't get it, and if we just wait a
little longer, then we know to retransmit.
So, two points.
This figure on the left.
You can see it, there's this huge gap.
So TCP is sitting idle for a long time,
when really, it could have retransmitted
much sooner.
There's also cases where it crosses.
So this is kind of bad.
Where this means that the packet took
longer.
You know, the estimate was in fact too was
too short.
So  if you look at the pre tahoe
algorithm on the right and post tahoe,
it's the tahoe algorithm we see that it's
tracking rtt is much better right.
The gap here between the observed rtt's
and the timeouts is much closer.
So the third improvement that tcp tahoe brought
was something called self clocking.
And this in some ways is the greatest
conceptual contribution of tcp tahoe.
This idea that.
You want to, essentially clock out the
packets that you send based on the
acknowledgements you receive.
And so, this is the, and this is the, sort
of the, the conceptual model of the Van
Jacobson laid out.
So let's say I have a sender that has a
really big pipe.
We show by, sort of, being fat here, where
the, the volume of these packets is
constant.
And the receiver also has a fat pipe.
But there is this bottleneck link in the
middle.
Well, since there is this bottleneck link,
what's going to happen is these packets
that are sent very fast from the sender
are going to be stretched out in time,
they're going to take longer.
And they're then going to be spaced out in
time at the receiver.
The receiver, if it generates
acknowledgements directly in response to
these packets, then it's going to be
sending acknowledgments back with the same
timing that it's receiving them, which is
determined by this congestion, by this,
the bottleneck congestion link.
Then those acts are going to arrive.
They've traversed the bottleneck link, you
can see they're much shorter, so they're
not filling it, they're only taking up
part of it.
And then these acknowledgments arrive at
the sender corresponding to the frequency
of the packets arriving at the receiver.
And then if the sender sends new packets
timed by these acknowledgements, which
essentially is going to inherently rate
limit itself or space out packets in
time, so that they're entering this
bottleneck link at the right rate.
That is, just as the packet's leaving, like
here which then falls through the neck,
A new packet starts arriving.
And this idea of self-clocking, that you
don't put a new packet in the network
until one comes out, and you clock
yourself based on this is what allows TCP
in a very simple mechanism to not stuff
lots of packets into the network and to
not suddenly send huge bursts of packets
that saturate this link, because you can
imagine there is some queue here.
And so even if TCP knows, oh I can only
send five packets per round trip time, if
it sends a burst of five packets then
those packets might fall off the end of
this queue.
But if they're spaced out properly due to
this timing, then it's going to be feeding
them out at a nice steady rate which will
fill this pipe without overfilling the
queue.
And so the principle here is you only want
to put data into the network when data has
left.
Otherwise you're increasing the amount of
data in the network and you're causing
congestion.
And so you send new data directly in
response to acknowledgements.
But also it's important that you send
acknowledgements aggressively.
Such as you saw with duplicate
acknowledgements, they're really important
signals to the sender.
And so if you are receiving additional
segments and you, and the segments that
have, you have missing segments, you
should send acknowledgements for those
segments aggressively so it sees that
there are duplicate acknowledgements so it
gets a signal that something has been
missed.
It also knows on receiving those
acknowledgements, those duplicate
acknowledgements, that packets have left
the network and it can make decisions
accordingly, So
this is the, those three mechanisms of a
congestion window.
Better RTT estimation that considers
variance and self clocking, are really the
foundation of TCP Tahoe.
And so, in 1987, 1988, Van Jacobson fixed
with these mechanisms as well as a few other tricks.
And published this seminal TCP paper, TCP
Tahoe.
And this is, basically solved TCP's,
condition control problem.
The internet started working again.
And this actually spawned a huge area of
research in TCP and this whole idea of how
do you manage your sending rate to not,
congest the network.
And so in this next, I've just talked
about the first version of TCP Tahoe.
But there's a long history.
So the next video's going to talk about,
TCP Reno and new Reno, which are closer to
what's done today.
They add a couple new mechanisms.
And so, if this is interesting, I, I
totally recommend reading Van Jacobson's
original paper "Congestion of Winds and
Control." Sort of lays out a little bit of
the story of what they saw, and then these
mechanisms and how they solved, and how
they solved it.