In this video, I'm going to tell you about
what packet switching is and why
packet switching is used in the internet.
Packet switching was first described by
Paul Barren in the early 1960s.
It describes the way in which packets of
information are routed one-by-one across
the internet to their destination, just
like letters are delivered by the post
office.
Packet-switching is really important for
us to understand, because when we choose
to use packet-switching, it dictates many
of the properties of the network.
Today I'm going to describe what packet
switching is, and why it was chosen for
the internet.
But first.
To set some set some context, I'm gonna
tell you about a predecessor of packet
switching that was called circuit
switching.
And we're all very familiar with circuit
switching, cause it's what's used in the
telephone network.
So the most common use of circuit
switching is in the telephone, the
traditional wired telephone network.
And we're gonna walk through what happens
when we place a phone call from the phone
on the left to the one on the right.
Now with the picture I've got here it
shows the telephones being connected by a
dedicated wire and that wouldn't make for
a very interesting telephone system we can
only talk to one other person.
But so in practice the telephones are
connected together through a through a
dedicated wire down to a switching,
switching center.
So in the early days of telephony back in
the 1880s or so, the dedicated wire went
to a switch-board operator and the
switch-board operator was a room full of
people who would take a dedicated wire
from the input and connect it to the
dedicated wire to the phone that you are
connecting to.
So it was all manually connected and well
the main point here is the wire is
dedicated for the phone conversation from
the start to the end of the phone call.
Nowadays of course we don't have a room full of
switch, switchboard operators and these
instead we use automatic circuit switches that
set up the circuit for us from one phone
to our friend's phone at the other end.
So it helps to think of a phone call
having three phases.
First we pick up the handset and dial the
number and dialing the number is saying
where do we want to be connected to.
This creates a dedicated circuit from one
end to the other.
So that dedicated circuit is gonna go
through all of the circuits along the way.
And the system has told each of the
circuits to connect an incoming wire to an
outcoming wire.
Or an incoming circuit to an outcoming
circuit.
So each switch is going to maintain the
state to map the incoming circuit to the
correct outgoing circuit.
And then in the second phase we talk.
In a digital phone system like most phone
systems are today our voice is sampled and
digitized at the first switch.
Then it's sent over a dedicated circuit as
a typically 64 kilobit channel for voice.
So our phone conversation has a dedicated
circuit or channel all the way along the
path and the circuit is not shared with
anyone else.
And then finally when we hang up, the
circuit has to be removed and any state in
the switches along the path has to be
removed, as well.
So in practice, between the switches the
there are trunk lines which are really,
really fast.
In other words, they have a very high data
rate.
Even the slow ones run at two and a half
gigabits per second.
And the fastest ones today run at 40 or
even 100 gigabits per second.
Sometimes you'll hear people call these
big trunk lines big fat pipes because of
the volume of data they can send.
But actually these big fat pipes are
really tiny, skinny, little optical
fibers.
Thinner than one of your hairs.
Many thousands of phone calls can share
that same trunk line between cities.
Each in its own dedicated circuit.
The key thing here to remember is every
phone call has its own dedicated
64-kilobit per second circuit.
That it doesn't have to share with anybody
else.
So, in summary we can think of circuit
switching as having the following
characteristics.
Each call has its own private guaranteed
isolated data rate from end to end.
Second, the call has three phases,
establish, communicate and close.
And third, originally a circuit was an end
to end physical wire.
But now a days it's made up of a virtual
private wire.
It's gonna share that wire with others but
it has it's own dedicated circuit within
that wire.
There are a few problems with circuit
switching.
Clearly it's worked very well for the phone
system.
But when we're thinking about using
circuit switching for the Internet or any
computer communications, there are a few
shortcomings that we that we need to
consider.
So we're gonna go through three main
problems.
The first one is it's inefficient.
Computers when computers communicate, they
tend to be very bursty.
We tend to send data in bursts of may be a
few seconds, a few packets, maybe even a
few minutes, depending on the application
that we're running.
For example, if I'm typing over an SSH
connection then.
I'm gonna have characters, that I'm gonna
send every now and again.
Sometimes a flurry of characters as I type
a word and then long periods of silence in
between.
Or if I am reading a sequence of web
pages.
I might have a burst as I fill up one
page, a burst as I fill up the figures to
populate that page, and then a period of
pause while I read those web pages.
So it tends to be very bursty.
Because during those times of, of silence,
when I am not doing anything, there is no
activity, I've got this dedicated circuit
which nobody else can use.
So it is very inefficient, very
inefficient use of the capacity of the
network as a whole.
The second thing is computers tend to have
very diverse applications that need very
different rates.
Communicators communicate at many, many
So a web server might be streaming video
at, say one, five or even six megabits per
second.
But if you compare that with me typing one
character every second, there's a huge
difference in the rates that the network
needs to support.
So if we pick a fixed rate circuit for the
video, and then I use if or typing, it
will be barely used.
Or vice versa then I wouldn't even be able
to stream the video.
So a fixed rate circuit really isn't much
use at all.
The third one, the third problem with
circuit switching is all of the state that
we need to maintain.
We need to maintain some state for every
phone call that's going on.
Every time we establish a call, we need to
set up the circuit mapping from the
ingress to the egress of every switch
along the way.
If a circuit fails, or a switch fails, or
a link fails, we need to go in and change
all of that state in order to reroute the,
reroute the calls.
So, we have to manage it, and at the end
we need to remember to take the state out.
If anything fails, then we may find that
the state becomes inconsistent, and then
we have a problem.
So, state management in circuit switches
is, is considered a problem.
And if we had thousands or hundreds of
thousands of communications going on at
the same time, that's just a lot of work
that has to be done.
So let's take a look at packet switching
in contrast to circuit switching.
So again, we're gonna look at two end
systems communicating and this in this
case we're gonna look at this laptop on
the left, A, and it's going to be talking
to the server on the right, B.
In practice these of course can be
anywhere, anywhere in the internet.
In packet switching there's no dedicated
circuit to carry our data.
Instead we just send when we are ready at
any time we want we send a block of data
by adding a header to it that's what we
call a packet.
A header contains the address of where the
packet is going just like an envelope
tells the post office where to send the
letter.
Packet switched network consists of end
host, the links, and packet switches.
When we send the packet, it's routed one
hope at a time from the source, in this
case that laptop, A, all the way through
to the destination B.
If you look at the packet it has the data
in it, and it also has the address, B of
where it's going to.
We'll see later that packets are a little
bit more complicated than this, but this
is the bare information, the minimum
information that it needs, the data that
we want to get to B, and then the address,
B, of where it's going to.
So when we send the packet it's gonna be
routed hop-by-hop from the source to the
destination.
Each packet switch along the way is gonna
look up the address in a forwarding table.
So it keeps a local forwarding table at
all of the packet switches.
And here I've got a forwarding table
saying if we see the adress B.
Then we're gonna send it to, on the next
top, to S2.
And this is S2 over here.
Okay, so once this switch S1 sees this
packet, it's gonna look it up in it's
table and send it along to switch S2, and
this is it going along its way.
Switch S2 will have it's own table and a
course that table is gonna be different
from S1's cause it's gonna have a
different set of next hops for each of the
addresses that it sees, so then it's gonna
send it along it's way this time to S4 and
then eventually to the correct
destination.
So in the inter, internet, there's lots of
different types of packet switch.
Some of them are called routers because
they deal with addresses that are internet
addresses and they may include little
routers that we have in our desks, on our
desks at home or huge routers that are in
big wiring closets in big switching
centers.
But we call those routers.
There're also things called ethernet
switches and we're gonna look at the
difference between different types of
packet switch in a later lecture.
I showed you one packet and of course at
any instance there's gonna be many packets
flowing across the Internet.
Millions and millions of packets flowing
in all sorts of different.
And they're all being routed hop-by-hop,
one at a time by the, by the packet
switches along the path.
So there'll be many flows of communication
going in all sorts of directions at the
same time.
So these packet switches have a lot of
work to do.
And remember they're, they're routing each
packet one at a time by picking the next
hop that it goes to and sending it on its
way.
We gonna take a quick look inside packet
switches and some of their, their relevant
features.
So, I've already told you that packet
switches have a forwarding table to tell it
where the packet goes next.
They also have to have buffers.
So, packet switches have buffers.
Let me to explain why that is.
So, in the middle here we've got a packet
switch, and this packet switch is going to
be receiving these two packets we got
here, and here.
So, we are gonna look what happens if
these packets go through the packet switch.
If they both arrive at the same time And
let's say they are arriving at the full
line rate, of the outgoing link.
Then the packet switch has to hold one of
them While it sends the other, it can't
send them both at the same time so it's
going to send one at a time.
And because it might have many incoming
links, the packet switch has to have a
buffer to hold perhaps, many, many
packets.
And we're gonna see that these packets
these buffers can be quite large in a
practice.
So the buffers hold packets, when two
normal packets arrive at the same time.
And particularly during periods of
congestion, when there are lots and lots
of packets coming in at all of these input
links, all trying to get to the same
output, it may actually have quite big
buffers to hold packets during those times of
congestion.
So in summary, packets are routed
individually by looking up the address in
the router's local forwarding table.
All packets share the full capacity of a
link.
And third, the routers maintain no per
communicate, per communication state.
Now this is really quite key.
In a circuit switch, remember, we need to
maintain state associated with every
circuit along the, every circuit we're
maintaining.
Here we maintain none, we just maintain
the forwarding table.
And then there's is no per communication,
no per packet, or no per flow state
associated with that communication.
So why does the internet use packet
switching?
Probably pretty obvious by now, but I
really wanted to spell that out.
There were three original reasons.
Two of that I've got listed here.
That the, that the internet used packet
switching.
The first two are very, are very obvious,
and come from what I've just what, what
I've just described.
This first one is, packet switching allows
us to use expensive links efficiently.
So, efficient use of expensive links.
Link, Links were assumed to be expensive
and scarce.
The first links that interconnected the
packet switches across the backbone of the
internet were running at a few kilobits
per second.
So they were expensive and everybody knew
that they would become they, they would be
a scarce resort, resource.
Packet switching allows many, many bursty
flows to share that same, those same links
very efficiently.
Because at any one instant, the packet can
use the entire link.
But it can be immediately followed by
another packet using the entire link
belonging to a different communication.
So there's a famous text book by
Bertsekas and Gallager.
Circuit switching is rarely used for data
networks, because of very inefficient use
of the links.
So the second big reason for using packet
switching, was It's widely felt that the
packet switching allows for more resilient
networks, networks that are resilient to
the failure of links and routers.
And the reason for this is, that because
each packet is individually routed along
the path, if something happens, if
something breaks, a link breaks or a
router breaks.
Then we can, because we have no state in
all of the switches for this particular
flow.
We can simply send the packet on a
different path.
We can send it over a different link, to a
different router, and it will find its way
eventually.
So, for this reason, Tanenbaum in
other famous text book, had said, for high
reliability, the internet was to be a
datagram subnet.
So, if some lines of routers were
destroyed, messages could easily be
rerouted.
And, the third big reason, that the
internet use packet switching, was that
the internet was originally designed as an
interconnection of the existing networks.
And, at that time, pretty much all, All
widely used communication networks.
All computer networks were packet
switched.
And so, if the internet was to
interconnect all of those existing
networks, then it too needed to be packet
switched as well.
Okay, this is the end of the first video
about packet switching.
By now you should be able to answer these
three questions very easily.
In the next few videos we're going to
learn more about packet switching, some
basic definitions, some ways to model
packet switching, and some properties of
packet switching that have been developed
over the years.
See you soon.