So welcome to unit 6. Unit 6 is about routing.
The basic question of how do we get a packet
from A to B across a large network such as
the Internet. We've already been assuming
implicitly that there was a way for packets
to be delivered from one side of the Internet
to the other in all of the exercises, assignments,
and videos that we've been working on so far.
Now we're actually going to look at the methods
and approaches that we can use to actually
route those packets through the Internet.
So there's a very obvious place to start.
And that is, what if each packet contained
a list of all the routers that it was going
to pass through, and then found it's own way
through the network, just with the state entirely
contained within the packet. That would work.
That's one way to do it. But it's not how
the Internet works. That method, what we call
source routing, was considered to be inefficient
and potentially a security loophole. And we'll
see that in the videos coming up. Instead,
as you know, the Internet uses forwarding
tables. Each router contains a forwarding
table that tells it, for each destination
prefix, which path or which next hop to send
a packet to. And so the next question to ask
is, how to those forwarding tables get populated?
For that, we use an algorithm. And that algorithm
runs as a distributed algorithm, so that the
routers can come to a conclusion as to the
entries that they will put in those forwarding
tables. The basic approach that gets used
is that the routers will build a spanning
tree. A spanning tree is a tree - therefore
it has no loops - and it's spanning in that
it has a way for every source to reach a given
destination. The root of the tree is the destination,
and the leaves are all of the other sources,
so that they can send on the spanning tree
to reach that destination. So the routers
now have to build that spanning tree. And
there are two algorithms that we'll be describing
in upcoming videos, about how those forwarding
table entries get built in order to create
that spanning tree. The first one is called
the Bellman Ford algorithm, as known as a
distance vector algorithm. And you'll see
why it's called distance vector in an upcoming
video. An alternative method, which is now
more widely used, is called Dijkstra's algorithm,
or Dijkstra's shortest path first algorithm,
and it is known as a link state algorithm.
And again, you'll see that described in detail
in an upcoming video. You're also going to
see how these algorithms are used in the internet
today. Well first off, the Internet is a collection
of many different parties, each with their
own networks, which are somehow interconnected.
Then we're going to talk a little bit about
the notion of an autonomous system, an administrative
domain of routing within the Internet. Stanford
is an autonomous system, it's actually multiple
ones. The Stanford Linear Accelerator is its
own autonomous system, then there's the main
Stanford campus. Many large ISPs might have
multiple AS's. Not a huge number, but multiple
autonomous systems. And there are different
kinds of AS's. For example, Stanford doesn't
route transit traffic across the Internet.
It acts as an edge AS, or a stub AS. So within
an autonomous system, there are two basic
routing algorithms that are used. RIP and
OSPF. RIP is a distance vector protocol, whereas
OSPF is a link state protocol. In general
today, almost everyone uses OSPF in order
to define their routing tables within an autonomous
system. It is, for example, what Stanford
uses. But then, the routing between autonomous
systems uses a different protocol - BGP, or
the Border Gateway Protocol. It turns out
that often autonomous systems don't want to
expose what their system is like, so just
doing the shortest path can be tricky. So
instead, BGP adds some additional mechanisms,
like actually knowing the path that packets
might take, in order to allow autonomous systems
to hide their internals while giving enough
information that routers can pick loop-free
paths. And so, suddenly we've so far been
talking about applications and transport and
all these things happening end-to-end. And
now we're going to look inside the middle,
and see what are actually the pieces at work
and the mechanisms and the algorithms to make
the Internet work as it does today. And so
when you come to the end of this unit, you
should have a very good idea of the different
strategies that we can take in order to route
packets from A to B.