This video is a continuation about packet
switching.
And in this video I'm gonna be talking
about a number of different queue models.
I'm gonna start out by describing a simple
deterministic queue model.
This is something that's gonna help us
understand the dynamics of many simple queue
system.
It often works as a good way of
understanding what's going on in the
network.
So.
Here's a router and as we know already
routers have to have queues in the
interface to hold packets during times of
congestion.
And this is where the variability in
queuing delay takes place.
So if we can understand the dynamics, even
just having a rough sense of the dynamics
of that queue, it really helps us
understand the end to end queuing delay
and the dynamics of the network.
So we're going to take a closer look at
this and we're just going to create a
simple model.
Here are the main characteristics of this
queue.
So I'm going to draw a queue like this,
this is a standard way to draw a queue.
Showing where the packets will be stored,
in that router queue.
This is a 4-port router so, packets could
be coming in from any of the interfaces,
into that queue and, then they will
depart, under the outgoing link.
We're going to say that queue has an occupancy
of Q(t).
So at time t it has Q packets or bytes in
it.
It's gonna be useful to think about the
aggregate or the cumulative departure
process.
That is all of the packets or all of the
bytes that have departed up until some
time t.
Similarly, it's going to be useful to
think of the cumulative arrivals.
The total number of packets that have
arrived up until time t.
Finally, because the outgoing link
typically has a deterministic and fixed
rate, which we're gonna say has a fixed
rate of r.
So they're gonna be the main parameters of
our model.
We can also think of a queue as being like
a bucket full of water.
And here's a simple example here.
A of t is the cumulative number of bytes
that have arrived up until time t.
D of t is the cumulative number of bytes
that have departed up until time t.
And in this example, they are going to
depart at a fixed link rate of r.
At any one time, there may be some bytes
that have arrived, but haven't yet
departed.
They're the ones sitting in the bucket
here.
And, the occupancy of that bucket is gonna
be Q of t.
So this is like a simple model of RQ.
It's just another way of thinking about
it.
We could draw the evolution of this as a
function of time.
And I'm gonna try and sketch how this
might look.
So here are gonna be the axes of my graph.
As a function of time we're gonna look at
the cumulative number of bytes, so
remember this is cumulative.
I'm gonna first look at the arrival
process, A of t.
Bytes tend to arrive as part of a packet
and they're going to arrive at some
particular link arrival rate.
So I'm gonna draw what that cumulative
arrival process might look like.
It could look like anything, but here is
the bytes arriving a packet.
This is the gap between the first packet
and the second packet.
Here's a bunch more bytes arriving a gap,
maybe it's a long gap this time, and then
a new packet arriving.
So this is supposed to be a straight line.
And this would be the arrival rate of the
packet on the incoming link and this is
the number of bits of it let's say the
packet is of length p the number of bytes
of that first packet.
Now let's look at what the departure
process might look like.
I'm going to try and draw that and label
it as A of t.
The cumulative arrival process.
And then in yellow, I'm going to try and
draw the, I'm gonna sketch out what the
departure process might look like.
We know that the departure process is
going to work at and operate at rate R.
So at some point after that first packet
has arrived, let's assume that it is a
store and forward model, that doesn't matter,
it's just for sake of my example.
So this time here the packet has arrived
and then we'll say okay, it's going to
depart at rate R.
So that's going to be my gradient there.
So that's the rate, that's rate R, that
packet on the right, that packet
departing.
At this point, there's nothing left, so,
we're gonna wait until there's a whole new
packet in the queue, and then we're gonna
depart again at rate R.
That's gonna be rate R.
And so on, when it went into a whole new
packet and it'll be at rate R again.
So this might be one way in which it
evolves.
The point here is not the particular shape
of this graph, but just to say you can
easily sketch the arrival and departure
process.
And what this kind of a cool property of
this is that we can immediately from this
tell some nice characteristics of the
system.
First of all, we can immediately tell how
what the value of Q of t is because at any
one time.
So if we were to pick a particular time, Q
of t is the number of bytes that have
arrived but not yet departed, so it's
simply D of t minus A of t, I'm sorry A of
t minus D of t, so it's the number that
have arrived, minus those that have
departed, so for example if we were to
take a line here, and here, so a vertical,
it's supposed to be a vertical line, that
value, that distance between the two of
those is Q(t), so at any one time it's
the occupancy of that queue.
Similarly, if we look at a particular byte
that arrives, say at this time here.
If we assume that all bytes arrive and
then depart in the same order.
Then this byte because it's this
particular accumulative byte.
We know that it departs here, so if we
take the horizontal distance between these
two lines, this is going to tell us the d
of t.
I'll call it little d of t.
The delay through the queue.
So this is a very useful model giving us
intuition.
I often sketch graphs like this when I'm
trying to understand, the dynamics of a
queue or the dynamics of a system.
Okay, then to summarize, we can say that
the queue occupancy, Q of t equals it's the
ones that have arrived minus the ones that
have departed.
So a nice simple expression for that and
that D of t is the time spent in the queue
by a byte that arrived at time t.
So it's the time spent in the queue, by a
byte arriving at time t.
And that's simply the horizontal distance
between those two lines.
Now, the assumption of this is always that
it's first come, first serve, or FIFO, we
also say first in, first out.
In this context those have the same
meaning.
So that's true.
If the bytes didn't arrive and depart in
the same order then we couldn't make this
statement here about D(t) cause we don't
know that we're referring to the same
byte.
Let's go on and look at an example now of
how we might use this.
So anyway, I'm going to work through an
example.
We're going to assume that every second.
A 100 bit packet is going to arrive to a
queue at rate, 1000 bits per second.
In other words, this packet is gonna
arrive at a rate of 1000 bits per second,
and it's 100 bits long.
We're going to see the maximum departure
rate, that was our R, is 500 bits per
second.
And the question is, what is the average
occupancy of the queue?
So just reading the question, it's not so
obvious.
But if we plot this in the way that I did
before.
I'm not gonna try and sketch it, 'cause I
want these numbers to be very clear.
A(t) shown in red here is the arrival
process.
This here is the packet arriving.
It's the 100 bit packet arriving at rate
of 1000 bits per second.
So therefore, it takes a tenth of a
second, .1 of a second, to arrive.
The maximum departure rate is 500 bits per
second.
It's slower.
So our departure rate D, of departure
D(t), the rate here is the gradient of that
is 500 bits per second.
So that 1,000, that 100 bit packet is
going to take.2 of a second, in order to
depart.
In the previous example I showed you the
store and forward of each packet.
Here I didn't, and that's just a choice
and I just made that choice when answering
the question.
Question isn't clear as to whether, which
way it is.
So we can now see the time evolution of Q(t), which is the vertical
difference between those two lines and the
delay of an indi-, individual packet.
But the question is, what is the average
occupancy of the queue?
Well let's look at how we might solve
that.
I am going to write this out just so that,
you have a clear record of this.
The solution is this.
During each repeating one second cycle the
queue is going to fill at rate 500 bits
per second for a tenth of a second.
So that was my arrival process here.
Then it drains for 500 bits per second
for.
Then drains at 500 bits per second for.10
second.
Over the first, two-tenths of a second.
The average queue occupancy is there for 0.5
times
0.1 times 500 equals 25 bits.
The queue is empty for eight tenths in a
second every cycle that's from here to
here and so the average q occupancy, q bar
of t is .2 over second when its 25 bits
and .8 over second when its zero.
So, the average queue occupancy is five bits.
Continuing with our theme of simple
deterministic queue models, I want to explain
why it is that small packets can reduce
end to end delay.
You may have been wondering why we can't
simply send an entire message in one
packet.
Why is it that we have to break messages
down into smaller packets?
There's very good reason to this, and I
want to explain this in terms of the end
to end delay.
So on the left, I've got an example of a
message, of length r.
That's being delivered from end to end.
And, it's going through three routers, R1,
R2 and R3.
And I am just showing, as we did before,
the, the delay across each link in terms
of the packetization delay and the
propagation delay over the links, as it
makes it way across the network.
We already know the expression for the end
to end delay for this, it's simply made up
of: the sum of all the M over the RIs.
This is the packetization delay, and then
the sum of the, all of the propagation
delays over the lengths.
So we've seen this before.
If you look at the one on the right we can
see that the packet is, the message has
been broken down into packets of length p.
So I've broken that same message as
before.
Overall this is the same message just
broken down into packets of length p.
So the packetization delay over the first
link is p over r1 and so now the one to
one delay is this expression here p over
ra for the packetization delay on each
link and then li over c for the for the.
Propagation delay.
And M over P, is simply the additional
time.
For the one, the ones who are arriving.
And strictly speaking this should be M
minus one over P because it's the remaining
packets.
I'm going to assume that M is much bigger
than P so that's basically the same.
M over P time R3.
The packetization delay of that packet, of
that set of packets, over the last link.
But the most important thing here is that
you can see what's going on.
In this case on the left, the whole
message has to be transferred over the
first link before it can start on the
second link, whereas over here, the first
packet goes and then is transferred on to
the second link while the first link is
carrying the second packet.
So we have got a pipelining effect.
We've got parallelism over the links and
so, therefore, the end-to-end layer is
gonna be reduced over a long network with
very big messages.
This will make a very significant
difference.
And so the end-to-end delay can be reduced
by making the packets smaller.
Let's look at this simple example here.
I've got a number of flows, 'n' flows are
in, in packets coming in on'n' external
links, all running at rate, r.
Got a packet buffer corresponding to the
upper queue of the router, and then an
outgoing link that's running at rate r, as
well.
Clearly, if all of those ingress links
were running at the full rate r, then the
output link would be overwhelmed and would
start dropping packets very quickly.
In effect, there would be, a rate of N
times R coming in, and a rate of 1R going
out.
So we'll be dropping them at a rate of N
minus one times R.
But because of the statistical
multiplexing and the burstiness of the
arrivals, we can potentially get away with
this if the average rates are sufficiently
low.
So, in general we say the reduction in
rate that we need at the egress, compared
to the ingress, is because of that
statistical multiplexing, and we call that
benefit the statistical multiplexing gain.
We never know what it's going to be
precisely because it's going to depend on
the particular arrival process of packets,
and temporarily if there are temporary
over subscription to the output link, the
buffer can absorb those brief periods, and
so a bigger buffer is going to absorb
bigger and longer periods when the
aggregate rate happens to exceed R.
But because the buffer has a finite size
there's always losses that can occur.
And that's just a fact of life in packet
switching.
Nothing that we can do about that.
Let's look at a couple of specific
examples here.
See the top bar at the top here.
I've got a, a communicating a rival
process A into this.
Round a buffer that's being drained at
rate C.
And a separate one that's going through a
router that's arriving at B, at rate B,
and being drained at rate C.
And I'm showing over here on the left hand
side, the rates as a function of time, and
you can see here that the peaks and
troughs don't exactly line up, so that if
we take the sum of the two, or the sum of
these two flows, then we can expect there
to be some statistical multiplexing gain.
Let's have a look at what that might be,
of course I made up these numbers these
are just, just to give us an example, but
if we take A plus B, here, that was the.
Rate of A plus B, and that's the line in
pink, that's this one here.
You can see that, their combined rate, the
rate of the combined flows are.
Is quite a bit less than 2C.
In other words less than the sum of the
two peaks.
So in this case we would say, the
statistical multiplexing gain equals 2C
over R.
It's the benefit that we're getting, from
summing the two of them.
We can actually come up with a different
definition.
And some people use a different definition
for statistical multiplexing gain.
Because, in this case, you can see, we
didn't actually take advantage of the fact
that there is a buffer.
We're not using that to buffer any, any
temporary rate that exceeds R.
So.
One definition could be that for a
given buffer size, B.
The ratio of the rates, that need, that we
need in order to prevent packet loss, is
the statistical multiplexing gain, and
that generally will be a lower rate,
because we can absorb the change.
So for example in this, in this case,
imagine that We were to serve it at this,
this rate, R', instead.
So we call that R', where R' is
a little bit less then R.
So long as the amount that we need to
buffer here and here,
when the rate exceeds R',
can be accommodated by the buffer, then
we're okay.
An so in this case for the, the buffer of
size B.
We might say that, instead.
The multiplexing gain is 2C over R',
which is a slightly larger number.
Okay, so two definitions of statistic
multiplexing gain.
One Where we don't consider the buffer,
and one where we do.
So, in summary, often we can use a simple
deterministic model of a queue to
understand the packet dynamics in a
network, and I'd encourage to do this.
It gives a very good intuitive
understanding of what's happening in the
network.
I often use this myself.
Second.
We learn that we can break messages into
packets or rather the reason that we break
messages into packets is because it lets
us pipeline the transfer of packets from
one end to another and reduces the end to
end delay.
Finally, statistical multiplexing lets us
carry many flows efficiently on a single
link and this is one of the prime reasons
that we use packet switching.
Okay, that's the end of this video.