53 is represented in little endian. 53 is
3 times 16 plus 5, and 0x35 is in the first
byte.
4116 is big endian. 4116 is equal to 4096
plus 20. So the two bytes are 0x10 and 0x14,
with 0x10 being the byte representing the
more significant bits, those of 4096. Since
the hexidecimal is 0x1014, this means the
most significant byte comes first and it’s
big endian.
5 is big endian -- the least significant byte
is last and has the highest address.
83,886,080 is little endian: it’s 5 times
2 to the 24th, so this means that 0x05 is
the most significant byte.
Finally, 305,414,945 is little endian. Rather
than try to figure out all of the digits on
this one, I just looked at the least significant
bit. The least significant bit is either part
of 0x21 or 0x12. If it’s 0x21 and the least
significant bit is 1, then the number is odd.
If it’s 0x12 and the least significant bit
is 0, then the number is even. Since 305,414,945
is odd, this means 0x21 is the least significant
byte and the number is being stored little-endian.