So how are IP addresses assigned? Originally,
they were broken up into three classes: class
A, class B, and class C. Each class separated
an IP address into two part, network and host.
The network part of the address denoted an
administrative domain, such as MIT, BBN, or
Stanford University. The host part of the
address denoted which device within that network.
Class A addresses had a leading 0, 7 bits
of network (for 128 networks) and 24 bits
of host, so could cover 16 million computers.
Class B addresses had 16 bits of host, so
could cover 65,536 computers. Class C addresses
had 8 bits of host, so could cover 256 computers.
While classes A, B, and C are simple, we quickly
found out they were not flexible enough. For
example, both MIT and Stanford received one
of the first class A address blocks - over
4 million addresses. For a while, MIT would
give each of its dorms the equivalent of a
class B -- 65,000 addresses for a few hundred
people! When IP addresses were plentiful,
this wasn’t a problem, but as their use
increased we needed a better allocation policy.
A useful note: Stanford gave up its class
A block in 1999, MIT still has its.
Today, IPv4 addresses are structured thought
something called CIDR, or Classless Inter-Domain
Routing. Rather than have prefixes only of
length 8, 16, and 24 bits, CIDR allows prefixes
to be any number of bits. This means all CIDR
prefixes define a block of addresses that
is a power of 2 in size. When we talk about
a CIDR address, we refer to its netmask length.
So, for example, when we talk about a “slash
16”, we mean a netmask of length 16. This
CIDR block describes 2 to the 16 addresses,
or 65,536. When we talk about a “slash 20”,
we mean a netmask of length 20. This CIDR
block describes 2 to the 12 addresses, or
4.096 addresses. CIDR blocks are how addresses
are structured, addressed, and managed today.
Stanford today has 5 /16 blocks, about 325,000
IPv4 addresses.
So how are IPv4 addresses allocated and managed?
There’s an organization called IANA, for
the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority. The
ultimate authority is ICANN, the Internet
Corporation for Assignment of Names and Numbers.
ICANN delegates the work to IANA.
IANA gives out slash-8s, describing 16 million
addresses, to Regional Internet Registries,
or RIRs. Each continent has its own RIR. The
RIR for the United States is ARIN, while the
RIR for the western Pacific is APNIC. These
RIRs each have their own policy for how they
break up the /8s into smaller blocks of addresses
and assign them to parties who need them.
You might have read in the news is that we’ve
run out of IP addresses. This isn’t really
true -- there are many unused addresses today.
What *did* happen is that IANA ran out of
/8s to give out. It reached a special end
case in its charter. When reduced to its last
5 /8s, IANA gave one /8 to each RIR. Now address
management and allocation is up to RIRs. In
2012, Jon Peterson, then a member of the Internet
Architecture Board, gave a talk at Stanford
on some of the political, economic, and technical
complications this raises. The talk isn’t
required material for this course, but I recommend
it highly.
So now you’ve seen the structure of IPv4
addresses, how they are allocated, and how
end hosts make their first hop routing decisions,
that is, whether to send to a local node or
their gateway router. Addresses today are
managed and allocated in terms of CIDR blocks,
whose size is defined by their prefix length.
A shorter prefix, say, a /8, is a larger block
than a longer prefix, say, a /10.