In this section, I want to add the idea of variables to code.
A variable in the computer is sort of like a box.
So, here, if I have code like this where I
say x is equal to 7, semicolon, what that means is
there&#39;s a box in the computer labeled x, as I&#39;ve
drawn here, and this just stores a 7 into that box.
Or we could store any value we wanted.
Then later in the code, if wherever an x appears, the computer
knows to use 7 or whatever it is I put in there.
So in effect, the variable becomes sort of a,
a convenient shorthand for whatever value I want to use.
So let me show you how this is going to work in typically in CS101.
I&#39;ll have a line like this, x equals 7, so that just puts a 7 in the box.
And then on the later lines, I will use that variable.
So I&#39;ll say, here it says print x or lucky x or actually, x is x.
So let me just try running that.
And what you see is the 7 just shows up through here because any
place I used x, the computer is pulling the value out of the box.
This makes it convenient to change.
So for example, if I change this to 4x equals 42
and run it, now the 42 shows up all over the place.
Or works for strings too.
I could say x equals quote hi quote, and
run it, and we get the hi all through there.
I should mention this use of equals to in the computer just puts a value in the box.
That&#39;s the only way we are going to use it.
In mathematics, the equals sign has a
different, and kind of a, a stronger meaning.
In mathematics, the equals sign means the two values are the same
at all times, and that is not what it means in the computer.
In, in this use it is a simpler, just assign value into box.
So let me try let me work this little problem.
So this says you know, write code to produce this
output, Alice Alice Alice, I had a crush on Alice.
And it says, do it in a way that we
can change the name very easily, so use a variable.
I put a little code here to start just to remind you of the syntax,
but it, this doesn&#39;t do anything like we, want we wanted, so I&#39;ll fix it.
So, I&#39;m going to say x is equal to quote Alice.
And then inside here, I&#39;ll just say x, x.
X will just try, this is not a complete solution, we&#39;ll just try it as we go.
So if I run that, right, we get the three Alices
and then I had this, I had a crush on thing.
So I&#39;ll say print quote, I had a crush on, comma and I&#39;ll say, x.
So that way, it&#39;ll just use whatever we had in the box there.
So if I run that, all right, that looks right.
And then this has the, the the desired feature that if
I changed this to like, if I just say x equals Zoe
at the top, then it just says Zoe, or I could
say, you know, Bob or whatever, or you know, bleh, let&#39;s say.
Then like, it just shows up all [INAUDIBLE].
So this shows those kind of shorthand nature of variables
and that&#39;s the way we&#39;re going to use them in CS101.
So, that&#39;s how to use variables in code, so try it yourself now in the exercises.